<chapter id="Ps 26">
			<pericope>A Prayer for Vindication</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 26:title">title</verse-number>Of David.<note>The Hebrew Bible counts the superscription as the first verse of the psalm</note> </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 26:1">1</verse-number>Judge me, O Yahweh, because I have walked in my integrity, </li1>
				<li1>and I have trusted Yahweh and not wavered. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 26:2">2</verse-number>Prove me, O Yahweh, and test me. </li1>
				<li1>Try my <idiom-start/>innermost being<idiom-end/><note>Literally “kidneys,” the locus of intense thoughts and emotions in biblical Hebrew</note> and my <idiom-start/>mind<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “heart”</note> </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 26:3">3</verse-number>Because your loyal love <supplied>is</supplied> before my eyes, </li1>
				<li1>and I walk about in your faithfulness. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 26:4">4</verse-number>I do not sit with deceitful people, </li1>
				<li1>nor will I go about with hypocrites. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 26:5">5</verse-number>I hate <supplied>the</supplied> crowd of evildoers, </li1>
				<li1>and with <supplied>the</supplied> wicked I will not sit. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 26:6">6</verse-number>I will wash my hands in innocence, </li1>
				<li1>and I will walk about your altar, O Yahweh, </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 26:7">7</verse-number>to declare with a voice of thanksgiving, </li1>
				<li1>and tell of all your wondrous deeds. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 26:8">8</verse-number>O Yahweh, I love <supplied>the</supplied> dwelling of your house,<note>Or “temple”</note> </li1>
				<li1>and <idiom-start/>the place where your glory abides<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the place of the dwelling place of your glory”</note> </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 26:9">9</verse-number>Do not destroy me<note>Or “gather my soul <supplied>for judgment</supplied>”</note> with <supplied>the</supplied> sinners, </li1>
				<li1>nor my life with men of bloodshed, </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 26:10">10</verse-number>in whose hands <supplied>is</supplied> an evil plan, </li1>
				<li1>and whose right hand is full of bribes.<note>Hebrew “bribe”</note> </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 26:11">11</verse-number>But as for me, I will walk in my integrity. </li1>
				<li1>Redeem me and be gracious to me. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 26:12">12</verse-number>My foot stands on level ground. </li1>
				<li1>In assemblies I will bless Yahweh. </li1>
			</ul>
		</chapter>