<chapter id="Ps 58">
			<pericope>Judgment on the Wicked</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 58:title">title</verse-number>For the <supplied>music</supplied> director, <supplied>according to</supplied> Do not Destroy. </li1>
				<li1>Of David. A miktam.<note>The Hebrew Bible counts the superscription as the first verse of the psalm; the English verse number is reduced by one</note> </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 58:1">1</verse-number>Do you really speak <supplied>what is</supplied> right <supplied>when</supplied> silent?<note>A slight emendation of the Hebrew text yields “what is right, O gods,” or “O mighty ones”</note> </li1>
				<li1><supplied>Do</supplied> you judge fairly the children of humankind?<note>Or “Do you judge fairly, O sons of humankind?”</note> </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 58:2">2</verse-number>No, in <supplied>your</supplied> heart you plan injustices; </li1>
				<li1>in the land<note>Or “on the earth”</note> you weigh out the violence of your hands. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 58:3">3</verse-number>The wicked are estranged from <supplied>the</supplied> womb. </li1>
				<li1>They go astray from <supplied>the</supplied> belly, speaking lies. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 58:4">4</verse-number>Their venom <supplied>is</supplied> like snake venom; </li1>
				<li1><supplied>They are</supplied> like a deaf viper that closes its ear </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 58:5">5</verse-number>so that it does not hear <supplied>the</supplied> voice of charmers </li1>
				<li1><supplied>or the</supplied> skilled caster of spells. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 58:6">6</verse-number>O God, break their teeth in their mouth. </li1>
				<li1>Break off <supplied>the</supplied> fangs of <supplied>the</supplied> young lions, O Yahweh. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 58:7">7</verse-number>Let them run <supplied>away</supplied> like water <supplied>that</supplied> runs off. </li1>
				<li1><supplied>When</supplied> he bends <supplied>the bow</supplied>, let his arrows <supplied>be</supplied> as though they were cut off.<note>Or “as though they were withered <supplied>stalks</supplied>”</note> </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 58:8">8</verse-number><supplied>Let them be</supplied> like a snail <supplied>that</supplied> melts away <supplied>as</supplied> it goes; </li1>
				<li1><supplied>like the</supplied> stillborn of woman <supplied>that</supplied> do not see <supplied>the</supplied> sun. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 58:9">9</verse-number>Before your pots can feel <supplied>the heat of</supplied> a thornbush, </li1>
				<li1>whether green <supplied>or</supplied> <idiom-start/>dry<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “burning”</note> he will sweep it away.<note>The Hebrew of this verse is difficult to interpret</note> </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 58:10">10</verse-number><supplied>The</supplied> righteous will rejoice when he sees <supplied>the</supplied> vengeance; </li1>
				<li1>he will wash his feet in the blood of the wicked. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 58:11">11</verse-number>And people<note>Hebrew “a person”</note> will say, “Surely <supplied>there is</supplied> a <idiom-start/>reward<idiom-end/><note>Literally “fruit”</note> for the righteous. </li1>
				<li1>Surely there is a God <supplied>who</supplied> judges in the land.”<note>Or “on the earth”</note> </li1>
			</ul>
		</chapter>