<chapter id="Ps 81">
			<pericope>An Appeal from God to Israel</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 81:title">title</verse-number>For the <supplied>music</supplied> director; on the Gittith. Of Asaph.<note>The Hebrew Bible counts the superscription as the first verse of the psalm; the English verse number is reduced by one</note> </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 81:1">1</verse-number>Shout out to God our strength; </li1>
				<li1>shout joyfully to the God of Jacob. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 81:2">2</verse-number>Lift up a song and strike<note>Hebrew “give”</note> <supplied>the</supplied> tambourine, </li1>
				<li1><supplied>the</supplied> pleasant lyre, together with <supplied>the</supplied> harp. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 81:3">3</verse-number>Blow <supplied>the</supplied> horn at new moon, </li1>
				<li1>at full moon, for our feast day, </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 81:4">4</verse-number>because it <supplied>is</supplied> a statute for Israel, </li1>
				<li1>an ordinance of the God of Jacob. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 81:5">5</verse-number>He made it a statute<note>Hebrew “testimony” or “witness”</note> in Joseph </li1>
				<li1>when he went out against the land of Egypt, </li1>
				<li1><supplied>where</supplied> I heard a language I did not know.<note>The meaning of this line is uncertain. The above is based on perhaps a similar thought in <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 114:1">Psa 114:1</cite></note> </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 81:6">6</verse-number>“I removed his shoulder from a burden. </li1>
				<li1>His hands were freed from <supplied>the</supplied> basket. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 81:7">7</verse-number>In this<note>Hebrew “the”</note> trouble you called, and I rescued you. </li1>
				<li1>Within <supplied>the</supplied> secret place of thunder I answered you; </li1>
				<li1>I tested you at the waters of Meribah. <i>Selah</i> </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 81:8">8</verse-number>Hear, O my people, and I will admonish you; </li1>
				<li1>O Israel, if you would <supplied>but</supplied> listen to me. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 81:9">9</verse-number>There shall be no strange god among you, </li1>
				<li1>and you shall not bow down to a foreign god. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 81:10">10</verse-number>I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh your God, </li1>
				<li1>who brought you up from the land of Egypt. </li1>
				<li1>Open wide your mouth and I will fill it. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 81:11">11</verse-number>But my people did not listen to my voice, </li1>
				<li1>and Israel did not yield to me. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 81:12">12</verse-number>So I let them<note>Hebrew “him”</note> go in the stubbornness of their heart; </li1>
				<li1>they walked in their counsels. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 81:13">13</verse-number>Oh that my people would listen to me; </li1>
				<li1><supplied>that</supplied> Israel would walk in my ways. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 81:14">14</verse-number>I would subdue their enemies quickly, </li1>
				<li1>and turn my hand against their adversaries. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 81:15">15</verse-number>Those who hate Yahweh would cringe before him, </li1>
				<li1>and their fate<note>Hebrew “time”</note> would be forever. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 81:16">16</verse-number>But he would feed him<note>That is, Israel</note> from <supplied>the</supplied> choicest wheat,<note>Hebrew “<supplied>the</supplied> fat of wheat”</note> </li1>
				<li1>and I would satisfy you with honey from a rock.” </li1>
			</ul>
		</chapter>