<chapter id="Ps 86">
			<pericope>A Prayer for Help against Ruthless Men</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 86:title">title</verse-number>A prayer of David.<note>The Hebrew Bible counts the superscription as the first verse of the psalm</note> </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 86:1">1</verse-number>Incline, O Yahweh, your ear <supplied>and</supplied> answer me, </li1>
				<li1>because I <supplied>am</supplied> poor and needy. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 86:2">2</verse-number>Watch over my life because I <supplied>am</supplied> faithful. </li1>
				<li1>You <supplied>are</supplied> my God; save your servant. </li1>
				<li1><supplied>I am</supplied> the one who trusts you. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 86:3">3</verse-number>Be gracious to me, O Lord, </li1>
				<li1>because I call to you <idiom-start/>all day long<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “all the day”</note> </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 86:4">4</verse-number>Make glad the soul of your servant, </li1>
				<li1>because <idiom-start/>I desire you<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “I lift up my soul to you”</note> O Lord. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 86:5">5</verse-number>For you, O Lord, <supplied>are</supplied> good and forgiving, </li1>
				<li1>and abundant in loyal love<note>Hebrew “and great with respect to loyal love”</note> for all who call to you. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 86:6">6</verse-number>Heed, O Yahweh, my prayer, </li1>
				<li1>and attend to the voice of my supplications. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 86:7">7</verse-number>In the day of my trouble I call to you, </li1>
				<li1>because you answer me. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 86:8">8</verse-number>There is none like you among the gods, O Lord, </li1>
				<li1>and there are no works like yours. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 86:9">9</verse-number>All <supplied>the</supplied> nations that you have made will come </li1>
				<li1>and bow down<note>Or “worship”</note> before you, O Lord, </li1>
				<li1>and glorify your name. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 86:10">10</verse-number>For you <supplied>are</supplied> great and doing wondrous things; </li1>
				<li1>you alone <supplied>are</supplied> God. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 86:11">11</verse-number>Teach me, O Yahweh, your way, </li1>
				<li1><supplied>that</supplied> I may walk in your truth. </li1>
				<li1>Unite my heart<note>That is, give singleness of heart</note> to fear your name. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 86:12">12</verse-number>I will give you thanks, O Lord my God, with all my heart, </li1>
				<li1>and glorify your name forever, </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 86:13">13</verse-number>because your loyal love <supplied>is</supplied> great toward me, </li1>
				<li1>and you will have delivered my life from Sheol<note>The nether world, the place of departed spirits.</note> below. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 86:14">14</verse-number>O God, arrogant men have risen up against me, </li1>
				<li1>even a gang of ruthless men seek my life, </li1>
				<li1>but they do not set you before them.<note>That is, they do not factor God into their actions</note> </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 86:15">15</verse-number>But you, O Lord, <supplied>are</supplied> a compassionate and gracious God, </li1>
				<li1><idiom-start/>slow to anger<idiom-end/><note>Literally “long of nostrils”</note> and abundant in loyal love and faithfulness. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 86:16">16</verse-number>Turn to me and be gracious to me. </li1>
				<li1>Give your strength to your servant, </li1>
				<li1>and grant victory to the son<note>Or “Save the son”</note> of your maidservant. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 86:17">17</verse-number>Do a sign <supplied>that</supplied> benefits me, </li1>
				<li1>that those who hate me may see and be put to shame, </li1>
				<li1>because you, O Yahweh, have helped me and comforted me. </li1>
			</ul>
		</chapter>