<chapter id="Ps 90">
			<pericope>God’s Eternity and Human Frailty</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 90:title">title</verse-number>A prayer of Moses, the man of God.<note>The Hebrew Bible counts the superscription as the first verse of the psalm</note> </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 90:1">1</verse-number>O Lord, you have been our help<note>Or “dwelling place”</note> <idiom-start/>in all generations<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “in a generation and a generation”</note> </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 90:2">2</verse-number>Before <supplied>the</supplied> mountains were born </li1>
				<li1>and you brought forth <supplied>the</supplied> earth and <supplied>the</supplied> world, </li1>
				<li1>even from everlasting to everlasting, you <supplied>are</supplied> God. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 90:3">3</verse-number>You return man to <supplied>the</supplied> dust, </li1>
				<li1><idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “and you say”</note> “Return, O sons of man.” </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 90:4">4</verse-number>For a thousand years in your eyes </li1>
				<li1><supplied>are</supplied> like yesterday when it passes, </li1>
				<li1>or <supplied>like</supplied> a watch in the night. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 90:5">5</verse-number>You sweep them away <supplied>like a flood</supplied>. </li1>
				<li1>They fall asleep.<note>The interpretation of 5a is difficult</note> </li1>
				<li1>In the morning <supplied>they are</supplied> like grass <supplied>that</supplied> sprouts anew. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 90:6">6</verse-number>In the morning it blossoms and sprouts anew; </li1>
				<li1>by evening it withers and dries up. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 90:7">7</verse-number>For we are brought to an end by your anger, </li1>
				<li1>and we hasten <supplied>off</supplied><note>Or “we are terrified”</note> by your wrath. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 90:8">8</verse-number>You have put our iniquities before you, </li1>
				<li1>our hidden <supplied>sins</supplied> into the light of your countenance. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 90:9">9</verse-number>For all of our days dwindle away in your rage; </li1>
				<li1>we complete our years like a sigh. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 90:10">10</verse-number>As for the days of our years, within them <supplied>are</supplied> seventy years </li1>
				<li1>or if by strength eighty years, and their pride<note>Or “span”</note> <supplied>is</supplied> trouble and disaster, </li1>
				<li1>for it passes quickly and we fly <supplied>away</supplied>. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 90:11">11</verse-number>Who knows the strength of your anger, </li1>
				<li1>and your rage consistent with<note>Hebrew “according to”</note> <supplied>the</supplied> fear due you? </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 90:12">12</verse-number>So teach <supplied>us</supplied> to number our days </li1>
				<li1>that we may gain a heart of wisdom. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 90:13">13</verse-number>Return,<note>Or “Turn back <supplied>your wrath</supplied>”</note> O Yahweh. How long? </li1>
				<li1>And have compassion on<note>Or “change your mind concerning”</note> your servants. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 90:14">14</verse-number>Satisfy us in the morning with your loyal love, </li1>
				<li1>that we may sing for joy and be glad all our days. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 90:15">15</verse-number>Make us glad for as many days as you have afflicted us, </li1>
				<li1><supplied>for as many</supplied> years <supplied>as</supplied> we have seen calamity. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 90:16">16</verse-number>Let your work be visible to your servants, </li1>
				<li1>and your majesty to their children. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 90:17">17</verse-number>And let the beauty of the Lord our God be upon us, </li1>
				<li1>and establish for us the work of our hands, </li1>
				<li1>yes, the work of our hands, establish it. </li1>
			</ul>
		</chapter>