<chapter id="Ps 91">
			<pericope>God’s Protection in Times of Crisis</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 91:1">1</verse-number><supplied>One who</supplied> lives in the secret place<note>Or “shelter”</note> of the Most High </li1>
				<li1>will lodge in the shadow of Shaddai.<note>Often translated “the Almighty,” this is perhaps better understood as “<supplied>God of the</supplied> Mountain”</note> </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 91:2">2</verse-number>I will say to Yahweh, “<supplied>You are</supplied> my refuge and my fortress, </li1>
				<li1>my God <supplied>in whom</supplied> I trust.” </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 91:3">3</verse-number>For he will deliver<note>Hebrew “he, he will deliver” is perhaps emphatic, “He will certainly deliver”</note> you from <supplied>the</supplied> snare of <supplied>the</supplied> fowler, </li1>
				<li1>from <supplied>the</supplied> plague of destruction. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 91:4">4</verse-number>With his feathers he will cover you, </li1>
				<li1>and under his wings you can take refuge. </li1>
				<li1>His faithfulness <supplied>will be</supplied> a shield and a buckler.<note>That is, a small, round shield, or perhaps a surrounding bulwark</note> </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 91:5">5</verse-number>You need not fear <supplied>the</supplied> terror of <supplied>the</supplied> night, </li1>
				<li1><supplied>or the</supplied> arrow <supplied>that</supplied> flies by day, </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 91:6">6</verse-number><supplied>or the</supplied> plague <supplied>that</supplied> spreads in the darkness, </li1>
				<li1><supplied>or the</supplied> destruction <supplied>that</supplied> devastates at noon. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 91:7">7</verse-number>A thousand may fall at your side, </li1>
				<li1>and ten thousand at your right <supplied>hand</supplied>, </li1>
				<li1><supplied>but</supplied> it will not come near you. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 91:8">8</verse-number>You will only look with your eyes, </li1>
				<li1>and see <supplied>the</supplied> punishment of <supplied>the</supplied> wicked. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 91:9">9</verse-number>For you, O Yahweh, <supplied>are</supplied> my refuge. </li1>
				<li1>You have made the Most High your dwelling place.<note>This is the most straightforward translation of the Hebrew, though the “you” of each line would refer to a different person. A more unusual rendering would be “Because Yahweh, my refuge, even the Most High, you have made your dwelling place …”</note> </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 91:10">10</verse-number>No harm will befall you, </li1>
				<li1>and no plague will come near your tent. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 91:11">11</verse-number>For he will command his angels concerning you, </li1>
				<li1>to watch over you in all your ways. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 91:12">12</verse-number>In <supplied>their</supplied> hands they will bear you up, </li1>
				<li1>lest you strike your foot against a stone. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 91:13">13</verse-number>You will tread on lion and viper; </li1>
				<li1>you will trample young lion and serpent. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 91:14">14</verse-number>Because he loves me, therefore I will deliver him; </li1>
				<li1>I will protect<note>The sense is that of making something inaccessibly high, like a fortress</note> him because he knows my name. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 91:15">15</verse-number>He will call upon me and I will answer him; </li1>
				<li1>I <supplied>will be</supplied> with him in trouble; </li1>
				<li1>I will rescue and honor him. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 91:16">16</verse-number><supplied>With</supplied> <idiom-start/>long life<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a length of days”</note> I will satisfy him, </li1>
				<li1>and show him my salvation. </li1>
			</ul>
		</chapter>