<chapter id="Ps 92">
			<pericope>Thanksgiving to Yahweh for Victory</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 92:title">title</verse-number>A psalm. A song. For the Sabbath day.<note>The Hebrew Bible counts the superscription as the first verse of the psalm; the English verse number is reduced by one</note> </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 92:1">1</verse-number><supplied>It is</supplied> good to give thanks to Yahweh, </li1>
				<li1>and to sing praise concerning your name, O Most High; </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 92:2">2</verse-number>to declare in the morning your loyal love </li1>
				<li1>and your faithfulness in the night, </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 92:3">3</verse-number>on <supplied>the</supplied> ten <supplied>string</supplied>, and on <supplied>the</supplied> harp, </li1>
				<li1>with a melody on <supplied>the</supplied> lyre. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 92:4">4</verse-number>For you, O Yahweh, have made me glad by your work; </li1>
				<li1>by the deeds of your hands I sing for joy. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 92:5">5</verse-number>How great are your deeds, O Yahweh; </li1>
				<li1><supplied>how</supplied> very deep are your thoughts. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 92:6">6</verse-number><supplied>The</supplied> brutish man does not know, </li1>
				<li1>and <supplied>the</supplied> fool cannot understand this. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 92:7">7</verse-number>When the wicked flourish like grass </li1>
				<li1>and all <supplied>the</supplied> workers of evil blossom, </li1>
				<li1><supplied>it is</supplied> so they can be destroyed forever. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 92:8">8</verse-number>But you <supplied>are</supplied> on high forever, O Yahweh. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 92:9">9</verse-number>For behold, your enemies, O Yahweh, </li1>
				<li1>for behold, your enemies will perish. </li1>
				<li1>All <supplied>the</supplied> workers of evil will be scattered. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 92:10">10</verse-number>But you have exalted my horn like <supplied>that of</supplied> a wild ox; </li1>
				<li1>you have anointed me<note>The Hebrew’s “<supplied>that</supplied> I have moistened with fresh oil” seems unlikely. The above translation presupposes the loss of a letter in the Hebrew textual tradition (<i>ballotani</i> for the MT’s <i>balloti</i>)</note> with fresh oil. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 92:11">11</verse-number>And <supplied>so</supplied> my eye looks on my enemies.<note>This word for “enemies” suggests those watching for any advantage</note> </li1>
				<li1>My ears hear those evildoers who rise up against me. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 92:12">12</verse-number><supplied>The</supplied> righteous<note>Hebrew singular, but used as a collective. The verbs of this verse are also singular</note> will flourish like the date palm. </li1>
				<li1>They will grow like a cedar in Lebanon. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 92:13">13</verse-number>Planted in the house<note>Or “temple”</note> of Yahweh, </li1>
				<li1>they will flourish in the courts of our God. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 92:14">14</verse-number>They will still prosper in old age. </li1>
				<li1>They will be fat and luxuriant,<note>This is the same word used of the oil in v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Ps 92:11">11</cite> and translated “fresh”</note> </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 92:15">15</verse-number>to declare that Yahweh <supplied>is</supplied> upright. </li1>
				<li1><supplied>He is</supplied> my rock, and <supplied>there is</supplied> no injustice<note>According to the reading tradition (<i>Qere</i>)</note> in him. </li1>
			</ul>
		</chapter>