<chapter id="Ps 140">
			<pericope>Prayer for Help in the Face of Enemies</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 140:title">title</verse-number>For the <supplied>music</supplied> director. A psalm of David.<note>The Hebrew Bible counts the superscription as the first verse of the psalm; the English verse number is reduced by one</note> </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 140:1">1</verse-number>Rescue me, O Yahweh, from evil men.<note>The several uses of the singular “man” in this psalm are probably collective</note> </li1>
				<li1>Preserve me from violent men, </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 140:2">2</verse-number>who plan evil <supplied>things</supplied> in <supplied>their</supplied> heart. </li1>
				<li1>They stir up wars continually. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 140:3">3</verse-number>They sharpen their tongue as <supplied>sharp as</supplied> a snake’s; </li1>
				<li1><supplied>the</supplied> venom of a viper <supplied>is</supplied> under their lips. <i>Selah</i> </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 140:4">4</verse-number>Protect me, O Yahweh, from <supplied>the</supplied> hands of <supplied>the</supplied> wicked. </li1>
				<li1>Preserve me from violent men, </li1>
				<li1>who have planned to <idiom-start/>make me stumble<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “push my steps”</note> </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 140:5">5</verse-number><supplied>The</supplied> proud have hidden a trap for me, and cords. </li1>
				<li1>They have spread out a net along <supplied>the</supplied> <idiom-start/>side<idiom-end/><note>Literally “hand”</note> of <supplied>the</supplied> path. </li1>
				<li1>They have set snares for me. <i>Selah</i> </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 140:6">6</verse-number>I say to Yahweh, “You <supplied>are</supplied> my God.” </li1>
				<li1>Listen, O Yahweh, to the voice of my supplications. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 140:7">7</verse-number>O Yahweh, my Lord, the strength of my salvation, </li1>
				<li1>you have covered my head in <supplied>the</supplied> day of battle. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 140:8">8</verse-number>Do not grant, O Yahweh, <supplied>the</supplied> desires of <supplied>the</supplied> wicked. </li1>
				<li1>Do not allow <supplied>them</supplied> to attain their<note>Hebrew “his”</note> plan, lest they be exalted. <i>Selah</i> </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 140:9">9</verse-number><supplied>With respect to the</supplied> head of <supplied>those who</supplied> surround me, </li1>
				<li1>may the harm of their lips cover them. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 140:10">10</verse-number>Let burning coals fall on them; </li1>
				<li1>let them be dropped into the fire, </li1>
				<li1>into bottomless pits <supplied>from which</supplied> they cannot rise. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 140:11">11</verse-number>Do not let a <idiom-start/>slanderer<idiom-end/><note>Literally “man of tongue”</note> be established in the land; </li1>
				<li1>as for <supplied>the</supplied> man of violence, let evil hunt him quickly. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 140:12">12</verse-number>I know<note>According to the reading tradition (<i>Qere</i>)</note> that Yahweh will maintain <supplied>the</supplied> cause of <supplied>the</supplied> afflicted, </li1>
				<li1><supplied>and</supplied> justice for <supplied>the</supplied> needy. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ps 140:13">13</verse-number>Surely <supplied>the</supplied> righteous will give thanks to your name; </li1>
				<li1><supplied>the</supplied> upright will dwell in your presence. </li1>
			</ul>
		</chapter>