<chapter id="2 Ti 1">
			<pericope>Greeting</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ti 1:1">1</verse-number> Paul, an apostle of Christ Jesus through the will of God, according to the promise of life which <supplied>is</supplied> in Christ Jesus, <verse-number id="2 Ti 1:2">2</verse-number>to Timothy, <supplied>my</supplied> dear child. Grace, mercy, <supplied>and</supplied> peace from God the Father and Christ Jesus our Lord. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Timothy’s Spiritual Heritage</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ti 1:3">3</verse-number><idiom-start/>I am thankful<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I have thankfulness”</note> to God, whom I have served with a clear conscience <idiom-start/>as my ancestors did<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from ancestors”</note>, when <idiom-start/>I remember you constantly<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I have remembrance concerning you constantly”</note> in my prayers night and day, <verse-number id="2 Ti 1:4">4</verse-number>longing to see you <supplied>as I</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“remember”) which is understood as temporal</note> remember your tears, so that I may be filled with joy, <verse-number id="2 Ti 1:5">5</verse-number><idiom-start/>remembering the<idiom-end/><note>Literally “receiving a remembrance of the”</note> sincere faith in you, which lived first in your grandmother Lois and your mother Eunice, and I am convinced that <supplied>is</supplied> in you also, <verse-number id="2 Ti 1:6">6</verse-number>for which reason I remind you to rekindle the gift of God that is in you through the laying on of my hands. <verse-number id="2 Ti 1:7">7</verse-number>For God has not given us a spirit of cowardice, but of power and love and self-discipline. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Exhortation to Share Paul’s Suffering</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ti 1:8">8</verse-number>Therefore, do not be ashamed of the testimony about our Lord, nor me his prisoner, but suffer along with <supplied>me</supplied> for the gospel, according to the power of God, <verse-number id="2 Ti 1:9">9</verse-number>who saved us and called <supplied>us</supplied> with a holy calling, not according to our works but according to his own purpose and grace that was given to us in Christ Jesus <idiom-start/>before time began<idiom-end/><note>Literally “before times eternal”</note>, <verse-number id="2 Ti 1:10">10</verse-number>but has now been disclosed by the appearing of our Savior Jesus Christ,<note>Some manuscripts have “our Savior Christ Jesus”</note> who has abolished death and brought to light life and immortality through the gospel, <verse-number id="2 Ti 1:11">11</verse-number>for which I was appointed a proclaimer and an apostle and a teacher, <verse-number id="2 Ti 1:12">12</verse-number>for which reason also I suffer these <supplied>things</supplied>. But <supplied>I am</supplied> not ashamed, because I know in whom I have believed, and I am convinced that he is able to guard <supplied>what</supplied> I have entrusted until that day. <verse-number id="2 Ti 1:13">13</verse-number>Hold fast to the pattern of sound words which you heard from me, in the faith and love <supplied>that are</supplied> in Christ Jesus. <verse-number id="2 Ti 1:14">14</verse-number>Guard the good deposit through the Holy Spirit who lives in us. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ti 1:15">15</verse-number>You know this, that all those in Asia turned away from me, among whom are Phygelus and Hermogenes. <verse-number id="2 Ti 1:16">16</verse-number>May the Lord grant mercy to the household of Onesiphorus, because he refreshed me many times, and was not ashamed of my imprisonment, <verse-number id="2 Ti 1:17">17</verse-number>but <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was”) which is understood as temporal</note> was in Rome, he diligently sought me and found <supplied>me</supplied>. <verse-number id="2 Ti 1:18">18</verse-number>May the Lord grant him to find mercy from the Lord in that day! And how much he served <supplied>me</supplied> in Ephesus you know very well. </p>
		</chapter>