<chapter id="2 Ti 2">
			<pericope>Exhortation to Be Strong in Grace</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ti 2:1">1</verse-number> You, therefore, my child, be strong in the grace <supplied>that is</supplied> in Christ Jesus, <verse-number id="2 Ti 2:2">2</verse-number>and <supplied>the things</supplied> which you have heard from me in the presence of many witnesses, entrust these <supplied>things</supplied> to faithful people who will be competent to teach others also. <verse-number id="2 Ti 2:3">3</verse-number>Suffer together with <supplied>me</supplied> as a good soldier of Christ Jesus. <verse-number id="2 Ti 2:4">4</verse-number>No one who serves as a soldier is entangled in the activities of <supplied>everyday</supplied> life, so that he may please the one who enlisted <supplied>him</supplied>. <verse-number id="2 Ti 2:5">5</verse-number>And also if anyone competes he is not crowned unless he competes according to the rules. <verse-number id="2 Ti 2:6">6</verse-number>The farmer who works hard must <supplied>be</supplied> the first to receive a share of the crops. <verse-number id="2 Ti 2:7">7</verse-number>Consider what I am saying, for the Lord will grant you understanding in all <supplied>these things</supplied>. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A Trustworthy Saying</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ti 2:8">8</verse-number>Remember Jesus Christ, raised from the dead, a descendant of David according to my gospel, <verse-number id="2 Ti 2:9">9</verse-number>in connection with which I suffer misfortune to the point of <idiom-start/>imprisonment<idiom-end/><note>Literally “bonds”</note> as a criminal, but the word of God is not bound. <verse-number id="2 Ti 2:10">10</verse-number>Because of this, I endure all <supplied>things</supplied> for the sake of the chosen, in order that they also may obtain salvation <supplied>which is</supplied> in Christ Jesus with eternal glory. <verse-number id="2 Ti 2:11">11</verse-number>The saying <supplied>is</supplied> trustworthy: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>For if we died with <supplied>him</supplied>, we will also live with <supplied>him</supplied>; </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="2 Ti 2:12">12</verse-number>if we endure, we will also reign with <supplied>him</supplied>; </li1>
				<li1>if we deny <supplied>him</supplied>, he also will deny us; </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="2 Ti 2:13">13</verse-number>if we are unfaithful, he remains faithful—<idiom-start/>he cannot deny himself<idiom-end/><note>Literally “he is not able to deny himself”</note>.<note>Some manuscripts have “because he is not able to deny himself”</note> </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A Worker Approved to God and Not Ashamed</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ti 2:14">14</verse-number>Remind <supplied>people</supplied> of these <supplied>things</supplied>, solemnly urging <supplied>them</supplied> before the Lord<note>Some manuscripts have “before God”</note> not to dispute about words. <supplied>This is</supplied> in no way beneficial <supplied>and leads to</supplied> the ruin of the hearers. <verse-number id="2 Ti 2:15">15</verse-number>Make every effort to present yourself approved to God, a worker having no need to be ashamed, guiding the word of truth along a straight path. <verse-number id="2 Ti 2:16">16</verse-number>But avoid pointless chatter, for it will progress to greater ungodliness, <verse-number id="2 Ti 2:17">17</verse-number>and their message <idiom-start/>will spread<idiom-end/><note>Literally “will experience spreading”</note> like gangrene, among whom are Hymenaeus and Philetus, <verse-number id="2 Ti 2:18">18</verse-number>who have deviated concerning the truth <supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saying”) which is understood as means</note> saying the resurrection has already taken place, and they are upsetting the faith of some. <verse-number id="2 Ti 2:19">19</verse-number>However, the solid foundation of God stands firm, having this seal: “The Lord knows those who are his,”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Nu 16:5">Num 16:5</cite></note> and “Everyone who names the name of the Lord must abstain from unrighteousness.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ti 2:20">20</verse-number>Now in a great house <supplied>there</supplied> are not only gold and silver vessels, but also wooden and earthenware <supplied>ones</supplied>, some of which <supplied>are</supplied> for honorable use, and some of which <supplied>are</supplied> for ordinary use. <verse-number id="2 Ti 2:21">21</verse-number>Therefore, if someone cleanses himself from these <supplied>things</supplied>, he will be a vessel for honorable use, set apart, useful to the Master, prepared for every good work. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ti 2:22">22</verse-number>But flee from youthful desires, and pursue righteousness, faith, love, <supplied>and</supplied> peace, in company with those who call upon the Lord from a pure heart. <verse-number id="2 Ti 2:23">23</verse-number>But avoid foolish and uninformed controversies, <supplied>because you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“know”) which is understood as causal</note> know that they produce quarrels. <verse-number id="2 Ti 2:24">24</verse-number>And the slave of the Lord must not quarrel, but be kind toward everyone, skillful in teaching, tolerant, <verse-number id="2 Ti 2:25">25</verse-number>correcting those who are opposed with gentleness, <supplied>seeing</supplied> whether perhaps God may grant them repentance to a knowledge of the truth, <verse-number id="2 Ti 2:26">26</verse-number>and they will come to their senses again <supplied>and escape</supplied> from the trap of the devil, being held captive by him to <supplied>do</supplied> his will. </p>
		</chapter>