<chapter id="2 Ti 3">
			<pericope>Difficult Times Ahead in the Last Days</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ti 3:1">1</verse-number> But know this, that in the last days difficult times will come, <verse-number id="2 Ti 3:2">2</verse-number>for people will be lovers of themselves, lovers of money, boasters, arrogant, slanderers, disobedient to parents, ungrateful, unholy, <verse-number id="2 Ti 3:3">3</verse-number>hardhearted, irreconcilable, slanderous, without self-control, savage, with no interest for what is good, <verse-number id="2 Ti 3:4">4</verse-number>traitors, reckless, conceited, loving pleasure rather than loving God, <verse-number id="2 Ti 3:5">5</verse-number>maintaining a form of godliness, but denying its power. Avoid these <supplied>people</supplied>. <verse-number id="2 Ti 3:6">6</verse-number>For from these are those who slip into houses and captivate foolish women loaded down with sins, led by various kinds of desires, <verse-number id="2 Ti 3:7">7</verse-number>always learning and never able to come to a knowledge of the truth. <verse-number id="2 Ti 3:8">8</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>just as<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the manner in which”</note> Jannes and Jambres opposed Moses, so also these oppose the truth, people corrupted in mind, disqualified concerning the faith. <verse-number id="2 Ti 3:9">9</verse-number>But they will not progress to a greater extent, for their folly will be quite evident to everyone, as also the <supplied>folly</supplied> of those <supplied>two</supplied> was. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Value of the Scriptures</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ti 3:10">10</verse-number>But you have faithfully followed my teaching, way of life, purpose, faith, patience, love, endurance, <verse-number id="2 Ti 3:11">11</verse-number>persecutions, <supplied>and</supplied> sufferings that happened to me in Antioch, in Iconium, <supplied>and</supplied> in Lystra, what sort of persecutions I endured, and the Lord delivered me from all <supplied>of them</supplied>. <verse-number id="2 Ti 3:12">12</verse-number>And indeed, all those who want to live in a godly manner in Christ Jesus will be persecuted. <verse-number id="2 Ti 3:13">13</verse-number>But evil people and imposters will progress to the worse, deceiving and being deceived. <verse-number id="2 Ti 3:14">14</verse-number>But you continue in <supplied>the things</supplied> which you have learned and are convinced <supplied>of</supplied>, <supplied>because you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“know”) which is understood as causal</note> know from whom you learned <supplied>them</supplied>, <verse-number id="2 Ti 3:15">15</verse-number>and that from childhood you have known the holy writings that are able <supplied>to make</supplied> you wise for salvation through faith in Christ Jesus. <verse-number id="2 Ti 3:16">16</verse-number>All scripture <supplied>is</supplied> inspired by God and profitable for teaching, for reproof, for correction, for training in righteousness, <verse-number id="2 Ti 3:17">17</verse-number>in order that the person of God may be competent, equipped for every good work. </p>
		</chapter>