<chapter id="2 Ti 4">
			<pericope>Paul’s Charge to Timothy</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ti 4:1">1</verse-number> I solemnly charge <supplied>you</supplied> before God and Christ Jesus, who is going to judge the living and the dead, and by his appearing and his kingdom, <verse-number id="2 Ti 4:2">2</verse-number>preach the word, be ready in season <supplied>and</supplied> out of season, reprove, rebuke, exhort, with all patience and instruction. <verse-number id="2 Ti 4:3">3</verse-number>For there will be a time when they will not put up with sound teaching, but in accordance with their own desires, they will accumulate for themselves teachers, <idiom-start/>because they have an insatiable curiosity<idiom-end/><note>Literally “feeling an itching in the ear”; “because” is supplied as a component of the participle (“feeling an itching”) which is understood as causal</note>, <verse-number id="2 Ti 4:4">4</verse-number>and they will turn away from the hearing of the truth, but will turn to myths. <verse-number id="2 Ti 4:5">5</verse-number>But you, be self-controlled in all <supplied>things</supplied>, bear hardship patiently, do the work of an evangelist, fulfill your ministry. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ti 4:6">6</verse-number>For I am already being poured out as a drink offering, and the time of my departure is imminent. <verse-number id="2 Ti 4:7">7</verse-number>I have fought the good fight, I have completed the race, I have kept the faith. <verse-number id="2 Ti 4:8">8</verse-number>Finally, the crown of righteousness is reserved for me, that the Lord, the righteous Judge, will award to me on that day, and not only to me, but also to all who have loved his appearing. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Final Instructions to Timothy</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ti 4:9">9</verse-number>Make haste to come to me quickly. <verse-number id="2 Ti 4:10">10</verse-number>For Demas deserted me, <supplied>because he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“loved”) which is understood as causal</note> loved the present age, and went to Thessalonica. Crescens <supplied>went</supplied> to Galatia; Titus <supplied>went</supplied> to Dalmatia. <verse-number id="2 Ti 4:11">11</verse-number>Luke alone is with me. Take along Mark <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“take along”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> bring <supplied>him</supplied> with you, because he is useful to me for ministry. <verse-number id="2 Ti 4:12">12</verse-number>But I have sent Tychicus to Ephesus. <verse-number id="2 Ti 4:13">13</verse-number><supplied>When you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“come”) which is understood as temporal</note> come, bring the cloak that I left behind in Troas with Carpus, and the scrolls, especially the parchments. <verse-number id="2 Ti 4:14">14</verse-number>Alexander the metalworker did me much harm; may the Lord pay back to him according to his deeds, <verse-number id="2 Ti 4:15">15</verse-number>against whom you also be on guard, because he vehemently opposed our words. <verse-number id="2 Ti 4:16">16</verse-number>At my first defense, no one came to my <supplied>aid</supplied>, but <supplied>they</supplied> all deserted me; may it not be counted against them. <verse-number id="2 Ti 4:17">17</verse-number>But the Lord helped me and strengthened me, so that through me the proclamation might be fulfilled and all the Gentiles might hear, and he rescued <supplied>me</supplied> from the lion’s mouth. <verse-number id="2 Ti 4:18">18</verse-number>The Lord will rescue me from every evil deed, and will save <supplied>me</supplied> for his heavenly kingdom, to whom <supplied>be</supplied> the glory <idiom-start/>forever and ever<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the ages of the ages”</note>. Amen. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Final Greetings and Benediction</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ti 4:19">19</verse-number>Greet Prisca and Aquila and the household of Onesiphorus. <verse-number id="2 Ti 4:20">20</verse-number>Erastus remained in Corinth, but Trophimus I left behind in Miletus <supplied>because he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was sick”) which is understood as causal</note> was sick. <verse-number id="2 Ti 4:21">21</verse-number>Make haste to come before winter. Eubulus and Pudens and Linus and Claudia and all the brothers greet you. <verse-number id="2 Ti 4:22">22</verse-number>The Lord <supplied>be</supplied> with your spirit. Grace <supplied>be</supplied> with you. </p>
		</chapter>