<chapter id="Ec 1">
			<pericope>Prologue</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ec 1:1">1</verse-number>The words of the Teacher,<note>Hebrew “Qohelet”</note> the son of David, king in Jerusalem. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Motto Introduced</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 1:2">2</verse-number>“Vanity of vanities!” says the Teacher,<note>Hebrew “Qohelet”</note> </li1>
				<li2>“Vanity of vanities! All <supplied>is</supplied> vanity!” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>All Toil is Profitless and Repetitious</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 1:3">3</verse-number>What does a person gain in all his toil </li1>
				<li2>with which he toils under the sun? </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 1:4">4</verse-number>A generation goes, and a generation comes, </li1>
				<li2>but the earth stands forever. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 1:5">5</verse-number>The sun rises, and the sun goes down; </li1>
				<li2>to its place it hurries,<note>The MT reads “<supplied>it</supplied> gasps <supplied>for breath</supplied>,” which is supported by LXX “to draw <supplied>breath</supplied>”; the BHS editors suggest “<supplied>it</supplied> returns again”</note> and there it rises again. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 1:6">6</verse-number>The wind goes to the south and goes around to the north; </li1>
				<li2>around and around it goes, and on its circuit the wind returns. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 1:7">7</verse-number>All the streams flow to the sea, </li1>
				<li2>but the sea is never full; </li2>
				<li1>to the place where the streams flow, </li1>
				<li2>there they continue to flow. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 1:8">8</verse-number>All things toil continuously;<note>Or “are wearisome”</note> </li1>
				<li2>no one can ever finish describing this.<note>The MT reads “no one is able to speak.” The BHS editors suggest “no one can finish speaking.” On the basis of internal evidence, the latter is adopted in the translation, since it makes better sense in the light of the immediate context</note> </li2>
				<li1>The eye is never<note>Or “not”</note> satisfied with seeing, </li1>
				<li2>and the ear is never<note>Or “not”</note> filled with hearing. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 1:9">9</verse-number>What has been—it is what will be; </li1>
				<li2>what has been done—it is what will be done; </li2>
				<li3>there is nothing new under the sun. </li3>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 1:10">10</verse-number>There is a thing <supplied>of</supplied> which it is said, “Look at this! This is new!” </li1>
				<li2><supplied>But</supplied> it already existed in ages past before us. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 1:11">11</verse-number>There is neither remembrance of former generations, </li1>
				<li2>nor will there be remembrance of future generations. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Qohelet Introduces His Quest</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ec 1:12">12</verse-number>I, the Teacher,<note>Hebrew “Qohelet”</note> <supplied>was</supplied> king over Israel in Jerusalem. <verse-number id="Ec 1:13">13</verse-number>I applied my mind to seek and to search by wisdom all that is done under the heavens.<note>MT reads “under the heavens,” which is supported by LXX; however, several versions (Syriac Peshitta, Aramaic Targum, Latin Vulgate) as well as the Cairo Geniza manuscript read, “under the sun,” cf. 1:3, 9, etc.</note> It <supplied>is</supplied> a grievous task God has given to <idiom-start/>humans<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the sons of the man”</note> <verse-number id="Ec 1:14">14</verse-number>I saw all the works that are done under the sun. Look! Everything <supplied>is</supplied> vanity and chasing wind. </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 1:15">15</verse-number>What is twisted cannot be straightened,<note>The MT reads the active “to be straight”; however, the BHS editors suggest the passive “to be straightened,” which is supported by LXX, which reflects a passive form</note> </li1>
				<li2>and what is lacking cannot be counted.<note>The MT reads “to be numbered”; however, the BHS editors suggest “to be supplied,” comparing 1:15b with similar wording in the Babylonian Talmud: “May the Almighty replenish your loss” (<i>b. Berachot</i> 16b)</note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Ec 1:16">16</verse-number><idiom-start/>I said to myself<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “I myself said to my heart”</note> “Look! I have become great and have increased <supplied>in</supplied> wisdom more than anyone who <idiom-start/>has preceded<idiom-end/><note>Literally “before me”</note> me over Jerusalem. <idiom-start/>I have acquired a great deal of wisdom and knowledge<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “And my mind has seen much wisdom and knowledge”</note> <verse-number id="Ec 1:17">17</verse-number>So <idiom-start/>I dedicated myself<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<cite title="BibleLEB2: So 1">So I </cite>gave my heart”</note> to learn about wisdom and <supplied>to</supplied> learn about delusion and folly. However, I discovered<note>Or “I knew”</note> that this also <supplied>is</supplied> chasing wind. </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 1:18">18</verse-number>For in much wisdom <supplied>is</supplied> much frustration,<note>Or “vexation”</note> </li1>
				<li2>and whoever increases knowledge increases sorrow. </li2>
			</ul>
		</chapter>