<chapter id="Ec 2">
			<pericope>Qohelet’s Investigation of Self-Indulgence</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ec 2:1">1</verse-number>I said <idiom-start/>to myself<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to my heart”</note> “Come! I will test<note>The MT reads “I will test you,” but the BHS editors propose “I will test …” Whether or not one adopts MT, Qohelet is speaking to himself</note> pleasure <idiom-start/>to see whether it is worthwhile<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “and look at goodness”; this idiom refers to the enjoyment of life</note> But look, “This also <supplied>is</supplied> vanity!” <verse-number id="Ec 2:2">2</verse-number>I said of laughter, “<supplied>It is</supplied> folly!” and of pleasure, “<idiom-start/>What does it accomplish?<idiom-end/>”<note>Literally “What does it give?”</note> <verse-number id="Ec 2:3">3</verse-number>I also <idiom-start/>explored<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I searched in my mind”</note> <idiom-start/>the effects of indulging my flesh<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to cheer my flesh”</note> with wine. My mind guiding me with wisdom, <idiom-start/>I investigated<idiom-end/><note>Literally “laid hold of”</note> folly so that I might discover what <supplied>is</supplied> good under heaven<note>Follows MT; two medieval Hebrew manuscripts, LXX, Peshitta read, “under the sun,” cf. 1:3, 9, etc.</note> for <idiom-start/>humans<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the sons of the man”</note> to do <idiom-start/>during the days of their lives<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the number of the days of their lives”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Qohelet’s Investigation of Personal Accomplishment</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ec 2:4">4</verse-number><idiom-start/>I accomplished great things<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “I made great my works”</note> I built for myself houses; I planted for myself vineyards. <verse-number id="Ec 2:5">5</verse-number>I made for myself gardens and parks, and I planted all <supplied>sorts of</supplied> fruit trees in them. <verse-number id="Ec 2:6">6</verse-number>I made for myself pools of water from which to irrigate a grove of flourishing trees. <verse-number id="Ec 2:7">7</verse-number>I acquired male slaves and female slaves, as well as children <supplied>born in my</supplied> house. I also had livestock, cattle, and flocks more than anyone who <supplied>was</supplied> before me in Jerusalem. <verse-number id="Ec 2:8">8</verse-number>I also gathered to myself silver and gold—the royal and provincial treasuries. I acquired for myself male and female singers, as well as the delight of <idiom-start/>men<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the sons of the man”</note> <idiom-start/>voluptuous concubines<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “a breast and breasts,” as a synecdoche for beautiful women in the king’s harem</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ec 2:9">9</verse-number>Thus, <idiom-start/>I accomplished far more<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I became great and I surpassed”</note> than anyone who <supplied>was</supplied> before me in Jerusalem—indeed, my wisdom stood by me. <verse-number id="Ec 2:10">10</verse-number>I neither withheld anything from my eyes that they desired, nor did I deprive any pleasure from my heart. My heart rejoiced in all my toil, for this was my reward from all my toil. <verse-number id="Ec 2:11">11</verse-number>Yet when I considered<note>Or “turned to”</note> all the effort which I expended and the toil with which I toiled to do, then behold, “Everything <supplied>is</supplied> vanity and chasing wind! There is nothing profitable under the sun!” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Living Must Abandon the Work of their Hands to Others at Death</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ec 2:12">12</verse-number>Next, I considered wisdom, as well as delusion and folly. What can anyone <supplied>do</supplied> who will come after the king that has not already been done? <verse-number id="Ec 2:13">13</verse-number>I realized that wisdom has an advantage over folly, just as light has an advantage over darkness. <verse-number id="Ec 2:14">14</verse-number><idiom-start/>The wise man can see where he is walking<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “The eyes of the wise <supplied>are</supplied> in his head”</note> but the fool walks in darkness. Yet I also realized that both of them suffer the same fate. <verse-number id="Ec 2:15">15</verse-number>So I said <idiom-start/>to myself<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “in my heart”</note> “<idiom-start/>If I also suffer the same fate as the fool<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “Just as the fate of the fool—so it will happen to me!”</note> <idiom-start/>what advantage is my great wisdom<idiom-end/>?”<note>Literally “why have I been so exceedingly wise?”</note> So I said <idiom-start/>to myself<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “in my heart”</note> “This also <supplied>is</supplied> vanity!” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ec 2:16">16</verse-number>Certainly no one will remember the wise man or the fool in <idiom-start/>future generations<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the futures”</note> When <supplied>future</supplied> days come, both will have been forgotten already. How <supplied>is it that</supplied> the wise man dies the same as the fool? <verse-number id="Ec 2:17">17</verse-number>So I hated life because the work done under the sun <supplied>is</supplied> grievous to me. For everything <supplied>is</supplied> vanity and chasing wind! </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ec 2:18">18</verse-number>So I hated all my toil with which I have toiled under the sun, for I must leave it behind to someone who will be after me. <verse-number id="Ec 2:19">19</verse-number>And who knows <supplied>whether</supplied> he will be wise or foolish? Yet he will exercise control of all <supplied>the fruit of</supplied> my toil with which I toiled wisely under the sun. This also <supplied>is</supplied> vanity! </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ec 2:20">20</verse-number>So <idiom-start/>I began to despair<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I myself turned to cause my heart to despair”</note> of all the toil with which I toiled under the sun. <verse-number id="Ec 2:21">21</verse-number>For although a person may toil with great wisdom and skill, he must leave his reward to someone who has not toiled for it. This also <supplied>is</supplied> vanity and a great calamity. <verse-number id="Ec 2:22">22</verse-number>For what does a person receive for all his toil and in the longing of his heart with which he toils under the sun? <verse-number id="Ec 2:23">23</verse-number>All his days <supplied>are</supplied> painful, his labor <supplied>brings</supplied> grief, and his heart cannot rest at night. This also <supplied>is</supplied> vanity! </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>It is Best to Simply Enjoy the Passing Pleasures of Life as Reward for Pleasing God</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ec 2:24">24</verse-number>There is nothing better for a person than to eat and drink and <idiom-start/>find delight<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to see good”</note> in his toil. For I also realized that this <supplied>is</supplied> from the hand of God! <verse-number id="Ec 2:25">25</verse-number>For who can eat <supplied>and drink</supplied>, and who can enjoy <supplied>life</supplied> apart from him?<note>The MT reads “more than me,” which is supported by Aramaic Targum and Latin Vulgate, but several medieval Hebrew manuscripts read “from him”</note> <verse-number id="Ec 2:26">26</verse-number>For to the person who <supplied>is</supplied> good in his eyes, he gives wisdom, knowledge, and joy; but to the sinner he gives the task of gathering and heaping up only to give <supplied>it</supplied> to <supplied>him who is</supplied> pleasing to him. This also <supplied>is</supplied> vanity and chasing wind! </p>
		</chapter>