<chapter id="Ec 3">
			<pericope>God Has Ordained the Ebb and Flow of Human Activities</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ec 3:1">1</verse-number>For everything there <supplied>is</supplied> an appointed time, a time for every matter under heaven: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 3:2">2</verse-number>a time to bear<note>Or “a time to be born”; MT reads the active form “to bear <supplied>children</supplied>”</note> and a time to die; </li1>
				<li2>a time to plant and a time to root up <supplied>what is</supplied> planted; </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 3:3">3</verse-number>a time to kill and a time to heal; </li1>
				<li2>a time to break down and a time to build up; </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 3:4">4</verse-number>a time to weep and a time to laugh; </li1>
				<li2>a time to mourn and a time to dance; </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 3:5">5</verse-number>a time to throw away stones and a time to gather stones; </li1>
				<li2>a time to embrace and a time to refrain from embracing; </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 3:6">6</verse-number>a time to seek and a time to lose; </li1>
				<li2>a time to keep and a time to throw away; </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 3:7">7</verse-number>a time to tear and a time to sew; </li1>
				<li2>a time to be silent and a time to speak; </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 3:8">8</verse-number>a time to love and a time to hate; </li1>
				<li2>a time <supplied>for</supplied> war and a time <supplied>for</supplied> peace. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Ec 3:9">9</verse-number>What does the worker gain in his toil? </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>No One Understands God’s Mysterious Plan</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ec 3:10">10</verse-number>I have seen the busyness God gives to <idiom-start/>humans<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the sons of the man”</note> to preoccupy<note>Or “to be busy”</note> them. <verse-number id="Ec 3:11">11</verse-number>He has made everything suitable in its time. He also has put <idiom-start/>the past<idiom-end/><note>Literally “eternity”</note> in their hearts, yet no one can grasp what God does from the beginning to the end. <verse-number id="Ec 3:12">12</verse-number>So I realized that there is <idiom-start/>nothing better<idiom-end/><note>Literally “no good”</note> for them than to <idiom-start/>rejoice and enjoy themselves<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to rejoice and to do good”</note> during their lives. <verse-number id="Ec 3:13">13</verse-number>And for anyone to eat and drink, that is, <idiom-start/>to enjoy the fruit of all his toil<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to see good in all his toil”</note> this also is a gift of God. </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 3:14">14</verse-number>I know everything God does endures forever; </li1>
				<li2>nothing can be added to it, and nothing can be taken from it, </li2>
				<li3>for God so acts that humans<note>Or “they”</note> might stand in awe before him. </li3>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 3:15">15</verse-number>What is—it already was, </li1>
				<li2>and what will be—it already is, </li2>
				<li3>for <idiom-start/>God will do what he has done.<idiom-end/><note>Literally “God seeks <supplied>what</supplied> is pursued”</note> </li3>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>God’s Mysterious Plan Allows Injustice to Exist in the World</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ec 3:16">16</verse-number>I saw something else under the sun: instead of justice <supplied>there was</supplied> evil; instead of righteousness <supplied>there was</supplied> wickedness. <verse-number id="Ec 3:17">17</verse-number>So I said <idiom-start/>to myself<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “in my heart”</note> “God will surely judge the righteous and the wicked, for he has appointed<note>The MT reads שָׁם “there,” but repointing to שָׂם, “he has appointed,” makes better sense</note> a time <supplied>of judgment</supplied> for every deed and every work.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ec 3:18">18</verse-number>I said to myself concerning <idiom-start/>humans<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the sons of the man”</note> “God sifts<note>Or “tests”</note> them in order to show<note>The MT reads active “to see,” but causative “to show” is reflected by LXX, Syriac Peshitta, and Latin Vulgate</note> them that they are like beasts.” <verse-number id="Ec 3:19">19</verse-number>For the fate of <idiom-start/>humans<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the sons of the man”</note> and the fate of the beast is <idiom-start/>the same<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “<supplied>is</supplied> one”</note> The death of the one is like the death of the other, for <idiom-start/>both are mortal<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “and one breath <supplied>is</supplied> for all”</note> Man has no advantage over the beast, for both are fleeting. <verse-number id="Ec 3:20">20</verse-number>Both go to one place—both came from dust and both return to dust. <verse-number id="Ec 3:21">21</verse-number>For no one knows <supplied>whether</supplied> the spirit of a human ascends <supplied>to heaven</supplied> and <supplied>whether</supplied> the spirit of the beast descends to the ground! </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ec 3:22">22</verse-number>So I concluded that there is nothing better for a person than to enjoy <supplied>the fruit of</supplied> his labor, for this is his lot in life. <idiom-start/>For no one knows what will happen in the future.<idiom-end/><note>Literally “For who can bring him to see in what will be after him?”</note> </p>
		</chapter>