<chapter id="Ec 4">
			<pericope>The Existence of Oppression in the World Makes Human Existence Miserable</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ec 4:1">1</verse-number>I looked again, and I saw all the oppression that occurs under the sun. </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><idiom-start/>I saw the tears of the oppressed— </li1>
				<li2>no one comforts them! </li2>
				<li1>Those who oppress them are powerful— </li1>
				<li2>no one can comfort them<idiom-end/>!<note>Literally “And look! The tears of the oppressed, and there is no comforting for them, and from the hand of oppressors <supplied>of</supplied> them <supplied>was</supplied> power, and there is no comforting for them”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 4:2">2</verse-number>So I deemed the dead who have already died </li1>
				<li2>more <supplied>fortunate</supplied> than the living who are still alive. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 4:3">3</verse-number>But better <supplied>off</supplied> than both of them is the one who has not yet been born </li1>
				<li2>and has not seen the evil deeds that are done under the sun. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>People Need Balance in Their Approach to Labor</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ec 4:4">4</verse-number>I also realized that all <supplied>of the</supplied> toil and all <supplied>of</supplied> the skillful work that is done—it <supplied>is</supplied> envy between one man and <idiom-start/>another<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “his friend”</note> This also <supplied>is</supplied> vanity and chasing wind! </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 4:5">5</verse-number><idiom-start/>The fool refuses to work with his hands, </li1>
				<li2>so he has nothing to eat except his own skin<idiom-end/>!<note>Literally “The fool folds his hands and eats his flesh”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 4:6">6</verse-number>Better <supplied>is</supplied> one handful with peace </li1>
				<li2>than two fists full with toil and chasing wind. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Wealth without Someone with Which to Enjoy It is Futile</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ec 4:7">7</verse-number>I turned again and saw another vanity under the sun. <verse-number id="Ec 4:8">8</verse-number>Sometimes a man is all alone with no companion; he also has neither son nor brother. Yet there is no end to all his toil, and his eye is not satisfied with wealth. <supplied>He laments,</supplied> “For whom am I toiling and depriving <idiom-start/>myself<idiom-end/><note>Literally “his soul”</note> of pleasure?” This also <supplied>is</supplied> vanity—it is an unhappy business! </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Friends and Family Can Help One Another in Life</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ec 4:9">9</verse-number>Two <supplied>are</supplied> better than the one, for they enjoy a better reward for their toil. <verse-number id="Ec 4:10">10</verse-number>For if one falls, his companion may help him up. But pity the one who falls and there is <idiom-start/>no one<idiom-end/><note>Literally “there is not a second”</note> to help him up. <verse-number id="Ec 4:11">11</verse-number>Also if two lie together, <idiom-start/>they can keep each other warm<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “and it will be warm for them”</note> But how can one person be warm? <verse-number id="Ec 4:12">12</verse-number><idiom-start/>Although an assailant may overpower one person, two may withstand him<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “And even though he will prevail against him, the one; the second, they will withstand opposite him”</note> A threefold cord <idiom-start/>is not easily broken<idiom-end/>!<note>Literally “will not be broken in haste”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>One Must Be Willing to Listen to Counsel</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ec 4:13">13</verse-number>A poor but wise youth <supplied>is</supplied> better than an old but foolish king who no longer knows <idiom-start/>how to receive advice<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “how to be warned”</note> <verse-number id="Ec 4:14">14</verse-number>For he came out of the prison house to reign, <idiom-start/>since he was born poor in his kingdom<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “for all in his kingdom he was born poor”</note> <verse-number id="Ec 4:15">15</verse-number>I saw all the living who move about under the sun with the youth; the second who will stand in his place. <verse-number id="Ec 4:16">16</verse-number>There is no end to all the people, to all who were before him. Yet the later generation will not rejoice in him, for this also <supplied>is</supplied> vanity and chasing wind! </p>
		</chapter>