<chapter id="Ec 5">
			<pericope>Listen to God Rather Than Uttering Rash Vows</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 5:1">1</verse-number><note><cite title="BibleLEB2: Ec 5:1–20">Ecclesiastes 5:1–20 </cite>in the English Bible is 4:17–5:19 in the Hebrew Bible</note> Guard your steps when you go to the house of God; </li1>
				<li2>draw near to listen <supplied>rather</supplied> than to offer a sacrifice of fools, </li2>
				<li3>for they do not know that they are doing evil. </li3>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 5:2">2</verse-number>Do not be rash with your mouth, </li1>
				<li2>and do not let your heart be quick to utter a word before God. </li2>
				<li1>For God is in heaven, and you <supplied>are</supplied> on earth; </li1>
				<li2>therefore, let your words be few. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 5:3">3</verse-number>For a dream comes with many cares, </li1>
				<li2>and the voice of a fool with many words. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 5:4">4</verse-number>When you make a vow to God, </li1>
				<li2>do not delay in fulfilling it, </li2>
				<li1>for <idiom-start/>he takes no pleasure<idiom-end/><note>Literally “there is no desire”</note> in fools. </li1>
				<li2>Fulfill what you vow! </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 5:5">5</verse-number>It is better that you not vow </li1>
				<li2>than that you vow and not fulfill it. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 5:6">6</verse-number>Do not let your mouth lead your flesh into sin, </li1>
				<li2>and do not tell the messenger that it <supplied>was</supplied> a mistake. </li2>
				<li1>Why anger God at your words, </li1>
				<li2>so that he destroys the work of your hands? </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 5:7">7</verse-number>For with many dreams <supplied>come</supplied> vanities and numerous words. </li1>
				<li2>Therefore, fear God! </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Powerful Bureaucrats Exploit the Helpless Poor</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 5:8">8</verse-number>Do not be surprised if you see the poor being oppressed with violence </li1>
				<li2>or <supplied>do not see</supplied> justice and righteousness in the province. </li2>
				<li1>For one official is watched by a higher official, </li1>
				<li2>and <supplied>there are</supplied> even higher officials over them! </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 5:9">9</verse-number>The produce of the land is exploited by everyone; </li1>
				<li2><idiom-start/>even the king profits from the field <supplied>of the poor</supplied><idiom-end/>!<note>Literally “for the field is even worked for the king”</note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>There is Never Enough Money to Satisfy</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 5:10">10</verse-number>Whoever loves money is not satisfied <supplied>with</supplied> money, </li1>
				<li2>and whoever loves wealth <supplied>is</supplied> not <supplied>satisfied with</supplied> profit. </li2>
				<li1>This also <supplied>is</supplied> vanity! </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 5:11">11</verse-number>When prosperity increases, </li1>
				<li2>those who consume it increase. </li2>
				<li1><idiom-start/>So its owner gains nothing, </li1>
				<li2>except to see his wealth before it is spent<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “And what gain has its owner but to see it with his eyes?”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 5:12">12</verse-number>The sleep of the laborer <supplied>is</supplied> pleasant, whether he eats little or much, </li1>
				<li2>but the wealth of the rich man does not allow him to rest. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Hoarding Wealth Can Backfire</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ec 5:13">13</verse-number>There is a grievous evil which I have seen under the sun: wealth <idiom-start/>hoarded<idiom-end/><note>Literally “kept ”</note> by its owner to his harm. <verse-number id="Ec 5:14">14</verse-number>That wealth was lost in a bad venture. Although he has borne a child, <idiom-start/>he has nothing to leave to him<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “he has nothing in his hand”</note> <verse-number id="Ec 5:15">15</verse-number>Just as he came from his mother’s womb naked, <idiom-start/>he will depart<idiom-end/><note>Literally “return to go”</note> just as he came; he will take nothing with him for his toil. <verse-number id="Ec 5:16">16</verse-number>This also <supplied>is</supplied> a grievous illness. Exactly as he came, so he will go. What profit <supplied>does</supplied> he gain for all his toil for the wind? <verse-number id="Ec 5:17">17</verse-number>Also, he eats in darkness all his days; he is frustrated <supplied>in</supplied> much sickness and resentment. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>If You Have Wealth, Enjoy It as God Enables</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ec 5:18">18</verse-number>Look! I have discovered what is good and fitting: to eat and to drink and <idiom-start/>to enjoy<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to see goodness”</note> all <supplied>the fruit of</supplied> the toil with which one toils under the sun during the number of the days of his life that God gives to him—for this <supplied>is</supplied> his lot.<note>Or “fate”</note> <verse-number id="Ec 5:19">19</verse-number>This indeed is a gift of God: everyone to whom God gives wealth and possessions, he also empowers him <idiom-start/>to enjoy them<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to eat from it”</note> to accept his lot, and to rejoice in <supplied>the fruit of</supplied> his toil. <verse-number id="Ec 5:20">20</verse-number>For he does not remember the <supplied>brief</supplied> days of his life, for God keeps his heart preoccupied with enjoyment <supplied>of life</supplied>. </p>
		</chapter>