<chapter id="Ec 6">
			<pericope>Those Who Have Wealth but Do Not Enjoy It Are Pitiful</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ec 6:1">1</verse-number>Here is another misfortune that I have seen under the sun, and it <supplied>is</supplied> prevalent among humankind. <verse-number id="Ec 6:2">2</verse-number>God gives a man wealth, possessions, and honor, so that he lacks nothing his heart desires; yet God does not enable him to enjoy it—instead someone else ends up enjoying it. This <supplied>is</supplied> vanity—indeed, it <supplied>is</supplied> a grievous ill! </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ec 6:3">3</verse-number>Even if a man fathers a hundred <supplied>children</supplied> and lives many years so that the days of his years are many, if his heart<note>Or “his soul”</note> is not satisfied with <idiom-start/>his prosperity<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the good”</note> and <idiom-start/>he does not receive a proper burial<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “and also there is no burial for him”</note> I deem the stillborn better than him. <verse-number id="Ec 6:4">4</verse-number>For he comes into vanity and departs into darkness, and his name is shrouded in darkness. <verse-number id="Ec 6:5">5</verse-number>He has neither seen nor known the sun, yet he has more rest than him. <verse-number id="Ec 6:6">6</verse-number>Even if a man<note>Hebrew “he”</note> lives a thousand years twice, if he<note>Hebrew “and”</note> does not enjoy <idiom-start/>prosperity<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “good”</note> <idiom-start/>both suffer the same fate<idiom-end/>!<note>Literally “are not the all going to the same place?”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>One Must Learn to Be Content with What One Has</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 6:7">7</verse-number>All of a man’s toil <supplied>is</supplied> for his mouth— </li1>
				<li2>yet his appetite is never satisfied. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 6:8">8</verse-number>So do the wise <supplied>really</supplied> have an advantage over fools? </li1>
				<li2><idiom-start/>Can the poor <supplied>really</supplied> gain anything by knowing how to act in front of others<idiom-end/>?<note>Literally “What <supplied>is there</supplied> for the poor knowing <supplied>how</supplied> to conduct themselves before the living?”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 6:9">9</verse-number><idiom-start/>Better to be content with what your eyes see </li1>
				<li2>than for your soul to constantly crave more<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “Sight of the eyes <supplied>is</supplied> better than wandering of desire”</note> </li2>
				<li1>This also <supplied>is</supplied> vanity and chasing wind! </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>It is Futile for Humans to Complain about God’s Irresistible Will</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 6:10">10</verse-number>Whatever is—it was already determined, </li1>
				<li2><idiom-start/>what will be—it has already been decided<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “and his name is known what he <supplied>is</supplied> man”</note> </li2>
				<li1>As for man, he cannot argue </li1>
				<li2>against what is more powerful than him. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 6:11">11</verse-number><idiom-start/>Increasing words only multiplies futility<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “<supplied>Where</supplied> there <supplied>are</supplied> numerous words, <supplied>it</supplied> makes numerous vanity”</note> </li1>
				<li2>how does that profit anyone? </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Future is Inscrutable to Humans</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ec 6:12">12</verse-number>For who knows what <supplied>is</supplied> good for a man in his life during the few days of his fleeting life, which are fleeting as a shadow? For who can tell anyone what will happen <idiom-start/>in the future<idiom-end/><note>Literally “after him”</note> under the sun? </p>
		</chapter>