<chapter id="Ec 7">
			<pericope>People Generally Do Not Know What is Best for Them</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 7:1">1</verse-number>A good name <supplied>is</supplied> better than precious ointment, </li1>
				<li2>and the day of death <supplied>is better</supplied> than the day of one’s birth. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 7:2">2</verse-number>Better to go to the house of mourning </li1>
				<li2>than to go to the house of feasting, </li2>
				<li1>for <supplied>death is</supplied> the end of every person, </li1>
				<li2>and the living should take <supplied>it</supplied> to his heart. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 7:3">3</verse-number>Sorrow <supplied>is</supplied> better than laughter, </li1>
				<li2>for by sadness of countenance the heart is made good. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 7:4">4</verse-number>The heart of the wise <supplied>is</supplied> in the house of mourning, </li1>
				<li2>but the heart of fools <supplied>is</supplied> in the house of mirth. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 7:5">5</verse-number>Better to listen to <supplied>the</supplied> rebuke of <supplied>the</supplied> wise </li1>
				<li2>than for a man to listen to <supplied>the</supplied> song of fools. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 7:6">6</verse-number>Like the sound of thorns under a pot, </li1>
				<li2>so also the laughter of fools. </li2>
				<li1>This also <supplied>is</supplied> vanity! </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Wisdom—Although Vulnerable—is Beneficial</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 7:7">7</verse-number>Surely oppression makes a fool of the wise, </li1>
				<li2>and a bribe corrupts the heart. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 7:8">8</verse-number>The end of a matter <supplied>is</supplied> better than its beginning; </li1>
				<li2><idiom-start/>better to be slow to anger than hot-headed<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “<supplied>one who is</supplied> long of spirit <supplied>is</supplied> better than <supplied>one who is</supplied> high of spirit”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 7:9">9</verse-number>Do not be quick in your spirit to anger, </li1>
				<li2>for anger lodges in the bosom of fools. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 7:10">10</verse-number>Do not say, “Why were the former days better than these?” </li1>
				<li2>For <supplied>it is</supplied> not from wisdom <supplied>that</supplied> you ask this. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 7:11">11</verse-number>Wisdom <supplied>is</supplied> good with an inheritance; </li1>
				<li2><idiom-start/>it benefits the living<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to those who see the sun”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 7:12">12</verse-number><idiom-start/>For wisdom offers protection like money offers protection<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “For in the shade of wisdom <supplied>is</supplied> the shade of money”</note> </li1>
				<li2>But knowledge <supplied>has</supplied> an advantage—wisdom restores life to its possessor. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Humans Must Accept God’s Will and Make the Best of It</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 7:13">13</verse-number>Consider the work of God. </li1>
				<li2>For who is able to make straight what he made crooked? </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 7:14">14</verse-number>In the day of prosperity, rejoice! </li1>
				<li2>But in the day of adversity, consider! </li2>
				<li1>For God made one in place of another </li1>
				<li2>so that mortals cannot find out what will happen <idiom-start/>in the future<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “after him”</note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Law of Retribution Does Not Always Work—but It Does Sometimes</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 7:15">15</verse-number>I have seen all these things in my vain life: </li1>
				<li2>Sometimes a righteous man perishes in <supplied>spite of</supplied> his righteousness, </li2>
				<li3>and sometimes a wicked man lives a long life in <supplied>spite of</supplied> his evil. </li3>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 7:16">16</verse-number>Do not be excessively<note>Or “abundantly”</note> righteous, </li1>
				<li2>and do not act excessively wise, lest you destroy yourself. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 7:17">17</verse-number>Do not act excessively wicked, </li1>
				<li2>and do not be a fool, lest you die before your time. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 7:18">18</verse-number><supplied>It is</supplied> good to take hold of the one and also must not let go of the other; </li1>
				<li2>for whoever fears God will hold both of them secure. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Wisdom is Valuable, but No One is Completely Righteous</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 7:19">19</verse-number>Wisdom gives more strength to the wise </li1>
				<li2>than ten rulers who are in the city. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 7:20">20</verse-number>Surely there is no one righteous on the earth </li1>
				<li2>who <supplied>continually</supplied> does good and never sins. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 7:21">21</verse-number>Do not pay attention to everything people say, </li1>
				<li2>lest you hear your own servant curse you. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 7:22">22</verse-number>For your heart knows </li1>
				<li2>that you also have cursed others many times. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Absolute Wisdom is Unattainable</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ec 7:23">23</verse-number>All this I have tested with wisdom. I said, “I will be wise!” but <idiom-start/>it was beyond my grasp<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “it <supplied>was</supplied> far from me”</note> <verse-number id="Ec 7:24">24</verse-number><idiom-start/>Whatever is—it is far beyond comprehension<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “That which is—it <supplied>is</supplied> far and deep deep”</note> Who can discover it? </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ec 7:25">25</verse-number>I set my mind to try to seek wisdom and the plan, and to know that wickedness <supplied>is</supplied> foolishness and that folly <supplied>is</supplied> delusion. <verse-number id="Ec 7:26">26</verse-number>I myself found <supplied>that</supplied> more bitter than death <supplied>is</supplied> the woman who <supplied>is</supplied> a trap, whose heart <supplied>is</supplied> a snare, and whose hands <supplied>are</supplied> bonds. The one who pleases God escapes from her, but the sinner is caught by her. <verse-number id="Ec 7:27">27</verse-number>“Look! I found this,” said the Teacher,<note>Hebrew “Qohelet”</note> “while trying to find how the plan fits together. <verse-number id="Ec 7:28">28</verse-number>What my heart sought, I did not find. Although I found one righteous man among one thousand, I did not find one <supplied>upright</supplied> woman among all these. <verse-number id="Ec 7:29">29</verse-number>Look! This alone I found: God made mankind upright, but they have devised many schemes.” </p>
		</chapter>