<chapter id="Ec 8">
			<pericope>Wisdom is Valuable</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 8:1">1</verse-number>Who <supplied>is</supplied> like the sage? </li1>
				<li2>Who knows <supplied>the</supplied> interpretation of a thing? </li2>
				<li1>A man’s wisdom makes his face shine, </li1>
				<li2>and the hardness of his face is changed. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 8:2">2</verse-number>Keep <supplied>the</supplied> command of <supplied>the</supplied> king<note>While MT reads “I <supplied>said</supplied>, ‘Keep <supplied>the</supplied> mouth of <supplied>the</supplied> king,’ ” the versions read “Keep <supplied>the</supplied> mouth of <supplied>the</supplied> king,” which is adopted in the translation</note> </li1>
				<li2><idiom-start/>because of your oath to God<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “because of the oath of God”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 8:3">3</verse-number>Do not be terrified of his presence! </li1>
				<li2>Go at once and do not delay when a matter <supplied>is</supplied> unpleasant, </li2>
				<li1>for he can do anything that he desires. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 8:4">4</verse-number>Since the word of the king <supplied>is</supplied> supreme, </li1>
				<li2>no one can say to him, “What are you doing?” </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 8:5">5</verse-number>Whoever obeys <supplied>his</supplied> command will not suffer disaster. </li1>
				<li2>The wise mind knows the <supplied>proper</supplied> time and the right <supplied>procedure</supplied>. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 8:6">6</verse-number>For there is a <supplied>proper</supplied> time and right <supplied>procedure</supplied> for every matter, </li1>
				<li2>even though the trouble of man <supplied>weighs</supplied> heavy upon him. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>No One Knows the Future</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 8:7">7</verse-number>Surely no one knows what will be, </li1>
				<li2>so who can tell anyone what will happen? </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 8:8">8</verse-number>Just as no one can control the wind to restrain the wind, </li1>
				<li2>so also no one can control the day of his death. </li2>
				<li1>Just as no one is discharged in time of war, </li1>
				<li2>so wickedness will not deliver the wicked. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The World Marred by Oppression and Injustice</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ec 8:9">9</verse-number>I saw all this as I applied my heart to all the deeds done under the sun: <idiom-start/>sometimes those in authority harm others<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sometimes one man domineers another man to his harm”</note> <verse-number id="Ec 8:10">10</verse-number>Meanwhile, I saw the wicked being <supplied>honorably</supplied> buried, but those who came and went from the holy place were forgotten in the city, even though they had done so. This also <supplied>is</supplied> vanity! </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Although Evil is Not Punished Swiftly, God Does Eventually Punish Sinners</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ec 8:11">11</verse-number>Because sentence against an evil deed is not carried out quickly, the heart of <idiom-start/>humans<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the sons of the man”</note> fills up within them to do evil. <verse-number id="Ec 8:12">12</verse-number>Although the sinner does evil a hundred times and prolongs his life, yet I also know that it will be good for those who fear God—because they fear <idiom-start/>his presence<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “from before his face”</note> <verse-number id="Ec 8:13">13</verse-number>But it will not go well with the wicked, and they will not prolong <supplied>their</supplied> days, like the shadow; because there is no fearing <idiom-start/>God’s presence<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “from before the face of God”</note> <verse-number id="Ec 8:14">14</verse-number>There <supplied>is</supplied> a vanity that happens on earth: sometimes the righteous suffer what the wicked deserve, and sometimes the wicked receive what the righteous deserve. I said, “This also <supplied>is</supplied> vanity!” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Humans Should Enjoy the Life That God Gives to Them</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ec 8:15">15</verse-number>So I recommend enjoyment. For there <supplied>is</supplied> nothing better for man under the sun than to eat and to drink and to rejoice. This will accompany him in his toil the days of his life that God gives to him under the sun. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>No One Can Discover the Rhyme and Reason for Things</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ec 8:16">16</verse-number>I applied my mind to know wisdom and to understand the business that is done on earth—how neither day nor night one’s eyes see sleep. <verse-number id="Ec 8:17">17</verse-number>Then I saw all the work of God—man <supplied>is</supplied> not able to discover the work that is done under the sun. Although man may toil in seeking, he cannot find it. Even if a wise man claims <supplied>that he</supplied> knows it, he cannot find it. </p>
		</chapter>