<chapter id="Ec 9">
			<pericope>The Same Fate—Death—Awaits Everyone</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ec 9:1">1</verse-number>So all this I laid to my heart, and I concluded<note>Or “examined”</note> that the righteous and the wise, as well as their deeds, <supplied>are</supplied> in the hand of God. So no one knows anything that will <supplied>come</supplied> to them, whether <supplied>it will be</supplied> love or hatred. <verse-number id="Ec 9:2">2</verse-number>The same fate <supplied>comes</supplied> to everyone: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>to the righteous and to the wicked, </li1>
				<li2>to the good and to the wicked,<note>Several versions (Greek, Syriac, Latin) insert “and to the bad”</note> </li2>
				<li1>to the clean and to the unclean, </li1>
				<li2>to those who sacrifice and to those who do not sacrifice. </li2>
				<li1>As <supplied>with</supplied> the good <supplied>man</supplied>, so also to the sinner; </li1>
				<li2><supplied>as with</supplied> those who swear an oath, so <supplied>also</supplied> those who fear oaths. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 9:3">3</verse-number>This <supplied>is</supplied> the <idiom-start/>injustice<idiom-end/><note>Literally “evil”</note> that is done under the sun: </li1>
				<li2>the same fate <supplied>comes</supplied> to everyone. </li2>
				<li1>Also the hearts of <idiom-start/>humans<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the sons of the man”</note> are full <supplied>of</supplied> evil; </li1>
				<li2>delusion <supplied>is</supplied> in their hearts during their lives, and then they die. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Death Deprives Humans of Everything in Life</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ec 9:4">4</verse-number>Whoever is joined<note>The <i>Kethib</i> reads “chosen,” but the <i>Qere</i> as well as all the versions and numerous medieval Hebrew manuscripts read “joined”</note> to all the living has hope. After all, even a live dog is better than a dead lion! <verse-number id="Ec 9:5">5</verse-number>For the living know that they will die, but the dead do not know anything. They no longer have a reward, and even the memory of them is forgotten. <verse-number id="Ec 9:6">6</verse-number>What they loved and hated, as well as what they desired, has already perished. They no longer have any share in what is done under the sun. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Enjoy Life While It Lasts</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ec 9:7">7</verse-number>Go—eat your food with joy, and drink your wine with a merry heart! For God already has approved your deeds. <verse-number id="Ec 9:8">8</verse-number>Always be clothed in white garments, and never let your head lack oil! <verse-number id="Ec 9:9">9</verse-number>Enjoy life with the wife whom you love all the days of your vain life which he gives you under the sun, because this <supplied>is</supplied> your lot in life and in the toil with which you toil under the sun. <verse-number id="Ec 9:10">10</verse-number>Whatever your hand finds to do—do <supplied>it</supplied> with <supplied>all</supplied> your might; for in Sheol—where you are going—no one works, plans, knows, or thinks about anything. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Injustice of Time and Chance</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ec 9:11">11</verse-number>I looked again and saw under the sun that the race <supplied>does</supplied> not <supplied>belong</supplied> to the swift, the battle <supplied>does</supplied> not <supplied>belong</supplied> to the mighty, food <supplied>does</supplied> not <supplied>belong</supplied> to the wise, wealth <supplied>does</supplied> not <supplied>belong</supplied> to the intelligent, and success<note>Or “favor”</note> <supplied>does</supplied> not <supplied>belong</supplied> to the skillful, for time and chance befalls all of them. <verse-number id="Ec 9:12">12</verse-number>For man does not know his time. Just as fish are caught in a cruel net and like birds who are seized in a snare, so also <idiom-start/>humans<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the sons of the man”</note> are ensnared at a cruel time when it falls suddenly upon them. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Wisdom—Although Vulnerable—is Superior to Power</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ec 9:13">13</verse-number>I have also seen this <supplied>example of</supplied> wisdom under the sun, and it <supplied>seemed</supplied> great to me. <verse-number id="Ec 9:14">14</verse-number><supplied>There was</supplied> a small city with few people in it. A great king came and besieged it, building great siege works against it. <verse-number id="Ec 9:15">15</verse-number>Now, a poor wise man was found in it, and he delivered the city by his wisdom. <verse-number id="Ec 9:16">16</verse-number>So I concluded that wisdom <supplied>is</supplied> better than might, yet the wisdom of the poor is despised, and his words are not heard. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Wisdom—Although Vulnerable—is Superior to Folly</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 9:17">17</verse-number>The words of the wise are heard in peace </li1>
				<li2><supplied>more</supplied> than the shouting of a ruler <supplied>is heard</supplied> among the fools. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 9:18">18</verse-number>Wisdom <supplied>is</supplied> better than weapons of war, </li1>
				<li2>but one sinner destroys much good. </li2>
			</ul>
		</chapter>