<chapter id="Ec 10">
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 10">10</verse-number><verse-number id="Ec 10:1">1</verse-number> Dead flies cause a bad smell <supplied>and</supplied> ruin<note>Or “spew”</note> the ointment of the perfumer. </li1>
				<li2>So also a little folly outweighs wisdom and honor. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 10:2">2</verse-number>The heart of the wise <supplied>inclines</supplied> to his right, </li1>
				<li2>but the heart of the fool <supplied>inclines</supplied> to his left. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 10:3">3</verse-number>Even when the fool walks along the road, he lacks sense; </li1>
				<li2>he tells everyone <supplied>that</supplied> he is a fool. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 10:4">4</verse-number>If the anger of the ruler rises against you, </li1>
				<li2>do not leave your post, </li2>
				<li2>for calmness can undo great offenses. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 10:5">5</verse-number>There is an evil I have seen under the sun— </li1>
				<li2><supplied>it is</supplied> an error that proceeds from a ruler! </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 10:6">6</verse-number>The fool is set in many high places, </li1>
				<li2>but the rich sit in lowly places. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 10:7">7</verse-number>I have even seen slaves <supplied>riding</supplied> on horses </li1>
				<li2>and princes walking like slaves on the earth! </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Accidents Happen—Even to Professionals</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 10:8">8</verse-number>Whoever digs a pit will fall into it. </li1>
				<li2>Whoever breaks through a wall, a snake will bite him. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 10:9">9</verse-number>Whoever <idiom-start/>quarries<idiom-end/><note>Literally “breaks out”</note> stones will be wounded by them. </li1>
				<li2>Whoever splits logs will be endangered by them. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Hard Work and Skill Alone Cannot Succeed—Wisdom is Necessary</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 10:10">10</verse-number>If the ax is blunt but one does not sharpen its edge, </li1>
				<li2><idiom-start/>he must exert more effort<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “he must be more strength”</note> </li2>
				<li1>but the advantage of wisdom <supplied>is</supplied> it brings success. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 10:11">11</verse-number>If the snake bites before the charming, </li1>
				<li2><idiom-start/>the snake charmer will not succeed<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “there is no advantage to the owner of the charm”</note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Consequences of Foolishness</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 10:12">12</verse-number>The wise man <supplied>wins</supplied> favor by the words of his mouth, </li1>
				<li2>but the fool is devoured by his own lips. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 10:13">13</verse-number>He begins by saying what is foolish </li1>
				<li2>and ends by uttering what is wicked delusion. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 10:14">14</verse-number>The fool <idiom-start/>talks too much<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “increases words”</note> </li1>
				<li2>for no one knows what will be. </li2>
				<li3>Who can tell anyone what will happen <idiom-start/>in the future<idiom-end/>?<note>Literally “after him”</note> </li3>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 10:15">15</verse-number>The fool is so worn out by a hard day’s work </li1>
				<li2><idiom-start/>he cannot even find his way home at night<idiom-end/>.<note>Or “for he knows not to go to a city”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 10:16">16</verse-number>Woe to you, O land, when your king is a youth </li1>
				<li2>and your princes feast in the morning. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 10:17">17</verse-number>Blessed are you, O land, when your king is a son of nobility </li1>
				<li2>and your princes feast at the proper time— </li2>
				<li3>to gain strength and not to get drunk. </li3>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 10:18">18</verse-number>Through sloth the roof sinks in, </li1>
				<li2>and through idleness of hands the house leaks. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 10:19">19</verse-number><idiom-start/>Feasts are held for celebration<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “They make bread for laughter”</note> </li1>
				<li2>wine cheers the living, </li2>
				<li3>and money answers everything. </li3>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 10:20">20</verse-number>Do not curse the king even in your thoughts, </li1>
				<li2>and do not curse the rich even in your own bedroom, </li2>
				<li1>for a bird of the sky may carry your voice; </li1>
				<li2>a winged messenger may repeat your words. </li2>
			</ul>
		</chapter>