<chapter id="Ec 11">
			<pericope>Living in the Light of the Limits of Human Knowledge</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 11:1">1</verse-number>Send out your bread on the water, </li1>
				<li2>for in many days you will find it. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 11:2">2</verse-number>Divide your share in seven or in eight, </li1>
				<li2>for you do not know what disaster will happen on the earth. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 11:3">3</verse-number>When the clouds are full, </li1>
				<li2>they empty rain on the earth. </li2>
				<li1>Whether a tree falls to the south or whether it falls to the north, </li1>
				<li2>the place where the tree falls—there it will be. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 11:4">4</verse-number>Whoever watches the wind will not sow; </li1>
				<li2>whoever watches the clouds will not reap. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 11:5">5</verse-number>Just as you do not know how the path of the wind<note>Or “the breath”</note> <supplied>goes</supplied>, </li1>
				<li2>nor how the bones <supplied>of a fetus</supplied> form in a mother’s womb, </li2>
				<li1>so you do not know the work of God who makes everything. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 11:6">6</verse-number>Sow your seed in the morning, </li1>
				<li2>and do not let your hands rest in the evening, </li2>
				<li1>for you do not know what will prosper— </li1>
				<li2>whether this or that, or whether both of them alike will succeed. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Enjoy Life to the Fullest within the Auspices of the Fear of God</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 11:7">7</verse-number>The light is sweet, </li1>
				<li2>and it <supplied>is</supplied> pleasant for the eyes to see the sun. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 11:8">8</verse-number>For if a man lives many years, </li1>
				<li2>let him rejoice in all of them! </li2>
				<li1>Let him remember that the days of the darkness will be many— </li1>
				<li2>all that is coming <supplied>is</supplied> vanity! </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 11:9">9</verse-number>Rejoice, O young man, in your youth, </li1>
				<li2>and let your heart cheer you in the days of your youth! </li2>
				<li1>Follow the ways of your heart and the sight of your eyes— </li1>
				<li2>but know that God will bring you into judgment for all these things. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 11:10">10</verse-number>Banish anxiety from your heart, </li1>
				<li2>and put away pain from your body, </li2>
				<li1>for youth and vigor <supplied>are</supplied> vanity. </li1>
			</ul>
		</chapter>