<chapter id="Ec 12">
			<pericope>Advice to the Young: Life is Short and Then You Die</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 12:1">1</verse-number>Remember your Creator in the days of your youth— </li1>
				<li2>before the days of trouble come </li2>
				<li1>and the years draw near when you will say, </li1>
				<li2>“I find no pleasure in them!” </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 12:2">2</verse-number>Before the sun, the light, the moon, and the stars darken </li1>
				<li2>and the clouds return after the rain. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 12:3">3</verse-number>When the guards of the house tremble, </li1>
				<li2>and the men of strength are bent; </li2>
				<li1>the grinders cease because they are few, </li1>
				<li2>and those looking through the windows see dimly. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 12:4">4</verse-number>When the doors on the street are shut, </li1>
				<li2>when the sound of the grinding mill is low; </li2>
				<li1>one rises up to the sound of the bird, </li1>
				<li2>and all the daughters of song are brought low. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 12:5">5</verse-number>They are afraid of heights, </li1>
				<li2>and terrors <supplied>are</supplied> on the road. </li2>
				<li1>The almond tree blossoms, </li1>
				<li2>and the grasshopper draws itself along, and desire fails </li2>
				<li1>because man goes to his eternal home, </li1>
				<li2>and the mourners go about in the streets. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 12:6">6</verse-number>Before the silver cord is snapped </li1>
				<li2>and the golden bowl is broken; </li2>
				<li1>and the jar at the foundation is broken, </li1>
				<li2>and the wheel at the cistern is broken. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 12:7">7</verse-number>And the dust returns to the earth as it was, </li1>
				<li2>and the breath returns to God who gave it. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Motto Restated</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 12:8">8</verse-number>“Vanity of vanity!” says the Teacher.<note>Hebrew “Qohelet”</note> </li1>
				<li2>“Everything <supplied>is</supplied> vanity!” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Epilogue</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ec 12:9">9</verse-number>The Teacher<note>Hebrew “Qohelet”</note> was full of wisdom, and he taught the people with knowledge. He carefully considered many proverbs and carefully arranged them. <verse-number id="Ec 12:10">10</verse-number>The Teacher<note>Hebrew “Qohelet”</note> sought to find delightful words,<note>Hebrew “words of delight”</note> and he wrote<note>The MT reads the term passively, “<supplied>what</supplied> is written,” but an alternate textual tradition reads, “and he wrote”</note> what is upright—truthful words. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ec 12:11">11</verse-number>The words of the wise <supplied>are</supplied> like cattle goads; the collections of the sages <supplied>are</supplied> like pricks inflicted by one shepherd.<note>Or “The owner of collections are given by one shepherd”</note> <verse-number id="Ec 12:12">12</verse-number>My son, be careful <idiom-start/>about anything beyond these things<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “but from more than them”</note> For the writing of books is endless, and too much study <idiom-start/>is wearisome<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “increases weariness of flesh”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 12:13">13</verse-number>Now that all has been heard, here is the final conclusion: </li1>
				<li2>Fear God and obey his commandments, </li2>
				<li3>for this <supplied>is</supplied> the whole <supplied>duty</supplied> of man. </li3>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ec 12:14">14</verse-number>For God will bring every deed into judgment, </li1>
				<li2>including every secret thing, whether good or evil. </li2>
			</ul>
		</chapter>