<chapter id="Ex 2">
			<pericope>The Birth and Early Life of Moses</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 2:1">1</verse-number>And a man from the <idiom-start/>family<idiom-end/><note>Literally “house”</note> of Levi went, and he took <idiom-start/>a descendent of Levi<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “daughter of Levi”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 2:2">2</verse-number>And the woman conceived, and she gave birth to a son, and she saw him, that he was a fine baby, and she hid him three months. <verse-number id="Ex 2:3">3</verse-number>But when she could no longer hide him, she got a papyrus basket for him, and she coated it with tar and with pitch, and she placed the boy in it, and she placed <supplied>it</supplied> among the reeds on the bank of the Nile. <verse-number id="Ex 2:4">4</verse-number>And his sister stood at a distance to know what would be done to him. <verse-number id="Ex 2:5">5</verse-number>And the daughter of Pharaoh went down to wash at the Nile, <supplied>while</supplied> her maidservants were walking alongside the Nile, and she saw the basket in the midst of the reeds, and she sent her slave woman <supplied>for it</supplied> and took it <verse-number id="Ex 2:6">6</verse-number>and opened <supplied>it</supplied> and saw him—the boy—and it was a lad weeping, and she had compassion for him and said, “This <supplied>must be</supplied> from the boys of the Hebrews.”<note>Each instance of the implied “she” in verses 5 and 6 is the daughter of Pharaoh</note> <verse-number id="Ex 2:7">7</verse-number>And his sister said to the daughter of Pharaoh, “Shall I go and call for you a woman from the Hebrews <supplied>who is</supplied> nursing <supplied>so that</supplied> she will nurse the boy for you?” <verse-number id="Ex 2:8">8</verse-number>And the daughter of Pharaoh said to her, “Go.” And the girl went, and she called the mother of the boy. <verse-number id="Ex 2:9">9</verse-number>And the daughter of Pharaoh said, “Take this boy and nurse him for me, and I myself will give you wages, and the woman took the boy, and she nursed him. <verse-number id="Ex 2:10">10</verse-number>And the boy grew, and she brought him to the daughter of Pharaoh, and he became her son, and she called his name Moses, and she said, “Because I drew him out from the water.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 2:11">11</verse-number><idiom-start/>And then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and he/it was”</note> in those days when Moses had grown up, he went out to his brothers, and he saw their <idiom-start/>forced labor<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “burdens” or “burdensome labor”</note> and he saw an Egyptian man striking a Hebrew man, <supplied>one of</supplied> his brothers.<note>Or “a Hebrew man from his brothers”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 2:12">12</verse-number>And he turned here and there, and he saw no one,<note>Literally “and he saw that there was not a man”</note> and he struck the Egyptian, and he hid him in the sand. <verse-number id="Ex 2:13">13</verse-number>And he went out on the second day, and there were two Hebrew men fighting, and he said to the guilty <supplied>one</supplied>, “Why do you strike your neighbor?” <verse-number id="Ex 2:14">14</verse-number>And he said, “Who <idiom-start/>appointed you as a commander<idiom-end/><note>Literally “put you for a man, a commander” or “placed you for a man, a commander”</note> and a judge over us? <supplied>Are</supplied> you intending to kill me like you killed the Egyptian?” And Moses was afraid, and he said, “Surely the matter has become known.” <verse-number id="Ex 2:15">15</verse-number>And Pharaoh heard this matter, and he sought to kill Moses, and Moses fled from Pharaoh, and he lived in the land of Midian, and he lived at <idiom-start/>a certain well<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the well”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 2:16">16</verse-number><supplied>Now</supplied> the priest of Midian had seven daughters, and they came and drew water and filled the troughs to water their father’s flock.<note>The Hebrew noun translated “flock” is used here and in verses 17 and 19 collectively for sheep or goats or a mix of the two</note> <verse-number id="Ex 2:17">17</verse-number>And the shepherds came and drove them away, but Moses stood up and came to their rescue and watered their flock. <verse-number id="Ex 2:18">18</verse-number>And they came to Reuel, their father, and he said, “<idiom-start/>Why have you come so quickly<idiom-end/><note>Literally “why did you hasten coming”</note> today?” <verse-number id="Ex 2:19">19</verse-number>And they said, “An Egyptian man delivered us from the hand of the shepherds, and he even drew <supplied>water</supplied> for us and watered the flock.” <verse-number id="Ex 2:20">20</verse-number>And he said to his daughters, “Where <supplied>is</supplied> he? <idiom-start/>Why then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “why this”</note> have you left the man? <idiom-start/>Call him so that he can eat some food<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “call to <supplied>or “summon/invite”</supplied> him and he will eat bread”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 2:21">21</verse-number>And Moses agreed to stay with the man, and he gave Zipporah his daughter to Moses. <verse-number id="Ex 2:22">22</verse-number>And she bore a son, and he called his name Gershom because he said, “I am an alien in a foreign land.”<note>The word translated “alien” sounds like the first syllable in the name Gershom. The second syllable sounds like the word for “there”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 2:23">23</verse-number><idiom-start/>And then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and he/it was”</note> during those many days, the king of Egypt died, and the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> groaned because of the work, and they cried out, and their cry for help because of the work went up to God. <verse-number id="Ex 2:24">24</verse-number>And God heard their groaning, and God remembered his covenant with Abraham, with Isaac, and with Jacob, <verse-number id="Ex 2:25">25</verse-number>and God saw the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and God took notice.<note>Or “and God knew”</note> </p>
		</chapter>