<chapter id="Ex 3">
			<pericope>Yahweh’s Plan to Rescue the Israelites</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 3:1">1</verse-number>And Moses was a shepherd with the flock<note>The Hebrew noun translated “flock” in this verse is used collectively for sheep or goats or a mix of the two.</note> of Jethro, his father-in-law, the priest of Midian, and he led the flock to the west <supplied>of</supplied> the desert, and he came to the mountain of God, to Horeb. <verse-number id="Ex 3:2">2</verse-number>And the angel of Yahweh appeared to him in a flame of fire from the midst of a bush, and he looked, and there was the bush burning with fire, but the bush was not being consumed. <verse-number id="Ex 3:3">3</verse-number>And Moses said, “Let me turn aside and see this great sight. Why does the bush not burn up?” <verse-number id="Ex 3:4">4</verse-number>And Yahweh saw that he turned aside to see, and God called to him from the midst of the bush, and he said, “Moses, Moses.” And he said, “Here I <supplied>am</supplied>.” <verse-number id="Ex 3:5">5</verse-number>And he said, “You must not come near to here. Take off your sandals from on your feet, because the place on which you <supplied>are</supplied> standing, it <supplied>is</supplied> holy ground.” <verse-number id="Ex 3:6">6</verse-number>And he said, “I am the God of your father, the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob.” And Moses hid his face because he was afraid of looking at God. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 3:7">7</verse-number>And Yahweh said, “Surely I have seen the misery of my people who <supplied>are</supplied> in Egypt, and I have heard their cry of distress because of their oppressors, for I know their sufferings. <verse-number id="Ex 3:8">8</verse-number>And I have come down to deliver them from the hand of <supplied>the</supplied> Egyptians and to bring them up from this land to a good and wide land, to a land flowing with milk and honey, to the place of the Canaanites<note>Hebrew “Canaanite”</note> and the Hittites<note>Hebrew “Hittite”</note> and the Amorites<note>Hebrew “Amorite”</note> and the Perizzites<note>Hebrew “Perizzite”</note> and the Hivites<note>Hebrew “Hivite”</note> and the Jebusites.<note>Hebrew “Jebusite”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 3:9">9</verse-number>And now, look, the cry of distress of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> has come to me, and also I see the oppression <supplied>with</supplied> which <supplied>the</supplied> Egyptians <supplied>are</supplied> oppressing them. <verse-number id="Ex 3:10">10</verse-number>And now come, and I will send you to Pharaoh, and <supplied>you must</supplied> bring my people, the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> out from Egypt.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 3:11">11</verse-number>But Moses said to God, “Who <supplied>am</supplied> I that I should go to Pharaoh and that I should bring the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> out from Egypt?” <verse-number id="Ex 3:12">12</verse-number>And he said, “Because I am with you, and this <supplied>will be</supplied> the sign for you that I myself have sent you: When you bring the people out from Egypt, you will serve God on this mountain.” <verse-number id="Ex 3:13">13</verse-number>But Moses said to God, “Look, <supplied>if</supplied> I go to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and I say to them, ‘The God of your ancestors<note>Or “fathers”</note> has sent me to you,’ and they say to me, ‘What <supplied>is</supplied> his name?’ <supplied>then</supplied> what shall I say to them?” <verse-number id="Ex 3:14">14</verse-number>And God said to Moses, “I am that I am.” And he said, “So you must say to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> ‘I am sent me to you.’ ” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 3:15">15</verse-number>And God said again to Moses, “So you must say to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> ‘Yahweh, the God of your ancestors,<note>Or “fathers”</note> the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob, has sent me to you. This <supplied>is</supplied> my name forever, and this <supplied>is</supplied> my remembrance from generation <supplied>to</supplied> generation.’ <verse-number id="Ex 3:16">16</verse-number>Go and gather the elders of Israel and say to them, ‘Yahweh, the God of your ancestors,<note>Or “fathers”</note> appeared to me, the God of Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, saying, “I have carefully attended to you and what has been done to you in Egypt.” <verse-number id="Ex 3:17">17</verse-number>And I said, “I will bring you up from the misery of Egypt to the land of the Canaanites<note>Hebrew “Canaanite”</note> and the Hittites<note>Hebrew “Hittite”</note> and the Amorites<note>Hebrew “Amorite”</note> and the Perizzites<note>Hebrew “Perizzite”</note> and the Hivites<note>Hebrew “Hivite”</note> and the Jebusites,<note>Hebrew “Jebusite”</note> to a land flowing with milk and honey.” ’ <verse-number id="Ex 3:18">18</verse-number>And they will listen to your voice, and you will go, you and the elders of Israel, to the king of Egypt, and you will say to him, ‘Yahweh, the God of the Hebrews has met with us, and now let us please go <supplied>on</supplied> a journey of three days into the desert, and let us sacrifice to Yahweh our God.’ </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 3:19">19</verse-number>But I myself know that the king of Egypt will not allow you to go <idiom-start/>unless compelled by a strong hand<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “and not with a strong hand”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 3:20">20</verse-number>And I will stretch out my hand, and I will strike Egypt with all of my wonders that I will do in its midst, and <idiom-start/>afterward<idiom-end/><note>Literally “after so” or “after <supplied>I do</supplied> so”</note> he will release you. <verse-number id="Ex 3:21">21</verse-number>And I will give this people favor in the eyes of <supplied>the</supplied> Egyptians, <idiom-start/>and then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and he/it will be”</note> when you go, you will not go empty-handed. <verse-number id="Ex 3:22">22</verse-number>And a woman will ask from her neighbor and from the woman dwelling as an alien in her house <supplied>for</supplied> objects of silver and objects of gold and garments, and you will put <supplied>them</supplied> on your sons and on your daughters; and you will plunder Egypt.” </p>
		</chapter>