<chapter id="Ex 5">
			<pericope>Pharaoh Rejects Yahweh’s Authority and Makes Israel’s Troubles Worse</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 5:1">1</verse-number>And afterward, Moses and Aaron went, and they said to Pharaoh, “Thus says Yahweh the God of Israel, ‘Release my people so that they may hold a festival for me in the desert.’ ” <verse-number id="Ex 5:2">2</verse-number>And Pharaoh said, “Who is Yahweh that I should listen to his voice to release Israel? I do not know Yahweh, and also I will not release Israel.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 5:3">3</verse-number>And they said, “The God of the Hebrews has met with us. Please let us go <supplied>on</supplied> a three-day journey into the desert, and let us sacrifice to Yahweh our God, lest he strike us with plague or with sword.” <verse-number id="Ex 5:4">4</verse-number>And the king of Egypt said, “Why, Moses and Aaron, do you take<note>Or “let loose,” “let run wild” (compare 32:25)</note> the people from their work? Go to your <idiom-start/>forced labor<idiom-end/>!”<note>Literally “burdens” or “burdensome labor”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 5:5">5</verse-number>And Pharaoh said, “Look, the people of the land <supplied>are</supplied> now many, and you want to stop them from their <idiom-start/>forced labor<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “burdens” or “burdensome labor”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 5:6">6</verse-number>And on that day Pharaoh commanded the slave drivers over the people and his foremen, saying, <verse-number id="Ex 5:7">7</verse-number>“You must no longer give straw to the people to make the bricks like <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “yesterday three days ago”</note> Let them go and gather straw for themselves. <verse-number id="Ex 5:8">8</verse-number>But the quota of the bricks that they <supplied>were</supplied> making <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “yesterday three days ago”</note> <idiom-start/>you must require of them<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “you will put on them”</note> You must not reduce from it, because they <supplied>are</supplied> lazy. Therefore they <supplied>are</supplied> crying out, saying, ‘Let us go and sacrifice to our God.’ <verse-number id="Ex 5:9">9</verse-number>Let the work be heavier on the men so that they will do it and not pay attention to words of deception.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 5:10">10</verse-number>And the slave drivers of the people and their foremen went out, and they spoke to the people, saying, “Thus says Pharaoh, ‘I <supplied>am</supplied> not giving you straw. <verse-number id="Ex 5:11">11</verse-number>You go, get straw for yourselves from whatever you find because not a thing is being reduced from your work.’ ” <verse-number id="Ex 5:12">12</verse-number>And the people spread out in all the land of Egypt to gather stubble for the straw. <verse-number id="Ex 5:13">13</verse-number>And the slave drivers <supplied>were</supplied> insisting, saying, “Finish your work <idiom-start/>for each day<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a thing of a day”</note> on its day, as <idiom-start/>when there was straw<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “in the being of the straw”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 5:14">14</verse-number>And the foremen of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> whom Pharaoh’s slave drivers had appointed over them, were beaten <supplied>by men who were</supplied> saying, “Why have you not completed your portion of brickmaking <idiom-start/>as before, both yesterday and today<idiom-end/>?”<note>Literally “as yesterday three days ago also yesterday also the day”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Foremen Complain to Pharaoh and Moses, and Moses Complains to Yahweh</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 5:15">15</verse-number>And the foremen of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> came and cried out to Pharaoh, saying, “Why do you treat your servants like this? <verse-number id="Ex 5:16">16</verse-number>Straw <supplied>is</supplied> not being given to your servants, but <supplied>they are</supplied> saying to us, ‘Make bricks!’ and, look, your servants <supplied>are</supplied> being beaten, but it is the fault of<note>The expression is difficult. The word translated “fault” or “sin” has pointing for a second-person feminine singular subject (“you sinned”), which does not go well with either “Pharaoh” or “your people” as a subject; but the noun translated “sin of” has the same consonants, leading to the possibility that the word should be understood as a noun</note> your people.” <verse-number id="Ex 5:17">17</verse-number>And he said, “You <supplied>are</supplied> lazy, lazy! Therefore you <supplied>are</supplied> saying, ‘Let us go; let us sacrifice to Yahweh.’ <verse-number id="Ex 5:18">18</verse-number>And now go, work, but straw will not be given to you, and you must give the full quota of bricks.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 5:19">19</verse-number>And the foremen of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> saw they were in trouble <idiom-start/>with the saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “saying”</note> “You will not reduce from your bricks <idiom-start/>for each day<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a thing of a day”</note> on its day.” <verse-number id="Ex 5:20">20</verse-number>And they met Moses and Aaron, <supplied>who were</supplied> waiting to meet them when they <supplied>were</supplied> going out from Pharaoh. <verse-number id="Ex 5:21">21</verse-number>And they said to them, “May Yahweh look upon you and judge because you have caused our fragrance to stink in the eyes of Pharaoh and in the eyes of his servants <supplied>so as</supplied> to put a sword into their hand to kill us.” <verse-number id="Ex 5:22">22</verse-number>And Moses returned to Yahweh and said, “Lord, why have you brought trouble to this people? Why ever did you send me? <verse-number id="Ex 5:23">23</verse-number>And from the time I came to Pharaoh to speak in your name, he has brought trouble to this people, and you have certainly not delivered your people.” </p>
		</chapter>