<chapter id="Ex 6">
			<pericope>Yahweh Discusses His Name and Israel’s Future</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 6:1">1</verse-number>And Yahweh said to Moses, “Now you will see what I will do to Pharaoh, because with a strong hand he will release them, and with a strong hand he will drive them out from his land.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 6:2">2</verse-number>And God spoke to Moses, and he said to him, “I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh. <verse-number id="Ex 6:3">3</verse-number>And I appeared to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob as God Shaddai,<note>Often translated as “Almighty”</note> but by my name Yahweh I was not known to them. <verse-number id="Ex 6:4">4</verse-number>And I not only established my covenant with them to give to them the land of Canaan, the land of their sojournings, in which they dwelt as aliens, <verse-number id="Ex 6:5">5</verse-number>but also I myself heard the groaning of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> whom <supplied>the</supplied> Egyptians <supplied>are</supplied> making to work, and I remembered my covenant. <verse-number id="Ex 6:6">6</verse-number>Therefore say to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> ‘I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh, and I will bring you out from under the <idiom-start/>forced labor<idiom-end/><note>Literally “burdens” or “burdensome labor”</note> of Egypt, and I will deliver you from their slavery, and I will redeem you with an outstretched arm and with great punishments. <verse-number id="Ex 6:7">7</verse-number>And I will take you <idiom-start/>as my people<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to/for me for a people”</note> and I will be <idiom-start/>your God<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to/for you for a God”</note> and you will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh your God, who brought you out from under the <idiom-start/>forced labor<idiom-end/><note>Literally “burdens” or “burdensome labor”</note> of Egypt. <verse-number id="Ex 6:8">8</verse-number>And I will bring you to the land <idiom-start/>that I swore<idiom-end/><note>Literally “that I raised my hand”</note> to give to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob, and I will give it to you <supplied>as</supplied> a possession. I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 6:9">9</verse-number>And Moses spoke thus to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> but they did not listen to Moses, because of <idiom-start/>discouragement<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a lack of spirit” or “shortness of spirit”</note> and because of hard work. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 6:10">10</verse-number>And Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Ex 6:11">11</verse-number>“Go, speak to Pharaoh, the king of Egypt, and let him release the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> from his land.” <verse-number id="Ex 6:12">12</verse-number>And Moses spoke before Yahweh, saying, “Look, the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> do not listen to me, and how will Pharaoh listen to me, since I <supplied>am</supplied> <idiom-start/>a poor speaker<idiom-end/>?”<note>Literally “uncircumcised of lips”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 6:13">13</verse-number>And Yahweh spoke to Moses and to Aaron, and he commanded them <supplied>to go</supplied> to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and to Pharaoh, the king of Egypt, to bring the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> out from the land of Egypt. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Genealogy of Moses and Aaron</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 6:14">14</verse-number>These <supplied>are</supplied> the heads of <idiom-start/>their families<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the house of their fathers”</note> </p>
			<p>The sons of Reuben, the firstborn of Israel, <supplied>are</supplied> Enoch and Pallu, Hezron and Carmi. These <supplied>are</supplied> the clans of Reuben. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 6:15">15</verse-number>And the sons of Simeon <supplied>are</supplied> Jemuel and Jamin and Ohad and Jakin and Zohar and Shaul the son of the Canaanitess.<note>Or “the Canaanite woman.” The Hebrew word is feminine</note> These <supplied>are</supplied> the clans of Simeon. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 6:16">16</verse-number>And these <supplied>are</supplied> the names of the sons of Levi according to their genealogies:<note>Or “generations”</note> Gershon and Kohath and Merari, and the years of the life of Levi <supplied>were</supplied> <idiom-start/>one hundred and thirty-seven years<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “seven and thirty and hundred of year”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 6:17">17</verse-number>The sons of Gershon <supplied>are</supplied> Libni and Shimei according to their clans. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 6:18">18</verse-number>And the sons of Kohath <supplied>are</supplied> Amram and Izhar and Hebron and Uzziel, and the years of the life of Kohath <supplied>were</supplied> <idiom-start/>one hundred and thirty-three years<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “three and thirty and hundred of year”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 6:19">19</verse-number>And the sons of Merari <supplied>are</supplied> Mahli and Mushi. These <supplied>are</supplied> clans of the Levites according to their genealogies.<note>Or “generations”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 6:20">20</verse-number>And Amram took Jochebed his aunt for himself as a wife, and she bore for him Aaron and Moses, and the years of the life of Amram <supplied>were</supplied> <idiom-start/>one hundred and thirty-seven years<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “seven and thirty and hundred of year”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 6:21">21</verse-number>And the sons of Izhar <supplied>are</supplied> Korah and Nepheg and Zikri. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 6:22">22</verse-number>And the sons of Uzziel <supplied>are</supplied> Mishael and Elzaphan and Sithri. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 6:23">23</verse-number>And Aaron took Elisheba the daughter of Amminadab, the sister of Nahshon, for himself as a wife, and she bore for him Nadab and Abihu, Eleazar and Ithamar. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 6:24">24</verse-number>And the sons of Korah <supplied>are</supplied> Assir and Elkanah and Abiasaph. These <supplied>are</supplied> the clans of the Korahites. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 6:25">25</verse-number>And Eleazar the son of Aaron took for himself <supplied>one</supplied> from the daughters of Putiel as a wife, and she bore for him Phinehas. These <supplied>are</supplied> the heads of the <idiom-start/>families<idiom-end/><note>Literally “fathers”</note> of the Levites according to their clans. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 6:26">26</verse-number><supplied>It was</supplied> that Aaron and Moses to whom Yahweh said, “Bring the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> out from the land of Egypt according to their divisions.” <verse-number id="Ex 6:27">27</verse-number>They <supplied>were</supplied> those who spoke to Pharaoh, the king of Egypt, in order to bring the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> out from Egypt. <supplied>It was</supplied> that Moses and Aaron. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 6:28">28</verse-number><idiom-start/>And so it was on a certain day<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and it was on a day”</note> Yahweh spoke to Moses in the land of Egypt. <verse-number id="Ex 6:29">29</verse-number>And Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, “I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh. Speak to Pharaoh, the king of Egypt, all that I <supplied>am</supplied> speaking to you.” <verse-number id="Ex 6:30">30</verse-number>And Moses said before Yahweh, “Look, I <supplied>am</supplied> <idiom-start/>a poor speaker<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “uncircumcised of lips”</note> And how will Pharaoh listen to me?” </p>
		</chapter>