<chapter id="Ex 7">
			<pericope>Yahweh Reviews Plans for Bringing the Israelites out of Egypt</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 7:1">1</verse-number>And Yahweh said to Moses, “See, I have made you <supplied>as</supplied> a god to Pharaoh, and Aaron your brother will be your prophet. <verse-number id="Ex 7:2">2</verse-number>You will speak all that I will command you, and Aaron your brother will speak to Pharaoh, and he will release the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> from his land. <verse-number id="Ex 7:3">3</verse-number>And I myself will harden the heart of Pharaoh, and I will make my signs and my wonders numerous in the land of Egypt. <verse-number id="Ex 7:4">4</verse-number>And Pharaoh will not listen to you, and I will put my hand into Egypt and bring out my divisions, my people, the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> from the land of Egypt with great punishments. <verse-number id="Ex 7:5">5</verse-number>And <supplied>the</supplied> Egyptians will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh when I stretch out my hand over Egypt and bring the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> out from their midst.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 7:6">6</verse-number>And Moses and Aaron did <supplied>it</supplied>; as Yahweh commanded them, so they did. <verse-number id="Ex 7:7">7</verse-number>(And Moses <supplied>was</supplied> <idiom-start/>eighty years old<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “a son of eighty year”</note> and Aaron <supplied>was</supplied> <idiom-start/>eighty-three years old<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a son of three and eighty year”</note> when they spoke to Pharaoh.) </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Provision of a Wonder: Aaron’s Staff Becomes a Snake</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 7:8">8</verse-number>And Yahweh said to Moses and to Aaron, saying, <verse-number id="Ex 7:9">9</verse-number>“When Pharaoh speaks to you, saying, ‘Do a wonder for yourselves,’ you will say to Aaron, ‘Take your staff and throw it before Pharaoh, and it will become a snake.’ ” <verse-number id="Ex 7:10">10</verse-number>And Moses and Aaron came to Pharaoh, and they did so, as Yahweh had commanded. And Aaron threw his staff before Pharaoh and before his servants, and it became a snake. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 7:11">11</verse-number>And Pharaoh also called the wise men and the sorcerers, and they also, the magicians of Egypt, did likewise with their secret arts. <verse-number id="Ex 7:12">12</verse-number>Each threw down his staff, and they became snakes, and Aaron’s staff swallowed up their staffs. <verse-number id="Ex 7:13">13</verse-number>And Pharaoh’s heart was hard, and he did not listen to them, as Yahweh had said. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Plague One: Blood</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 7:14">14</verse-number>And Yahweh said to Moses, “Pharaoh’s heart <supplied>is</supplied> <idiom-start/>insensitive<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “heavy”</note> he refuses to release the people. <verse-number id="Ex 7:15">15</verse-number>Go to Pharaoh in the morning. Look, <supplied>he is</supplied> going out to the water, and you must wait to meet him on the bank of the Nile, and you must take in your hand the staff that was changed into a snake. <verse-number id="Ex 7:16">16</verse-number>And you must say to him, ‘Yahweh, the God of the Hebrews, has sent me to you, saying, “Release my people that they may serve me in the desert, and, look, you have not listened until now.” <verse-number id="Ex 7:17">17</verse-number>Thus says Yahweh, “By this you will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh. Look, I <supplied>am about to</supplied> strike with the staff that is in my hand the water that is in the Nile, and it will be changed to blood. <verse-number id="Ex 7:18">18</verse-number>And the fish that <supplied>are</supplied> in the Nile will die, and the Nile will stink, and <supplied>the</supplied> Egyptians will be unable to drink water from the Nile.” ’ ” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 7:19">19</verse-number>And Yahweh said to Moses, “Say to Aaron, ‘Take your staff and stretch your hand out over the waters of Egypt and over their rivers, over their canals, and over their pools and over all of their reservoirs of water, so that they become blood,’ and blood will be in all the land of Egypt and in <supplied>vessels of</supplied> wood and of stone.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 7:20">20</verse-number>And Moses and Aaron did so, as Yahweh had commanded, and he raised the staff and struck the water that was in the Nile before the eyes of Pharaoh and before the eyes of his servants, and all of the water that was in the Nile was changed to blood. <verse-number id="Ex 7:21">21</verse-number>And the fish that <supplied>were</supplied> in the Nile died, and the Nile stank, and <supplied>the</supplied> Egyptians were not able to drink water from the Nile, and the blood was in all the land of Egypt. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 7:22">22</verse-number>And the magicians of Egypt did likewise with their secret arts, and Pharaoh’s heart was hard, and he did not listen to them, as Yahweh had spoken. <verse-number id="Ex 7:23">23</verse-number>And Pharaoh turned and went to his house, and <idiom-start/>he did not take also this to heart<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “he did not put his heart also to this”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 7:24">24</verse-number>And all of <supplied>the</supplied> Egyptians dug around the Nile <supplied>for</supplied> water to drink, because they were unable to drink from the water of the Nile. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 7:25">25</verse-number>And seven days passed after Yahweh struck the Nile. </p>
		</chapter>