<chapter id="Ex 10">
			<pericope>Plague Eight: Locusts</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 10:1">1</verse-number>And Yahweh said to Moses, “Go to Pharaoh, for I have made his heart <idiom-start/>insensitive<idiom-end/><note>Literally “heavy”</note> and the heart of his servants in order to put these signs of mine in his midst, <verse-number id="Ex 10:2">2</verse-number>so that you will tell in the ears of your child and <idiom-start/>your grandchild<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the son of your son”</note> that I dealt harshly with <supplied>the</supplied> Egyptians and <supplied>so that you will tell about</supplied> my signs that I have done among them, and so you will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 10:3">3</verse-number>And Moses and Aaron came to Pharaoh, and they said to him, “Thus says Yahweh, the God of the Hebrews, ‘Until when will you refuse to submit before me? Release my people so that they may serve me. <verse-number id="Ex 10:4">4</verse-number>But if you <supplied>are</supplied> refusing to release my people, look, I <supplied>am</supplied> about to bring locusts into your territory tomorrow. <verse-number id="Ex 10:5">5</verse-number>And they will cover the surface of the land, and no one will be able to see the land, and they will eat the remainder of what is left—what is left over for you from the hail—and they will eat every sprouting tree <supplied>belonging</supplied> to you from the field. <verse-number id="Ex 10:6">6</verse-number>And your houses will be full, and the houses of all your servants and the houses of all Egypt, <supplied>something</supplied> that your fathers and <idiom-start/>your grandfathers<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the fathers of your fathers”</note> never saw from the day they were on the earth until this day.’ ” And he turned and went out from Pharaoh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 10:7">7</verse-number>And the servants of Pharaoh said to him, “Until when will this be a snare for us? Release the men so that they may serve Yahweh their God. Do you not yet know that Egypt is destroyed?” <verse-number id="Ex 10:8">8</verse-number>And Moses and Aaron were brought back to Pharaoh, and he said to them, “Serve Yahweh your God. <idiom-start/>Who are the ones going<idiom-end/>?<note>Literally “who and who the goers?”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 10:9">9</verse-number>And Moses said, “With our young and with our old we will go; with our sons and with our daughters, with our sheep and goats and with our cattle we will go because <supplied>it is</supplied> the feast of Yahweh for us.” <verse-number id="Ex 10:10">10</verse-number>And he said to them, “Let Yahweh be thus with you <supplied>as soon</supplied> as I release you and your dependents.<note>Or “little children” or “little ones”</note> See that evil is before your faces. <verse-number id="Ex 10:11">11</verse-number><idiom-start/>No indeed<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “not so”</note> <supplied>just</supplied> the men<note>This word for “men” indicates that Pharaoh means only the able-bodied men can go</note> go and serve Yahweh, since this <supplied>is what</supplied> you <supplied>are</supplied> seeking.” And he drove them out from the presence of Pharaoh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 10:12">12</verse-number>And Yahweh said to Moses, “Stretch out your hand over the land of Egypt with the locusts so that they may come up over the land of Egypt, and let them eat all the vegetation of the land, all that the hail left behind.” <verse-number id="Ex 10:13">13</verse-number>And Moses stretched out his staff over the land of Egypt, and Yahweh drove an east wind into the land all that day and all night. The morning came, and the east wind had brought the locusts. <verse-number id="Ex 10:14">14</verse-number>And the locusts went up over all the land of Egypt, and they settled in all the territory of Egypt, very <idiom-start/>severe<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “heavy”</note> Before it there were not locusts like them, nor will there be after it. <verse-number id="Ex 10:15">15</verse-number>And they covered the surface of all the land, and the land was dark <supplied>with them</supplied>, and they ate all the vegetation of the land and all the fruit of the trees that the hail had left, and no green was left in the trees nor in the vegetation of the field in all the land of Egypt. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 10:16">16</verse-number>And Pharaoh hurried to call Moses and Aaron, and he said, “I have sinned against Yahweh your God and against you. <verse-number id="Ex 10:17">17</verse-number>And now forgive my sin surely this time, and pray to Yahweh your God so that he may only remove from me this death.” <verse-number id="Ex 10:18">18</verse-number>And he went out from Pharaoh, and he prayed to Yahweh. <verse-number id="Ex 10:19">19</verse-number>And Yahweh turned a very strong <idiom-start/>west wind<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sea wind,” a wind from the Mediterranean Sea to the west</note> and lifted up the locusts and thrust them into the <idiom-start/>Red Sea<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sea of reed”</note> and not one locust remained in all the territory of Egypt. <verse-number id="Ex 10:20">20</verse-number>And Yahweh hardened Pharaoh’s heart, and he did not release the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Plague Nine: Darkness</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 10:21">21</verse-number>And Yahweh said to Moses, “Stretch out your hand toward the heavens so that there may be darkness over the land of Egypt and so that <supplied>a person can</supplied> feel darkness.” <verse-number id="Ex 10:22">22</verse-number>And Moses stretched out his hand toward the heavens, and there was darkness of night in all the land of Egypt <supplied>for</supplied> three days. <verse-number id="Ex 10:23">23</verse-number>No one could see his brother, and <idiom-start/>because of it no one could move from where they were<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a man did not rise from under it”</note> <supplied>for</supplied> three days, but there was light for the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> in their dwellings. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 10:24">24</verse-number>And Pharaoh called Moses and said, “Go, serve Yahweh. Only your sheep and goats and your cattle must be left behind. Your dependents<note>Or “little children” or “little ones”; the term here includes women and children and men too old or ill to fight</note> may also go with you.” <verse-number id="Ex 10:25">25</verse-number>And Moses said, “Even <supplied>if</supplied> you yourself put into our hand sacrifices and burnt offerings and we offer <supplied>them</supplied> to Yahweh our God, <verse-number id="Ex 10:26">26</verse-number>our livestock must also go with us. Not a hoof can be left because we must take from them to serve Yahweh our God. And we will not know <supplied>with</supplied> what we are to serve Yahweh until we come there.” <verse-number id="Ex 10:27">27</verse-number>And Yahweh hardened Pharaoh’s heart, and he was not willing to release them. <verse-number id="Ex 10:28">28</verse-number>And Pharaoh said to him, “Go from me. <idiom-start/>Be careful<idiom-end/><note>Literally “watch for you”</note> not to see my face again, because on the day of your seeing my face you will die.” <verse-number id="Ex 10:29">29</verse-number>And Moses said, “<idiom-start/>That is right<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “right you said”</note> <idiom-start/>I will not again see your face<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “I will not add again seeing of your face”</note> </p>
		</chapter>