<chapter id="Ex 11">
			<pericope>Announcement of the Tenth Plague: Death of the Firstborn</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 11:1">1</verse-number>And Yahweh said to Moses, “Still one plague I will bring upon Pharaoh and upon Egypt; afterward he will release you from here. At the moment of his releasing, he will certainly drive you completely out from here. <verse-number id="Ex 11:2">2</verse-number>Speak in the ears of the people, and let them ask, a man from his neighbor and a woman from her neighbor, <supplied>for</supplied> objects of silver and objects of gold.” <verse-number id="Ex 11:3">3</verse-number>And Yahweh gave the people favor in the eyes of Egypt. Also the man Moses <supplied>was</supplied> very great in the land of Egypt, in the eyes of the servants of Pharaoh and in the eyes of the people. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 11:4">4</verse-number>And Moses said, “Thus says Yahweh, ‘About the middle of the night I <supplied>will</supplied> go out through the midst of Egypt, <verse-number id="Ex 11:5">5</verse-number>and every firstborn in the land of Egypt will die, from the firstborn of Pharaoh who sits on his throne to the firstborn of the slave woman who <supplied>is</supplied> behind the pair of millstones and every firstborn animal.<note>The Hebrew word often refers to domestic animals</note> <verse-number id="Ex 11:6">6</verse-number>And there will be a great cry of distress in all the land of Egypt, the like of which has not been nor will be again.<note>Literally “which like it has not been and like it will not be again”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 11:7">7</verse-number>But against all the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> from a man to an animal, a dog will not <supplied>even</supplied> <idiom-start/>bark<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “move his tongue” or “sharpen his tongue”</note> so that you will know that Yahweh makes a distinction between Egypt and Israel.’ <verse-number id="Ex 11:8">8</verse-number>And all of these your servants will come down to me and bow to me, saying, ‘Go out, you and all the people who <supplied>are</supplied> at your feet.’ And afterward I will go out.” And he went out from Pharaoh <idiom-start/>in great anger<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “with heat of nose”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 11:9">9</verse-number>And Yahweh said to Moses, “Pharaoh will not listen to you, <idiom-start/>so that my wonders may multiply<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for the sake of the multiplying of my wonders”</note> in the land of Egypt.” <verse-number id="Ex 11:10">10</verse-number>And Moses and Aaron did all these wonders before Pharaoh, and Yahweh hardened Pharaoh’s heart, and he did not release the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> from his land. </p>
		</chapter>