<chapter id="Ex 12">
			<pericope>Instructions for the Feast of Passover</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 12:1">1</verse-number>And Yahweh said to Moses and to Aaron in the land of Egypt, saying, <verse-number id="Ex 12:2">2</verse-number>“This month <supplied>will be</supplied> the beginning of months; it <supplied>will be</supplied> for you the first of the months of the year. <verse-number id="Ex 12:3">3</verse-number>Speak to all the community of Israel, saying, ‘On the tenth of this month, they will each take for themselves <idiom-start/>a lamb for the family<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “a lamb/kid for the house of fathers.” The word translated “lamb” refers to a small livestock animal and could be either a young sheep or a young goat</note> a lamb for the household. <verse-number id="Ex 12:4">4</verse-number>And if the household is too small for a lamb, he and the neighbor nearest to his house will take <supplied>one</supplied> according to the number of persons;<note>Or “the number of selves”</note> you will count out portions of the lamb <idiom-start/>according to how much each one can eat<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “a man for the mouth of his eating”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 12:5">5</verse-number>The lamb for you must be a male, without defect, in its first year; you will take <supplied>it</supplied> from the sheep or from the goats. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 12:6">6</verse-number>“<idiom-start/>You will keep it<idiom-end/><note>Literally “It will be for you for observation”</note> until the fourteenth day of this month, and all the assembly of the community of Israel will slaughter it <idiom-start/>at twilight<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “between the evenings”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 12:7">7</verse-number>And they will take <supplied>some</supplied> of the blood and put <supplied>it</supplied> on the two doorposts and on the lintel on the houses in which they eat it. <verse-number id="Ex 12:8">8</verse-number>And they will eat the meat on this night; they will eat it fire-roasted and <supplied>with</supplied> unleavened bread on <idiom-start/>bitter herbs<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “bitter <supplied>things</supplied>”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 12:9">9</verse-number>You must not eat any of it raw or boiled, boiled in the water, but rather roasted with fire, its head with its legs and with its inner parts. <verse-number id="Ex 12:10">10</verse-number>And you must not leave any of it until morning; anything left from it until morning you must burn in the fire. <verse-number id="Ex 12:11">11</verse-number>And this is how you will eat it—<supplied>with</supplied> your waists fastened, your sandals on your feet, and your staff in your hand, and you will eat it in haste. It <supplied>is</supplied> Yahweh’s Passover. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 12:12">12</verse-number>“And I will go through the land of Egypt during this night, and I will strike all of the firstborn in the land of Egypt, from human to animal, and I will do punishments among all of the gods of Egypt. I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh. <verse-number id="Ex 12:13">13</verse-number>And the blood will be a sign for you on the houses where you are, and I will see the blood, and I will pass over you, and there will not be a destructive plague among you when I strike the land of Egypt. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 12:14">14</verse-number>“And this day will become a memorial for you, and you will celebrate it as a religious feast for Yahweh throughout your generations; you will celebrate it as a lasting statute. <verse-number id="Ex 12:15">15</verse-number>You will eat unleavened bread for seven days. Surely on the first day you shall remove yeast from your houses, because anyone <supplied>who</supplied> eats <supplied>food with</supplied> yeast from the first day until the seventh day—that person will be cut off from Israel. <verse-number id="Ex 12:16">16</verse-number>It will be for you on the first day a holy assembly<note>Or “summons,” “convocation”</note> and on the seventh day a holy assembly;<note>Or “summons,” “convocation”</note> no work will be done on them; only what is eaten by every person, it alone will be prepared for you. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 12:17">17</verse-number>“And you will keep the Feast of Unleavened Bread, because on this very day I brought out your divisions from the land of Egypt, and you will keep this day for your generations as a lasting statute. <verse-number id="Ex 12:18">18</verse-number>On the first <supplied>day</supplied>, on the fourteenth day of the month, in the evening, you will eat unleavened bread until the evening of the twenty-first day of the month. <verse-number id="Ex 12:19">19</verse-number>For seven days yeast must not be found in your houses, because <idiom-start/>anyone eating food with yeast<idiom-end/><note>Literally “anyone eating yeasted food, that person”</note> will be cut off from the community of Israel—<supplied>whether</supplied> an alien or a native of the land. <verse-number id="Ex 12:20">20</verse-number>You will eat no <supplied>food with</supplied> yeast; in all of your dwellings you will eat unleavened bread.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 12:21">21</verse-number>And Moses called all the elders of Israel, and he said to them, “Select and take for yourselves sheep for your clans and slaughter the Passover sacrifice. <verse-number id="Ex 12:22">22</verse-number>And take a bunch of hyssop and dip <supplied>it</supplied> into the blood that <supplied>is</supplied> in the basin and apply <supplied>some</supplied> of the blood that is in the basin to the lintel and the two doorposts. And you will not go out, anyone from the doorway of his house, until morning. <verse-number id="Ex 12:23">23</verse-number>And Yahweh will go through to strike Egypt, and he will see the blood on the lintel and on the two doorposts, and Yahweh will pass over the doorway and will not allow the destroyer to come to your houses to strike <supplied>you</supplied>. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 12:24">24</verse-number>“And you will keep this event as a rule for you and for your children forever.<note>Or “until eternity”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 12:25">25</verse-number><idiom-start/>And<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and it will be”</note> when you come into the land that Yahweh will give to you, as he said, you will keep this <idiom-start/>religious custom<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “service” or “work”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 12:26">26</verse-number><idiom-start/>And<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and it will be”</note> when your children say to you, ‘What <supplied>is</supplied> this <idiom-start/>religious custom<idiom-end/><note>Literally “service” or “work”</note> for you?’<note>Or “What does this service mean to you?”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 12:27">27</verse-number>you will say, ‘It <supplied>is</supplied> a Passover sacrifice for Yahweh, who passed over the houses of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> in Egypt when he struck Egypt; and he delivered our houses.’ ” And the people knelt down and they worshiped. <verse-number id="Ex 12:28">28</verse-number>And the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> went, and they did as Yahweh had commanded Moses and Aaron; so they did. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Death of Firstborn and Deliverance from Egypt</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 12:29">29</verse-number><idiom-start/>And<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and it was”</note> in the middle of the night, Yahweh struck all of the firstborn in the land of Egypt, from the firstborn of Pharaoh sitting on his throne to the firstborn of the captive who <supplied>was</supplied> in the prison house and every firstborn of an animal. <verse-number id="Ex 12:30">30</verse-number>And Pharaoh got up <supplied>at</supplied> night, he and all his servants and all Egypt, and a great cry of distress was in Egypt because there was not a house where there was no one dead. <verse-number id="Ex 12:31">31</verse-number>And he called Moses and Aaron <supplied>at</supplied> night, and he said, “Get up, go out from the midst of my people, both you as well as the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and go, serve Yahweh, as you have said. <verse-number id="Ex 12:32">32</verse-number>Take both your sheep and goats as well as your cattle, and go, and bless also me.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 12:33">33</verse-number>And <supplied>the</supplied> Egyptians urged the people <supplied>in order</supplied> to hurry their release<note>Or “to hasten to release them”</note> from the land, because they said, “All of us <supplied>will</supplied> die!”<note>Or “We all are dead!”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 12:34">34</verse-number>And the people lifted up their dough before it had yeast; their kneading troughs <supplied>were</supplied> wrapped up in their cloaks on their shoulder. <verse-number id="Ex 12:35">35</verse-number>And the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> did according to the word of Moses, and they asked from <supplied>the</supplied> Egyptians <supplied>for</supplied> objects of silver and objects of gold and <supplied>for</supplied> clothing. <verse-number id="Ex 12:36">36</verse-number>And Yahweh gave the people favor in the eyes of <supplied>the</supplied> Egyptians, and they granted <supplied>their</supplied> requests, and they plundered <supplied>the</supplied> Egyptians. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 12:37">37</verse-number>And the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> set out from Rameses to Succoth; the men <supplied>were</supplied> about six hundred thousand on foot,<note>Or “footmen,” “infantrymen.” The word probably has military connotations, as when it is used elsewhere in the numbering of soldiers (compare <cite title="BibleLEB2: 2 Sa 10:6">2 Sam 10:6</cite>; <cite title="BibleLEB2: 1 Ki 20:29">1 Kgs 20:29</cite>; <cite title="BibleLEB2: 2 Ki 13:7">2 Kgs 13:7</cite>)</note> besides dependents. <verse-number id="Ex 12:38">38</verse-number>And also a <idiom-start/>mixed multitude<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a large mixture” (compare <cite title="BibleLEB2: Je 25:20">Jer 25:20</cite>; <cite title="BibleLEB2: Eze 30:5">Ezek 30:5</cite>)</note> went up with them and sheep and goats and cattle, very numerous livestock. <verse-number id="Ex 12:39">39</verse-number>And they baked the dough that they had brought out from Egypt <supplied>as</supplied> cakes, unleavened bread, because it had no yeast when they were driven out from Egypt, and they were not able to delay, and also they had not made provisions for themselves. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 12:40">40</verse-number>And the period of dwelling of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> that they dwelled in Egypt <supplied>was</supplied> four hundred and thirty years. <verse-number id="Ex 12:41">41</verse-number>And at the end of four hundred and thirty years, on this exact day, all of Yahweh’s divisions went out from the land of Egypt. <verse-number id="Ex 12:42">42</verse-number>It <supplied>is</supplied> a night of vigils<note>Or “observances”</note> <supplied>belonging</supplied> to Yahweh for bringing them out from the land of Egypt; it <supplied>is</supplied> this night <supplied>belonging</supplied> to Yahweh <supplied>with</supplied> vigils for all of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> throughout their generations. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 12:43">43</verse-number>And Yahweh said to Moses and Aaron, “This <supplied>is</supplied> the statute of the Passover: No foreigner may eat it. <verse-number id="Ex 12:44">44</verse-number>But any slave of a man, an acquisition by money, and you have circumcised him, then he may eat it. <verse-number id="Ex 12:45">45</verse-number>A temporary resident and a hired worker may not eat it. <verse-number id="Ex 12:46">46</verse-number>It will be eaten in one house; you will not bring part of the meat out from the house to the outside; and you will not break a bone of it. <verse-number id="Ex 12:47">47</verse-number>All of the community of Israel will prepare it. <verse-number id="Ex 12:48">48</verse-number>And when an alien dwells with you and he wants to prepare <supplied>the</supplied> Passover for Yahweh, every male belonging to him must be circumcised, and then he may come near to prepare it, and he will be as the native of the land, but any uncircumcised <supplied>man</supplied> may not eat it. <verse-number id="Ex 12:49">49</verse-number>One law will be for the native and for the alien who is dwelling in your midst.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 12:50">50</verse-number>And all the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> did as Yahweh had commanded Moses and Aaron; so they did. <verse-number id="Ex 12:51">51</verse-number>And it was on exactly this day Yahweh brought the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> out from the land of Egypt by their divisions. </p>
		</chapter>