<chapter id="Ex 13">
			<pericope>Unleavened Bread and Dedication of Firstborn to Commemorate the Rescue from Egypt</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 13:1">1</verse-number>And Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Ex 13:2">2</verse-number>“Consecrate to me every firstborn, the first offspring of every womb among the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> among humans<note>Hebrew “human”</note> and among domestic animals;<note>Hebrew “animal”</note> <idiom-start/>it belongs to me<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “to/for me it”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 13:3">3</verse-number>And Moses said to the people, “Remember this day when you went out from Egypt, from a house of slaves, because with strength of hand Yahweh brought you out from here, and <supplied>food with</supplied> yeast will not be eaten. <verse-number id="Ex 13:4">4</verse-number>Today you are going out in the month of Abib. <verse-number id="Ex 13:5">5</verse-number>And when Yahweh brings you to the land of the Canaanites<note>Hebrew “Canaanite”</note> and the Hittites<note>Hebrew “Hittite”</note> and the Amorites<note>Hebrew “Amorite”</note> and the Hivites<note>Hebrew “Hivite”</note> and the Jebusites<note>Hebrew “Jebusite”</note>—which he swore to your ancestors<note>Or “fathers”</note> to give to you, a land flowing with milk and honey—you will perform this service in this month. <verse-number id="Ex 13:6">6</verse-number>Seven days you will eat unleavened bread, and on the seventh day <supplied>will be</supplied> a feast for Yahweh. <verse-number id="Ex 13:7">7</verse-number>Unleavened bread will be eaten the seven days; <supplied>food with</supplied> yeast will not be seen for you; and yeast will not be seen for you in all your territory. <verse-number id="Ex 13:8">8</verse-number>And you shall tell your son on that day, saying, ‘This <supplied>is</supplied> because of what Yahweh did for me when I came out from Egypt.’ <verse-number id="Ex 13:9">9</verse-number>And it will be as a sign on your hand and as a memorial between your eyes so that the law of Yahweh will be in your mouth, that with a strong hand Yahweh brought you out from Egypt. <verse-number id="Ex 13:10">10</verse-number>And you will keep this statute at its appointed time <idiom-start/>from year to year<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “from days to days”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 13:11">11</verse-number>“And when Yahweh brings you to the land of the Canaanite, as he swore to you and to your ancestors,<note>Or “fathers”</note> and he gives it to you, <verse-number id="Ex 13:12">12</verse-number>you will hand over every first offspring of a womb to Yahweh, and every first offspring dropped by a domestic animal that will belong to you, the males <supplied>will be</supplied> for Yahweh. <verse-number id="Ex 13:13">13</verse-number>And every first offspring of a donkey you will redeem with small livestock, and if you will not redeem <supplied>it</supplied>, then you will break its neck, and every firstborn human among your sons you will redeem. <verse-number id="Ex 13:14">14</verse-number>And when your son asks you <idiom-start/>in the future<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “tomorrow”</note> saying, ‘What <supplied>is</supplied> this?’ you will say to him, ‘With strength of hand Yahweh brought us out from Egypt, from a house of slaves. <verse-number id="Ex 13:15">15</verse-number>And when Pharaoh was stubborn to release us, Yahweh killed every firstborn in the land of Egypt, from firstborn human to firstborn domestic animal. Therefore I <supplied>am</supplied> sacrificing to Yahweh every first offspring of a womb, the males, and every firstborn of my sons I redeem.’ <verse-number id="Ex 13:16">16</verse-number>And it will be as a sign on your hand and as symbolic ornaments between your eyes that with strength of hand Yahweh brought us out from Egypt.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Summary of Travel</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 13:17">17</verse-number>And when Pharaoh released the people, God did not lead them the way of the land of the Philistines, though it <supplied>was</supplied> nearer, because God said, “Lest the people change their mind when they see war and return to Egypt.” <verse-number id="Ex 13:18">18</verse-number>So God led the people around <supplied>by</supplied> the way of the desert <supplied>to</supplied> the <idiom-start/>Red Sea<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sea of reed”</note> and the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> went up in battle array from the land of Egypt. <verse-number id="Ex 13:19">19</verse-number>And Moses took the bones of Joseph with him because <supplied>Joseph</supplied><note>Hebrew “he”</note> had made the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> solemnly swear an oath, saying, “God will surely attend to you, and you will take up my bones from here with you.” <verse-number id="Ex 13:20">20</verse-number>And they set out from Succoth, and they encamped at Etham on the edge of the desert. <verse-number id="Ex 13:21">21</verse-number>And Yahweh was going before them by day in a column of cloud to lead them <supplied>on</supplied> the way and <supplied>by</supplied> night in a column of fire to give light to them to go by day and night. <verse-number id="Ex 13:22">22</verse-number>The column of cloud by day and the column of fire <supplied>by</supplied> night did not depart from before the people. </p>
		</chapter>