<chapter id="Ex 14">
			<pericope>Yahweh Rescues Israel at the Red Sea</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 14:1">1</verse-number>And Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Ex 14:2">2</verse-number>“Speak to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> so that they turn and encamp before Pi-hahiroth, between Migdol <idiom-start/>and the sea<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “and between the sea”</note> before Baal Zephon, <supplied>which is</supplied> opposite it, you will camp by the sea. <verse-number id="Ex 14:3">3</verse-number>And Pharaoh will say of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> ‘They are wandering around in the land. The desert has closed in on them.’ <verse-number id="Ex 14:4">4</verse-number>And I will harden the heart of Pharaoh, and he will chase after them, and I will be glorified through Pharaoh and through all his army, and <supplied>the</supplied> Egyptians will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh.” And they did so. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 14:5">5</verse-number>And it was told to the king of Egypt that the people fled, and the heart of Pharaoh was changed and <supplied>that of</supplied> his servants toward the people, and they said, “What <supplied>is</supplied> this we have done, that we have released Israel from serving us!” <verse-number id="Ex 14:6">6</verse-number>And he harnessed his chariot and took with him his people. <verse-number id="Ex 14:7">7</verse-number>And he took six hundred select chariots and all the chariots of Egypt and officers over all of them. <verse-number id="Ex 14:8">8</verse-number>And Yahweh hardened the heart of Pharaoh the king of Egypt, and he chased after the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> (Now the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> <supplied>were</supplied> going out <idiom-start/>boldly<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “with a raised/high hand”</note>) <verse-number id="Ex 14:9">9</verse-number>And <supplied>the</supplied> Egyptians chased after them, and they overtook them encamped at the sea—all the horses of the chariots of Pharaoh and his charioteers and his army—at Pi-hahiroth before Baal Zephon. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 14:10">10</verse-number>And Pharaoh approached, and the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> lifted their eyes, and there were the Egyptians traveling after them! And they were very afraid, and the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> cried out to Yahweh. <verse-number id="Ex 14:11">11</verse-number>And they said to Moses, “Because there are no graves in Egypt? Is that why you have taken us to die in the desert? What <supplied>is</supplied> this you have done to us by bringing us out from Egypt! <verse-number id="Ex 14:12">12</verse-number>Isn’t this the word we spoke to you in Egypt, saying, ‘Leave us alone <supplied>so that</supplied> we can serve Egypt!’ because serving Egypt is better for us than our dying in the desert.” <verse-number id="Ex 14:13">13</verse-number>And Moses said to the people, “You must not be afraid. Stand <supplied>still</supplied> and see the salvation of Yahweh, which he will accomplish for you today, because <supplied>the</supplied> Egyptians whom you see today you will see never again. <verse-number id="Ex 14:14">14</verse-number>Yahweh will fight for you, and you must be quiet.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 14:15">15</verse-number>And Yahweh said to Moses, “Why do you cry out to me? Speak to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> <supplied>so that</supplied> they set out.<note>Or “journey,” “move on,” “travel”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 14:16">16</verse-number>And you, lift up your staff and stretch out your hand over the sea and divide it <supplied>so that</supplied> the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> can go in the middle of the sea on the dry land. <verse-number id="Ex 14:17">17</verse-number>And as for me, look, I <supplied>am</supplied> about to harden the heart of <supplied>the</supplied> Egyptians <supplied>so that</supplied> they come after them, and I will display my glory through Pharaoh and through all of his army, through his chariots and through his charioteers. <verse-number id="Ex 14:18">18</verse-number>And <supplied>the</supplied> Egyptians will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh when I display my glory through Pharaoh, through his chariots, and through his charioteers.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 14:19">19</verse-number>And the angel of God who was going before the camp of Israel set out and went behind them. And the column of cloud set out ahead of them, and it stood <supplied>still</supplied> behind them, <verse-number id="Ex 14:20">20</verse-number><supplied>so that</supplied> it came between the camp of Egypt and the camp of Israel. And <idiom-start/>it was a dark cloud<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the cloud was and the darkness”</note> but it gave light <supplied>to</supplied> the night,<note>Or “it illumined the night”</note> <supplied>so that</supplied> <idiom-start/>neither approached the other<idiom-end/><note>Literally “this did not come near to this”</note> all night. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 14:21">21</verse-number>And Moses stretched out his hand over the sea, and Yahweh moved the sea<note>Or “caused the sea to go,” “drove the sea”</note> with a strong east wind all night, and he made the sea <supplied>become</supplied> dry ground, and the waters were divided. <verse-number id="Ex 14:22">22</verse-number>And the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> entered the middle of the sea on the dry land. The waters <supplied>were</supplied> a wall for them on their right and on their left. <verse-number id="Ex 14:23">23</verse-number>And <supplied>the</supplied> Egyptians gave chase<note>Or “pursued,” “chased”</note> and entered after them—all the horses of Pharaoh, his chariots, and his charioteers—into the middle of the sea. <verse-number id="Ex 14:24">24</verse-number>And during the morning watch, Yahweh looked down to the Egyptian camp <supplied>from</supplied> in the column of fire and cloud, and he threw the Egyptian camp into a panic. <verse-number id="Ex 14:25">25</verse-number>And he removed<note>Or “let turn aside”</note> the wheels of their chariots <supplied>so that</supplied> they drove them with difficulty, and <supplied>the</supplied> Egyptians said, “We must flee away<note>Or “let us flee,” “let me run away”; the verb is singular, but it is plural in context</note> from Israel because Yahweh <supplied>is</supplied> fighting for them against Egypt.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 14:26">26</verse-number>And Yahweh said to Moses, “Stretch out your hand over the sea, and let the waters return over <supplied>the</supplied> Egyptians, over their chariots, and over their charioteers.” <verse-number id="Ex 14:27">27</verse-number>And Moses stretched out his hand over the sea, and the sea returned <idiom-start/>at daybreak<idiom-end/><note>Literally “at the turning of morning”</note> to its normal level, and <supplied>the</supplied> Egyptians <supplied>were</supplied> fleeing <idiom-start/>because of it<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to/for/from the meeting of it”</note> and Yahweh swept <supplied>the</supplied> Egyptians into the middle of the sea. <verse-number id="Ex 14:28">28</verse-number>And the waters returned and covered the chariots and the charioteers—all the army of Pharaoh coming after them into the sea. Not <idiom-start/>even<idiom-end/><note>Literally “up to,” “as far as”</note> one survived among them. <verse-number id="Ex 14:29">29</verse-number>But the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> walked on the dry land in the middle of the sea. The waters <supplied>were</supplied> a wall for them on their right and on their left. <verse-number id="Ex 14:30">30</verse-number>And Yahweh saved Israel on that day from the hand<note>Or “power”</note> of Egypt, and Israel saw the Egyptians dead on the shore of the sea. <verse-number id="Ex 14:31">31</verse-number>And Israel saw the great hand<note>Or “power”</note> that Yahweh displayed against Egypt, and the people feared Yahweh, and they believed in Yahweh and in Moses his servant. </p>
		</chapter>