<chapter id="Ex 16">
			<pericope>Yahweh Provides Food in the Desert</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 16:1">1</verse-number>And they set out from Elim, and all the community of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> came to the desert of Sin, which <supplied>is</supplied> between Elim <idiom-start/>and Sinai<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “and between Sinai”</note> in the fifteenth day of the second month of their going out from the land of Egypt. <verse-number id="Ex 16:2">2</verse-number>And all the community of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> grumbled against Moses and against Aaron in the desert. <verse-number id="Ex 16:3">3</verse-number>And the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> said to them, “<idiom-start/>If only we had died<idiom-end/><note>Literally “who will give our dying”</note> by the hand of Yahweh in the land of Egypt, when we sat by the pots<note>Hebrew “pot”</note> of meat, when we ate bread <idiom-start/>until we were full<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to contentment” or “to satisfaction”</note> because you have brought us out to this desert to kill all of this assembly with hunger.” <verse-number id="Ex 16:4">4</verse-number>And Yahweh said to Moses, “Look, I am going to rain down for you bread from the heavens, and the people will go out and gather enough for the day on its day; in that way I will test them: Will they go according to my law or not? <verse-number id="Ex 16:5">5</verse-number>And then on the sixth day, they will prepare what they bring, and it will be twice over what they will gather every <supplied>other</supplied> day.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 16:6">6</verse-number>And Moses and Aaron said to all the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> “<supplied>In the</supplied> evening, you will know that Yahweh has brought you out from the land of Egypt, <verse-number id="Ex 16:7">7</verse-number>and <supplied>in the</supplied> morning, you will see the glory of Yahweh, <idiom-start/>for he hears<idiom-end/><note>Literally “at/in his hearing”</note> your grumblings against Yahweh, and what <supplied>are</supplied> we that you grumble against us?” <verse-number id="Ex 16:8">8</verse-number>And Moses said, “When in the evening Yahweh gives you meat to eat and bread in the morning <idiom-start/>to fill up on<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to be satisfied”</note> <idiom-start/>for he hears<idiom-end/><note>Literally “at/in his hearing”</note> your grumblings that you grumble against him—and what <supplied>are</supplied> we? Your grumblings <supplied>are</supplied> not against us but against Yahweh.” <verse-number id="Ex 16:9">9</verse-number>And Moses said to Aaron, “Say to all the community of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> ‘Come near before Yahweh because he has heard your grumblings.’ ” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 16:10">10</verse-number>And at the moment of Aaron’s speaking to all the community of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> they turned to the desert, <idiom-start/>and just then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “look” or “behold”</note> the glory of Yahweh appeared in the cloud. <verse-number id="Ex 16:11">11</verse-number>And Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Ex 16:12">12</verse-number>“I have heard the grumblings of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> Speak to them, saying, ‘<idiom-start/>At twilight<idiom-end/><note>Literally “between the evenings”</note> you will eat meat, and in the morning you will be full <supplied>with</supplied> bread, and you will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh your God.’ ” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 16:13">13</verse-number>And so it was, in the evening, the quail came up and covered the camp, and in the morning, a layer of dew was all around the camp. <verse-number id="Ex 16:14">14</verse-number>And the layer of dew came up, <idiom-start/>and there<idiom-end/><note>Literally “look” or “behold”</note> on the face of the desert was a fine granular substance, fine like frost on the ground. <verse-number id="Ex 16:15">15</verse-number>And the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> saw, and they said <idiom-start/>to each other<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “a man to his brother”</note> “What <supplied>is</supplied> this?” because they did not know what it <supplied>was</supplied>. And Moses said to them, “That <supplied>is</supplied> the bread that Yahweh has given to you as food. <verse-number id="Ex 16:16">16</verse-number>This <supplied>is</supplied> the word that Yahweh commanded, ‘Gather from it, <idiom-start/>each according to what he can eat<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “a man for the mouth of his eating”</note> an omer per person<note>Literally “skull” or “head”</note> <supplied>according to</supplied> the number of you.<note>Or “the number of your selves”</note> You each shall take <supplied>enough</supplied> for whoever <supplied>is</supplied> in his tent.’ ” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 16:17">17</verse-number>And the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> did so, and they gathered, some more and some less. <verse-number id="Ex 16:18">18</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied> they measured with the omer, the one gathering more had no surplus, and the one gathering less had no lack; they gathered <idiom-start/>each according to what he could eat<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “a man for the mouth of his eating”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 16:19">19</verse-number>And Moses said to them, “Let no one leave any of it until morning.” <verse-number id="Ex 16:20">20</verse-number>But they did not listen to Moses. Some people<note>Literally “men”</note> left <supplied>some</supplied> of it until morning, and it bred worms and stank. And Moses was angry with them. <verse-number id="Ex 16:21">21</verse-number>And they gathered it morning by morning, <idiom-start/>each according to what he could eat<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “a man according to the mouth of his eating”</note> and it melted <supplied>when</supplied> the sun was hot.<note>Literally “and the sun was hot, and he/it melted”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 16:22">22</verse-number>And when it was the sixth day, they gathered twice <supplied>as much</supplied> bread, two omers for one <supplied>person</supplied>, and all the leaders of the community came and told Moses. <verse-number id="Ex 16:23">23</verse-number>And he said to them, “This is what Yahweh has said. Tomorrow <supplied>is</supplied> a rest period, a holy Sabbath for Yahweh. Bake what you <supplied>want to</supplied> bake, and boil what you <supplied>want to</supplied> boil. Put aside all the surplus for yourselves for safekeeping until the morning.” <verse-number id="Ex 16:24">24</verse-number>And they put it aside until the morning, as Moses had commanded, and it did not make a stench, and not a maggot was in it. <verse-number id="Ex 16:25">25</verse-number>And Moses said, “Eat it today, because today is a Sabbath for Yahweh. Today you will not find it in the field. <verse-number id="Ex 16:26">26</verse-number>Six days you will gather it, but on the seventh day, <supplied>the</supplied> Sabbath, it will not be <supplied>present</supplied> on it.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 16:27">27</verse-number>And on the seventh day <supplied>some</supplied> of the people went out to gather, and they did not find <supplied>any</supplied>. <verse-number id="Ex 16:28">28</verse-number>And Yahweh said to Moses, “How long do you<note>Plural</note> refuse to keep my commands and my laws? <verse-number id="Ex 16:29">29</verse-number>See, because Yahweh has given to you the Sabbath, therefore he is giving to you on the sixth day bread for two days. Stay, <idiom-start/>each in his location<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “a man under him/it”</note> let no one go from his place on the seventh day.” <verse-number id="Ex 16:30">30</verse-number>And the people rested on the seventh day. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 16:31">31</verse-number>And the house of Israel called its name “manna.” And it <supplied>was</supplied> like coriander seed, white, and its taste <supplied>was</supplied> like a wafer with honey. <verse-number id="Ex 16:32">32</verse-number>And Moses said, “This is the word that Yahweh has commanded. ‘A full omer of it <supplied>is</supplied> for safekeeping for your generations so that they will see the bread that I fed you in the desert when I brought you from the land of Egypt.’ ” <verse-number id="Ex 16:33">33</verse-number>And Moses said to Aaron, “Take one jar and put there a full omer of manna. Leave it before Yahweh for safekeeping for your generations.” <verse-number id="Ex 16:34">34</verse-number>As Yahweh had commanded Moses, so Aaron left it before the testimony for safekeeping. <verse-number id="Ex 16:35">35</verse-number>And the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> ate the manna forty years, until their coming to an inhabited land; they ate the manna until their coming to the border of the land of Canaan. <verse-number id="Ex 16:36">36</verse-number>(And an omer <supplied>is</supplied> a tenth of an ephah.) </p>
		</chapter>