<chapter id="Ex 17">
			<pericope>Water from a Rock</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 17:1">1</verse-number>And all the community of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> set out from the desert of Sin for their journeys according to the command of Yahweh, and they camped in Rephidim, and there was no water for the people to drink. <verse-number id="Ex 17:2">2</verse-number>And the people quarreled with Moses, and they said, “Give us water so that we can drink.” And Moses said to them, “Why do you quarrel with me? Why do you test Yahweh?” <verse-number id="Ex 17:3">3</verse-number>And the people thirsted for water, and the people grumbled against Moses and said, “Why <idiom-start/>ever<idiom-end/><note>Or “at all”; literally “this”</note> did you bring us up from Egypt to kill me<note>The unexpected switch to first-person singular pronouns reflects the fact that the question summarizes a host of angry accusations and self-centered concern</note> and my sons and my cattle with thirst?” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 17:4">4</verse-number>And Moses cried out to Yahweh, saying, “What will I do with this people? A little longer and they will stone me.” <verse-number id="Ex 17:5">5</verse-number>And Yahweh said to Moses, “Go on before the people and take with you <supplied>some</supplied> from the elders of Israel, and the staff with which you struck the Nile take in your hand, and go. <verse-number id="Ex 17:6">6</verse-number>Look, I <supplied>will be</supplied> standing before you there on the rock in Horeb, and you will strike the rock, and water will come out from it, and the people will drink.” </p>
			<p>And Moses did so before the eyes of the elders of Israel. <verse-number id="Ex 17:7">7</verse-number>And he called the name of the place Massah and Meribah because of the quarrel of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and because of their testing Yahweh <supplied>by</supplied> saying, “Is Yahweh in our midst or not?” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Battle with the Amalekites</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 17:8">8</verse-number>And Amalek came and fought with Israel at Rephidim. <verse-number id="Ex 17:9">9</verse-number>And Moses said to Joshua, “Choose men for us, and go out, fight against Amalek tomorrow. I <supplied>will be</supplied> standing on the top of the hill, and the staff of God <supplied>will be</supplied> in my hand.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 17:10">10</verse-number>And Joshua did as Moses had said to him to fight with Amalek. And Moses, Aaron, and Hur went up <supplied>to</supplied> the top of the hill. <verse-number id="Ex 17:11">11</verse-number>And<note>Literally “and it would be”</note> when Moses raised his hand, Israel would prevail, but when he rested his hand, Amalek would prevail. <verse-number id="Ex 17:12">12</verse-number>But the hands of Moses <supplied>were</supplied> heavy, and they took a stone and placed it under him, and he sat on it; Aaron and Hur supported his hands, <idiom-start/>one on each side<idiom-end/>,<note>Or “one on one side and one on the other”; literally “one from this and one from this”</note> and his hands <supplied>were</supplied> steady until <idiom-start/>sundown<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the coming in of the sun”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 17:13">13</verse-number>And Joshua defeated Amalek and his people with <supplied>the</supplied> <idiom-start/>edge of the sword<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “mouth of <supplied>the</supplied> sword”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 17:14">14</verse-number>And Yahweh said to Moses, “Write this <supplied>as</supplied> a memorial in the scroll and <idiom-start/>recite it in the hearing of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and put in the ears of”</note> Joshua, because I will utterly blot out the remembrance of Amalek from under the heavens.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 17:15">15</verse-number>And Moses built an altar, and he called its name Yahweh <supplied>Is</supplied> My Banner. <verse-number id="Ex 17:16">16</verse-number>And he said, “Because a hand <supplied>was</supplied> against the throne of Yah,<note>Or “indeed a hand on the throne of Yah”; the phrase is unclear</note> a war <supplied>will be</supplied> for Yahweh with Amalek from generation <supplied>to</supplied> generation.” </p>
		</chapter>