<chapter id="Ex 20">
			<pericope>Ten Commandments</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 20:1">1</verse-number>And God spoke all these words, saying, <verse-number id="Ex 20:2">2</verse-number>“I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh, your God, who brought you out from the land of Egypt, from the house of slaves. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 20:3">3</verse-number>“There shall be for you no other gods before me. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 20:4">4</verse-number>“You shall not make for yourself a divine image <supplied>with</supplied> any form that <supplied>is</supplied> in the heavens above or that <supplied>is</supplied> in the earth below or that <supplied>is</supplied> in the water below the earth. <verse-number id="Ex 20:5">5</verse-number>You will not bow down to them, and you will not serve them, because I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh your God, a jealous God, punishing <supplied>the</supplied> guilt of <supplied>the</supplied> parents on the children on <supplied>the</supplied> third and on <supplied>the</supplied> fourth <supplied>generations</supplied><note>“Generations” is understood from comparison with parallel verses (compare <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ex 34:6–7">Exod 34:6–7</cite>; <cite title="BibleLEB2: Dt 7:9">Deut 7:9</cite>)</note> of those hating me, <verse-number id="Ex 20:6">6</verse-number>and showing loyal love to thousands <supplied>of generations</supplied><note>“Generations” is understood from comparison with parallel verses ( compare <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ex 34:6–7">Exod 34:6–7</cite>; <cite title="BibleLEB2: Dt 7:9">Deut 7:9</cite>)</note> of those loving me and of those keeping my commandments. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 20:7">7</verse-number>“You shall not <idiom-start/>misuse the name of Yahweh your God<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “take up/bear/carry the name of Yahweh your God for <supplied>what is</supplied> worthless/false/empty”</note> because Yahweh will not leave unpunished <supplied>anyone</supplied> who <idiom-start/>misuses his name<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “bears his name for <supplied>what is</supplied> false”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 20:8">8</verse-number>“Remember the day of the Sabbath, to consecrate it. <verse-number id="Ex 20:9">9</verse-number>Six days you will work, and you will do all your work. <verse-number id="Ex 20:10">10</verse-number>But the seventh day <supplied>is</supplied> a Sabbath for Yahweh your God; you will not do any work—you or your son or your daughter, your male slave or your female slave, or your animal, or your alien who <supplied>is</supplied> in your gates—<verse-number id="Ex 20:11">11</verse-number>because <supplied>in</supplied> six days Yahweh made the heavens and the earth, the sea and all that <supplied>is</supplied> in them, and on the seventh day he rested. Therefore Yahweh blessed the seventh day and consecrated it. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 20:12">12</verse-number>“Honor your father and your mother, so that your days can be long on the land that Yahweh your God <supplied>is</supplied> giving you. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 20:13">13</verse-number>“You shall not murder. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 20:14">14</verse-number>“You shall not commit adultery. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 20:15">15</verse-number>“You shall not steal. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 20:16">16</verse-number>“You shall not testify against your neighbor <supplied>with</supplied> a false witness. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 20:17">17</verse-number>“You shall not covet the house of your neighbor; you will not covet the wife of your neighbor or his male servant or his female servant or his ox or his donkey or anything that <supplied>is</supplied> your neighbor’s.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 20:18">18</verse-number>And all the people <supplied>were</supplied> seeing the thunder and the lightning and the sound of the ram’s horn and the mountain smoking, and the people saw, and they trembled, and they stood at a distance. <verse-number id="Ex 20:19">19</verse-number>And they said to Moses, “You speak with us, and we will listen, but let not God speak with us, lest we die.” <verse-number id="Ex 20:20">20</verse-number>And Moses said to the people, “Do not be afraid. God has come to test you so that his fear will be before you so that you do not sin.” <verse-number id="Ex 20:21">21</verse-number>And the people stood at a distance, and Moses approached the very thick cloud where God was. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Instructions for Building Altars</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 20:22">22</verse-number>And Yahweh said to Moses, “Thus you will say to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> ‘You yourselves have seen that I have spoken to you from the heavens. <verse-number id="Ex 20:23">23</verse-number>You will not make alongside me gods of silver, and gods of gold you will not make for yourselves. <verse-number id="Ex 20:24">24</verse-number>An altar of earth you will make for me, and you will sacrifice on it your burnt offerings and your fellowship offerings, your sheep and your cattle. In every place where I cause my name to be remembered,<note>Or “proclaimed”</note> I will come to you, and I will bless you. <verse-number id="Ex 20:25">25</verse-number>And if you make an altar of stones for me, you will not build them <supplied>as</supplied> hewn stone, because if you use your chisel on it, you have defiled it. <verse-number id="Ex 20:26">26</verse-number>You will not go up with steps onto my altar, that your nakedness not be exposed on it.’ </p>
		</chapter>