<chapter id="Ex 22">
			<pericope>Regulations Regarding Theft, Borrowing, and Accidental Damage or Loss</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 22:1">1</verse-number><note><cite title="BibleLEB2: Ex 22:1–31">Exodus 22:1–31 </cite>in the English Bible is 21:37–22:30 in the Hebrew Bible</note> “ ‘If a man steals an ox or small livestock and slaughters it or sells it, he will make restitution with five cattle in place of the ox and with four sheep or goats in place of the small livestock. <verse-number id="Ex 22:2">2</verse-number>“ ‘If a thief is found in the act of breaking in and he is struck and he dies, there is not bloodguilt for him. <verse-number id="Ex 22:3">3</verse-number>(If the sun has risen over him, <supplied>there is</supplied> bloodguilt for him. He will make full restitution. If <idiom-start/>he does not have enough<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “there is not to him”</note> he will be sold for his theft. <verse-number id="Ex 22:4">4</verse-number>If indeed the stolen item is found <idiom-start/>in his possession<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in his hand”</note> alive, from ox to donkey to small livestock, he will make double restitution. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 22:5">5</verse-number>“ ‘If a man grazes <supplied>his livestock</supplied> in a field or a vineyard and he releases his livestock and it grazes in the field of another, he will make restitution <supplied>from</supplied> the best of his field and the best of his vineyard. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 22:6">6</verse-number>“ ‘If a fire is started and finds thorn bushes and a stack of sheaves or the standing grain or the field is consumed, the one who started the fire will surely make restitution. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 22:7">7</verse-number>“ ‘If a man gives to his neighbor money or objects to watch over and it is stolen from the house of the man, if the thief is found, he will make double restitution. <verse-number id="Ex 22:8">8</verse-number>If the thief is not found, the owner of the house will be brought <idiom-start/>to the sanctuary<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to God” or perhaps “to the judges”</note> <supplied>to learn</supplied> whether or not he reached out his hand to his neighbor’s possession. <verse-number id="Ex 22:9">9</verse-number>Concerning every account of transgression—concerning an ox, concerning a donkey, concerning small livestock, concerning clothing, concerning all lost property—where <supplied>someone</supplied> says, “This belongs to me,” the matter of the two of them will come to God;<note>Or “the judges”</note> whomever God declares guilty will make double restitution to his neighbor. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 22:10">10</verse-number>“ ‘If a man gives to his neighbor a donkey or an ox or small livestock or any beast to watch over and it dies or is injured or is captured <supplied>when</supplied> there is no one who sees, <verse-number id="Ex 22:11">11</verse-number>the oath of Yahweh will be between the two of them <supplied>concerning</supplied> whether or not he has reached out his hand to his neighbor’s possession, and its owner will accept <supplied>this</supplied>, and he will not make restitution. <verse-number id="Ex 22:12">12</verse-number>But if indeed it was stolen from him, he will make restitution to its owner. <verse-number id="Ex 22:13">13</verse-number>If indeed it was torn to pieces, he will bring it as evidence—the mangled carcass; he will not make restitution. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 22:14">14</verse-number>“ ‘If a man borrows from his neighbor and it is injured or dies <supplied>while</supplied> its owner is not with it, he will make restitution. <verse-number id="Ex 22:15">15</verse-number>If its owner <supplied>was</supplied> with it, he will not make restitution; if it was hired, it came with its hiring fee. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Regulations Regarding Various Offences</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 22:16">16</verse-number>“ ‘If a man seduces a virgin who is not engaged and he lies with her, he surely will give her bride price <idiom-start/>to have her as his wife<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “for him for a woman”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 22:17">17</verse-number>If her father absolutely refuses to give her to him, he will weigh out money according to the bride price for the virgin. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 22:18">18</verse-number>“ ‘You will not let a witch live. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 22:19">19</verse-number>“ ‘Anyone lying with an animal will surely be put to death. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 22:20">20</verse-number>“ ‘Whoever sacrifices to the gods—not to Yahweh, to him alone—will be destroyed. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Regulations Regarding Foreigners and the Poor</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 22:21">21</verse-number>“ ‘You will not mistreat an alien, and you will not oppress him, because you were aliens in the land of Egypt. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 22:22">22</verse-number>“ ‘You will not afflict any widow or orphan. <verse-number id="Ex 22:23">23</verse-number>If you indeed afflict him, yes, if he cries out at all to me, I will certainly hear his cry of distress. <verse-number id="Ex 22:24">24</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>I will become angry<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “my nose will burn”</note> and I will kill you with the sword, and your wives will be widows and your children orphans. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 22:25">25</verse-number>“ ‘If you lend money <supplied>to</supplied> my people, <supplied>to</supplied> the needy with you, you will not be to him as a creditor; you will not <idiom-start/>charge him interest<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “put on him interest”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 22:26">26</verse-number>If indeed you require the cloak of your neighbor as a pledge, you will return it to him at sundown, <verse-number id="Ex 22:27">27</verse-number>because it is his only garment; it is his cloak for his skin. In what will he sleep? <idiom-start/>And<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And it will be”</note> when he cries out to me, I will hear, because I <supplied>am</supplied> gracious. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Regulations Regarding Tribute and Holiness</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 22:28">28</verse-number>“ ‘You will not curse God,<note>Or “a judge”</note> and you will not curse a leader among your people. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 22:29">29</verse-number>“ ‘You will not delay the fullness of your harvest and the juice from your press; you will give me the firstborn of your sons. <verse-number id="Ex 22:30">30</verse-number>You will do likewise for your ox and for your sheep and goats; seven days it will be with its mother; on the eighth, you will give it to me. <verse-number id="Ex 22:31">31</verse-number>And you will be men of holiness for me; and you will not eat meat <supplied>from</supplied> a carcass mangled in the field; you will throw it to the dog. </p>
		</chapter>