<chapter id="Ex 25">
			<pericope>Instruction to Collect Materials</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 25:1">1</verse-number>And Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Ex 25:2">2</verse-number>“Speak to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and let them bring to me a contribution. You will receive my contribution from every man whose heart prompts him. <verse-number id="Ex 25:3">3</verse-number>And this is the contribution that you will receive from them—gold and silver and bronze, <verse-number id="Ex 25:4">4</verse-number>blue, purple, and crimson <supplied>yarns</supplied>, and fine linen and goat hair, <verse-number id="Ex 25:5">5</verse-number>and red-dyed ram skins, and fine leather,<note>The particular kind of leather is uncertain</note> and acacia wood, <verse-number id="Ex 25:6">6</verse-number>oil for the lamp, balsam oils for the anointing oil and for the fragrant incense, <verse-number id="Ex 25:7">7</verse-number>onyx stones and stones for mountings on the ephod and the breast piece. <verse-number id="Ex 25:8">8</verse-number>And make a sanctuary for me, and I will dwell in the midst of them, <verse-number id="Ex 25:9">9</verse-number>according to all that I show you—the pattern of the tabernacle and the pattern of all its equipment—and so you will do. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Instructions for Making the Ark of the Covenant</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 25:10">10</verse-number>“And they will make an ark of acacia wood, two and a half cubits its length and a cubit and a half its width and a cubit and a half its height. <verse-number id="Ex 25:11">11</verse-number>And you will overlay it with pure gold, inside and outside you will overlay it, and you will make on it a gold molding all around. <verse-number id="Ex 25:12">12</verse-number>And you will cast for it four gold rings, and you will put <supplied>them</supplied> on its four feet, with two rings on its one side and two rings on its second side. <verse-number id="Ex 25:13">13</verse-number>And you will make poles of acacia wood, and you will overlay them <supplied>with</supplied> gold. <verse-number id="Ex 25:14">14</verse-number>And you will put the poles into the rings on the sides of the ark to carry the ark with them. <verse-number id="Ex 25:15">15</verse-number>In the rings of the ark will be the poles; they will not be removed from it.<note>Literally “they will not turn aside from it”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 25:16">16</verse-number>And you will put into the ark the testimony that I will give to you. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 25:17">17</verse-number>“And you will make an atonement cover of pure gold, two and a half cubits its length and a cubit and a half its width. <verse-number id="Ex 25:18">18</verse-number>And you will make two cherubim of gold; you will make them of hammered work at the two ends of the atonement cover. <verse-number id="Ex 25:19">19</verse-number>And make one cherub <idiom-start/>at one end<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from end from this”</note> and one cherub <idiom-start/>at the other end<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from end from this”</note> of the atonement cover; you will make the cherubim on its two ends. <verse-number id="Ex 25:20">20</verse-number>And the cherubim will be <supplied>with</supplied> outspread wings above, covering with their wings over the atonement cover <idiom-start/>and facing each other<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “and their faces a man to his brother”</note> the faces of the cherubim will be toward the atonement cover. <verse-number id="Ex 25:21">21</verse-number>And you will put the atonement cover above onto the ark, and into the ark you will put the testimony that I will give you. <verse-number id="Ex 25:22">22</verse-number>And I will meet you there, and I will speak with you from over the atonement cover, from between the two cherubim that <supplied>are to be</supplied> on the ark of the testimony—all that I will command you to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Instructions for Making a Table and a Lampstand</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 25:23">23</verse-number>“And you will make a table of acacia wood, two cubits its length and a cubit its width and a cubit and a half its height. <verse-number id="Ex 25:24">24</verse-number>And you will overlay it <supplied>with</supplied> pure gold, and you will make for it a gold molding all around. <verse-number id="Ex 25:25">25</verse-number>And you will make for it a handbreadth rim all around, and you will make a gold molding for its rim all around. <verse-number id="Ex 25:26">26</verse-number>And you will make four gold rings for it, and you will put the rings on the four corners where its four <idiom-start/>legs<idiom-end/><note>Literally “feet”</note> <supplied>are</supplied>. <verse-number id="Ex 25:27">27</verse-number>The rings will be near the rim as <idiom-start/>holders<idiom-end/><note>Literally “houses”</note> for poles to carry the table. <verse-number id="Ex 25:28">28</verse-number>And you will make the poles of acacia wood and overlay them <supplied>with</supplied> gold, and the table will be carried with them. <verse-number id="Ex 25:29">29</verse-number>And you will make its plates and its ladles<note>Or “bowls”</note> and its pitchers and its bowls with which <supplied>libations</supplied> will be poured; of pure gold you will make them. <verse-number id="Ex 25:30">30</verse-number>And you will put on the table <supplied>the</supplied> bread of presence <supplied>to be</supplied> before me continually. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 25:31">31</verse-number>“And you will make a lampstand of pure gold; the lampstand will be made of hammered work—its base and its branch,<note>Or “reed”</note> its cups, its buds, and its blossoms will be from it. <verse-number id="Ex 25:32">32</verse-number>And six branches <supplied>will be</supplied> going out from its sides, three branches of the lampstand from its one side and three branches of the lampstand from its second side. <verse-number id="Ex 25:33">33</verse-number>Three almond-flower cups <supplied>will be</supplied> on the one branch <supplied>with</supplied> a bud and a blossom, and three almond-flower cups <supplied>will be</supplied> on the one branch <supplied>with</supplied> a bud and a blossom—likewise for the six branches going out from the lampstand. <verse-number id="Ex 25:34">34</verse-number>And on the lampstand <supplied>will be</supplied> four almond-flower cups, <supplied>with</supplied> its buds and its blossoms. <verse-number id="Ex 25:35">35</verse-number>And a bud <supplied>will be</supplied> under the two branches <supplied>that come</supplied> from it, and a bud under the two branches from it, and a bud under the two branches from it, <supplied>likewise</supplied> for the six branches coming out from the lampstand. <verse-number id="Ex 25:36">36</verse-number>Their buds and their branches will be from it, all of it one <supplied>piece</supplied> of pure gold hammered work. <verse-number id="Ex 25:37">37</verse-number>And you will make its seven lamps, and its lamps will be set up, and it will give light <idiom-start/>in the space in front of it<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “on beyond its face”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 25:38">38</verse-number>And its snuffers and its fire pans <supplied>will be</supplied> pure gold. <verse-number id="Ex 25:39">39</verse-number>It will be made <supplied>from</supplied> a talent of pure gold, with all these <supplied>pieces of</supplied> equipment. <verse-number id="Ex 25:40">40</verse-number>And see and make <supplied>all</supplied> according to their pattern, which you were shown in the mountain. </p>
		</chapter>