<chapter id="Ex 26">
			<pericope>Instructions for Making the Tabernacle</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 26:1">1</verse-number>“And the tabernacle you will make <supplied>with</supplied> ten curtains; you will make them of finely twisted linen and blue and purple and crimson <supplied>yarns</supplied>, <supplied>with</supplied> cherubim, the work of a skilled craftsman. <verse-number id="Ex 26:2">2</verse-number>The length of the one curtain <supplied>will be</supplied> twenty-eight cubits, and the width <supplied>will be</supplied> four cubits <supplied>for</supplied> the one curtain; one measure <supplied>will be</supplied> for all the curtains. <verse-number id="Ex 26:3">3</verse-number>Five curtains will be joined <idiom-start/>to one another<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “a woman to her sister”</note> and five curtains joined <idiom-start/>to one another<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “a woman to her sister”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 26:4">4</verse-number>And you will make loops of blue on the edge of the one curtain, at the end in the set; and you will do so on the edge of the end curtain in the second set. <verse-number id="Ex 26:5">5</verse-number>You will make fifty loops on the one curtain, and you will make fifty loops on the end of the curtain that <supplied>is</supplied> in the second set; the loops are to be opposite<note>Or “interlinked” or “matching”</note> <idiom-start/>to one another<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “a woman to her sister”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 26:6">6</verse-number>And you will make fifty gold clasps and join the curtains <idiom-start/>to one another<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a woman to her sister”</note> with the clasps, so that the tabernacle will be one. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 26:7">7</verse-number>“And you will make curtains of goat hair for a tent over the tabernacle; you will make them eleven curtains. <verse-number id="Ex 26:8">8</verse-number>The length of the one curtain <supplied>will be</supplied> thirty cubits, and the width <supplied>will be</supplied> four cubits <supplied>for</supplied> the one curtain; one measure <supplied>will be</supplied> for <supplied>the</supplied> eleven curtains. <verse-number id="Ex 26:9">9</verse-number>And you will join five curtains together and six curtains together, and you will fold double the sixth curtain at the front of the tent. <verse-number id="Ex 26:10">10</verse-number>And you will make fifty loops on the edge of the one curtain at the end of the <supplied>first</supplied> set and fifty loops on the edge of the curtain <supplied>in</supplied> the second set. <verse-number id="Ex 26:11">11</verse-number>And you will make fifty bronze clasps, and you will put the clasps in the loops and join the tent, so that it will be one. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 26:12">12</verse-number>“And the surplus in the curtains of the tent <supplied>will be</supplied> an overhang; the surplus half curtain will hang over the back of the tabernacle. <verse-number id="Ex 26:13">13</verse-number>And a cubit <idiom-start/>from one side<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from this”</note> and a cubit <idiom-start/>from the other side<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from this”</note> in the surplus in the length of the curtains of the tent will be hung over the sides of the tabernacle <idiom-start/>equally<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from this and from this”</note> to cover it. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 26:14">14</verse-number>“And you will make a covering for the tent of red-dyed ram skins and a covering of fine leather <supplied>to go</supplied> above. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 26:15">15</verse-number>“And you will make the frames<note>Or “boards” or “planks”</note> for the tabernacle of acacia wood <supplied>as</supplied> uprights.<note>Literally “standing”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 26:16">16</verse-number>The length of the frame<note>Or “board” or “plank”</note> <supplied>will be</supplied> ten cubits, and the width of the one frame<note>Or “board” or “plank”</note> <supplied>will be</supplied> one and a half cubits. <verse-number id="Ex 26:17">17</verse-number>You will make two <idiom-start/>pegs<idiom-end/><note>Literally “hands”</note> for the one frame<note>Or “board” or “plank”</note> <supplied>for</supplied> joining <idiom-start/>each to another<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a woman to her sister”</note> <supplied>and</supplied> likewise for all the frames<note>Or “boards” or “planks”</note> of the tabernacle. <verse-number id="Ex 26:18">18</verse-number>And you will make the frames<note>Or “boards” or “planks”</note> for the tabernacle <supplied>with</supplied> twenty frames<note>Or “boards” or “planks”</note> for the <idiom-start/>south<idiom-end/><note>Literally “south southward”</note> side. <verse-number id="Ex 26:19">19</verse-number>And you will make forty silver bases under the twenty frames,<note>Or “boards” or “planks”</note> <supplied>with</supplied> two bases under the one frame<note>Or “board” or “plank”</note> for its two <idiom-start/>pegs<idiom-end/><note>Literally “hands”</note> and two bases under the <idiom-start/>next<idiom-end/><note>Literally “one”</note> frame<note>Or “board” or “plank”</note> for its two <idiom-start/>pegs<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “hands”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 26:20">20</verse-number>And for the second side of the tabernacle, the north side, <supplied>there will be</supplied> twenty frames<note>Or “boards” or “planks”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 26:21">21</verse-number>and their forty silver bases, <supplied>with</supplied> two bases under the one frame<note>Or “board” or “plank”</note> and two bases under the <idiom-start/>next<idiom-end/><note>Literally “one”</note> frame.<note>Or “board” or “plank”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 26:22">22</verse-number>“And for the rear of the tabernacle <idiom-start/>on the west<idiom-end/><note>Or “westward,” literally “seaward,” toward the Mediterranean Sea</note> you will make six frames.<note>Or “boards” or “planks”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 26:23">23</verse-number>And you will make two frames<note>Or “boards” or “planks”</note> for the tabernacle corners at the rear. <verse-number id="Ex 26:24">24</verse-number>They will be double at the bottom, and they will be completely together on its top to the one ring; it will be likewise for the two of them; they will be for the two corners. <verse-number id="Ex 26:25">25</verse-number>And there will be eight frames<note>Or “boards” or “planks”</note> and their silver bases, sixteen bases, with two bases under the one frame<note>Or “board” or “plank”</note> and two bases under the <idiom-start/>next<idiom-end/><note>Literally “one”</note> frame.<note>Or “board” or “plank”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 26:26">26</verse-number>“You will make five bars of acacia wood for the frames<note>Or “boards” or “planks”</note> on the one side of the tabernacle, <verse-number id="Ex 26:27">27</verse-number>and five bars for the frames<note>Or “boards” or “planks”</note> on the second side of the tabernacle, and five bars for the frames<note>Or “boards” or “planks”</note> on the side of the tabernacle at the rear <idiom-start/>on the west<idiom-end/>.<note>Or “westward,” literally “seaward,” toward the Mediterranean Sea</note> <verse-number id="Ex 26:28">28</verse-number>And the bar in the middle, in the midst of the frames<note>Or “boards” or “planks”</note> <supplied>will</supplied> run from end to end. <verse-number id="Ex 26:29">29</verse-number>And you will overlay the frames<note>Or “boards” or “planks”</note> with gold, and you will make their rings of gold <supplied>as</supplied> <idiom-start/>holders<idiom-end/><note>Literally “houses”</note> for the bars, and you will overlay the bars with gold. <verse-number id="Ex 26:30">30</verse-number>And you will erect the tabernacle according to its plan, which you have been shown on the mountain. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 26:31">31</verse-number>“And you will make a curtain of blue and purple and crimson <supplied>yarns</supplied> and finely twisted linen, <supplied>the</supplied> work of a skilled craftsman; he will make it <supplied>with</supplied> cherubim. <verse-number id="Ex 26:32">32</verse-number>And you will put it on four acacia pillars overlaid with gold <supplied>with</supplied> their gold hooks on four silver bases. <verse-number id="Ex 26:33">33</verse-number>And you will put the curtain under the clasps, and you will bring the ark of the testimony there inside the curtain, and the curtain will separate for you between the holy and the <idiom-start/>most holy place<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “holy place of the holiness”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 26:34">34</verse-number>And you will put the atonement cover on the ark of the testimony in the <idiom-start/>most holy place<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “holy place of the holiness”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 26:35">35</verse-number>And you will place the table outside the curtain and the lampstand opposite the table on the south side of the tabernacle, and you will put the table on the north side. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 26:36">36</verse-number>“And you will make for the entrance of the tent a screen of blue and purple and crimson <supplied>yarns</supplied> and finely twisted linen, <supplied>the</supplied> work of an embroiderer. <verse-number id="Ex 26:37">37</verse-number>And you will make for the screen five acacia pillars, and you will overlay them with gold <supplied>with</supplied> their gold hooks, and you will cast for them five bronze bases. </p>
		</chapter>