<chapter id="Ex 29">
			<pericope>Instructions for Consecrating Aaron and His Sons</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 29:1">1</verse-number>“And this <supplied>is</supplied> the thing that you will do for them to consecrate them to serve as a priest for me: Take <idiom-start/>one young bull<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a son of cattle”</note> and two rams without defect <verse-number id="Ex 29:2">2</verse-number>and unleavened bread and unleavened, ring-shaped bread cakes mixed with oil, and wafers of unleavened breads smeared with oil. You will make them <supplied>with</supplied> finely milled wheat flour, <verse-number id="Ex 29:3">3</verse-number>and you will put them on one basket, and you will bring them on the basket and <supplied>bring</supplied> the bull and the two rams. <verse-number id="Ex 29:4">4</verse-number>And you will bring Aaron and his sons to the entrance of the tent of assembly, and you will wash them with water. <verse-number id="Ex 29:5">5</verse-number>And you will take the garments and clothe Aaron with the tunic and the robe of the ephod, and you will fasten to him the ephod and the breast piece with the waistband of the ephod. <verse-number id="Ex 29:6">6</verse-number>And you will set the turban on his head, and you will put the holy diadem on the turban. <verse-number id="Ex 29:7">7</verse-number>And you will take the anointing oil and pour it on his head and anoint him. <verse-number id="Ex 29:8">8</verse-number>And you will bring his sons and clothe them with tunics. <verse-number id="Ex 29:9">9</verse-number>And you will gird Aaron and his sons <supplied>with</supplied> sashes and wrap headdresses on them. And priesthood will be theirs as a lasting rule, and <idiom-start/>you will ordain Aaron and his sons.<idiom-end/><note>Literally “you will fill the hand of Aaron and the hands of his sons”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 29:10">10</verse-number>“And you will bring the bull before the tent of assembly, and Aaron and his sons will lay their hands on the head of the bull. <verse-number id="Ex 29:11">11</verse-number>And you will slaughter the bull before Yahweh <supplied>at</supplied> the entrance of the tent of assembly. <verse-number id="Ex 29:12">12</verse-number>And you will take <supplied>some</supplied> of the blood of the bull and with your finger put it on the horns of the altar, and you will pour out all the blood at the base of the altar. <verse-number id="Ex 29:13">13</verse-number>And you will take and turn into smoke <supplied>on</supplied> the altar all the fat covering the inner parts and the lobe on the liver and the two kidneys and the fat that <supplied>is</supplied> on them. <verse-number id="Ex 29:14">14</verse-number>And the flesh of the bull and its skin and its offal you will burn with fire outside the camp; it <supplied>is</supplied> a sin offering. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 29:15">15</verse-number>“And you will take the one ram, and Aaron and his sons will lay their hands on the head of the ram. <verse-number id="Ex 29:16">16</verse-number>And you will slaughter the ram and take its blood and sprinkle <supplied>it</supplied> on the altar all around. <verse-number id="Ex 29:17">17</verse-number>And you will cut the ram into pieces and wash its inner parts, and you will put its legs with its pieces and with its head. <verse-number id="Ex 29:18">18</verse-number>And you will turn into smoke <supplied>on</supplied> the altar all of the ram; it is a burnt offering for Yahweh; it <supplied>is</supplied> a smell of appeasement, an offering by fire for Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 29:19">19</verse-number>“And you will take the second ram, and Aaron and his sons will lay their hands on the head of the ram. <verse-number id="Ex 29:20">20</verse-number>And you will slaughter the ram and take <supplied>some</supplied> of its blood and put <supplied>it</supplied> on Aaron’s <supplied>right</supplied> earlobe and on the right earlobe of his sons and on the thumb of their right hand and on <idiom-start/>the big toe<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the thumb of”</note> of their right foot, and you will sprinkle the blood at the base of the altar all around. <verse-number id="Ex 29:21">21</verse-number>And you will take <supplied>some</supplied> of the blood that is on the altar and <supplied>some</supplied> of the anointing oil, and you will spatter <supplied>it</supplied> on Aaron and on his garments and on his sons and on his sons’ garments with him, and he will be sacred, and his garments and his sons and his sons’ garments with him. <verse-number id="Ex 29:22">22</verse-number>And you will take from the ram the fat and the fat tail and the fat covering the inner parts and the lobe of the liver and the two kidneys and the fat that is on them and the right thigh, because it <supplied>is</supplied> the ram of ordination. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 29:23">23</verse-number>“And one loaf of bread and one ring-shaped bread cake of oiled bread and one wafer from the basket of unleavened bread that <supplied>is</supplied> before Yahweh— <verse-number id="Ex 29:24">24</verse-number>you will put <supplied>them</supplied> all on the palms of Aaron and on the palms of his sons, and you will wave them as a wave offering before Yahweh. <verse-number id="Ex 29:25">25</verse-number>And you will take them from their hand and turn <supplied>them</supplied> to smoke on the altar beside the burnt offering as a fragrance of appeasement before Yahweh; it is an offering made by fire before Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 29:26">26</verse-number>“And you will take the breast section from the ram of ordination that <supplied>is</supplied> for Aaron, and you will wave it <supplied>as</supplied> a wave offering before Yahweh. It will be your portion. <verse-number id="Ex 29:27">27</verse-number>And you will consecrate the wave offering breast section and the thigh of the contribution that was waved and that was presented<note>Literally “lifted up”</note> from the ram of the ordination that <supplied>is</supplied> for Aaron and for his sons. <verse-number id="Ex 29:28">28</verse-number>And it will be for<note>Or “belong to”</note> Aaron and for his sons as a lasting rule from the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> because it is a contribution, and it will be a contribution from the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> from their sacrifices of fellowship, their contribution to Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 29:29">29</verse-number>“And the holy garments that <supplied>are</supplied> for Aaron will be for his sons after him in which to anoint them and <idiom-start/>to ordain them<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to fill in them their hands”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 29:30">30</verse-number>Seven days the priest who replaces him from among his sons will wear them, who comes to the tent of assembly to serve in the sanctuary. <verse-number id="Ex 29:31">31</verse-number>And you will take the ram of ordination and boil its meat in a holy place. <verse-number id="Ex 29:32">32</verse-number>And Aaron and his sons will eat the meat of the ram and the bread that <supplied>is</supplied> in the basket at the entrance of the tent of assembly. <verse-number id="Ex 29:33">33</verse-number>And they will eat them—<supplied>the things</supplied> by which atonement was made for them to ordain them to consecrate them—and a stranger will not eat <supplied>them</supplied> because they are holy objects. <verse-number id="Ex 29:34">34</verse-number>If any remains until morning from the ordination meat or from the bread, you will burn the remainder in fire; it will not be eaten, because it <supplied>is</supplied> a holy object. <verse-number id="Ex 29:35">35</verse-number>And you will do so for Aaron and for his sons, according to all that I have commanded you; seven days you will ordain them. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Instructions for Regular Offerings at the Tabernacle</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 29:36">36</verse-number>“And you will offer a bull for a sin offering every day for the atonement; and you will offer a sin offering on the altar<note>Or “you will purify the altar”</note> when you make atonement for it, and you will anoint it to consecrate it. <verse-number id="Ex 29:37">37</verse-number>Seven days you will make atonement for the altar, and you will consecrate it, and the altar will be <idiom-start/>a most holy thing<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “a holiness of holinesses” or “a holy <supplied>thing</supplied> among holy <supplied>things</supplied>,” a thing of utmost holiness</note> <idiom-start/>Anyone who<idiom-end/><note>Or “anything that”; literally “all touching”</note> touches the altar will be holy. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 29:38">38</verse-number>“And this is what you shall offer on the altar: Two <idiom-start/>one-year-old<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons of a year”</note> male lambs <idiom-start/>every day<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for the day,” or per day</note> continually. <verse-number id="Ex 29:39">39</verse-number>The first lamb you will offer in the morning, and the second lamb you will offer <idiom-start/>at twilight<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “between the evenings”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 29:40">40</verse-number>And a tenth of finely milled flour mixed with a fourth of a hin of beaten oil, and a fourth of a hin of wine as a libation with the first lamb. <verse-number id="Ex 29:41">41</verse-number>And the second lamb you will offer <idiom-start/>at twilight<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “between the evenings”</note> you will offer a grain offering and its libation like that of the morning for a fragrance of appeasement, an offering made by fire for Yahweh. <verse-number id="Ex 29:42">42</verse-number><supplied>It will be</supplied> a burnt offering of continuity throughout your generations <supplied>at</supplied> the entrance of the tent of assembly before Yahweh, where I will meet with you to speak to you there. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 29:43">43</verse-number>“And I will meet with the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> there, and it will be consecrated by my glory. <verse-number id="Ex 29:44">44</verse-number>And I will consecrate the tent of assembly and the altar, and Aaron and his sons I will consecrate to serve as priests for me. <verse-number id="Ex 29:45">45</verse-number>And I will dwell in the midst of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and I will be their God. <verse-number id="Ex 29:46">46</verse-number>And they will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh, their God, who brought them out from the land of Egypt in order to dwell in their midst. I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh their God. </p>
		</chapter>