<chapter id="Ex 31">
			<pericope>Provision of Skilled People</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 31:1">1</verse-number>And Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Ex 31:2">2</verse-number>“See, I have called by name<note>In other words, “specifically chosen”</note> Bezalel the son of Uri the son of Hur, from the tribe of Judah. <verse-number id="Ex 31:3">3</verse-number>And I have filled him <supplied>with</supplied> the Spirit of God, with wisdom and with skill<note>Or “understanding,” “discernment,” “cleverness”</note> and with knowledge and with every <supplied>kind of</supplied> craftsmanship, <verse-number id="Ex 31:4">4</verse-number>to devise designs, to work with gold and with silver and with bronze, <verse-number id="Ex 31:5">5</verse-number>and in stonecutting for setting and in cutting wood, for doing every <supplied>kind of</supplied> craftsmanship. <verse-number id="Ex 31:6">6</verse-number>And, look, I have given with him Oholiab the son of Ahisamach, from the tribe of Dan, and I have put skill in the heart of all <supplied>the</supplied> skilled of heart, and they will make all that I have commanded you— <verse-number id="Ex 31:7">7</verse-number>the tent of assembly and the ark of the testimony and the atonement cover that <supplied>is</supplied> on it and all the equipment of the tent, <verse-number id="Ex 31:8">8</verse-number>and the table and all its equipment, and the pure <supplied>gold</supplied> lampstand and all its equipment, and the incense altar, <verse-number id="Ex 31:9">9</verse-number>and the altar of burnt offering and all its equipment, and the basin and its stand, <verse-number id="Ex 31:10">10</verse-number>and the garments of woven material, and <idiom-start/>the garments of the sanctuary<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the garments of the holiness” or “the holy garments”</note> for Aaron the priest and the garments of his sons to serve as priests, <verse-number id="Ex 31:11">11</verse-number>and the anointing oil and the fragrant incense for the sanctuary. According to all that I have commanded you, they will make <supplied>it</supplied>. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Provision of Rest from Work</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 31:12">12</verse-number>And Yahweh spoke to Moses <supplied>and</supplied> said, <verse-number id="Ex 31:13">13</verse-number>“And you, speak to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> saying, ‘Surely you must keep my Sabbaths, because it <supplied>is</supplied> a sign between me and you throughout your generations, <supplied>in order</supplied> to know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh, who consecrates you. <verse-number id="Ex 31:14">14</verse-number>And you must keep the Sabbath, because it is holy for you; defilers<note>Or “profaners,” those who treat it as common</note> of it will surely be put to death, because anyone who does work on it—that person will be cut off from among his people. <verse-number id="Ex 31:15">15</verse-number><supplied>On</supplied> six days work can be done, and on the seventh <idiom-start/>is a Sabbath of complete rest<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “a Sabbath of ‘Sabbathation.’ ” “Sabbathation” is not a real word, but devised as an attempt to convey the sounds of the related nouns in the Hebrew phrase</note> <idiom-start/>a holy day<idiom-end/><note>Literally “holiness”</note> for Yahweh; anyone doing work on the Sabbath day will surely be put to death. <verse-number id="Ex 31:16">16</verse-number>The <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> will pay attention to the Sabbath <supplied>in order</supplied> to fulfill the Sabbath<note>Or “keep the Sabbath to do/observe the Sabbath”</note> throughout their generations <supplied>as</supplied> a lasting covenant. <verse-number id="Ex 31:17">17</verse-number>It <supplied>is</supplied> a sign between me and the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> forever, because <supplied>in</supplied> six days Yahweh made the heavens and the earth, and on the seventh he ceased<note>Or “rested”</note> and recovered.”<note>Or “breathed freely,” “got his breath”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 31:18">18</verse-number>And when he finished speaking with him on Mount Sinai, he gave to Moses the two tablets of the testimony, stone tablets, written with the finger of God. </p>
		</chapter>