<chapter id="Ex 33">
			<pericope>Command to Resume Travel</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 33:1">1</verse-number>And Yahweh spoke to Moses, “Go, go up from here, you and the people whom you have brought up from the land of Egypt, to the land that I swore to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob, saying, ‘I will give it to your offspring.’ <verse-number id="Ex 33:2">2</verse-number>And I will send an angel before you, and I will drive out the Canaanites,<note>Hebrew “Canaanite”</note> the Amorites,<note>Hebrew “Amorite”</note> and the Hittites<note>Hebrew “Hittite”</note> and the Perizzites,<note>Hebrew “Perizzite”</note> the Hivites,<note>Hebrew “Hivite”</note> and the Jebusites,<note>Hebrew “Jebusite”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 33:3">3</verse-number><supplied>Go</supplied> to a land flowing with milk and honey, but I will not go up among you, because you <supplied>are</supplied> a stiff-necked people, lest I destroy you on the way.” <verse-number id="Ex 33:4">4</verse-number>And the people heard this troubling<note>Or “bad,” “disastrous,” “calamitous”</note> word, and they mourned, and they each did not put their ornaments on themselves. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 33:5">5</verse-number>And Yahweh said to Moses, “Say to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> ‘You <supplied>are</supplied> a stiff-necked people; <supplied>if</supplied> one moment I were to go up among you, I would destroy you. And now take down your ornaments from on you, and I will <idiom-start/>decide<idiom-end/><note>Literally “know”</note> what I will do to you.” <verse-number id="Ex 33:6">6</verse-number>And the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> stripped themselves of their ornaments from Mount Horeb <supplied>onward</supplied>. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Tent outside the Camp</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 33:7">7</verse-number>And Moses took the tent and pitched it outside the camp far from the camp, and he called it the tent of assembly, <idiom-start/>and<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and it would be”</note> all seeking Yahweh would go out to the tent of assembly, which <supplied>was</supplied> outside the camp. <verse-number id="Ex 33:8">8</verse-number><idiom-start/>And<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and it would be”</note> at the going out of Moses to the tent, all the people would rise and stand, each at the opening of his tent, and gaze after Moses until his entering the tent. <verse-number id="Ex 33:9">9</verse-number><idiom-start/>And<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and it would be”</note> at the entering of Moses <supplied>into</supplied> the tent the column of cloud would descend and stand <supplied>at</supplied> the opening of the tent, and he would speak with Moses. <verse-number id="Ex 33:10">10</verse-number>And all the people would see the column of cloud standing <supplied>at</supplied> the opening of the tent, and all the people would rise and bow in worship, each <supplied>at</supplied> the opening of his tent. <verse-number id="Ex 33:11">11</verse-number>And Yahweh would speak to Moses face to face, as a man speaks to his neighbor. And he would return to the camp, and his assistant Joshua the son of Nun, a young man, did not leave the middle of the tent. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Presence and Glory</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 33:12">12</verse-number>And Moses said to Yahweh, “See, you <supplied>are</supplied> saying to me, ‘Take this people up.’ But you have not let me know whom you will send with me, and you yourself have said, ‘I know you by name, and you also have found favor in my eyes.’ <verse-number id="Ex 33:13">13</verse-number>And now if I have found favor in your eyes, make known <supplied>to</supplied> me, please, your way, and so I may know you so that I can find favor in your eyes. And see that this nation is your people.” <verse-number id="Ex 33:14">14</verse-number>And he said, “My presence will go, and I will give you rest.” <verse-number id="Ex 33:15">15</verse-number>And he said to him, “If your presence <supplied>is</supplied> not going, do not bring us up from here. <verse-number id="Ex 33:16">16</verse-number>And by what will it be known then that I have found favor in your eyes, I and your people? Is it not by your going with us? And <supplied>so</supplied> we will be distinguished, I and your people, from all the people who <supplied>are</supplied> on the face of the ground.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 33:17">17</verse-number>And Yahweh said to Moses, “Also I will do this thing that you have spoken, because you have found favor in my eyes and I have known you by name.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 33:18">18</verse-number>And he said, “Please show me your glory.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 33:19">19</verse-number>And he said, “I myself will cause all my goodness to pass over before you, and I will proclaim the name of Yahweh before you, and I will be gracious <supplied>to</supplied> whom I will be gracious, and I will show compassion <supplied>to</supplied> whom I will show compassion.” <verse-number id="Ex 33:20">20</verse-number>But he said, “You are not able to see my face, because <supplied>a</supplied> human will not see me and live.” <verse-number id="Ex 33:21">21</verse-number>And Yahweh said, “There is a place with me, and you will stand on the rock. <verse-number id="Ex 33:22">22</verse-number><idiom-start/>And<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and it will be”</note> when my glory passes over, I will put you in the rock’s crevice, and I will cover you <supplied>with</supplied> my hand until I pass over. <verse-number id="Ex 33:23">23</verse-number>And I will remove my hand, and you will see my back, but my face will not be visible.” </p>
		</chapter>