<chapter id="Ex 34">
			<pericope>Yahweh’s Description of Himself</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 34:1">1</verse-number>And Yahweh said to Moses, “Cut for yourself two stone tablets like the first ones, and I will write on the tablets the words that were on the first tablets, which you broke. <verse-number id="Ex 34:2">2</verse-number>And be ready for the morning, and go up in the morning to Mount Sinai and present yourself to me there on the top of the mountain. <verse-number id="Ex 34:3">3</verse-number>And no one will go up with you, and neither let anyone be seen on all the mountain, nor let the sheep and goats and the cattle graze <idiom-start/>opposite<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the front of”</note> that mountain.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 34:4">4</verse-number>And Moses cut two stone tablets like the first ones, and he started early in the morning, and he went up to Mount Sinai, as Yahweh had commanded him, and he took in his hand the two stone tablets. <verse-number id="Ex 34:5">5</verse-number>And Yahweh descended in the cloud, and he stood with him there, and he proclaimed the name of Yahweh. <verse-number id="Ex 34:6">6</verse-number>And Yahweh passed over before him, and he proclaimed, “Yahweh, Yahweh, God, <supplied>who is</supplied> compassionate and gracious, <idiom-start/>slow to anger<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “long of nose”</note> and abounding with<note>Or “rich in” or “great of”</note> loyal love and faithfulness, <verse-number id="Ex 34:7">7</verse-number>keeping loyal love to the thousands, forgiving iniquity and transgression and sin, and he does not leave utterly unpunished, punishing <supplied>the</supplied> guilt of fathers on sons and on sons of sons on third and fourth <supplied>generations</supplied>.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 34:8">8</verse-number>And Moses hurried and knelt down to the earth and worshiped. <verse-number id="Ex 34:9">9</verse-number>And he said, “Please, if I have found favor in your eyes, Lord, let my Lord, please, go among us—indeed it is a stiff-necked people—and forgive our iniquity and our sin and <idiom-start/>take us as your possession<idiom-end/>.”<note>Or “take possession of us,” “make us your inheritance”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Covenant Stipulations</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 34:10">10</verse-number>And he said, “Look, I <supplied>am about to</supplied> make a covenant. In front of all your people I will do wonders that have not been created on all the earth and among all the nations, and all the people among whom you <supplied>are</supplied> will see Yahweh’s work, because what I <supplied>am about to</supplied> do with you <supplied>will be</supplied> awesome. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 34:11">11</verse-number>“Keep for yourself what I myself have commanded you today. Look, I <supplied>am about to</supplied> drive from before you the Amorites and the Canaanites<note>Hebrew “Canaanite”</note> and the Hittites<note>Hebrew “Hittite”</note> and the Perizzites<note>Hebrew “Perizzite”</note> and the Hivites<note>Hebrew “Hivite”</note> and the Jebusites.<note>Hebrew “Jebusite”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 34:12">12</verse-number>Be careful for yourself, lest you make a covenant with the inhabitants of the land to which you are going, lest it be a snare among you. <verse-number id="Ex 34:13">13</verse-number>Rather, you will tear down their altars, and you will break their stone pillars, and you will cut off their Asherah poles. <verse-number id="Ex 34:14">14</verse-number>For you will not bow in worship to another god, for ‘Yahweh <supplied>Is</supplied> Jealous’ is his name, he <supplied>is</supplied> a jealous God, <verse-number id="Ex 34:15">15</verse-number>lest you make a covenant with the inhabitants of the land, and they prostitute <supplied>themselves</supplied> after their gods, and they sacrifice to their gods, and they invite you, and you eat their sacrifice, <verse-number id="Ex 34:16">16</verse-number>and you take from their daughters for your sons, and their daughters prostitute <supplied>themselves</supplied> after their gods, and they cause your sons to prostitute <supplied>themselves</supplied> after their gods. <verse-number id="Ex 34:17">17</verse-number>You will not make gods of cast metal for yourself. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 34:18">18</verse-number>“You will keep the Feast of Unleavened Bread. Seven days you will eat unleavened bread, which I commanded you, at the appointed time of the month of Abib, for in the month of Abib you came out from Egypt. <verse-number id="Ex 34:19">19</verse-number>Every first offspring of a womb <supplied>is</supplied> for me—all of your male livestock, <supplied>the</supplied> first offspring of cattle and small livestock. <verse-number id="Ex 34:20">20</verse-number>But the first offspring of a donkey you will redeem with small livestock, and if you will not redeem <supplied>it</supplied>, you will break its neck. Every firstborn of your sons you will redeem, and you will not appear before me empty-handed. <verse-number id="Ex 34:21">21</verse-number>Six days you will work, and on the seventh day you will rest; in the <supplied>time of</supplied> plowing and in the <supplied>time of</supplied> harvest you will rest. <verse-number id="Ex 34:22">22</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>you yourself<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for yourself” or “as for you, you will observe”</note> will observe the Feast of Weeks—the firstfruits of the wheat harvest—and the Feast of Harvest Gathering at the turn of the year. <verse-number id="Ex 34:23">23</verse-number>Three times in the year all your males will appear before the Lord, Yahweh, the God of Israel, <verse-number id="Ex 34:24">24</verse-number>because I will evict nations before you, and I will enlarge your territory, and no one will covet your land when you go up to appear before Yahweh your God three times in the year. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 34:25">25</verse-number>“You will not slaughter the blood of my sacrifice on <supplied>food with</supplied> yeast, and the sacrifice of the Feast of the Passover will not stay overnight to the morning. <verse-number id="Ex 34:26">26</verse-number>The beginning of the firstfruits of your land you will bring <supplied>to</supplied> the house of Yahweh your God. You will not boil a young goat<note>Or “kid”</note> in its mother’s milk.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 34:27">27</verse-number>And Yahweh said to Moses, “Write for yourself these words, because <idiom-start/>according to<idiom-end/><note>Literally “on the mouth of”</note> these words I have made a covenant with you and with Israel.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Shining Face of Moses</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 34:28">28</verse-number>And he was there with Yahweh forty days and forty nights. He ate no food and drank no water. And he wrote on the tablets the words of the covenant, the ten words. <verse-number id="Ex 34:29">29</verse-number><idiom-start/>And<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And it was”</note> when Moses came down from Mount Sinai, the two tablets of the testimony <supplied>were</supplied> in the hand of Moses at his coming down from the mountain; and Moses did not know that the skin of his face shone because of his speaking with him. <verse-number id="Ex 34:30">30</verse-number>And Aaron and all the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> saw Moses, and, <idiom-start/>to their amazement<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “look” or “behold”</note> the skin of his face shone, and they were afraid of coming near to him. <verse-number id="Ex 34:31">31</verse-number>And Moses called to them, and Aaron and all the leaders of the community returned to him, and Moses spoke to them. <verse-number id="Ex 34:32">32</verse-number>And afterward all the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> came near, and he commanded them all that Yahweh had spoken with him on Mount Sinai. <verse-number id="Ex 34:33">33</verse-number>And Moses finished speaking with them, and he put a veil on his face. <verse-number id="Ex 34:34">34</verse-number>And when Moses came before Yahweh to speak with him, he would remove the veil until he went out, and he would go out and would speak to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> what he had been commanded. <verse-number id="Ex 34:35">35</verse-number>And the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> would see the face of Moses, that the skin of the face of Moses shone, and Moses would put back the veil on his face until his coming to speak with him. </p>
		</chapter>