<chapter id="Ex 35">
			<pericope>Preparation of Materials and People for Building</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 35:1">1</verse-number>And Moses assembled all the community of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and he said to them, “These are the words that Yahweh has commanded <supplied>for us</supplied> to do them. <verse-number id="Ex 35:2">2</verse-number><supplied>On</supplied> six days work can be done, and on the seventh there will be for you a holy <supplied>day</supplied>,<note>Literally “holiness”</note> a <idiom-start/>Sabbath of complete rest<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “a Sabbath of ‘Sabbathation.’ ” “Sabbathation” is not a real word, but it is devised as an attempt to convey the sounds of the related nouns in the Hebrew phrase</note> for Yahweh; anyone doing work on it will be put to death. <verse-number id="Ex 35:3">3</verse-number>You will not kindle a fire in any of your dwellings on the day of the Sabbath.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 35:4">4</verse-number>And Moses said to all the community of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> saying, “This is the word that Yahweh has commanded, saying, <verse-number id="Ex 35:5">5</verse-number>‘Take from among you a contribution for Yahweh, anyone willing of heart, let him bring Yahweh’s contribution—gold and silver and bronze, <verse-number id="Ex 35:6">6</verse-number>and blue and purple and crimson <supplied>yarns</supplied>, and fine linen and goat hair, <verse-number id="Ex 35:7">7</verse-number>and red-dyed ram skins, and fine leather,<note>The particular kind of leather is uncertain</note> and acacia wood, <verse-number id="Ex 35:8">8</verse-number>and oil for the lamp, balsam oils for the anointing oil and for the fragrant incense, <verse-number id="Ex 35:9">9</verse-number>onyx stones and stones for mountings on the ephod and the breast piece. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 35:10">10</verse-number>“And let all <supplied>the</supplied> skilled of heart among you come and make all that Yahweh has commanded: <verse-number id="Ex 35:11">11</verse-number>The tabernacle, its tent, and its covering; its clasps and its frames;<note>Or “boards” or “planks”</note> its bars, its pillars, and its bases; <verse-number id="Ex 35:12">12</verse-number>the ark and its poles; the atonement cover and the curtain of the screen; <verse-number id="Ex 35:13">13</verse-number>the table and its poles and all its equipment; and the bread of the presence; <verse-number id="Ex 35:14">14</verse-number>and lampstand of the light and its equipment and its lamps and the oil for the light; <verse-number id="Ex 35:15">15</verse-number>and the altar of incense and its poles; and the anointing oil and the fragrant incense and the entrance curtain for the entrance of the tabernacle; <verse-number id="Ex 35:16">16</verse-number>the altar of the burnt offering and the bronze grating that <supplied>is</supplied> for it, its poles and all its equipment; the basin and its stand; <verse-number id="Ex 35:17">17</verse-number>the hangings of the courtyard, its pillars, and its bases, and the screen for the courtyard gate; <verse-number id="Ex 35:18">18</verse-number>the <idiom-start/>pegs<idiom-end/><note>Literally “hands”</note> of the tabernacle and the <idiom-start/>pegs<idiom-end/><note>Literally “hands”</note> of the courtyard and their cords; <verse-number id="Ex 35:19">19</verse-number>the woven garments for serving in the sanctuary—the holy garments for Aaron the priest and the garments of his sons to serve as priests.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 35:20">20</verse-number>And all the community of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> went out from before Moses. <verse-number id="Ex 35:21">21</verse-number>And they came—every man whose heart lifted him and every man whose spirit impelled him—they brought Yahweh’s contribution for the work of the tent of assembly and for all its service and for the holy garments. <verse-number id="Ex 35:22">22</verse-number>And they came, the men in addition to the women, all <supplied>who were</supplied> willing of heart; they brought brooches and jewelry rings and signet rings and ornaments—every <supplied>variety</supplied> of gold object—every man who waved a wave offering of gold for Yahweh, <verse-number id="Ex 35:23">23</verse-number>and every man with whom was found blue and purple and crimson <supplied>yarns</supplied> and fine linen and goat hair and red-dyed ram skins and fine leather brought <supplied>it</supplied>. <verse-number id="Ex 35:24">24</verse-number>All <supplied>who were</supplied> presenting a contribution of silver and bronze brought Yahweh’s contribution, and all with whom was found acacia wood for all the work of service brought <supplied>it</supplied>. <verse-number id="Ex 35:25">25</verse-number>And every woman <supplied>who was</supplied> skilled of heart with her hands they spun, and they brought yarn—the blue and the purple, the crimson and the fine linen. <verse-number id="Ex 35:26">26</verse-number>And all the women whose heart lifted them with skill spun the goat hair. <verse-number id="Ex 35:27">27</verse-number>And the leaders brought the onyx stones and stones for mountings for the ephod and for the breast piece <verse-number id="Ex 35:28">28</verse-number>and the balsam oils and the oil for light and for the anointing oil and for the fragrant incense. <verse-number id="Ex 35:29">29</verse-number>Every man and woman whose heart impelled them to bring for all the work to be done that Yahweh had commanded <idiom-start/>by the agency of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “by the hand of”</note> Moses—the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> brought freely to Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 35:30">30</verse-number>And Moses said to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> “See, Yahweh has called by name<note>In other words, “specifically chosen”</note> Bezalel the son of Uri the son of Hur, from the tribe of Judah. <verse-number id="Ex 35:31">31</verse-number>And he has filled him <supplied>with</supplied> the Spirit of God, with wisdom and with skill<note>Or “understanding,” “discernment,” “cleverness”</note> and with knowledge and with every <supplied>kind of</supplied> craftsmanship, <verse-number id="Ex 35:32">32</verse-number>and to devise designs, to work with the gold and with the silver and with the bronze, <verse-number id="Ex 35:33">33</verse-number>and in stonecutting for setting and in cutting wood, for doing every <supplied>kind of</supplied> design craftsmanship. <verse-number id="Ex 35:34">34</verse-number>And he has put <supplied>it</supplied> in his heart to teach—he and Oholiab the son of Ahisamach, from the tribe of Dan. <verse-number id="Ex 35:35">35</verse-number>He has filled them <supplied>with</supplied> skill of heart to do every work of a craftsman and a designer and an embroiderer with the blue and with the purple, with the crimson <supplied>yarns</supplied> and with the fine linen and a weaver; <supplied>they are</supplied> doers of every <supplied>kind of</supplied> craftsmanship and devisers of designs. </p>
		</chapter>