<chapter id="Ex 36">
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 36">36</verse-number><verse-number id="Ex 36:1">1</verse-number> And Bezalel and Oholiab and everyone <supplied>who is</supplied> skilled of heart in whom Yahweh has put wisdom and skill to know and to do all the work for the service of the sanctuary—<supplied>they</supplied> will do <supplied>it</supplied>, according to all that Yahweh has commanded.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Making the Tabernacle</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 36:2">2</verse-number>And Moses called Bezalel and Oholiab and everyone skilled of heart, in whose heart Yahweh had put skill, all whose heart lifted him to come near to the work in order to do it. <verse-number id="Ex 36:3">3</verse-number>And they took from Moses all the contributions<note>Hebrew “contribution”</note> that the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> had brought for the work of the service for the sanctuary in order to do it, and they still brought to him voluntary offerings <idiom-start/>every morning<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “in the morning in the morning”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 36:4">4</verse-number>And all the skilled <supplied>workers who were</supplied> doing all the work for the sanctuary came, <idiom-start/>each<idiom-end/><note>Literally “man man”</note> from his work that they were doing. <verse-number id="Ex 36:5">5</verse-number>And they said to Moses, saying, “The people are <idiom-start/>bringing more<idiom-end/><note>Literally “making much to bring”</note> than enough for the service of the work that Yahweh has commanded <idiom-start/>to be done<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “to do it”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 36:6">6</verse-number>And Moses commanded, and they <idiom-start/>proclaimed the message<idiom-end/><note>Literally “caused a voice to cross through”</note> in the camp, saying, “Let no man or woman again make anything for the sanctuary contribution.” And so the people were restrained from bringing. <verse-number id="Ex 36:7">7</verse-number>And the material was enough for doing all the work, and it was left over. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 36:8">8</verse-number>And all who were skilled of heart among the doers of the work made the tabernacle <supplied>with</supplied> ten curtains of finely twisted linen and blue and purple and crimson <supplied>yarns</supplied>, <supplied>with</supplied> cherubim; he made them, the work of a skilled craftsman. <verse-number id="Ex 36:9">9</verse-number>The length of the one curtain <supplied>was</supplied> twenty-eight cubits, and the width <supplied>was</supplied> four cubits <supplied>for</supplied> the one curtain; one measurement <supplied>was</supplied> for all the curtains. <verse-number id="Ex 36:10">10</verse-number>And he joined five of the curtains <idiom-start/>one to another<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “one to one”</note> and five curtains he joined <idiom-start/>one to another<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “one to one”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 36:11">11</verse-number>And he made loops of blue on the edge of the one curtain, at the end in the set; so he did on the edge of the end curtain in the second set. <verse-number id="Ex 36:12">12</verse-number>He made fifty loops on the one curtain, and he made fifty loops on the end of the curtain that <supplied>was</supplied> in the second set; the loops were opposite<note>Or “interlinked” or “matching”</note> <idiom-start/>one to another<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “one to one”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 36:13">13</verse-number>And he made fifty gold clasps and joined the curtains <idiom-start/>one to another<idiom-end/><note>Literally “one to one”</note> with the clasps, so that the tabernacle was one. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 36:14">14</verse-number>And he made curtains of goat hair for a tent over the tabernacle; he made them eleven curtains. <verse-number id="Ex 36:15">15</verse-number>The length of the one curtain <supplied>was</supplied> thirty cubits, and the width <supplied>was</supplied> four cubits <supplied>for</supplied> the one curtain; one measure <supplied>was</supplied> for <supplied>the</supplied> eleven curtains. <verse-number id="Ex 36:16">16</verse-number>And he joined five curtains together and six curtains together. <verse-number id="Ex 36:17">17</verse-number>And he made fifty loops on the edge of the end curtain in the set, and he made fifty loops on the edge of the curtain <supplied>in</supplied> the second set. <verse-number id="Ex 36:18">18</verse-number>And he made fifty bronze clasps for joining the tent to become one. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 36:19">19</verse-number>And he made a covering for the tent of red-dyed ram skin and a covering of fine leather <supplied>to go</supplied> above. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 36:20">20</verse-number>And he made the frames<note>Or “boards” or “planks”</note> for the tabernacle of acacia wood <supplied>as</supplied> uprights.<note>Literally “standing”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 36:21">21</verse-number>The length of the frame<note>Or “board” or “plank”</note> <supplied>was</supplied> ten cubits, and the width of the one frame<note>Or “board” or “plank”</note> <supplied>was</supplied> one and a half cubits. <verse-number id="Ex 36:22">22</verse-number>He made two <idiom-start/>pegs<idiom-end/><note>Literally “hands”</note> for the one frame<note>Or “board” or “plank”</note> <supplied>for</supplied> joining <idiom-start/>one to another<idiom-end/><note>Literally “one to one”</note> <supplied>and</supplied> likewise for all the frames<note>Or “boards” or “planks”</note> of the tabernacle. <verse-number id="Ex 36:23">23</verse-number>And he made the frames<note>Or “boards” or “planks”</note> for the tabernacle <supplied>with</supplied> twenty frames<note>Or “boards” or “planks”</note> for the south<note>Or “southward southward”</note> side. <verse-number id="Ex 36:24">24</verse-number>And he made forty silver bases under the twenty frames,<note>Or “boards” or “planks”</note> <supplied>with</supplied> two bases under the one frame<note>Or “board” or “plank”</note> for its two <idiom-start/>pegs<idiom-end/><note>Literally “hands”</note> and two bases under the <idiom-start/>next<idiom-end/><note>Literally “one”</note> frame<note>Or “board” or “plank”</note> for its two <idiom-start/>pegs<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “hands”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 36:25">25</verse-number>And for the second side of the tabernacle, the north side, he made twenty frames<note>Or “boards” or “planks”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 36:26">26</verse-number>and their forty silver bases, <supplied>with</supplied> two bases under the one frame<note>Or “board” or “plank”</note> and two bases under the <idiom-start/>next<idiom-end/><note>Literally “one”</note> frame.<note>Or “board” or “plank”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 36:27">27</verse-number>And for the rear of the tabernacle <idiom-start/>on the west<idiom-end/><note>Or “westward,” literally “seaward,” toward the Mediterranean Sea</note> he made six frames.<note>Or “boards” or “planks”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 36:28">28</verse-number>And he made two frames<note>Or “boards” or “planks”</note> for the tabernacle corners at the rear. <verse-number id="Ex 36:29">29</verse-number>And they were double at the bottom, and they were completely together on its top to the one ring; he did likewise for the two of them, for the two corners. <verse-number id="Ex 36:30">30</verse-number>And there were eight frames<note>Or “boards” or “planks”</note> and their sixteen silver bases, two bases, two bases under the one frame.<note>Or “board” or “plank”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 36:31">31</verse-number>And he made five bars of acacia wood for the frames<note>Or “boards” or “planks”</note> on the one side of the tabernacle, <verse-number id="Ex 36:32">32</verse-number>and five bars for the frames<note>Or “boards” or “planks”</note> on the second side of the tabernacle, and five bars for the frames<note>Or “boards” or “planks”</note> at the rear <idiom-start/>on the west<idiom-end/>.<note>Or “westward,” literally “seaward,” toward the Mediterranean Sea</note> <verse-number id="Ex 36:33">33</verse-number>And he made the middle bar to run in the midst of the frames<note>Or “boards” or “planks”</note> from end to end. <verse-number id="Ex 36:34">34</verse-number>And he overlaid the frames<note>Or “boards” or “planks”</note> with gold, and he made their rings of gold <supplied>as</supplied> <idiom-start/>holders<idiom-end/><note>Literally “houses”</note> for the bars, and he overlaid the bars with gold. <verse-number id="Ex 36:35">35</verse-number>And he made the curtain of blue and purple and crimson <supplied>yarns</supplied> and finely twisted linen, <supplied>the</supplied> work of a craftsman; he made it <supplied>with</supplied> cherubim. <verse-number id="Ex 36:36">36</verse-number>And he made for it four acacia pillars, and he overlaid them with gold, <supplied>with</supplied> their gold hooks, and he cast for them four silver bases. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 36:37">37</verse-number>And he made for the entrance of the tent a screen of blue and purple and crimson <supplied>yarns</supplied> and finely twisted linen, <supplied>the</supplied> work of an embroiderer, <verse-number id="Ex 36:38">38</verse-number>and the five pillars and their hooks, and he overlaid their tops and their connections <supplied>with</supplied> gold, and their five bases <supplied>were</supplied> bronze. </p>
		</chapter>