<chapter id="Ex 37">
			<pericope>Making the Ark of the Covenant</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 37:1">1</verse-number>And Bezalel made the ark of acacia wood, two and a half cubits its length and a cubit and a half its width and a cubit and a half its height. <verse-number id="Ex 37:2">2</verse-number>And he overlaid it <supplied>with</supplied> pure gold inside and outside, and he made for it a gold molding all around. <verse-number id="Ex 37:3">3</verse-number>And he cast for it four gold rings on its four feet; and two rings were on its one side, and two rings were on its second side. <verse-number id="Ex 37:4">4</verse-number>And he made poles of acacia wood, and he overlaid them <supplied>with</supplied> gold. <verse-number id="Ex 37:5">5</verse-number>And he put the poles into the rings on the sides of the ark to carry the ark. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 37:6">6</verse-number>And he made an atonement cover of pure gold, two and a half cubits its length and a cubit and a half its width. <verse-number id="Ex 37:7">7</verse-number>And he made two cherubim of gold; he made them of hammered work at the two ends of the atonement cover. <verse-number id="Ex 37:8">8</verse-number>One cherub <supplied>was</supplied> <idiom-start/>at one end<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from end from this”</note> and one cherub <supplied>was</supplied> <idiom-start/>at the other end<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from end from this”</note> of the atonement cover; he made the cherubim at its two ends. <verse-number id="Ex 37:9">9</verse-number>And the cherubim were <supplied>with</supplied> outspread wings above, covering with their wings over the atonement cover <idiom-start/>and facing each other<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “and their faces a man to his brother”</note> the faces of the cherubim were toward the atonement cover. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Making the Table and the Lampstand</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 37:10">10</verse-number>And he made the table of acacia wood, two cubits its length and a cubit its width and a cubit and a half its height. <verse-number id="Ex 37:11">11</verse-number>And he overlaid it <supplied>with</supplied> pure gold, and he made for it a gold molding all around. <verse-number id="Ex 37:12">12</verse-number>And he made for it a handbreadth rim all around, and he made a gold molding for its rim all around. <verse-number id="Ex 37:13">13</verse-number>And he cast for it four gold rings, and he put the rings on the four corners where its four <idiom-start/>legs<idiom-end/><note>Literally “feet”</note> <supplied>were</supplied>. <verse-number id="Ex 37:14">14</verse-number>The rings were near the rim as <idiom-start/>holders<idiom-end/><note>Literally “houses”</note> for the poles to carry the table. <verse-number id="Ex 37:15">15</verse-number>And he made the poles of acacia wood, and he overlaid them <supplied>with</supplied> gold to carry the table. <verse-number id="Ex 37:16">16</verse-number>And he made the vessels that <supplied>were</supplied> on the table—its plates and its ladles,<note>Or “bowls”</note> and its bowls and its pitchers with which <supplied>libations</supplied> were poured—<supplied>of</supplied> pure gold. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 37:17">17</verse-number>And he made the lampstand of pure gold; he made the lampstand of hammered work—its base and its branch, its cups, its buds, and its blossoms were <idiom-start/>all part of it<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “from it”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 37:18">18</verse-number>And six branches <supplied>were</supplied> going out from its sides, three branches of the lampstand from its one side and three branches of the lampstand from its second side. <verse-number id="Ex 37:19">19</verse-number>Three almond-flower cups <supplied>were</supplied> on the one branch <supplied>with</supplied> a bud and a blossom, and three almond-flower cups <supplied>were</supplied> on the one branch <supplied>with</supplied> a bud and a blossom—likewise for the six branches going out from the lampstand. <verse-number id="Ex 37:20">20</verse-number>And on the lampstand <supplied>were</supplied> four almond-flower cups, <supplied>with</supplied> its<note>Refers to the lampstand</note> buds and its blossoms. <verse-number id="Ex 37:21">21</verse-number>And a bud <supplied>was</supplied> under the two branches <supplied>that came</supplied> from it, and a bud under the two branches from it, and a bud under the two branches from it, <supplied>likewise</supplied> for the six branches coming out from the lampstand. <verse-number id="Ex 37:22">22</verse-number>Their buds and their branches were from it, all of it one <supplied>piece</supplied> of pure gold, hammered work. <verse-number id="Ex 37:23">23</verse-number>And he made its seven lamps and its snuffers and its fire pans of pure gold. <verse-number id="Ex 37:24">24</verse-number>He made it <supplied>from</supplied> a talent of pure gold and all its <supplied>pieces of</supplied> equipment. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Making the Incense Altar and Anointing Oil</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 37:25">25</verse-number>And he made the incense altar of acacia wood, a cubit its length and a cubit its width—a square—and two cubits its height; its horns were <idiom-start/>of one piece with it<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “from it”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 37:26">26</verse-number>And he overlaid it <supplied>with</supplied> pure gold—its top and its sides all around and its horns—and he made for it a gold molding all around. <verse-number id="Ex 37:27">27</verse-number>And he made for it two gold rings under its molding <idiom-start/>on two opposite sides<idiom-end/><note>Literally “on two of its sides on two of its sides”</note> as <idiom-start/>holders<idiom-end/><note>Literally “houses”</note> for poles to carry it with them. <verse-number id="Ex 37:28">28</verse-number>And he made the poles of acacia wood, and he overlaid them with gold. <verse-number id="Ex 37:29">29</verse-number>And he made the holy anointing oil and the pure fragrant incense—work of a perfumer. </p>
		</chapter>