<chapter id="Ex 38">
			<pericope>Making the Bronze Altar and the Basin</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 38:1">1</verse-number>And he made the burnt-offering altar of acacia wood; its length <supplied>was</supplied> five cubits, and its width <supplied>was</supplied> five cubits—<supplied>it was</supplied> square—and its height <supplied>was</supplied> three cubits. <verse-number id="Ex 38:2">2</verse-number>And he made its horns on its four corners; its horns were <idiom-start/>of one piece with it<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “from it”</note> and he overlaid it <supplied>with</supplied> bronze. <verse-number id="Ex 38:3">3</verse-number>And he made all the equipment of the altar—the pots and the shovels and the sprinkling bowls and the forks<note><cite title="BibleLEB2: 1 Sa 2:13">1 Samuel 2:13 </cite>mentions a fork with “three teeth” used by priests</note> and the fire pans—all its equipment he made <supplied>with</supplied> bronze. <verse-number id="Ex 38:4">4</verse-number>And he made for the altar a grating, a work of bronze network under its ledge, below, up to its middle. <verse-number id="Ex 38:5">5</verse-number>And he cast four rings on the four ends of the bronze grating <supplied>as</supplied> <idiom-start/>holders<idiom-end/><note>Literally “houses”</note> for the poles. <verse-number id="Ex 38:6">6</verse-number>And he made the poles of acacia wood, and he overlaid them <supplied>with</supplied> bronze. <verse-number id="Ex 38:7">7</verse-number>And he put the poles into the rings on the sides of the altar to carry it with them. He made it hollow with boards. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 38:8">8</verse-number>And he made the basin of bronze and its stand of bronze from the mirrors of the serving women who served <supplied>at</supplied> the entrance of the tent of assembly. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Making the Courtyard</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 38:9">9</verse-number>And he made the courtyard; for the south<note>Or “southward southward”</note> side <supplied>were</supplied> the hangings of the court of finely twisted linen, one hundred cubits, <verse-number id="Ex 38:10">10</verse-number><supplied>with</supplied> their twenty pillars and their twenty bases of bronze <supplied>and with</supplied> the hooks of the pillars and their bands of silver. <verse-number id="Ex 38:11">11</verse-number>And for the north side <supplied>the hangings were</supplied> one hundred cubits <supplied>with</supplied> their twenty pillars and their twenty bases of bronze <supplied>and with</supplied> the hooks of the pillars and their bands of silver. <verse-number id="Ex 38:12">12</verse-number>And for the <idiom-start/>west<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sea”</note> side fifty cubits <supplied>of</supplied> hangings <supplied>with</supplied> their ten pillars and their ten bases <supplied>and with</supplied> the hooks of the pillars and their bands of silver. <verse-number id="Ex 38:13">13</verse-number>And for the eastward side, toward sunrise, fifty cubits; <verse-number id="Ex 38:14">14</verse-number>fifteen cubits of hangings <supplied>were</supplied> to the shoulder,<note>Or “side,” referring to the span on one side of the courtyard’s entry</note> <supplied>with</supplied> their three pillars and their three bases, <verse-number id="Ex 38:15">15</verse-number>and for the second shoulder<note>Or “side,” referring to the span on one side of the courtyard’s entry</note> <idiom-start/>on each side<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from this and from this”</note> of the gate of the courtyard <supplied>were</supplied> fifteen cubits of hangings, <supplied>with</supplied> their three pillars and their three bases. <verse-number id="Ex 38:16">16</verse-number>All the hangings of the courtyard all around <supplied>were</supplied> finely twisted linen, <verse-number id="Ex 38:17">17</verse-number>and the bases for the pillars <supplied>were</supplied> bronze, the hooks of the pillars and their bands <supplied>were</supplied> silver, and the overlay of their tops <supplied>was</supplied> silver, and all the pillars of the courtyard <supplied>were</supplied> banded <supplied>with</supplied> silver. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 38:18">18</verse-number>And the screen of the gate of the courtyard <supplied>was</supplied> the work of an embroiderer, <supplied>with</supplied> blue and purple and crimson <supplied>yarns</supplied> and finely twisted linen; <supplied>it was</supplied> twenty cubits long and five cubits <idiom-start/>high<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “height in width”</note> like the hangings of the courtyard, <verse-number id="Ex 38:19">19</verse-number>and <supplied>with</supplied> their four pillars and their four bases of bronze, <supplied>with</supplied> their silver hooks and <supplied>with</supplied> their tops and their bands of silver. <verse-number id="Ex 38:20">20</verse-number>And all the <idiom-start/>pegs<idiom-end/><note>Literally “hands”</note> for the tabernacle and for the courtyard all around <supplied>were</supplied> bronze. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Amounts of Gold, Silver, and Bronze Used</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 38:21">21</verse-number>These are the records of the tabernacle, the tabernacle of the testimony, which <supplied>were</supplied> recorded at the <idiom-start/>command of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “mouth of”</note> Moses, the work of the Levites, in the hand of Ithamar the son of Aaron the priest. <verse-number id="Ex 38:22">22</verse-number>And Bezalel the son of Uri the son of Hur, of the tribe of Judah, did all that Yahweh commanded Moses. <verse-number id="Ex 38:23">23</verse-number>And with him <supplied>was</supplied> Oholiab the son of Ahisamach of the tribe of Dan, a skilled craftsman and a designer and an embroiderer with the blue and with the purple and with the crimson <supplied>yarns</supplied> and with the linen. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 38:24">24</verse-number>And all the gold used for the work, in the work of the sanctuary, it was the gold of the wave offering—twenty-nine talents and seven hundred and thirty shekels, according to the sanctuary shekel. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 38:25">25</verse-number>And the silver recorded from the community <supplied>was</supplied> a hundred talents and a thousand seven hundred and seventy-five shekels, according to the sanctuary shekel. <verse-number id="Ex 38:26">26</verse-number><supplied>It was</supplied> a bekah for the individual, the half shekel according to the sanctuary shekel, for <idiom-start/>everyone who was counted<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “all of the going over to the being counted”</note> from <idiom-start/>twenty years old<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a son of twenty years”</note> and above, for six hundred and three thousand five hundred and fifty. <verse-number id="Ex 38:27">27</verse-number>And it was one hundred talents of the silver to cast the bases of the sanctuary and the bases of the curtain—one hundred bases for one hundred talents of silver, a talent for <supplied>each</supplied> base. <verse-number id="Ex 38:28">28</verse-number>And <supplied>from</supplied> the thousand seven hundred and seventy-five <supplied>shekels</supplied> he made hooks for the pillars, and he overlaid their tops, and he made bands <supplied>for</supplied> them. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 38:29">29</verse-number>And the bronze of the wave offering <supplied>was</supplied> seventy talents and two thousand four hundred shekels. <verse-number id="Ex 38:30">30</verse-number>And he made with it the bases of the entrance of the tent of assembly and the bronze altar and the bronze grating that belonged to it and all the equipment of the altar <verse-number id="Ex 38:31">31</verse-number>and the bases of the courtyard all around and the bases of the gate of the courtyard and all the <idiom-start/>pegs<idiom-end/><note>Literally “hands”</note> of the tabernacle and all the <idiom-start/>pegs<idiom-end/><note>Literally “hands”</note> of the courtyard all around. </p>
		</chapter>