<chapter id="Ex 39">
			<pericope>Making Garments for Priests</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 39:1">1</verse-number>And from the blue and the purple and the crimson <supplied>yarns</supplied> they made woven garments for serving in the sanctuary, and they made the holy garments that were for Aaron, as Yahweh had commanded Moses. <verse-number id="Ex 39:2">2</verse-number>And he made the ephod <supplied>of</supplied> gold, blue, and purple and crimson <supplied>yarns</supplied>, and finely twisted linen. <verse-number id="Ex 39:3">3</verse-number>And he hammered out the leaves of gold, and he cut off cords to weave in the midst of the blue and in the midst of the purple and in the midst of the crimson and in the midst of the linen—<supplied>the</supplied> work of a skilled craftsman. <verse-number id="Ex 39:4">4</verse-number>They made joined shoulder pieces for it; it was joined on its two edges. <verse-number id="Ex 39:5">5</verse-number>And the waistband of his ephod, which <idiom-start/>was of one piece with it<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “on it from it”</note> <supplied>was of</supplied> like work, gold, blue, and purple and crimson <supplied>yarns</supplied>, and finely twisted linen, as Yahweh had commanded Moses. <verse-number id="Ex 39:6">6</verse-number>And they made onyx stones mounted <supplied>in</supplied> gold filigree settings, engraved <supplied>with</supplied> seal engravings according to the names of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 39:7">7</verse-number>And he set them on the ephod’s shoulder pieces <supplied>as</supplied> stones of remembrance for the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> as Yahweh had commanded Moses. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 39:8">8</verse-number>And he made the breast piece, <supplied>the</supplied> work of a skilled craftsman, like <supplied>the</supplied> work of <supplied>the</supplied> ephod, <supplied>of</supplied> gold, blue, and purple and crimson <supplied>yarns</supplied>, and finely twisted linen. <verse-number id="Ex 39:9">9</verse-number>It was squared; they made the breast piece doubled; its length <supplied>was</supplied> a span, and its width <supplied>was</supplied> a span <supplied>when</supplied> doubled. <verse-number id="Ex 39:10">10</verse-number>And they filled it <supplied>with</supplied> four rows of stone; a row of carnelian, topaz, and emerald <supplied>was</supplied> the first row; <verse-number id="Ex 39:11">11</verse-number>and the second row <supplied>was</supplied> a malachite, a sapphire, and a moonstone; <verse-number id="Ex 39:12">12</verse-number>and the third row <supplied>was</supplied> a jacinth, an agate, and an amethyst; <verse-number id="Ex 39:13">13</verse-number>and the fourth row <supplied>was</supplied> a turquoise, an onyx, and a jasper. <supplied>They were</supplied> set <supplied>with</supplied> gold filigree settings in their mountings. <verse-number id="Ex 39:14">14</verse-number>And the stones <supplied>were</supplied> according to the names of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> they <supplied>were</supplied> twelve according to their names, <supplied>with</supplied> seal engravings, each according to its name for <supplied>the</supplied> twelve tribes. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 39:15">15</verse-number>And they made on the breast piece braided chains, a work of pure gold ornamental cord. <verse-number id="Ex 39:16">16</verse-number>And they made two gold filigree settings and two gold rings, and they put the two rings on the two edges of the breast piece. <verse-number id="Ex 39:17">17</verse-number>And they put the two gold ornamental cords on the two rings on the edges of the breast piece. <verse-number id="Ex 39:18">18</verse-number>And they put the two ends of the two ornamental cords on the two filigree settings, and they put them on the shoulder pieces of the ephod at the front of it. <verse-number id="Ex 39:19">19</verse-number>And they made two gold rings, and they placed <supplied>them</supplied> on the two edges of the breast piece, on its lip that <supplied>is</supplied> on <idiom-start/>the other side<idiom-end/><note>Literally “beyond”</note> of the ephod, <idiom-start/>to the inside<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “houseward,” “to house,” meaning “inward”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 39:20">20</verse-number>And they made two gold rings and put them on the ephod’s two shoulder pieces below, at its front near its seam above the waistband of the ephod. <verse-number id="Ex 39:21">21</verse-number>And they tied the breast piece by its rings to the rings of the ephod with a blue cord <supplied>so that</supplied> the breast piece <supplied>would</supplied> be on the waistband of the ephod and not come loose from the ephod, as Yahweh had commanded Moses. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 39:22">22</verse-number>And he made the robe of the ephod, weaver’s work, totally of blue <supplied>yarn</supplied>. <verse-number id="Ex 39:23">23</verse-number>And the opening of the robe in the middle of it was like the opening of a sturdy garment, <supplied>with</supplied> an edge for its opening all around so that it would not be torn. <verse-number id="Ex 39:24">24</verse-number>And they made on the hem of the robe pomegranates of finely twisted blue and purple and crimson. <verse-number id="Ex 39:25">25</verse-number>And they made pure gold bells and put the bells in the midst of the pomegranates on the hem of the robe all around in the midst of the pomegranates, <verse-number id="Ex 39:26">26</verse-number>a bell and a pomegranate, a bell and a pomegranate on the hem of the robe all around for serving, as Yahweh had commanded Moses. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 39:27">27</verse-number>And they made the tunics of fine linen, a weaver’s work, for Aaron and for his sons, <verse-number id="Ex 39:28">28</verse-number>and the turban of fine linen and the headdresses of the headbands of fine linen and undergarments of the linen cloth, finely twisted, <verse-number id="Ex 39:29">29</verse-number>and the sash of finely twisted linen and blue and purple and crimson <supplied>yarns</supplied>, the work of an embroiderer, as Yahweh had commanded Moses. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 39:30">30</verse-number>And they made the rosette<note>Or “medallion”</note> of the holy diadem <supplied>of</supplied> pure gold, and they wrote on it <supplied>with the</supplied> writing of seal engravings: “A holy object for Yahweh.” <verse-number id="Ex 39:31">31</verse-number>And they put a blue cord on it to put it above on the turban, as Yahweh had commanded Moses. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Preparations Complete</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 39:32">32</verse-number>And all the work of the tabernacle of the tent of assembly was finished, and the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> had done according to all that Yahweh had commanded Moses; so they did. <verse-number id="Ex 39:33">33</verse-number>And they brought the tabernacle to Moses, the tent and all its equipment, its hooks, its frames,<note>Or “boards” or “planks”</note> its bars, and its pillars and its bases; <verse-number id="Ex 39:34">34</verse-number>and the covering of the red-dyed ram skins and the covering of fine leather and the curtain of the screen; <verse-number id="Ex 39:35">35</verse-number>the ark of the testimony and its poles and the atonement cover; <verse-number id="Ex 39:36">36</verse-number>the table, all its equipment, and the bread of the presence; <verse-number id="Ex 39:37">37</verse-number>the pure <supplied>gold</supplied> lampstand, its lamps—the lamps of the row—and all its equipment and the oil of the light; <verse-number id="Ex 39:38">38</verse-number>the gold altar, the anointing oil, the fragrant incense, and the screen of the entrance of the tent; <verse-number id="Ex 39:39">39</verse-number>the bronze altar, and the bronze grating that <supplied>is</supplied> for it, its poles, and all its equipment, the basin and its stand, <verse-number id="Ex 39:40">40</verse-number>the hangings of the courtyard, its pillars, and its bases; and the screen for the courtyard gate, its tent cords and its <idiom-start/>pegs<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “hands”</note> and all the equipment of the service of the tabernacle for the tent of assembly, <verse-number id="Ex 39:41">41</verse-number>the woven garments for serving in the sanctuary—the holy garments for Aaron the priest and the garments for his sons to serve as priests. <verse-number id="Ex 39:42">42</verse-number>According to all that Yahweh had commanded Moses, so the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> did all the work. <verse-number id="Ex 39:43">43</verse-number>And Moses saw all the work, and, indeed, they had done it as Yahweh had commanded; so they did, and Moses blessed them. </p>
		</chapter>