<chapter id="Ex 40">
			<pericope>Completion of the Tabernacle</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 40:1">1</verse-number>And Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Ex 40:2">2</verse-number>“On the first day of the month, you will set up the tabernacle of the tent of assembly. <verse-number id="Ex 40:3">3</verse-number>And you will put there the ark of the testimony, and you will cover over the ark <supplied>with</supplied> the curtain.<note>Or “veil the ark with the curtain”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 40:4">4</verse-number>And you will bring the table, and you will arrange its setting, and you will bring the lampstand, and you will set up its lamps. <verse-number id="Ex 40:5">5</verse-number>And you will put the gold altar for incense before the ark of the testimony, and you will set up the entrance screen for the tabernacle. <verse-number id="Ex 40:6">6</verse-number>And you will put the altar of the burnt offering before the entrance of the tabernacle of the tent of assembly. <verse-number id="Ex 40:7">7</verse-number>And you will put the basin between the tent of assembly and the altar, and you will put water <idiom-start/>in it<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “there”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 40:8">8</verse-number>And you will set up the courtyard all around, and you will put up the screen of the gate of the courtyard. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 40:9">9</verse-number>“And you will take the anointing oil, and you will anoint the tabernacle and all that <supplied>is</supplied> in it, and you will consecrate all of its equipment,<note>Or “vessels” or “utensils” or “contents”</note> and it will be holy. <verse-number id="Ex 40:10">10</verse-number>And you will anoint the altar of the burnt offering and all of its equipment,<note>Or “vessels” or “utensils” or “contents”</note> and you will consecrate the altar, and the altar will be a most holy thing.<note>Literally “holiness of holinesses,” that is, “a holy thing among holy things”</note> <verse-number id="Ex 40:11">11</verse-number>And you will anoint the basin and its stand, and you will consecrate it. <verse-number id="Ex 40:12">12</verse-number>And you will bring Aaron and his sons to the entrance of the tent of assembly, and you will wash them with the water. <verse-number id="Ex 40:13">13</verse-number>And you will clothe Aaron with the holy garments, and you will anoint him, and you will consecrate him, and he will serve as a priest for me. <verse-number id="Ex 40:14">14</verse-number>And you will bring his sons, and you will clothe them <supplied>with</supplied> tunics. <verse-number id="Ex 40:15">15</verse-number>And you will anoint them as you anointed their father, and they will serve as priests for me. And their anointing will be for them to be a lasting priesthood<note>Or “a priesthood of eternity”</note> throughout their generations.” <verse-number id="Ex 40:16">16</verse-number>And Moses did according to all that Yahweh had commanded him; so he did. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 40:17">17</verse-number><idiom-start/>In<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and it was in”</note> the first month of the second year, on <supplied>the</supplied> first of the month, the tabernacle was set up. <verse-number id="Ex 40:18">18</verse-number>And Moses raised the tabernacle, and he placed its bases, and he set up its frames,<note>Or “boards” or “planks”</note> and he placed its bars, and he raised its pillars. <verse-number id="Ex 40:19">19</verse-number>And he spread the tent over the tabernacle; he placed the covering of the tent over it, above <supplied>it</supplied>, as Yahweh had commanded Moses. <verse-number id="Ex 40:20">20</verse-number>And he took and he put the testimony into the ark, and he placed the poles on the ark, and he put the atonement cover on the ark, above <supplied>it</supplied>. <verse-number id="Ex 40:21">21</verse-number>And he brought the ark into the tabernacle, and he set up the curtain of the screening, and he shielded the ark of the testimony, as Yahweh had commanded Moses. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 40:22">22</verse-number>And he put the table in the tent of assembly on the north side of the tabernacle outside the curtain. <verse-number id="Ex 40:23">23</verse-number>And he arranged on it an arrangement of bread before Yahweh, as Yahweh had commanded Moses. <verse-number id="Ex 40:24">24</verse-number>And he placed the lampstand in the tent of assembly opposite the table on the south side of the tabernacle. <verse-number id="Ex 40:25">25</verse-number>And he set up the lamps before Yahweh, as Yahweh had commanded Moses. <verse-number id="Ex 40:26">26</verse-number>And he placed the gold altar in the tent of assembly before the curtain. <verse-number id="Ex 40:27">27</verse-number>And he turned fragrant incense into smoke on it, as Yahweh had commanded Moses. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 40:28">28</verse-number>And he set up the entrance screen for the tabernacle. <verse-number id="Ex 40:29">29</verse-number>And the altar of burnt offering he placed <supplied>at</supplied> the entrance of the tabernacle of the tent of assembly, and he offered on it the burnt offering and the grain offering, as Yahweh had commanded Moses. <verse-number id="Ex 40:30">30</verse-number>And he placed the basin between the tent of assembly and the altar, and he put there water for washing. <verse-number id="Ex 40:31">31</verse-number>And Moses and Aaron and his sons washed their hands and their feet from it. <verse-number id="Ex 40:32">32</verse-number>At their going into the tent of assembly and at their approaching the altar, they washed, as Yahweh had commanded Moses. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ex 40:33">33</verse-number>And he set up the courtyard all around the tabernacle and the altar, and he put up the screen of the gate of the courtyard, and Moses completed the work. <verse-number id="Ex 40:34">34</verse-number>And the cloud covered the tent of assembly, and the glory of Yahweh filled the tabernacle. <verse-number id="Ex 40:35">35</verse-number>And Moses was unable to go into the tent of assembly because the cloud settled on it and the glory of Yahweh filled the tabernacle. <verse-number id="Ex 40:36">36</verse-number>And when the cloud was lifted from the tabernacle, the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> set out on all their journeys. <verse-number id="Ex 40:37">37</verse-number>But if the cloud was not lifted, they did not set out until the day of its being lifted. <verse-number id="Ex 40:38">38</verse-number>For the cloud of Yahweh <supplied>was</supplied> on the tabernacle by day, and fire was on it <supplied>by</supplied> night before the eyes of all the house of Israel throughout all their journeys. </p>
		</chapter>