<chapter id="Da 1">
			<pericope>Daniel’s Development in the King’s Court</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 1:1">1</verse-number>In <supplied>the</supplied> third year of the reign of Jehoiakim king of Judah, Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon came to Jerusalem and besieged it. <verse-number id="Da 1:2">2</verse-number>And the Lord gave Jehoiakim the king of Judah into his hand and <idiom-start/>some of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from the end/extremity/limits”</note> of the utensils of the temple of God,<note>Hebrew “the God”</note> and he brought them <supplied>to</supplied> the land of Shinar <supplied>to</supplied> the temple of his gods, and he brought the utensils to <idiom-start/>the treasury<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the house of the treasury”</note> of his gods. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 1:3">3</verse-number>And the king <idiom-start/>ordered<idiom-end/><note>Literally “said to”</note> Ashpenaz, the commander of his court officials, to bring <idiom-start/>some of the Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from the sons/children of Israel”</note> from <idiom-start/>the royal family<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from the seed of the kingship”</note> and from the lords,<note>Or “nobles”</note> <verse-number id="Da 1:4">4</verse-number>youths who <idiom-start/>have no physical defect<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “there is not in them any physical defect”</note> and <supplied>who are</supplied> <idiom-start/>handsome<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “good/pleasing of appearance”</note> and <supplied>who are</supplied> prudent<note>Or “insightful”</note> in all wisdom and <idiom-start/>endowed with knowledge<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “<supplied>who have</supplied> knowledge of knowledge”</note> and <supplied>who</supplied> understand insight, and who <supplied>have</supplied> the <idiom-start/>ability<idiom-end/><note>Literally “strength”</note> in them to serve in the palace of the king. <supplied>And the king ordered him</supplied> to teach them the literature and the language of <supplied>the</supplied> Chaldeans. <verse-number id="Da 1:5">5</verse-number>And the king assigned to them <idiom-start/>his daily portion<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<supplied>the</supplied> portion of the day on its day”</note> from the fine food of the king, and from <idiom-start/>the wine that he drank<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the wine of his drink”</note> and <supplied>instructed that</supplied> <idiom-start/>they were to be educated for three years<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “and to be educated them years three”</note> And at the end <supplied>of</supplied> their <supplied>training</supplied>, <idiom-start/>they were to be stationed<idiom-end/><note>Literally “they would stand”</note> <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of”</note> the king. <verse-number id="Da 1:6">6</verse-number>Now there was among them <idiom-start/>from the Judeans<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from the children of Judah”</note> Daniel, Hananiah, Mishael and Azariah. <verse-number id="Da 1:7">7</verse-number>And the commander of the court officials gave them names, and he called Daniel, Belteshazzar; and Hananiah, Shadrach; and Mishael, Meshach; and Azariah, Abednego. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Daniel’s Resolve</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 1:8">8</verse-number>Now <idiom-start/>Daniel resolved<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Daniel placed upon his heart”</note> that he would not defile himself with the fine food of the king, and with <idiom-start/>the wine that he drank<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the wine of his drink”</note> and <supplied>so</supplied> he requested from the commander of the court officials <supplied>permission so</supplied> that he would not defile himself. <verse-number id="Da 1:9">9</verse-number>And God<note>Hebrew “the God”</note> gave Daniel favor and compassion <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of”</note> the commander of the court officials, <verse-number id="Da 1:10">10</verse-number>and the commander of the court officials said to Daniel, “I <supplied>am</supplied> afraid <supplied>of</supplied> my lord, the king, who has determined your food and your drink, for <idiom-start/>why should<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to what would”</note> he see your face having a worse appearance than the young men who <idiom-start/>are your age<idiom-end/>?<note>Literally “like your age”; “your” is plural</note> Then you will endanger my head with the king.” <verse-number id="Da 1:11">11</verse-number>Then<note>Hebrew “And”</note> Daniel asked the guard<note>Or “overseer”</note> whom the commander of the court officials <supplied>had</supplied> appointed over Daniel, Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah, <verse-number id="Da 1:12">12</verse-number>“Please test your servants <supplied>for</supplied> ten days, and let them give us <idiom-start/>some of the vegetables<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from the vegetables”</note> and let us eat and let us drink water. <verse-number id="Da 1:13">13</verse-number>Then<note>Hebrew “And”</note> let our appearances and the appearance of the young men who are eating the fine food of the king be compared <idiom-start/>before you<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “in your presence”</note> and <supplied>then</supplied> deal with your servants <idiom-start/>according to what you see<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “and according to/that you see”</note> <verse-number id="Da 1:14">14</verse-number>So he agreed to this proposal with them, and he tested them <supplied>for</supplied> ten days. <verse-number id="Da 1:15">15</verse-number>And at the end of ten days their appearances appeared better and <supplied>they were</supplied> healthier of body than all the young men who were eating the fine food of the king. <verse-number id="Da 1:16">16</verse-number><idiom-start/>So<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And it happened”</note> the guard <idiom-start/>continued to withhold<idiom-end/><note>Literally “he was … withdrawing”</note> their fine food and the wine of their drink, and he gave them<note>Hebrew “to them”</note> vegetables. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 1:17">17</verse-number><idiom-start/>And as for these four young men<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “And these young men, four of them”</note> God<note>Hebrew “the God”</note> gave to them knowledge and insight into all literature and wisdom, and Daniel had insight into all visions<note>Hebrew “vision”</note> and dreams. <verse-number id="Da 1:18">18</verse-number>And at the end of the time the king had set to bring them, the commander of the court officials brought them in <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of”</note> Nebuchadnezzar. <verse-number id="Da 1:19">19</verse-number>And the king spoke with them, <idiom-start/>and among all of them no one was found like<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and he was not found from all of them like”</note> Daniel, Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah; then they stood <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of”</note> the king. <verse-number id="Da 1:20">20</verse-number>And in every matter of wisdom <supplied>and</supplied> understanding <supplied>about</supplied> which the king inquired from them, he found them ten times better <supplied>than</supplied> all <supplied>of</supplied> the magicians<note>Or “soothsayer-priests”</note> <supplied>and</supplied> conjurers<note>Or “enchanters”</note> that <idiom-start/>were in his entire kingdom<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “in the whole of his kingdom”</note> <verse-number id="Da 1:21">21</verse-number>And Daniel was <supplied>there</supplied> until the first year of Cyrus the king. </p>
		</chapter>