<chapter id="Da 2">
			<pericope>The King’s Troubling Dream</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 2:1">1</verse-number>Now<note>Hebrew “And”</note> in the second year of the reign of Nebuchadnezzar, Nebuchadnezzar dreamed dreams; and his spirit was troubled and his sleep left him. <verse-number id="Da 2:2">2</verse-number>So the king said to call the magicians<note>Or “soothsayer-priests”</note> and the conjurers<note>Or “enchanters”</note> and the sorcerers and the <idiom-start/>astrologers<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Chaldeans”</note> to tell to the king his dreams. And they came in and they stood <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of”</note> the king. <verse-number id="Da 2:3">3</verse-number>And the king said to them, “<idiom-start/>I have had a dream<idiom-end/><note>Literally “A dream I have dreamed”</note> and my spirit is anxious to know the dream.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 2:4">4</verse-number>And the <idiom-start/>astrologers<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Chaldeans”</note> said to the king <supplied>in</supplied> Aramaic,<note>The text of Daniel is in Aramaic from this point on through Daniel chapter 7. Then the text resumes in Hebrew to the end of the book</note> “O king, live forever! Tell the dream to your servants and we will reveal the explanation.” <verse-number id="Da 2:5">5</verse-number>The king answered and said to the <idiom-start/>astrologers<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “Chaldeans”</note> “The command from me is firm: if you <supplied>do</supplied> not make known to me the dream and its explanation,<note>Or “interpretation”</note> <supplied>then</supplied> you will be broken into pieces and your houses will be laid in ruins. <verse-number id="Da 2:6">6</verse-number>But if you tell me the dream and its explanation, you will receive gifts and rewards<note>Aramaic “reward”</note> and great honor from me. Therefore, tell me the dream and its explanation.”<note>Or “interpretation”</note> <verse-number id="Da 2:7">7</verse-number>They answered once more and said, “Let the king tell the dream to his servants and we will make the explanation known.” <verse-number id="Da 2:8">8</verse-number>The king answered and said, “<idiom-start/>Certainly<idiom-end/><note>Literally “From <supplied>a</supplied> certainty”</note> I know that <idiom-start/>you are trying to gain time<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the time you are gaining”</note> <idiom-start/>because<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all because of that”</note> you have seen <idiom-start/>that this matter is firmly decreed by me<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “that firm from me <supplied>is</supplied> the decree”</note> <verse-number id="Da 2:9">9</verse-number>for if you <supplied>do</supplied> not make the dream known to me, <idiom-start/>your verdict is fixed<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “one is your verdict”</note> and you have conspired to say <supplied>a</supplied> lying and deceitful word to me until the <idiom-start/>circumstances<idiom-end/><note>Literally “time”</note> will change. Therefore, tell me the dream, and I will know that you can tell me its explanation.” <verse-number id="Da 2:10">10</verse-number>The <idiom-start/>astrologers<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Chaldeans”</note> answered the king and said, “There is not a man on earth that is able to reveal the word of the king; <idiom-start/>in fact<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “all because that”</note> no great and powerful king has <supplied>ever</supplied> asked a thing like this of any magician<note>Or “soothsayer-priest”</note> or conjurer<note>Or “enchanter”</note> or <idiom-start/>astrologer<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “Chaldean”</note> <verse-number id="Da 2:11">11</verse-number>And the thing that the king is asking <supplied>is too</supplied> difficult and <idiom-start/>there is no one who<idiom-end/><note>Literally “there is not another”</note> can reveal it to the king except <supplied>the</supplied> gods <idiom-start/>whose dwelling is not with mortals<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “concerning their dwelling is not with flesh”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 2:12">12</verse-number>Because of this the king became angry, and he became very much enraged, and he said <supplied>that</supplied> all the wise men of Babylon <supplied>are</supplied> to be destroyed. <verse-number id="Da 2:13">13</verse-number>And the decree was issued, and the wise men <idiom-start/>were on the verge of being executed<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “were in the process of being killed”</note> and they searched for Daniel and his companions to be executed. <verse-number id="Da 2:14">14</verse-number>Then Daniel responded prudently and discretely to Arioch, the commander of the imperial guard of the king, who had gone out to execute the wise men of Babylon. <verse-number id="Da 2:15">15</verse-number><idiom-start/>He asked<idiom-end/><note>Literally “he answered”</note> and said to Arioch, the royal official of the king, “<idiom-start/>Why<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Over what”</note> is the decree from the king <supplied>so</supplied> severe?” Then Arioch explained the matter<note>Or “situation”</note> to Daniel. <verse-number id="Da 2:16">16</verse-number>And Daniel went in and requested from the king that he would give him time, and <idiom-start/>he would tell the king<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to tell/reveal to the king”</note> the explanation.<note>Or “interpretation”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 2:17">17</verse-number>Then Daniel went to his home, and he made the matter known to Hananiah, Mishael and Azariah, his companions, <verse-number id="Da 2:18">18</verse-number>and <supplied>told them</supplied> to seek mercy <idiom-start/>from the God of heaven<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from before the God of the heaven”</note> concerning this mystery, so that Daniel and his companions, along with the remainder of the wise men of Babylon, would not be killed. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 2:19">19</verse-number>Then in a vision of the night the mystery was revealed to Daniel; then Daniel blessed the God of heaven. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 2:20">20</verse-number>Daniel <idiom-start/>said<idiom-end/>:<note>Literally “answered and he said”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Let his name, <supplied>the name</supplied> of God,<note>Aramaic “the God”</note> be blessed <idiom-start/>throughout the ages<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from the age unto the age”</note> </li1>
				<li2>for the wisdom and the power <idiom-start/>are his<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “of to him it <supplied>is</supplied>”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Da 2:21">21</verse-number>And he changes the times and the seasons, </li1>
				<li2>and he deposes kings and he sets up kings; </li2>
				<li1>he gives wisdom<note>Aramaic “the wisdom”</note> to wise men </li1>
				<li2>and knowledge to <supplied>men who</supplied> know understanding. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Da 2:22">22</verse-number>He reveals the deep and the hidden things; </li1>
				<li2>he knows what <supplied>is</supplied> in the darkness, </li2>
				<li2>and the light dwells with him. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Da 2:23">23</verse-number>To you, O God of my ancestors,<note>Or “fathers”</note> </li1>
				<li2>I give thanks and I give praises, </li2>
				<li1>for the wisdom and the power you gave to me, </li1>
				<li2>and now you have made known to me </li2>
				<li1>what we have asked from you, </li1>
				<li2>for you have made known to us the matter of the king.” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Daniel Praises God and Interprets the King’s Dream</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 2:24">24</verse-number><idiom-start/>Therefore<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Now because this”</note> Daniel went to Arioch, whom the king had appointed<note>Aramaic “has appointed”</note> to destroy the wise men of Babylon; he went and thus he said to him: “You must not destroy the wise men of Babylon; take me in before the king and I will give the explanation<note>Or “interpretation”</note> to the king.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 2:25">25</verse-number>Then Arioch <idiom-start/>quickly<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in haste”</note> brought Daniel in before the king and thus he said to him: “I have found a man among <idiom-start/>the exiles<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the children of exiles”</note> of Judah<note>Aramaic “Jehud”</note> who <idiom-start/>can relate<idiom-end/><note>Literally “he will make known”</note> the explanation<note>Or “interpretation”</note> to the king. <verse-number id="Da 2:26">26</verse-number><idiom-start/>The king then asked<idiom-end/><note>Literally “The king answered”</note> and said to Daniel, whose name <supplied>was</supplied> Belteshazzar, “Are you able to make known to me the dream that I have seen and its explanation?”<note>Or “interpretation”</note> <verse-number id="Da 2:27">27</verse-number>Daniel answered the king and said, “The mystery that the king asks, no wise men, conjurers,<note>Or “enchanters”</note> magicians,<note>Or “soothsayer-priests”</note> <supplied>or</supplied> diviners are able to make known to the king. <verse-number id="Da 2:28">28</verse-number>But there is a God in heaven <supplied>who</supplied> reveals mysteries, and he has made known to King Nebuchadnezzar what <supplied>it is</supplied> that will be at the end of days. This <supplied>is</supplied> your dream and the visions of your head on your bed. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 2:29">29</verse-number>“<supplied>As for you</supplied>, king,<note>Aramaic “the king”</note> your thoughts on your bed <idiom-start/>turned to<idiom-end/><note>Literally “they went up”</note> what <supplied>it was</supplied> that would be <idiom-start/>in the future<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “after this”</note> and the revealer of mysteries has made known to you what that would be. <verse-number id="Da 2:30">30</verse-number>And as for me, <supplied>it is</supplied> not because of wisdom that is in me more than <idiom-start/>any other living person<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all of living beings”</note> <supplied>that</supplied> this mystery is revealed to me, but <idiom-start/>in order that<idiom-end/><note>Literally “concerning the matter of”</note> the explanation<note>Or “interpretation”</note> may be made known to the king and you will <idiom-start/>understand<idiom-end/><note>Literally “know”</note> the thoughts of your <idiom-start/>mind<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “heart”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 2:31">31</verse-number>“You, O king, were looking and, look, there was one great statue. This statue <supplied>was</supplied> huge and its brilliance extraordinary, standing <supplied>there</supplied> before you, and its appearance <supplied>was</supplied> frightening.<note>Or “dreadful”</note> <verse-number id="Da 2:32">32</verse-number>The head of this statue <supplied>was</supplied> of fine gold, its chest and its arms of silver, its belly and its thighs of bronze, <verse-number id="Da 2:33">33</verse-number>its legs of iron, its feet, part of them of iron and part of them of clay. <verse-number id="Da 2:34">34</verse-number>You were looking on <idiom-start/>until<idiom-end/><note>Literally “until that”</note> a stone was chiseled out<note>Or “became loose”</note>—that not by hands—and it struck the statue on its feet of iron and clay, and it broke them in pieces. <verse-number id="Da 2:35">35</verse-number>Then the iron, the clay, the bronze, the silver and the gold <idiom-start/>all at once<idiom-end/><note>Literally “like one”</note> broke into pieces<note>Or “were crushed”</note> and they became like chaff from the summer threshing floor, and the wind carried them away and any trace of them could not be found. But the stone that struck the statue became a great mountain and it filled the whole earth. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 2:36">36</verse-number>“This <supplied>was</supplied> the dream, and <supplied>now</supplied> we will tell its interpretation to the king. <verse-number id="Da 2:37">37</verse-number>You, O king, the king of kings, to whom the God of heaven has given the kingdom, the power and the might and the glory, <verse-number id="Da 2:38">38</verse-number>and <supplied>also</supplied> <idiom-start/>human beings wherever they dwell<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “and into all that dwell sons of humankind”</note> the animals of the field and the birds<note>Aramaic “bird”</note> of heaven<note>Or “the sky”</note>—he has given into your hand and made you ruler over all of them—you are the head of gold. <verse-number id="Da 2:39">39</verse-number>And after you another kingdom inferior to yours will arise, and another third <supplied>kingdom</supplied> of bronze that will rule over the whole earth. <verse-number id="Da 2:40">40</verse-number>And <supplied>a</supplied> fourth kingdom will be strong as iron, <supplied>and</supplied> <idiom-start/>just as<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all of because”</note> iron crushes and smashes <idiom-start/>everything<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the whole thing”</note> and as iron shatters all of these <supplied>other metals</supplied>, <supplied>so</supplied> it will crush and it will shatter <supplied>these nations</supplied>. <verse-number id="Da 2:41">41</verse-number><idiom-start/>And just as<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And that”</note> you saw the feet and the toes, <idiom-start/>partly potter’s clay<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from them clay of the potter”</note> and <idiom-start/>partly iron<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from them iron”</note> it will be a divided kingdom; and <idiom-start/>some hardness<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from the hardness”</note> of the iron will be <supplied>in it</supplied>, <idiom-start/>just as<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all of because that”</note> you have seen the iron mixed with the wet clay. <verse-number id="Da 2:42">42</verse-number>And <supplied>as</supplied> the toes of the feet <supplied>were</supplied> partly iron and partly clay, <supplied>so</supplied> part of the kingdom will be strong <idiom-start/>and partly brittle<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “and from it, it will be brittle”</note> <verse-number id="Da 2:43">43</verse-number>And <supplied>in</supplied> that you saw the iron was mixed with wet clay, <supplied>so</supplied> <idiom-start/>they will mix in marriage<idiom-end/><note>Literally “mixing they will in the seed of man”</note> and they will not cling <idiom-start/>to one another<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “this one with that one”</note> just as iron <supplied>does</supplied> not mix with clay. <verse-number id="Da 2:44">44</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>in the day of those kings<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “in their days of those kings”</note> the God of heaven will set up a kingdom that will <idiom-start/>never<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to forever not”</note> be destroyed, and the kingdom will not be left for another nation,<note>Or “people”</note> and it will bring an end to all these kingdoms, but it will stand <idiom-start/>forever<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to eternity”</note> <verse-number id="Da 2:45">45</verse-number><idiom-start/>Inasmuch as<idiom-end/><note>Literally “All of because that”</note> you saw that a stone from the mountain was chiseled out<note>Or “became loose”</note> <supplied>but</supplied> not by hands, and <supplied>that</supplied> it crushed the iron, the bronze, the clay, the silver and the gold, <supplied>thereby</supplied> the great God made known to the king what will be <idiom-start/>in the future<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “after this”</note> and the dream is certain and its explanation trustworthy.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The King’s Response to Daniel and His God</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 2:46">46</verse-number>Then the king, Nebuchadnezzar, fell on his face and he paid homage to Daniel; and he commanded <supplied>them</supplied> to offer <supplied>a</supplied> grain offering and incense offering to him. <verse-number id="Da 2:47">47</verse-number>The king answered Daniel and said, “<idiom-start/>Truly<idiom-end/><note>Literally “From truth that”</note> your God <supplied>is</supplied> the God of gods and the Lord of kings, and he reveals mysteries, for you are able to reveal this mystery.” <verse-number id="Da 2:48">48</verse-number>Then the king promoted Daniel and gave him many great gifts, and made him ruler over the whole province of Babylon and the chief prefect over all the wise men of Babylon. <verse-number id="Da 2:49">49</verse-number>And Daniel made a request from the king, and he appointed Shadrach, Meshach and Abednego over the affairs of the province of Babylon, while Daniel <supplied>remained</supplied> in the court of the king. </p>
		</chapter>