<chapter id="Da 4">
			<pericope>Nebuchadnezzar Declares What the Most High God Has Done for Him</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 4:1">1</verse-number><note><cite title="BibleLEB2: Da 4:1–37">Daniel 4:1–4:37 </cite>in the English Bible is 3:31–4:34 in the Hebrew Bible</note> Nebuchadnezzar the king to all of the nations, the peoples and languages that live in the whole earth: “May your prosperity increase! <verse-number id="Da 4:2">2</verse-number>It is pleasing to me to recount the signs and wonders that the Most High God worked for me. <verse-number id="Da 4:3">3</verse-number>How great <supplied>are</supplied> his signs and wonders, how strong <supplied>is</supplied> his kingdom, <idiom-start/>an everlasting kingdom<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “a kingdom of eternity”</note> and his sovereignty is from generation to generation. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Dream and the King’s Search for an Interpreter</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 4:4">4</verse-number>“I, Nebuchadnezzar, was content in my house and prospering in my palace. <verse-number id="Da 4:5">5</verse-number>And I saw a dream and a revelation on my bed and it frightened me, and the visions of my head terrified me. <verse-number id="Da 4:6">6</verse-number>And a decree was <idiom-start/>sent out<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “put/placed”</note> <supplied>ordering that</supplied> all <supplied>the</supplied> wise men of Babylon <supplied>were</supplied> to be brought in before me <supplied>so</supplied> that they may make known to me <supplied>the</supplied> explanation of the dream. <verse-number id="Da 4:7">7</verse-number>Then the magicians,<note>Or “soothsayer-priests”</note> the conjurers,<note>Or “enchanters”</note> the <idiom-start/>astrologers<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Chaldeans”</note> and the diviners came in and I told them the dream, but they could not make known to me its explanation.<note>Or “interpretation”</note> <verse-number id="Da 4:8">8</verse-number>Then <idiom-start/>at last<idiom-end/><note>Literally “until another”</note> Daniel came before me <idiom-start/>whose name was<idiom-end/><note>Literally “who name his”</note> Belteshazzar, <idiom-start/>according to<idiom-end/><note>Literally “like”</note> the name of my god, <supplied>and</supplied> <idiom-start/>in whom was the spirit of the holy gods<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “and who <supplied>the</supplied> spirit of gods holy in him”</note> <idiom-start/>and I related the dream to him<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “and the dream before him I told”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 4:9">9</verse-number>“ ‘<supplied>O</supplied> Belteshazzar, chief of the magicians,<note>Or “soothsayer-priests”</note> I myself know that <supplied>the</supplied> spirit<note>Or “a spirit”</note> of <supplied>the</supplied> holy gods <supplied>is</supplied> in you, and <idiom-start/>no mystery is too difficult<idiom-end/><note>Literally “every mystery is not difficult”</note> for you. <supplied>Now</supplied> tell <supplied>me</supplied> <supplied>the</supplied> visions of my dream that I saw, and its explanation.<note>Or “interpretation”</note> <verse-number id="Da 4:10">10</verse-number>Now <supplied>these were</supplied> the visions of my head <supplied>as I was lying</supplied> on my bed: I was <idiom-start/>gazing<idiom-end/><note>Literally “seeing”</note> and, look, a tree <supplied>was</supplied> in the midst of the earth, and its height <supplied>was</supplied> exalted. </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Da 4:11">11</verse-number>The tree grew and it became strong, </li1>
				<li2>and its height reached to heaven,<note>Or “the sky”</note> </li2>
				<li2>and <idiom-start/>it was visible to the end of the whole earth<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “and its appearance <supplied>was</supplied> to <supplied>the</supplied> end of the whole earth”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Da 4:12">12</verse-number>Its foliage <supplied>was</supplied> beautiful, </li1>
				<li2>and its fruit abundant, </li2>
				<li2>and in it <supplied>was</supplied> provision for all. </li2>
				<li1>Under it the animals<note>Aramaic “animal”</note> of the field sought shade, </li1>
				<li2>and in its branches the birds of heaven<note>Or “the sky”</note> nested, </li2>
				<li2>and from it all the living beings were fed. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 4:13">13</verse-number>“ ‘I was looking in the vision of my head <supplied>as I lay</supplied> on my bed, and look, a watcher,<note>Or “angelic being”</note> and <supplied>a</supplied> holy <supplied>one</supplied>, came down from heaven. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 4:14">14</verse-number>He cried <idiom-start/>aloud<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in strength”</note> and so he said: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Cut down the tree and chop off its branches; </li1>
				<li2>shake off its foliage and scatter its fruit. </li2>
				<li1>Let the animals flee from under it, </li1>
				<li2>and the birds from its branches. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Da 4:15">15</verse-number>But the stump of its roots </li1>
				<li2>leave in the earth, </li2>
				<li1><idiom-start/>along with<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and with”</note> a band of iron and bronze; </li1>
				<li2><supplied>leave it</supplied> in the grass of the field. </li2>
				<li1>And in<note>Or “with”</note> the dew of heaven </li1>
				<li2>let it<note>Or “him,” that is, the king</note> be watered, </li2>
				<li1>and with the animals<note>Aramaic “animal”</note> </li1>
				<li2>let his lot <supplied>be</supplied> in <supplied>the</supplied> grass of the earth. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Da 4:16">16</verse-number>Let his mind be changed from <supplied>that of a</supplied> human,<note>Or “the human”</note> </li1>
				<li2>and let <supplied>the</supplied> mind of an animal be given to him, </li2>
				<li2>and let seven times pass over him. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Da 4:17">17</verse-number>The sentence <supplied>is</supplied> by <supplied>the</supplied> decree of <supplied>the</supplied> watchers, </li1>
				<li2>and the decision <supplied>by</supplied> <supplied>the</supplied> command of <supplied>the</supplied> holy <supplied>ones</supplied>, </li2>
				<li1><idiom-start/>in order that<idiom-end/><note>Literally “until matter that”</note> the living will know </li1>
				<li2>that the Most High <supplied>is</supplied> sovereign over <supplied>the</supplied> kingdom of humankind, </li2>
				<li1>and <idiom-start/>to whomever<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to whom that”</note> he wills he gives it, </li1>
				<li2>and he <supplied>even</supplied> sets <supplied>the</supplied> humblest of men over it.” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 4:18">18</verse-number>“ ‘This <supplied>is</supplied> the dream <supplied>that</supplied> I, Nebuchadnezzar the king, saw. Now<note>Or “And”</note> you, Belteshazzar, declare its explanation, <idiom-start/>for<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all of because that”</note> all of <supplied>the</supplied> wise men of my kingdom were not able to make the explanation known to me, but you are able because <supplied>the</supplied> spirit of holy gods <supplied>is</supplied> in you.’ </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Daniel Relates and Interprets the Dream</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 4:19">19</verse-number>“Then Daniel, whose name <supplied>was</supplied> Belteshazzar, was distressed <idiom-start/>for some time<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “for one hour”</note> and his thoughts disturbed him. The king answered and he said, ‘Belteshazzar, let the dream and its explanation not disturb you.’ Belteshazzar answered and said, ‘My lord, <supplied>may</supplied> the dream and its explanation <supplied>be</supplied> for <supplied>those who</supplied> hate you and for your enemies. <verse-number id="Da 4:20">20</verse-number>The tree that you saw, which grew and became strong and its height reached to heaven<note>Or “the sky”</note> and <idiom-start/>it was visible to the end of the whole earth<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “its appearance to the all the earth”</note> <verse-number id="Da 4:21">21</verse-number>and its foliage <supplied>was</supplied> beautiful and its fruit abundant, and <supplied>so there was</supplied> provision for all in it, <supplied>and</supplied> the animals<note>Aramaic “animal”</note> of the field lived under it and in its branches nest <supplied>the</supplied> birds of heaven,<note>Or “the sky”</note> <verse-number id="Da 4:22">22</verse-number>—it is you, O king, who have grown <supplied>great</supplied> and you have grown strong, and <supplied>so</supplied> your greatness has increased and it has reached to heaven<note>Or “the sky”</note> and your sovereignty to the end of the earth. <verse-number id="Da 4:23">23</verse-number>And <supplied>inasmuch</supplied> that the king saw <supplied>the</supplied> watcher, a holy <supplied>one</supplied> coming down from heaven<note>Or “the sky”</note> and he said, “Cut down the tree and destroy it, but the stump of its root in the earth leave with a band of iron and bronze in the grass of the field, and let it be watered with the dew of heaven and <supplied>let</supplied> his lot <supplied>be</supplied> with <supplied>the</supplied> animals of the field <idiom-start/>until seven times have passed over him<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “until that seven times <supplied>they</supplied> pass over him”</note> <verse-number id="Da 4:24">24</verse-number>This <supplied>is</supplied> the explanation, O king, and it <supplied>is</supplied> a decree of the Most High that has come upon my lord the king: <verse-number id="Da 4:25">25</verse-number>you will be driven away <idiom-start/>from human society<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from the humankind”</note> and <idiom-start/>you will dwell<idiom-end/><note>Literally “your dwelling will be”</note> with the animals<note>Aramaic “animal”</note> of the field, and you will be caused to graze grass like the oxen <idiom-start/>yourself<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “with respect to you”</note> and you will be watered with the dew of heaven, and seven <supplied>periods of</supplied> time will pass over you until that you have acknowledged that the Most High <supplied>is</supplied> sovereign over the kingdom of humankind, and <idiom-start/>to whom he wills<idiom-end/><note>Literally “that he wills”</note> he gives it. <verse-number id="Da 4:26">26</verse-number><idiom-start/>And in that<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And for”</note> they said to leave alone the stump of the tree’s root, so your kingdom <supplied>will be</supplied> restored for you <idiom-start/>when<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from that”</note> you acknowledge that heaven <supplied>is</supplied> sovereign. <verse-number id="Da 4:27">27</verse-number>Therefore, O king, let my advice be acceptable <supplied>to you</supplied> and your sin remove<note>Or “replace”</note> with righteousness and your iniquity with having mercy on <supplied>the</supplied> oppressed, <idiom-start/>in case there might be a prolongation of your prosperity<idiom-end/>.’ ”<note>Literally “if will be prolongation for your prosperity”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>God Judges the King for His Hubris</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 4:28">28</verse-number><idiom-start/>All this happened<idiom-end/><note>Literally “It came upon”</note> to Nebuchadnezzar the king. <verse-number id="Da 4:29">29</verse-number>At the end of twelve months he was walking on the <supplied>roof of</supplied> <idiom-start/>the royal palace<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the place of the kingdom”</note> of Babylon. <verse-number id="Da 4:30">30</verse-number>And the king answered and said, “Is this not the great Babylon which I have built as a royal palace by the strength of my own power, and for the glory of my own majesty?” <verse-number id="Da 4:31">31</verse-number><supplied>While</supplied> the words <supplied>were</supplied> still in the mouth of the king, a voice from heaven came, <supplied>saying</supplied>, ‘To you, King Nebuchadnezzar, <supplied>it</supplied> is declared that the kingdom has departed from you, <verse-number id="Da 4:32">32</verse-number>and you will be driven away from <idiom-start/>human society<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the humankind”</note> and your dwelling <supplied>will be</supplied> with the animals<note>Aramaic “animal”</note> of the field and they will cause you to graze <supplied>the</supplied> grass like oxen, and seven times will pass over you, until you acknowledge that the Most High <supplied>is</supplied> sovereign over the kingdom of humankind and that he gives it to whom he wills.’ <verse-number id="Da 4:33">33</verse-number><idiom-start/>Immediately<idiom-end/><note>Literally “In that hour”</note> the word was fulfilled <idiom-start/>concerning<idiom-end/><note>Literally “over”</note> Nebuchadnezzar, and he was expelled from <idiom-start/>human society<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the humankind”</note> and he ate grass like oxen, and his body was bathed with the dew of heaven until his hair <supplied>was</supplied> like <supplied>the hair of</supplied> an eagle and his nails grew like <supplied>a</supplied> bird’s <supplied>claws</supplied>. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The King Praises and Extols the Most High God</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 4:34">34</verse-number>“But at the end of <idiom-start/>that period<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the day”</note> I, Nebuchadnezzar, lifted up my eyes to heaven, and <supplied>then</supplied> my reason returned to me; and I blessed the Most High and <idiom-start/>the one who lives forever<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<supplied>the one</supplied> living forever”</note> I praised and I honored. </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“For his sovereignty <supplied>is</supplied> <supplied>an</supplied> everlasting sovereignty, </li1>
				<li2>and his kingdom <supplied>continues</supplied> from generation to generation. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Da 4:35">35</verse-number>And all the dwellers of the earth </li1>
				<li2>are regarded as nothing, </li2>
				<li1>and he does <idiom-start/>according to<idiom-end/><note>Literally “as”</note> his desire </li1>
				<li2>in the host of heaven and <supplied>among</supplied> the dwellers of earth, </li2>
				<li1>and there is not <supplied>one</supplied> who can hold back his hand, </li1>
				<li2>or <idiom-start/>ask him<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “or asks to him”</note> ‘What are you doing?’ </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 4:36">36</verse-number>“<idiom-start/>At that time<idiom-end/><note>Literally “In it the time”</note> my reason returned to me, and <supplied>also</supplied> the glory of my kingdom and my majesty and splendor returned to me, and my advisers and my lords<note>Or “nobles”</note> searched <supplied>me</supplied> out, and I was established over my kingdom and abundant greatness was added to me. <verse-number id="Da 4:37">37</verse-number>Now I, Nebuchadnezzar, praise and exalt and honor the king of heaven, for all his works <supplied>are</supplied> truth,<note>Or “true”</note> and his ways <supplied>are</supplied> justice and that he is able to humble those who walk in pride.” </p>
		</chapter>