<chapter id="Da 5">
			<pericope>The Mysterious Writing on the Wall</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 5:1">1</verse-number>Belshazzar the king made a great festival for <supplied>a</supplied> thousand <supplied>of</supplied> his lords,<note>Or “nobles”</note> and <idiom-start/>in the presence of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to over against”</note> the thousand <supplied>lords</supplied> he was drinking wine.<note>Or “the wine”</note> <verse-number id="Da 5:2">2</verse-number><idiom-start/>When he tasted the wine<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “At the taste of the wine”</note> Belshazzar commanded <supplied>that they</supplied> bring <supplied>the</supplied> vessels of gold and silver that Nebuchadnezzar his <idiom-start/>predecessor<idiom-end/><note>Literally “father”</note> had taken from the temple that <supplied>was</supplied> in Jerusalem, so that the king and his lords,<note>Or “nobles”</note> his wives and his concubines may drink from them. <verse-number id="Da 5:3">3</verse-number>Then they brought in the vessels of gold that they took from the temple, the house of God that <supplied>was</supplied> in Jerusalem, and the king and his lords,<note>Or “nobles”</note> his wives and his concubines drank from them. <verse-number id="Da 5:4">4</verse-number>They drank the wine and praised the gods of gold and silver, bronze, iron, wood and stone.<note>All these metals have the definite article that does not have to be translated into English to retain the meaning</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 5:5">5</verse-number><idiom-start/>Immediately<idiom-end/><note>Literally “In its the hour”</note> <idiom-start/>human fingers<idiom-end/><note>Literally “fingers of <supplied>the</supplied> hand of a man”</note> appeared and they wrote <idiom-start/>opposite<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to over against”</note> the lampstand on the plaster of the wall of the palace of the king, and the king was watching<note>Or “gazing at”</note> the palm of the hand that was writing. <verse-number id="Da 5:6">6</verse-number>Then his face changed and his thoughts terrified him, and <idiom-start/>his hip joints gave way<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the limbs of his hip became loose”</note> and <idiom-start/>his knees knocked together<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “his knees this to this they knocked together”</note> <verse-number id="Da 5:7">7</verse-number>The king cried <idiom-start/>aloud<idiom-end/><note>Literally “with strength”</note> to bring <supplied>in</supplied> the conjurers,<note>Or “enchanters”</note> the <idiom-start/>astrologers<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Chaldeans”</note> and the diviners; the king <idiom-start/>spoke<idiom-end/><note>Literally “answered”</note> and said to <supplied>the</supplied> wise men of Babylon, “Any man that can read this writing and can tell me its explanation will be clothed <supplied>in</supplied> purple and <supplied>will have</supplied> <supplied>a</supplied> necklace of gold <supplied>hung</supplied> around his neck and he will rule <supplied>as</supplied> third <supplied>in authority</supplied> in the kingdom.” <verse-number id="Da 5:8">8</verse-number>Then all the wise men of the king came in, but they were not able to read the writing or to make known its explanation.<note>Aramaic “the explanation/ interpretation”</note> <verse-number id="Da 5:9">9</verse-number>Then the king, Belshazzar, became greatly terrified, and <idiom-start/>his facial features<idiom-end/><note>Literally “shining of his face”</note> changed upon him, and his lords<note>Or “nobles”</note> were perplexed. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 5:10">10</verse-number>Because of the words of the king and his lords,<note>Or “nobles”</note> the queen came into <idiom-start/>the banqueting hall<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the house of the drinking”</note> and the queen <idiom-start/>spoke up<idiom-end/><note>Literally “answered”</note> and said, “O king, live <idiom-start/>forever<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to eternity”</note> and let not your thoughts terrify you and <supplied>do</supplied> not let your facial expressions <idiom-start/>grow pale<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “change”</note> <verse-number id="Da 5:11">11</verse-number>There is a man in your kingdom <idiom-start/>who has the spirit of the holy gods in him<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “who <supplied>the</supplied> spirit of holy gods <supplied>is</supplied> in him”</note> And in the days of your <idiom-start/>predecessor<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “father”</note> enlightenment and insight and wisdom like the wisdom of the gods was found in him; and, O king, Nebuchadnezzar your <idiom-start/>predecessor<idiom-end/><note>Literally “father”</note> appointed him <supplied>as</supplied> chief of the magicians,<note>Or “soothsayer-priests”</note> the conjurers,<note>Or “enchanters”</note> the <idiom-start/>astrologers<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “Chaldeans”</note> <supplied>and</supplied> the diviners. Your <idiom-start/>predecessor<idiom-end/><note>Literally “father”</note> the king <supplied>did this</supplied> <verse-number id="Da 5:12">12</verse-number><idiom-start/>because<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all of because that”</note> <supplied>there</supplied> was found in him <supplied>an</supplied> excellent spirit and understanding and insight <supplied>for</supplied> interpreting dreams and explaining riddles and solving riddles; <supplied>that is</supplied>, in Daniel <idiom-start/>whom the king named<idiom-end/><note>Literally “whom the king gave his name”</note> Belteshazzar. Now, let Daniel be called and he will tell the explanation.”<note>Or “interpretation”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Daniel Deciphers and Interprets the Writing</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 5:13">13</verse-number>Then Daniel was brought in before the king, <supplied>and</supplied> the king <idiom-start/>spoke<idiom-end/><note>Literally “answered”</note> and said to Daniel, “You <supplied>are</supplied> Daniel <idiom-start/>who are one of the exiles<idiom-end/><note>Literally “who from sons of the exile”</note> of Judah<note>Aramaic “Jehud”</note> whom my <idiom-start/>predecessor<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “father”</note> the king, brought from Judah.<note>Aramaic “Jehud”</note> <verse-number id="Da 5:14">14</verse-number>And I have heard that a spirit of the gods <supplied>is</supplied> in you and enlightenment and insight and excellent wisdom was found in you. <verse-number id="Da 5:15">15</verse-number>And now the wise men <supplied>and</supplied> the conjurers<note>Or “enchanters”</note> were brought in before me <supplied>so</supplied> that they could read this writing <supplied>in order to</supplied> make its explanation<note>Or “interpretation”</note> known to me, but they were not able to disclose the explanation<note>Or “interpretation”</note> of the matter. <verse-number id="Da 5:16">16</verse-number>But I have heard concerning you that you are able <idiom-start/>to produce interpretations<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to interpret interpretations”</note> and to solve riddles; now if you are able to read the writing and to make known its explanation<note>Or “interpretation”</note> to me, you will be clothed <supplied>in</supplied> purple and <supplied>a</supplied> necklace of gold <supplied>will be placed</supplied> around your neck and you will rule <supplied>as</supplied> third <supplied>in command</supplied> in the kingdom.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 5:17">17</verse-number>Then Daniel answered and said before the king, “Let your gifts be for yourself or your rewards give to another; nevertheless, I will read the writing to the king and I will make known to him the explanation.<note>Or “interpretation”</note> <verse-number id="Da 5:18">18</verse-number><idiom-start/>O king<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “You, O king”</note> the Most High God gave the kingdom and the greatness and the glory and the majesty to Nebuchadnezzar your <idiom-start/>predecessor<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “father”</note> <verse-number id="Da 5:19">19</verse-number>And because of the greatness that he gave to him, all the peoples, the nations and languages trembled and feared before him; whomever he wanted he killed, and whomever he wanted he let live, and whomever he wanted he honored, and whomever he wanted he humbled. <verse-number id="Da 5:20">20</verse-number>But <idiom-start/>when<idiom-end/><note>Literally “as that”</note> his heart became arrogant and his spirit became hard <supplied>so as</supplied> to act proudly, he was deposed from the throne of his kingdom and the<note>Or “his”</note> glory <idiom-start/>was taken away from him<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “they took away”</note> <verse-number id="Da 5:21">21</verse-number>And he was driven away <idiom-start/>from human society<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from the sons of the humankind”</note> and his mind was made like the animals<note>Aramaic “with the animals”</note> and his dwelling <supplied>was</supplied> with the wild asses; <supplied>and</supplied> <idiom-start/>he was given<idiom-end/><note>Literally “they gave him”</note> grass like oxen to eat, and with<note>Aramaic “from”</note> the dew of heaven his body was bathed, until he acknowledged that the Most High God <supplied>is</supplied> sovereign over the kingdom of humankind, and <idiom-start/>whoever<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to from that”</note> he wants he sets over it. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 5:22">22</verse-number>“But you his <idiom-start/>successor<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “son”</note> Belshazzar, have not humbled your heart <idiom-start/>even though<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all of because that”</note> you knew all this. <verse-number id="Da 5:23">23</verse-number>And <supplied>now</supplied> you have exalted yourself against the Lord of heaven, and the vessels of his temple you have brought in before you, and you and your lords,<note>Or “nobles”</note> your wives and your concubines, have been drinking wine from<note>Aramaic “with”</note> them, and you have praised the gods of silver, gold, bronze, iron, wood, and stone<note>All the materials in this list have the definite article that does not have to be translated into English</note> that <supplied>do</supplied> not see and <supplied>do</supplied> not hear and <supplied>do</supplied> not know, but the God <idiom-start/>who holds your life in his hand<idiom-end/><note>Literally “who your breath <supplied>is</supplied> in his hand”</note> and all of your ways <idiom-start/>come from him<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “<supplied>belong</supplied> to him”</note> you have not honored. <verse-number id="Da 5:24">24</verse-number>So then the palm of the hand was sent out from his presence and this writing was inscribed. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 5:25">25</verse-number>“Now this was the writing that was inscribed: ‘Mene, Mene, Tekel and Parsin.’ </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 5:26">26</verse-number>“This <supplied>is</supplied> the explanation of the matter:<note>Or “word, message”</note> ‘Mene’—God has numbered your kingdom and brought an end <supplied>to</supplied> it. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 5:27">27</verse-number>“ ‘Tekel’—you have been weighed on scales and you have been found wanting.<note>Or “deficient”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 5:28">28</verse-number>“ ‘Peres’—your kingdom has been divided and given to <supplied>the</supplied> Medes and Persians.’ ” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 5:29">29</verse-number>Then Belshazzar commanded, and they clothed Daniel <supplied>with</supplied> purple and <supplied>placed</supplied> a necklace of gold around his neck, and they made a proclamation concerning him that he would be <supplied>the</supplied> third ruler <supplied>in authority</supplied> in the kingdom. <verse-number id="Da 5:30">30</verse-number><idiom-start/>That same night<idiom-end/><note>Literally “In it, in the night”</note> Belshazzar, the Chaldean king, was killed. <verse-number id="Da 5:31">31</verse-number><note><cite title="BibleLEB2: Da 5:31–6:28">Daniel 5:31–6:28 </cite>in the English Bible is 6:1–29 in the Hebrew Bible</note> And Darius the Mede received the kingdom <idiom-start/>when he was about sixty-two years old<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “when a son of sixty and two years”</note> </p>
		</chapter>