<chapter id="Da 6">
			<pericope>Daniel’s Integrity and His Entrapment by His Enemies</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 6:1">1</verse-number><idiom-start/>It pleased Darius<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “It was pleasant before Darius”</note> and he set up one hundred and twenty satraps over the kingdom, that they were <idiom-start/>throughout the whole kingdom<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “in all the kingdom”</note> <verse-number id="Da 6:2">2</verse-number>and over them <supplied>were</supplied> three administrators, <supplied>of</supplied> whom Daniel <supplied>was</supplied> one, <supplied>so</supplied> that these satraps were giving account to them, and the king would not be suffering loss. <verse-number id="Da 6:3">3</verse-number>Then Daniel <idiom-start/>began distinguishing himself<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was distinguishing himself”</note> above the administrators and the satraps <idiom-start/>because<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all of because that”</note> an exceptional spirit <supplied>was</supplied> in him, and <supplied>so</supplied> the king planned to appoint him over the whole kingdom. <verse-number id="Da 6:4">4</verse-number>Then the <supplied>other</supplied> administrators and satraps <idiom-start/>began to seek<idiom-end/><note>Literally “were seeking”</note> to find <supplied>a</supplied> pretext against Daniel <idiom-start/>in connection with the kingdom<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from the side of the kingdom”</note> but they were not able to find any pretext and <idiom-start/>corruption<idiom-end/><note>Literally “being corrupt”</note> <idiom-start/>because<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all because that”</note> he was trustworthy, and no<note>Aramaic “any”</note> negligence or <idiom-start/>corruption<idiom-end/><note>Literally “being corrupt”</note> <idiom-start/>could be found in him<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “not could be found”</note> <verse-number id="Da 6:5">5</verse-number>Then these men <idiom-start/>said<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “<supplied>were</supplied> saying”</note> “We will not find any pretext<note>Or “basis for accusation”</note> against this Daniel unless we find it in connection with the law of his God.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 6:6">6</verse-number>So the administrators and the satraps conspired <idiom-start/>with respect to<idiom-end/><note>Literally “on/upon”</note> the king and so they said to him, “Darius, O king, live <idiom-start/>forever<idiom-end/>!<note>Literally “to eternity”</note> <verse-number id="Da 6:7">7</verse-number>All of <supplied>the</supplied> administrators of the kingdom, and the prefects, the satraps, the counselors and the governors took counsel <supplied>and have</supplied> agreed to establish an edict of the king and to enforce a decree that <idiom-start/>whoever<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all that”</note> will seek a prayer from any god or human except from you <supplied>for</supplied> up to thirty days will be thrown into <idiom-start/>the lion pit<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “pit of lions”</note> <verse-number id="Da 6:8">8</verse-number>Now, O king, establish the edict and you must sign the document <supplied>so</supplied> that <supplied>it</supplied> cannot be changed, according to <supplied>the</supplied> law of <supplied>the</supplied> Medes and Persians which cannot be revoked.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 6:9">9</verse-number><idiom-start/>So<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Like to before this”</note> the king, Darius, signed the writing and the interdict.<note>Or “the writing that is the interdict”</note> <verse-number id="Da 6:10">10</verse-number>Now <idiom-start/>when<idiom-end/><note>Literally “as that”</note> Daniel realized that the document was signed, he went to his house (<idiom-start/>now he had windows in his upper room that were open<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and windows were open to him in his upper room”</note> toward Jerusalem), and three times <idiom-start/>daily<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the day”</note> he knelt on his knees and prayed and <supplied>gave</supplied> praise before his God, <idiom-start/>just as<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all because that”</note> he had been doing <idiom-start/>previously<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “from before this”</note> <verse-number id="Da 6:11">11</verse-number>Then these men came as a group and they found Daniel praying and pleading for mercy before his God. <verse-number id="Da 6:12">12</verse-number>Then they approached <idiom-start/>and spoke with the king<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and saying before the king”</note> concerning the edict of the king, “<idiom-start/>Did you not sign an edict<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Not an edict you signed?”</note> that any person who would seek <supplied>anything</supplied> from any God or human within thirty days except from you, O king, would be thrown into <idiom-start/>the lion pit<idiom-end/>?”<note>Literally “pit of lions”</note> The king answered and said, “The matter <supplied>as you have just stated</supplied> is certain according to <supplied>the</supplied> law of <supplied>the</supplied> Medes and Persians which cannot be revoked.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>God’s Miraculous Deliverance of Daniel Again</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 6:13">13</verse-number>Then <idiom-start/>they responded<idiom-end/><note>Literally “they answered”</note> and said before the king, “Daniel, who <supplied>is</supplied> from <idiom-start/>the exiles<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the sons of the exile”</note> of Judah,<note>Aramaic “Jehud”</note> <idiom-start/>is not paying any attention<idiom-end/><note>Literally “not he sets <supplied>his mind</supplied>”</note> to you, O king, or to the decree that you have signed, <idiom-start/>and three times daily<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and three times on the day”</note> he says his prayer.” <verse-number id="Da 6:14">14</verse-number>Then the king, when<note>Aramaic “as ”</note> he heard that <idiom-start/>report<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “word”</note> he was extremely distressed over it; and <idiom-start/>concerning Daniel<idiom-end/><note>Literally “upon Daniel”</note> <idiom-start/>he was determined<idiom-end/><note>Literally “he set <supplied>his</supplied> heart”</note> to rescue him. And until the setting of the sun he was making every effort to deliver him. <verse-number id="Da 6:15">15</verse-number>Then these men came as <supplied>a</supplied> group to the king and <idiom-start/>said<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “saying”</note> “Recall, O king, that <supplied>with respect to</supplied> <supplied>the</supplied> law of<note>Aramaic “to”</note> <supplied>the</supplied> Medes and Persians that <idiom-start/>any<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all/every”</note> decree or edict that the king establishes cannot be changed.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 6:16">16</verse-number>Then the king gave the command, and Daniel was brought in and they threw <supplied>him</supplied> into <idiom-start/>the lion pit<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “pit of lions”</note> <idiom-start/>The king said<idiom-end/><note>Literally “The king answered and saying”</note> to Daniel, “Your God, whom you serve <idiom-start/>faithfully<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “in the loyalty”</note> may he rescue you!” <verse-number id="Da 6:17">17</verse-number>And a<note>Aramaic “one”</note> stone was brought and it was put on the entrance of the pit, and the king sealed it with his signet <supplied>ring</supplied> and with the signet <supplied>rings</supplied> of his lords,<note>Or “nobles”</note> so that nothing would be changed concerning Daniel. <verse-number id="Da 6:18">18</verse-number>Then the king went to his palace and spent the night in fasting, and no food was brought in before him and his sleep fled from him. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 6:19">19</verse-number>Then the king got up at daybreak, at first light, and he went <idiom-start/>in haste<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to hasten”</note> to <idiom-start/>the lion pit<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “pit of lions”</note> <verse-number id="Da 6:20">20</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>when he came near<idiom-end/><note>Literally “as coming near him”</note> to the pit, he cried out to Daniel with <supplied>a</supplied> distressed voice, <supplied>and</supplied> the king <idiom-start/>spoke<idiom-end/><note>Literally “answered”</note> and said to Daniel, “O Daniel, servant of the living God, your God whom you serve faithfully, was he able to rescue you from the lions?” <verse-number id="Da 6:21">21</verse-number>Then Daniel spoke to<note>Aramaic “with”</note> the king, “O king, live <idiom-start/>forever<idiom-end/>!<note>Literally “unto endless ages”</note> <verse-number id="Da 6:22">22</verse-number>My God sent his angel and he shut the mouth of the lions and they did not<note>Aramaic “would not”</note> hurt me, <idiom-start/>because<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all of because that”</note> before him <idiom-start/>I was found<idiom-end/><note>Literally “it was found for me”</note> blameless, and also before you, O king, I have not done <supplied>any</supplied> wrong.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 6:23">23</verse-number>Then the king was exceedingly glad over it<note>That is, the situation</note> and commanded <supplied>that</supplied> Daniel be lifted up from the pit; and <supplied>there</supplied> was not any wound found on him, because he had trusted in his God. <verse-number id="Da 6:24">24</verse-number>The king then commanded, and these men were brought <idiom-start/>who had accused Daniel<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “they ate his pieces of Daniel”</note> and they threw them and their children and their wives into <idiom-start/>the lion pit<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “pit of lions”</note> and they had not reached the floor of the pit <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “until that”</note> the lions had overpowered them and they had crushed all of their bones. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The King Praises the God of Daniel and Daniel Prospers</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 6:25">25</verse-number>Then Darius the king wrote to all the people, the nations, and the languages living in the whole earth, “May your prosperity become great! <verse-number id="Da 6:26">26</verse-number><idiom-start/>I make a decree<idiom-end/><note>Literally “From before me is put forth a decree”</note> that in all the dominion of my kingdom <supplied>people</supplied> will be trembling and fearing before the God of Daniel, for he <supplied>is</supplied> the living God and endures <idiom-start/>forever<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to eternity/endless ages”</note> and his<note>Literally “and whose”</note> kingdom <supplied>is</supplied> one that will not be destroyed and his <idiom-start/>dominion has no end<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “dominion his to the end”</note> <verse-number id="Da 6:27">27</verse-number><supplied>He is</supplied> rescuing, delivering, and working signs and wonders in the heavens and on earth, for he <supplied>has</supplied> rescued Daniel from the <idiom-start/>power<idiom-end/><note>Literally “hand”</note> of the lions.” <verse-number id="Da 6:28">28</verse-number>So this Daniel prospered during the kingdom of Darius and during the kingdom of Cyrus the Persian. </p>
		</chapter>