<chapter id="Da 7">
			<pericope>Daniel’s Vision of Four Beasts and the Son of Man</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 7:1">1</verse-number>In the first year of Belshazzar the king of Babylon, Daniel saw a dream and visions<note>Or “the visions”</note> of his head <supplied>as he lay</supplied> on his bed; then he wrote down the dream <supplied>and</supplied> <supplied>the</supplied> <idiom-start/>summary<idiom-end/><note>Literally “head”</note> of <supplied>the</supplied> words <idiom-start/>as follows<idiom-end/>:<note>Literally “saying”</note> <verse-number id="Da 7:2">2</verse-number>Daniel <idiom-start/>explained<idiom-end/><note>Literally “answered”</note> and said, “I was looking in my vision in the night, and look, the four winds of heaven were stirring <supplied>up</supplied> the great sea. <verse-number id="Da 7:3">3</verse-number>And four great beasts <supplied>were</supplied> coming up from the sea, differing <idiom-start/>from one another<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “this from this”</note> <verse-number id="Da 7:4">4</verse-number>The first <supplied>was</supplied> like <supplied>a</supplied> lion and <idiom-start/>had<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for him/it”</note> <supplied>the</supplied> wings of an eagle. I was watching until its wings were plucked off, and it was lifted up from the earth and it was raised on <supplied>its</supplied> feet like a human, and a human heart was given to it. <verse-number id="Da 7:5">5</verse-number>And look, another beast, a second one, looking like a bear. And it was raised up on one side and three tusks<note>Or “ribs”</note> <supplied>were</supplied> in its mouth between its teeth, and so <idiom-start/>it was told<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “they were saying”</note> “Arise, eat much flesh!” <verse-number id="Da 7:6">6</verse-number>After this I was watching and look, another <supplied>beast</supplied> like a leopard; <idiom-start/>it had four wings<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and <supplied>there were</supplied> to it four wings”</note> of a bird on its back, and <idiom-start/>the beast had<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the beast”</note> four heads, and dominion was given to it. <verse-number id="Da 7:7">7</verse-number>After this in the visions of the night I was looking and there was a fourth beast, terrifying and frightful and exceedingly strong, and <idiom-start/>it had<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<supplied>were</supplied> to it”</note> <idiom-start/>great iron teeth<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “teeth of iron for it great”</note> <supplied>and it was</supplied> devouring and crushing, and it stamped the remainder<note>Or “residue”</note> with its feet; and it was different from all <supplied>the other</supplied> beasts <idiom-start/>that preceded it<idiom-end/><note>Literally “that preceding her/it”</note> <idiom-start/>and it had ten horns<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “and ten horns for her/it”</note> <verse-number id="Da 7:8">8</verse-number>I was considering the horns, and look, another little horn came up <idiom-start/>among<idiom-end/><note>Literally “between”</note> them, and three of the earlier horns <idiom-start/>were rooted out<idiom-end/><note>Literally “dehorned”</note> from before it, and there were eyes like the eyes of <supplied>a</supplied> human<note>Or “humankind”</note> in this horn and <supplied>also</supplied> a mouth <supplied>that was</supplied> speaking boastfully. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 7:9">9</verse-number>“<idiom-start/>I continued watching<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I was watching”</note> until thrones were placed and an Ancient of Days sat; his clothing <supplied>was</supplied> like white snow and the hair of his head <supplied>was</supplied> like pure wool and his throne <supplied>was</supplied> a flame<note>Or “ablaze with”</note> of fire and its wheels<note>Aramaic “wheel”</note> <supplied>were</supplied> burning fire. <verse-number id="Da 7:10">10</verse-number>A stream of fire issued forth and flowed <idiom-start/>from his presence<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “from before him”</note> thousands <supplied>upon</supplied> thousands served him and ten thousand <supplied>upon</supplied> ten thousand stood before him. The judge sat, and <supplied>the</supplied> books were opened. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 7:11">11</verse-number>“<idiom-start/>I continued watching<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I was watching”</note> then<note>Aramaic “in then”</note> because of the noise of the boastful words of the horn <supplied>who was</supplied> speaking; <idiom-start/>I continued watching<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I was watching”</note> until the beast was slain and its body was destroyed, and it was given <supplied>over</supplied> to burning with fire. <verse-number id="Da 7:12">12</verse-number>And <supplied>as for</supplied> the remainder of the beasts, <idiom-start/>their dominion was taken away<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “they took away their dominion”</note> but a prolongation <idiom-start/>of their life<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in life”</note> was given to them for a season and a time. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 7:13">13</verse-number>“<idiom-start/>I continued watching<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I was watching”</note> in the visions of the night, and look, with the clouds of heaven <supplied>one</supplied> like a son of man<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> was coming, and he came to the Ancient of Days, and <idiom-start/>was presented<idiom-end/><note>Literally “they presented him”</note> before him. <verse-number id="Da 7:14">14</verse-number>And to him was given dominion and glory and kingship that<note>Aramaic “and”</note> all the peoples, the nations, and languages <supplied>would</supplied> serve him; his dominion <supplied>is</supplied> a dominion <idiom-start/>without end<idiom-end/><note>Literally “of eternity”</note> that will not cease, and his kingdom <supplied>is one</supplied> that will not be destroyed. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Daniel Explains and Interprets the Vision</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 7:15">15</verse-number>“<idiom-start/>As for me, Daniel<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “I Daniel”</note> my spirit was troubled <idiom-start/>within me<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “in the midst of sheath”</note> and the visions of my head terrified me. <verse-number id="Da 7:16">16</verse-number><supplied>So</supplied> I approached one of the attendants and I asked him<note>Aramaic “from him”</note> <supplied>about</supplied> the truth concerning all this; and he told me<note>Aramaic “to me”</note> <supplied>that</supplied> he would make known to me the explanation of the matter. <verse-number id="Da 7:17">17</verse-number>‘These great beasts which are four <supplied>in number</supplied> <supplied>are</supplied> four kings <supplied>who</supplied> will arise from the earth. <verse-number id="Da 7:18">18</verse-number>But the holy ones<note>Or “saints”</note> of the Most High will receive the kingdom, and they will take possession of the kingdom forever, <idiom-start/>forever and ever<idiom-end/>.’<note>Literally “forever and to forever”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 7:19">19</verse-number>“Then I desired to make certain concerning the fourth beast that was different from <idiom-start/>all the others<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all <supplied>of</supplied> them”</note>—exceedingly terrifying, with its iron teeth and its claws of bronze; it devoured and crushed <supplied>and</supplied> stamped the remainder with its feet—<verse-number id="Da 7:20">20</verse-number>and concerning the horns that <supplied>were</supplied> on its head, and <supplied>concerning</supplied> <supplied>the</supplied> other <supplied>horn</supplied> that came up and <idiom-start/>before which three horns fell<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “and fell from before it three”</note> and this horn <idiom-start/>had eyes<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and eyes to it”</note> and <supplied>a</supplied> mouth speaking <idiom-start/>boastfully<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “abundantly”</note> and its appearance <supplied>was</supplied> larger than its companions. <verse-number id="Da 7:21">21</verse-number><idiom-start/>I continued watching<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “I was watching”</note> and this horn made war with <supplied>the</supplied> holy ones<note>Or “saints”</note> and it prevailed over them, <verse-number id="Da 7:22">22</verse-number>until the Ancient of Days came and gave judgment to <supplied>the</supplied> holy ones<note>Or “saints”</note> of <supplied>the</supplied> Most High; and the time arrived and <supplied>the</supplied> holy ones<note>Or “saints”</note> took possession of the kingdom. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 7:23">23</verse-number>“And he said, ‘The fourth beast <supplied>is</supplied> the fourth kingdom <supplied>that</supplied> will be on the earth that will be different from all the <supplied>other</supplied> kingdoms, and it will devour the whole earth and it will trample it and it will crush it. <verse-number id="Da 7:24">24</verse-number>And <supplied>as for</supplied> the ten horns <supplied>coming</supplied> from it, <supplied>from</supplied> this kingdom<note>Or “the kingdom”</note> ten kings will arise, and another will arise after them. And he will be different from the earlier <supplied>ones</supplied>, and he will subdue three kings. <verse-number id="Da 7:25">25</verse-number>And he will speak words against the Most High, and he will wear out <supplied>the</supplied> holy ones<note>Or “saints”</note> of the Most High, and he will attempt to change times and law, and they will be given into his hand for a time and two times and half a time. <verse-number id="Da 7:26">26</verse-number>Then the court will sit, and his dominion will be removed,<note>Or “taken away”</note> to be eradicated and to be destroyed <idiom-start/>totally<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “until the end”</note> <verse-number id="Da 7:27">27</verse-number>And the kingdom and the dominion and the greatness of the kingdoms under the whole heaven will be given to <supplied>the</supplied> nation of <supplied>the</supplied> holy ones<note>Or “saints”</note> of the Most High; his kingdom <idiom-start/>is an everlasting kingdom<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “<supplied>is</supplied> a kingdom of eternity”</note> and all the dominions will serve and obey him.’ </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 7:28">28</verse-number><idiom-start/>This is the end of the account<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “Up to here <supplied>is</supplied> the end of the account”</note> <idiom-start/>As for me, Daniel<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I Daniel”</note>—my thoughts terrified me greatly and my face changed over me, but I kept the matter in my heart.”<note>Or “to myself”</note> </p>
		</chapter>