<chapter id="Da 8">
			<pericope>The Vision of a Small Horn that Oppresses Israel and Threatens the Temple</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 8:1">1</verse-number>In the third year <supplied>of</supplied> the kingdom of Belshazzar the king, a vision appeared <idiom-start/>to me, Daniel<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “I Daniel”</note> after the one that appeared to me <idiom-start/>previously<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “in the beginning”</note> <verse-number id="Da 8:2">2</verse-number>And I saw in the vision, <idiom-start/>and when I saw<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “and it was at my seeing”</note> I <supplied>was</supplied> in Susa, the citadel that <supplied>was</supplied> in the province of Elam. And I saw in the vision, and <idiom-start/>I myself<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I, I was”</note> was at the stream of Ulai.<note>Or “Ulai Canal” (NASB); “stream of the Ulai” (NEB)</note> <verse-number id="Da 8:3">3</verse-number>And I lifted up my eyes and I saw, and look! A ram<note>Hebrew “One ram”</note> standing <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of”</note> the stream, and <idiom-start/>it had<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for it”</note> two horns, and the horns <supplied>were</supplied> long, but the one <supplied>was</supplied> longer than the second, and the longer <supplied>one</supplied> came up <idiom-start/>after the other one<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “in the behind of the other”</note> <verse-number id="Da 8:4">4</verse-number>I saw the ram charging westward and northward and southward, and <idiom-start/>none of the beasts stood before it<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “all <supplied>the</supplied> beasts not they withstood to the face of him”</note> and there was no rescuing from <idiom-start/>its power<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “its hand”</note> and it did <idiom-start/>what it wanted<idiom-end/><note>Literally “according to its will”</note> and it became strong.<note>Or “it/he magnified itself/himself”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 8:5">5</verse-number>And I was considering <supplied>this</supplied>, and look, a he-goat coming from the west across the face of the whole earth, and <supplied>it</supplied> was not touching the ground;<note>Or “earth,” or “land”</note> and the he-goat <supplied>had</supplied> <idiom-start/>a conspicuous horn<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a horn of vision”</note> between its eyes. <verse-number id="Da 8:6">6</verse-number>Then it came toward the ram <idiom-start/>that had the two horns<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the owner of the two horns”</note> that I saw standing <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of”</note> the stream, and it ran at it with<note>Or “in”</note> the rage of its power. <verse-number id="Da 8:7">7</verse-number>And I saw it approaching the ram and it was furious at it, and it struck the ram, and it broke its two horns, and <idiom-start/>there was not strength in the ram to stand before him<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “and not was strength in the ram to withstand to the face of him”</note> and he threw it down to the ground and trampled it, <idiom-start/>and there was no one who could rescue the ram<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and not he/it was one rescuing”</note> from its power. <verse-number id="Da 8:8">8</verse-number>And the he-goat grew <idiom-start/>exceedingly great<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “until much”</note> and <idiom-start/>at the height of its power<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and at his being powerful”</note> the great horn was broken, and four conspicuous horns<note>LXX reads “others” here for “conspicuous.” The words in Hebrew can be confused for each other</note> came up in place of it toward the four winds of heaven. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 8:9">9</verse-number><idiom-start/>And from one of them<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And from the one from them”</note> came forth <supplied>a</supplied> horn, <idiom-start/>a little one<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “one from little”</note> and it grew exceedingly<note>Or “pre-eminently”</note> toward the south, and toward the east, and toward the beautiful land. <verse-number id="Da 8:10">10</verse-number>And it grew up to the host of heaven, and it threw down to the ground some of the host and some of the stars and trampled them. <verse-number id="Da 8:11">11</verse-number>Even against the prince of the hosts it acted arrogantly and took away from him the regular burnt offering, and the place of his sanctuary was overthrown. <verse-number id="Da 8:12">12</verse-number>And on account of transgression, <supplied>the</supplied> host was given over <supplied>to the horn</supplied> in addition to the regular burnt offering. And it cast down truth to the ground, and it <idiom-start/>acted<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “did”</note> and it had success. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 8:13">13</verse-number>And I heard a certain holy one speaking, and a certain other holy one said to the specific one <idiom-start/>who was speaking<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the <supplied>one</supplied> speaking”</note> “<idiom-start/>For how long<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Until when”</note> <supplied>is</supplied> the vision <supplied>concerning</supplied> the regular burnt offering, and the transgression <supplied>that</supplied> makes desolate, and <supplied>the</supplied> giving over <supplied>of the</supplied> sanctuary and <supplied>the</supplied> host to trampling?” <verse-number id="Da 8:14">14</verse-number>And he said to me, “For two thousand three hundred evenings and mornings, then <supplied>the</supplied> sanctuary will be restored.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Gabriel Gives Angelic Help and Interprets the Vision</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 8:15">15</verse-number><idiom-start/>And then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And it happened”</note> when I, Daniel, saw the vision, and I was seeking understanding, there was <supplied>one</supplied> standing before me with <supplied>the</supplied> appearance of a man. <verse-number id="Da 8:16">16</verse-number>And I heard <supplied>the</supplied> voice of a human at <supplied>the</supplied> Ulai, and he called and said, “Gabriel, <supplied>make</supplied> this <supplied>man</supplied> understand the vision.” <verse-number id="Da 8:17">17</verse-number>And he came beside <idiom-start/>where I was standing<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “my standing”</note> and <idiom-start/>when he came<idiom-end/><note>Literally “at his coming”</note> I became terrified and I fell prostrate on my face. And he said to me, “Understand, son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> that the vision <supplied>is</supplied> for <supplied>the</supplied> time of <supplied>the</supplied> end.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 8:18">18</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>when he spoke<idiom-end/><note>Literally “at his speaking”</note> with me I fell into a trance with my face to the ground, and he touched me and made me stand on by feet. <verse-number id="Da 8:19">19</verse-number>And he said, “Look, I am making known to you what will happen in the period of wrath,<note>Or “the wrath”</note> for <supplied>it refers</supplied> to <supplied>the</supplied> appointed time of <supplied>the</supplied> end. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 8:20">20</verse-number>“The ram that you saw <idiom-start/>who had two horns<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the owner of the two horns”</note> <supplied>represents</supplied> the kings of Media and Persia. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 8:21">21</verse-number>“And the hairy he-goat <supplied>is</supplied> the <idiom-start/>kingdom<idiom-end/><note>Literally “king”</note> of Greece, and the great horn that <supplied>is</supplied> between his eyes—he <supplied>is</supplied> the first king. <verse-number id="Da 8:22">22</verse-number>And the <supplied>horn</supplied> <supplied>that</supplied> was broken, and <supplied>then</supplied> there arose four <supplied>horns</supplied> in place of it—<supplied>these are</supplied> four kingdoms <supplied>that</supplied> will arise from <supplied>his</supplied> nation, but not with his power. <verse-number id="Da 8:23">23</verse-number>And at the end of their kingdom, when the transgressions are completed, a king will arise, fierce in countenance and skilled in riddles. <verse-number id="Da 8:24">24</verse-number>And his power will grow, but not by his <supplied>own</supplied> power, and he will cause fearful destruction, and he will succeed and <idiom-start/>he will act<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “he will do”</note> and he will destroy <supplied>the</supplied> mighty and <supplied>the</supplied> people of <supplied>the</supplied> holy ones.<note>Or “saints”</note> <verse-number id="Da 8:25">25</verse-number>And by his planning<note>Or “cunning”</note> he will make a success of deceit by<note>Hebrew “in”</note> his hand, and in his <idiom-start/>mind<idiom-end/><note>Literally “heart”</note> he will <idiom-start/>boast<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “magnify himself”</note> and in <supplied>their</supplied> ease he will destroy many, and <supplied>even</supplied> against <supplied>the</supplied> prince of princes he will rise up, and he will be broken, <supplied>but</supplied> not by human hands. <verse-number id="Da 8:26">26</verse-number>And the vision of the evening and the morning that has been <idiom-start/>described<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “told”</note> it <supplied>is</supplied> true; and you, seal <supplied>up</supplied> the vision, for <idiom-start/>it refers to many days to come<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “for to days many”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 8:27">27</verse-number>And I, Daniel, was overcome, and I became ill for <supplied>some</supplied> days, and I <idiom-start/>performed<idiom-end/><note>Literally “did”</note> the business of the king, and I was dismayed over the vision and <idiom-start/>I did not understand it<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “there was not understanding”</note> </p>
		</chapter>