<chapter id="Da 10">
			<pericope>Daniel’s Vision of a Dazzling Heavenly Messenger</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 10:1">1</verse-number>In the third year of Cyrus <supplied>the</supplied> king of <supplied>the</supplied> Persians, a word<note>Or “matter,” or “message”</note> was revealed to Daniel, who was called <supplied>by</supplied> his name Belteshazzar, and the word<note>Or “matter,” or “message”</note> <supplied>was</supplied> reliable and <supplied>it concerned</supplied> a great tribulation,<note>Or “conflict”</note> and he understood the word<note>Or “matter,” or “message”</note> and <idiom-start/>he received understanding<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “and understanding to him”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 10:2">2</verse-number>In those days, I, Daniel, I <supplied>myself</supplied><note>This is an emphatic use of the first person personal pronoun</note> was <supplied>in</supplied> mourning <idiom-start/>for three whole weeks<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “three weeks <supplied>of</supplied> days”</note> <verse-number id="Da 10:3">3</verse-number>I had not eaten <supplied>any</supplied> choice food, and meat and wine did not enter my mouth, and <idiom-start/>I did not use any ointment<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I have not anointed at all”</note> <idiom-start/>until the end of three whole weeks<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “until being full/complete three weeks <supplied>of</supplied> days”</note> <verse-number id="Da 10:4">4</verse-number>And <supplied>then</supplied> on <supplied>the</supplied> twenty-fourth day of the first month, I <supplied>myself</supplied><note>This is an emphatic use of the first person personal pronoun</note> was on the bank of the great river; that is, <supplied>the</supplied> Tigris. <verse-number id="Da 10:5">5</verse-number>And I lifted up my eyes and I saw,<note>Or “looked”</note> and there was a man, <supplied>and</supplied> he was dressed <supplied>in</supplied> linen, and his waist was girded with <supplied>the</supplied> gold of Uphaz. <verse-number id="Da 10:6">6</verse-number>Now his body <supplied>was</supplied> like turquoise,<note>Or “yellow jasper” or other gold-colored stones; the exact identity of ancient precious stones is difficult</note> and his face <supplied>was</supplied> like <supplied>the</supplied> appearance of lightning, and his eyes <supplied>were</supplied> like torches of fire, and his arms and his legs <supplied>were</supplied> like <supplied>the</supplied> gleam of polished bronze, and the sound of his words <supplied>was</supplied> like <supplied>the</supplied> sound of a multitude. <verse-number id="Da 10:7">7</verse-number>And I saw, I, Daniel <idiom-start/>alone<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to alone me”</note> the vision; and the people who were with me <idiom-start/>did not see<idiom-end/><note>Literally “not they saw”</note> the vision; nevertheless, a great trembling fell upon them and they fled <supplied>in order</supplied> to hide themselves. <verse-number id="Da 10:8">8</verse-number>And I myself, Daniel, alone saw this great vision, and <supplied>as a result</supplied> <idiom-start/>no strength was left in me<idiom-end/><note>Literally “not was left in me strength”</note> and <idiom-start/>my complexion grew deathly pale<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “and complexion my changed over me to destruction”</note> and I did not retain any strength. <verse-number id="Da 10:9">9</verse-number>And I heard the sound of his words, and <idiom-start/>when I heard<idiom-end/><note>Literally “at my hearing”</note> the sound of his words I myself <supplied>began</supplied> falling into a trance on my face, <idiom-start/>with my face to the ground<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “and my face toward the ground”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 10:10">10</verse-number>And look, a hand touched me and it roused me to my knees<note>Hebrew “on my knees”</note> and the palms<note>Hebrew “palm”</note> of my hands. <verse-number id="Da 10:11">11</verse-number>And he said to me, “Daniel, <supplied>a</supplied> man beloved, pay attention to the words that I <supplied>am</supplied> speaking to you and <idiom-start/>stand upright where you are<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “stand on your position”</note> for I have now been sent to you.” And <idiom-start/>while he was speaking<idiom-end/><note>Literally “at his speaking”</note> with me this word,<note>Or “matter,” or “message”</note> I stood up trembling. <verse-number id="Da 10:12">12</verse-number>And he said to me, “You must not fear, Daniel, for from the first day that you set your heart to understand and to humble yourself <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of”</note> your God, your words were heard, and I <supplied>myself</supplied><note>This is an emphatic use of the first person personal pronoun</note> have come because of your words. <verse-number id="Da 10:13">13</verse-number>But <supplied>the</supplied> prince of <supplied>the</supplied> kingdom of Persia stood <idiom-start/>before me<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to front of me”</note> <supplied>for</supplied> twenty-one days. And look,<note>Or “finally”</note> Michael, one of the chief princes, came to assist me, and I left <supplied>him</supplied> there beside <supplied>the</supplied> king of <supplied>the</supplied> Persians. <verse-number id="Da 10:14">14</verse-number>And I have come<note>Hebrew “I came”</note> to instruct you about what<note>Hebrew “that”</note> will happen to your people <idiom-start/>in the future<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “at the end of the days”</note> for <supplied>there is</supplied> a further vision <supplied>here</supplied> <idiom-start/>for the future<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “for the days”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 10:15">15</verse-number>And while he was speaking with me according to these words, I turned my face toward the ground and I was speechless. <verse-number id="Da 10:16">16</verse-number>Then look, there was <idiom-start/>one in the form of a human<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “as <supplied>the</supplied> likeness of <supplied>a</supplied> son of man”</note> he touched my lips and I opened my mouth and I spoke and I said to the <supplied>one</supplied> standing <idiom-start/>before me<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to opposite me”</note> “My lord, because of the vision my anxieties fell upon me and I <supplied>have</supplied> not retained <supplied>my</supplied> strength. <verse-number id="Da 10:17">17</verse-number>So <idiom-start/>how am I, a servant of my lord<idiom-end/><note>Literally “how is <supplied>he</supplied> able a servant <supplied>of</supplied> my lord this”</note> to speak with <idiom-start/>you, my lord<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “with my lord this”</note> and I <idiom-start/>just now<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from now”</note> <idiom-start/>have no strength in me<idiom-end/>?”<note>Literally “not it remains in me strength”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 10:18">18</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>he again touched<idiom-end/><note>Literally “he added to and touched”</note> me, <idiom-start/>the one in the form of a human<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “like vision of a man”</note> and he strengthened me. <verse-number id="Da 10:19">19</verse-number>And he said, “You must not fear, <supplied>O</supplied> beloved man. <idiom-start/>Peace be to you<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “Peace to/for you”</note> be strong and be courageous!” And <idiom-start/>when he spoke<idiom-end/><note>Literally “at his speaking”</note> with me, I was strengthened and I said, “Let my lord speak, for you have strengthened me.” <verse-number id="Da 10:20">20</verse-number>Then he asked, “Do you know why I have come to you? And now I return to fight against the prince of Persia and I <supplied>myself</supplied><note>This is an emphatic use of the first person personal pronoun</note> <supplied>am</supplied> going, and look,<note>Or “listen”</note> <supplied>the</supplied> prince of Javan<note>That is, Greece</note> will come. <verse-number id="Da 10:21">21</verse-number>However, I will tell you <idiom-start/>what is inscribed<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the being inscribed”</note> in <supplied>the</supplied> book of truth, and there is not one <supplied>who</supplied> contends with me against these <supplied>beings</supplied> <idiom-start/>except<idiom-end/><note>Literally “but if”</note> Michael, your prince.” </p>
		</chapter>