<chapter id="Da 11">
			<pericope>A Survey of the Kings of the North and South</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 11:1">1</verse-number>“And I, in the first year of Darius the Mede, <idiom-start/>I stood<idiom-end/><note>Literally “my standing”</note> as a support and as a protection for him. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 11:2">2</verse-number>And now I will reveal <supplied>the</supplied> truth to you. Look! Still three kings will arise in Persia, and the fourth will get abundance <supplied>and</supplied> great wealth, <supplied>even</supplied> more than all <supplied>of them</supplied>, and <idiom-start/>when he becomes strong<idiom-end/><note>Literally “at his strength”</note> through his wealth, <supplied>then</supplied> he will stir up <idiom-start/>everyone<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the all”</note> against <supplied>the</supplied> kingdom of Javan.<note>That is, Greece</note> <verse-number id="Da 11:3">3</verse-number>And a mighty king will arise, and he will rule <supplied>with</supplied> great dominion, and he will do <idiom-start/>as he pleases<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “as his pleasure”</note> <verse-number id="Da 11:4">4</verse-number>But <idiom-start/>as he rises in power<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “as his rising/to rise”</note> his kingdom will be divided toward the four winds of heaven, but not to his posterity, and not according to his dominion <supplied>by</supplied> which he ruled, for his kingdom will be uprooted and <supplied>be given</supplied> <idiom-start/>to others besides them<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to others from to alone these”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 11:5">5</verse-number>“Then the king of the south will grow strong and <supplied>also</supplied> <idiom-start/>one of his officials<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from among his officials”</note> and he will grow stronger <idiom-start/>than him<idiom-end/><note>Literally “over him”</note> and he will rule <idiom-start/>a dominion greater than his dominion<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “a dominion great dominion his”</note> <verse-number id="Da 11:6">6</verse-number>And at <supplied>the</supplied> end of <supplied>some</supplied> years they will make an alliance, and the daughter of the king of the south will come to the king of the north to make a peace treaty, but <idiom-start/>she will not retain her position of power<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “she will not retain the power of her arm”</note> and his offspring<note>Or “power”</note> will not endure, and she will be given up, she and her attendants and her child supporting her, in those times.<note>Hebrew “in the times”</note> <verse-number id="Da 11:7">7</verse-number>And a branch from her roots<note>That is, a member of her family</note> will rise up <supplied>in</supplied> his place, and he will come against the army and he will enter the stronghold of the king of the north and he will take action against them and he will prevail. <verse-number id="Da 11:8">8</verse-number>And also their gods with their idols <supplied>and</supplied> with the <idiom-start/>precious vessels<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “vessels of their desire”</note> silver and gold he will take to Egypt into captivity, and <supplied>for</supplied> years <idiom-start/>he will leave the king of the north alone<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “he will stand back from the king of the north”</note> <verse-number id="Da 11:9">9</verse-number>And <supplied>then</supplied> he<note>That is, the king of the north</note> will come into the kingdom of the king of the south, but he will return to his land. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 11:10">10</verse-number>“But his sons will wage war and they will gather a multitude of great forces and <idiom-start/>he will advance with great force<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “he will come, to come”</note> and he will overflow <supplied>like a flood</supplied> and he will pass through and he will return, and they will wage war up to his fortress. <verse-number id="Da 11:11">11</verse-number>And the king of the south will become furious, and he will go and he will battle against him, against the king of the north; and he will muster a great multitude, and the multitude will be given into his hand. <verse-number id="Da 11:12">12</verse-number>When the multitude is carried off, his heart will be exalted and he will overthrow <idiom-start/>tens of thousands<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “myriads”</note> but he will not prevail. <verse-number id="Da 11:13">13</verse-number>And the king of the north will again raise a multitude, greater than the former, and <idiom-start/>at the end of some years<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the end of the times years”</note> he will surely come with <supplied>a</supplied> great army and with great supplies.<note>Or “resources”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 11:14">14</verse-number>“And in these times many will rise <supplied>up</supplied> against the king of the south, and <idiom-start/>the violent ones of your people<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the sons of the lawless ones of your people”</note> will lift themselves <idiom-start/>to fulfill<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to cause to stand”</note> <supplied>the</supplied> vision, but they will fall. <verse-number id="Da 11:15">15</verse-number>And the king of the north will come, and he will throw up siege ramps<note>Hebrew “ramp”</note> and capture a city of fortifications and the military forces of the south and <idiom-start/>his choice troops<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the army of his chosen troops”</note> will not stand, for<note>Hebrew “and”</note> there is no strength <supplied>left</supplied> to resist. <verse-number id="Da 11:16">16</verse-number>And the <supplied>one</supplied> coming to him will act <idiom-start/>according to<idiom-end/><note>Literally “as”</note> his pleasure, and there is no <supplied>one who</supplied> <idiom-start/>will stand<idiom-end/><note>Literally “standing”</note> <idiom-start/>before him<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to the face of him”</note> and he will stand in <idiom-start/>the beautiful land<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the land of the beauty”</note> and complete destruction <supplied>will be</supplied> in his power. <verse-number id="Da 11:17">17</verse-number>And he will set his face to come with the authority of his whole kingdom and will form an agreement;<note>Or “treaty,” or “peace proposal”; the Hebrew is difficult</note> and he will <idiom-start/>act<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “do, perform”</note> and the daughter of women he will give to him to destroy it,<note>Or “her”</note> but <supplied>the ploy</supplied> will not succeed <idiom-start/>and she will not support him<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “and not for him will she be”</note> <verse-number id="Da 11:18">18</verse-number>And he will turn his face to <supplied>the</supplied> coastlands, and he will capture many, but<note>Hebrew “and”</note> a commander will end his insults to him <idiom-start/>so that instead his insults will turn back upon him<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “so that not his insults he will return against him”</note> <verse-number id="Da 11:19">19</verse-number>And he will turn back his face toward<note>Hebrew “to”</note> the strongholds of his land, but he will stumble and he will fall and will not be found. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 11:20">20</verse-number>“Then in his place will arise <supplied>one</supplied> sending an official <supplied>throughout</supplied> <supplied>the</supplied> glory<note>Or “splendor”</note> of <supplied>his</supplied> kingdom, and <idiom-start/>in a few days<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in some days”</note> he will be broken, but not in anger and not in battle. <verse-number id="Da 11:21">21</verse-number>And in his place a despicable person will arise on whom<note>Hebrew “him”</note> they have not conferred the majesty of <supplied>the</supplied> kingdom, and he will come in <idiom-start/>without warning<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in ease”</note> and he will seize <supplied>the</supplied> kingdom by deceit. <verse-number id="Da 11:22">22</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>before him<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of him”</note> <idiom-start/>mighty military forces<idiom-end/><note>Literally “military forces of the flood”</note> will be utterly swept away, and they will be broken, and also <supplied>the</supplied> leader of <supplied>the</supplied> covenant. <verse-number id="Da 11:23">23</verse-number>And after an alliance <supplied>is made</supplied> with him, he will act deceitfully, and he will rise and he will become powerful with few people <supplied>backing him</supplied>. <verse-number id="Da 11:24">24</verse-number>In <supplied>a time of</supplied> ease and in <supplied>the</supplied> rich parts of <supplied>the</supplied> province, he will come and he will do what <idiom-start/>his predecessors<idiom-end/><note>Literally “his fathers and the father of his fathers”</note> did not do; he will distribute plunder and spoil and possessions to them, and he will devise his plans against fortifications, but <supplied>only</supplied> <idiom-start/>for a time<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “until time”</note> <verse-number id="Da 11:25">25</verse-number>And he will stir up his power and his heart against the king of the south and <idiom-start/>with a much greater and stronger army<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “with an army great and numerous exceedingly”</note> but he will not succeed, for they will devise plans against him. <verse-number id="Da 11:26">26</verse-number>And those who eat of his royal rations will break him and his army will be overwhelmed, and many will fall, slain. <verse-number id="Da 11:27">27</verse-number><idiom-start/>And two of the kings<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And two of them, the kings”</note> <idiom-start/>will bend their hearts<idiom-end/><note>Literally “their heart”</note> to evil. And at the <idiom-start/>same table<idiom-end/><note>Literally “one table”</note> they will speak lies, but <supplied>what is discussed</supplied> will not succeed, for still an end <supplied>is coming</supplied> at the appointed time. <verse-number id="Da 11:28">28</verse-number>Then he will return to his land with many possessions, but his heart <supplied>will be set</supplied> against <idiom-start/>the holy covenant<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “covenant of holiness”</note> and he will take action and he will return to his land. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 11:29">29</verse-number>“At the appointed time he will return and he will come into the south, but it will not be <idiom-start/>as it was before<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “as the former and as the last”</note> <verse-number id="Da 11:30">30</verse-number>And <supplied>the</supplied> ships of Kittim will come against him, and he will lose heart, and he will turn back, and he will be enraged <idiom-start/>against the holy covenant<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “against the covenant of holiness”</note> and he will take action, and he will turn back, and he will pay attention to <supplied>those who</supplied> forsake <idiom-start/>the holy covenant<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “<supplied>the</supplied> covenant of holiness”</note> <verse-number id="Da 11:31">31</verse-number>And military forces from him <idiom-start/>will occupy<idiom-end/><note>Literally “will stand forth”</note> and will profane<note>Or “desecrate”</note> the <idiom-start/>sanctuary stronghold<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the sanctuary, the stronghold”</note> and they will abolish the regular burnt offering, and they will set up the abomination that causes desolation. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 11:32">32</verse-number>“And those who violate <supplied>the</supplied> covenant he will seduce with flattery, but the persons who know their God<note>Hebrew “the ones who know his God”</note> will stand firm and will take action. <verse-number id="Da 11:33">33</verse-number>And those who have insight <idiom-start/>will instruct<idiom-end/><note>Literally “make understand”</note> the many, but they will fall by sword and by flame, by captivity and by plunder <idiom-start/>for some time<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “<supplied>during</supplied> days”</note> <verse-number id="Da 11:34">34</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>when they fall<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in/at their falling”</note> they will receive little help, and many will join with them <supplied>in</supplied> hypocrisy. <verse-number id="Da 11:35">35</verse-number>And <supplied>even</supplied> some of those <idiom-start/>who have insight<idiom-end/>﻿<note>Literally “the <supplied>ones</supplied> who produce insight”</note> will fall<note>Or “stumble”</note> <supplied>in order for</supplied> them to be refined by it, and to be purified and cleansed until the time of <supplied>the</supplied> end, for the appointed time <supplied>is</supplied> still to come. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 11:36">36</verse-number>“Then the king will do <idiom-start/>as he pleases<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “as his pleasure”</note> and he will exalt himself and will consider himself above any god, and he will speak horrendous things <idiom-start/>against<idiom-end/><note>Literally “over”</note> <supplied>the</supplied> God of gods, yet he will succeed until <supplied>the period</supplied> of anger is finished, for <supplied>what</supplied> is determined will be done. <verse-number id="Da 11:37">37</verse-number>He will not pay respect to the gods of his ancestors,<note>Or “fathers”</note> or to <supplied>the</supplied> darling of women, and not to any god will he pay respect, for he will consider himself great over all <supplied>gods</supplied>. <verse-number id="Da 11:38">38</verse-number>But <idiom-start/>instead<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in his place”</note> he will honor the god of fortresses, a god whom his ancestors<note>Or “fathers”</note> did not know. He will honor <supplied>him</supplied> with gold, and with silver, and with precious stones<note>Hebrew “precious stone”</note> and with costly gifts. <verse-number id="Da 11:39">39</verse-number>And he will deal with <supplied>the</supplied> <idiom-start/>fortified strongholds<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the fortifications of strongholds”</note> with <supplied>the help of</supplied> <idiom-start/>a foreign god<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “<supplied>the</supplied> god of a foreign land”</note> and he will increase wealth for whoever will acknowledge <supplied>him</supplied>, and he will cause them to rule<note>Or “appoint”</note> over the many, and he will distribute land for a price. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 11:40">40</verse-number>“And at <supplied>the</supplied> time of <supplied>the</supplied> end the king of the south will attack him, and the king of the north will storm against him with chariots<note>Hebrew “chariot”</note> and with horsemen and with many ships, and he will advance against the countries and <idiom-start/>he will sweep through like a flood<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “and he will overflow <supplied>them</supplied> and he will pass through”</note> <verse-number id="Da 11:41">41</verse-number>And he will come <idiom-start/>into the beautiful land<idiom-end/><note>Literally “into the land of the beauty”</note> and many will fall victim, but these will escape from his power: Edom and Moab and the best part<note>A difficult word to translate in this context: possibly it means “the foremost” (NASB), or it may mean “the remnant” (NEB)</note> of the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sons/children of Ammon”</note> <verse-number id="Da 11:42">42</verse-number>And he will stretch out his hand against countries and the land of Egypt <idiom-start/>will not escape<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “not it will be to escape”</note> <verse-number id="Da 11:43">43</verse-number>And he will rule over the treasures of gold and the silver and over all the precious things of Egypt; and <supplied>the</supplied> Libyans and <supplied>the</supplied> Cushites <supplied>will follow</supplied> in his footsteps. <verse-number id="Da 11:44">44</verse-number>But reports will terrify him from <supplied>the</supplied> east and from <supplied>the</supplied> north, and he will go out with great fury to destroy and <supplied>to</supplied> exterminate many. <verse-number id="Da 11:45">45</verse-number>And <supplied>then</supplied> he will pitch the tents of his palace between <supplied>the</supplied> sea <supplied>and</supplied> <idiom-start/>the beautiful holy mountain<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “<supplied>the</supplied> mountain of the beauty holiness”</note> and he will come to his end, and there is no one<note>Or “not one”</note> helping him.” </p>
		</chapter>