<chapter id="Da 12">
			<pericope>The Time of the Judgment and the Resurrection of Two Groups</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 12:1">1</verse-number>“Now at that time, Michael, the great prince, will arise, <idiom-start/>the protector<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the one who stands with”</note> over the sons of your people, and it will be a time of distress that has not been since <supplied>your people</supplied> <idiom-start/>have been<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to be” or “being”</note> a nation until that time. And at that time your people will escape, <idiom-start/>everyone who is found<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all <supplied>of</supplied> the being found”</note> written in the scroll.<note>Or “book”</note> <verse-number id="Da 12:2">2</verse-number>And many from <supplied>those</supplied> sleeping <idiom-start/>in the dusty ground<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<supplied>of the</supplied> ground of dust”</note> will awake, some to <idiom-start/>everlasting life<idiom-end/><note>Literally “life of eternity”</note> and some to disgrace and <idiom-start/>everlasting contempt<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “contempt <supplied>of</supplied> eternity”</note> <verse-number id="Da 12:3">3</verse-number>But the <supplied>ones</supplied> having insight will shine like the brightness of the expanse, and <supplied>the ones</supplied> providing justice <supplied>for</supplied> the many<note>Or “leading the many in righteousness”</note> <supplied>will be</supplied> like the stars <idiom-start/>forever and ever<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to eternity and ever”</note> <verse-number id="Da 12:4">4</verse-number>But you, Daniel, keep the words secret and seal the scroll<note>Or “book”</note> until <supplied>the</supplied> time of <supplied>the</supplied> end; many will run back and forth and knowledge will increase.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 12:5">5</verse-number>Then I looked, I myself, Daniel, and look, there were two others standing: <idiom-start/>one on this bank of the stream and one on the other<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “one here on the bank of the stream and one there on the bank of the stream”</note> <verse-number id="Da 12:6">6</verse-number>Then he said to the man <supplied>who</supplied> was clothed in linen who <supplied>was</supplied> above<note>Hebrew “from above”</note> the water of the stream,<note>Or “river”</note> “<idiom-start/>How long until<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Until when”</note> the end of the wonders?” <verse-number id="Da 12:7">7</verse-number>And I heard the man <supplied>who</supplied> was clothed in linen who <supplied>was</supplied> above<note>Hebrew “from above”</note> the water of the stream,<note>Or “river”</note> and he raised his right hand and his left hand to heaven and he swore <idiom-start/>by the one who lives forever<idiom-end/><note>Literally “by the life of the eternity”</note> that <supplied>an</supplied> appointed time, appointed times, and half <supplied>an appointed time</supplied> <supplied>would pass</supplied> when <supplied>the</supplied> shattering of <idiom-start/>the power of the holy people<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<supplied>the</supplied> power of <supplied>the</supplied> people of holiness”</note> <idiom-start/>would be completed<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “to come to an end”</note> <supplied>then</supplied> all these things will be accomplished. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Daniel Seeks Additional Insights</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Da 12:8">8</verse-number>Now I myself heard, but I <supplied>did</supplied> not understand, and I said, “My lord, what <supplied>will be the</supplied> outcome <supplied>of</supplied> these <supplied>things</supplied>?” <verse-number id="Da 12:9">9</verse-number>And he said, “Go, Daniel, for the words <supplied>are</supplied> secret and <supplied>are</supplied> sealed <supplied>up</supplied> until <supplied>the</supplied> time of <supplied>the</supplied> end. <verse-number id="Da 12:10">10</verse-number>Many will be purified and will be cleansed and will be refined, but <supplied>the</supplied> wicked will act wickedly <idiom-start/>and none of the wicked will understand<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “and not will understand all the wicked”</note> but <idiom-start/>those who have insight<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the <supplied>ones</supplied> having insight”</note> will understand. <verse-number id="Da 12:11">11</verse-number>And from <supplied>the</supplied> time the regular burnt offering is removed and <supplied>the</supplied> abomination that causes desolation <idiom-start/>is set up<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to be set up” or “to put in place”</note> <supplied>there will be</supplied> one thousand two hundred and ninety days. <verse-number id="Da 12:12">12</verse-number>Happy <supplied>is</supplied> the <supplied>one who is</supplied> persevering, and attains <supplied>to</supplied> <supplied>the</supplied> one thousand three hundred and thirty-five days. <verse-number id="Da 12:13">13</verse-number>But you, go <supplied>on</supplied> to the end and rest, and you will arise for your allotted inheritance at the end of the days.” </p>
		</chapter>