<chapter id="Ge 1">
			<pericope>The Creation</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 1:1">1</verse-number>In the beginning, God created the heavens and the earth— <verse-number id="Ge 1:2">2</verse-number>Now<note>Or “And”</note> the earth was formless and empty, and darkness <supplied>was</supplied> over the face of the deep. And the Spirit of God <supplied>was</supplied> hovering over the surface of the waters. <verse-number id="Ge 1:3">3</verse-number>And God said, “Let there be light!” And there was light. <verse-number id="Ge 1:4">4</verse-number>And God saw the light, that <supplied>it was</supplied> good, and God caused <supplied>there to be</supplied> a separation between the light and between the darkness. <verse-number id="Ge 1:5">5</verse-number>And God called the light Day, and the darkness he called Night. And there was evening and there was morning, <supplied>the</supplied> first day. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 1:6">6</verse-number>And God said, “Let there be a vaulted dome<note>Or “expanse”</note> in the midst of the waters, and <idiom-start/>let it cause a separation between the waters<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “Let there be a separation made between waters to waters”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 1:7">7</verse-number>So<note>Or “And”</note> God made the vaulted dome,<note>Or “expanse”</note> and he caused a separation between the waters which <supplied>were</supplied> under the vaulted dome<note>Or “expanse”</note> and between the waters which were over the vaulted dome.<note>Or “expanse”</note> And it was so. <verse-number id="Ge 1:8">8</verse-number>And God called the vaulted dome<note>Or “expanse”</note> “heaven.”<note>Or “sky”</note> And there was evening, and there was morning, a second day. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 1:9">9</verse-number>And God said, “Let the waters under heaven<note>Or “the sky”</note> be gathered to one place, and let the dry ground appear.” And it was so. <verse-number id="Ge 1:10">10</verse-number>And God called the dry ground “earth,” and he called the collection of the waters “seas.” And God saw that <supplied>it was</supplied> good. <verse-number id="Ge 1:11">11</verse-number>And God said, “Let the earth produce green plants <supplied>that will</supplied> bear seed—fruit trees bearing fruit <idiom-start/>in which there is seed<idiom-end/><note>Literally “which its seed <supplied>is</supplied> in it”</note>—according to its<note>Or “their”</note> kind, on the earth.” And it was so. <verse-number id="Ge 1:12">12</verse-number>And the earth brought forth green plants bearing seed according to its<note>Or “their”</note> kind, and trees bearing fruit <idiom-start/>in which there was seed<idiom-end/><note>Literally “which its seed <supplied>is</supplied> in it”</note> according to its<note>Or “their”</note> kind. And God saw that <supplied>it was</supplied> good. <verse-number id="Ge 1:13">13</verse-number>And there was evening and there was morning, a third day. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 1:14">14</verse-number>And God said, “Let there be lights<note>Or “light sources”</note> in the vaulted dome<note>Or “expanse”</note> of heaven<note>Or “the sky”</note> <idiom-start/>to separate day from night<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to make a separation between the day and between the night”</note> and let them be as signs and for appointed times, and for days and years, <verse-number id="Ge 1:15">15</verse-number>and they shall be as lights<note>Or “light sources”</note> in the vaulted dome<note>Or “expanse”</note> of heaven<note>Or “the sky”</note> to give light on the earth.” And it <supplied>was</supplied> so. <verse-number id="Ge 1:16">16</verse-number>And God made two lights,<note>Or “light sources”</note> the greater light<note>Or “light source”</note> to rule<note>Literally “as the authority of”</note> the day and the smaller light<note>Or “light source”</note> to rule<note>Literally “as the authority of”</note> the night, and the stars. <verse-number id="Ge 1:17">17</verse-number>And God placed them in the vaulted dome<note>Or “expanse”</note> of heaven<note>Or “the sky”</note> to give light on the earth <verse-number id="Ge 1:18">18</verse-number>and to rule over the day and over the night, and to <idiom-start/>separate light from darkness<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “make a separation between the light and between the darkness”</note> And God saw that <supplied>it was</supplied> good. <verse-number id="Ge 1:19">19</verse-number>And there was evening and there was morning, a fourth day. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 1:20">20</verse-number>And God said, “Let the waters swarm <supplied>with</supplied> swarms of living creatures, and let birds fly over the earth across the face of the vaulted dome<note>Or “expanse”</note> of heaven.<note>Or “the sky”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 1:21">21</verse-number>So<note>Or “And”</note> God created the great sea creatures and every living creature <supplied>that</supplied> moves, <supplied>with</supplied> which the waters swarm, according to their kind, and every bird <supplied>with</supplied> wings according to its<note>Or “their”</note> kind. And God saw that <supplied>it was</supplied> good. <verse-number id="Ge 1:22">22</verse-number>And God blessed them, saying, “Be fruitful and multiply, and fill the waters in the seas, and let the birds multiply on the earth.” <verse-number id="Ge 1:23">23</verse-number>And there was evening, and there was morning, a fifth day. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 1:24">24</verse-number>And God said, “Let the earth bring forth living creatures according to their kind: cattle and moving things, and wild animals<note>Literally “animals of the earth/land”</note> according to their kind.” And it was so. <verse-number id="Ge 1:25">25</verse-number>So<note>Or “And”</note> God made wild animals<note>Literally “animals of the earth/land”</note> according to their kind and the cattle according to their kind, and every creeping thing of the earth according to its<note>Or “their”</note> kind. And God saw that <supplied>it was</supplied> good. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 1:26">26</verse-number>And God said, “Let us make humankind in<note>Or “as”</note> our image and according to<note>Or “as”</note> our likeness, and let them rule over the fish of the sea, and over the birds of heaven,<note>Or “the sky”</note> and over the cattle, and over all the earth, and over every moving thing that moves upon the earth.” <verse-number id="Ge 1:27">27</verse-number>So<note>Or “And”</note> God created humankind in<note>Or “as”</note> his image, in<note>Or “as”</note> the likeness of God he created him,<note>Or “it” <supplied>collective: humankind</supplied></note> male and female he created them. <verse-number id="Ge 1:28">28</verse-number>And God blessed them, and God said to them, “Be fruitful and multiply, and fill the earth and subdue it, and rule over the fish of the sea and the birds of heaven,<note>Or “the sky”</note> and over every animal that moves upon the earth.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 1:29">29</verse-number>And God said, “Look—I am giving to you every plant <supplied>that</supplied> bears seed which <supplied>is</supplied> on the face of the whole earth, and every kind of tree <idiom-start/>that bears fruit<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “which in it fruit of a tree bears seed”</note> They shall be yours as food.” <verse-number id="Ge 1:30">30</verse-number>And to every kind of animal of the earth and to every bird of heaven,<note>Or “the sky”</note> and to everything that moves upon the earth in which <supplied>there is</supplied> life <supplied>I am giving</supplied> every green plant as food.” And it was so. <verse-number id="Ge 1:31">31</verse-number>And God saw everything that he had made and, behold, <supplied>it was</supplied> very good. And there was evening, and there was morning, a sixth day. </p>
		</chapter>