<chapter id="Ge 2">
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 2">2</verse-number><verse-number id="Ge 2:1">1</verse-number> And heaven<note>Or “the sky”</note> and earth<note>Or “the earth”</note> and all their array<note>Or “host”</note> were finished. <verse-number id="Ge 2:2">2</verse-number>And on the seventh day God finished his work that he had done, and he rested on the seventh day from all his work that he had done. <verse-number id="Ge 2:3">3</verse-number>And God blessed the seventh day, and he sanctified<note>Or “hallowed”</note> it, because on it he rested from all his work <idiom-start/>of creating that <supplied>there was</supplied> to do<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “which God created to do”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Generations of Heaven and Earth</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 2:4">4</verse-number>These are the generations<note>Or “family records”</note> of heaven<note>Or “the sky”</note> and earth<note>Or “the earth”</note> when they were created, in the day <supplied>that</supplied> Yahweh God made earth and heaven<note>Or “sky”</note>—<verse-number id="Ge 2:5">5</verse-number><idiom-start/>before any plant of the field was<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and every plant of the field not yet was”</note> on earth, and <supplied>before</supplied> <idiom-start/>any plant of the field<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and every plant of the field not yet”</note> had sprung up, because Yahweh God had not caused it to rain upon the earth, and there was no human being to cultivate the ground, <verse-number id="Ge 2:6">6</verse-number>but a stream <supplied>would</supplied> rise from the earth and water the whole face of the ground—<verse-number id="Ge 2:7">7</verse-number>when<note>Or “and”</note> Yahweh God formed the man<note>“The man” indicates the noun is singular and occurs with the definite article</note> <supplied>of</supplied> dust from the ground, and he blew into his nostrils the breath of life, and the man became a living creature. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 2:8">8</verse-number>And Yahweh God planted a garden in Eden in the east, and there he put the man<note>“The man” indicates the noun is singular and occurs with the definite article</note> whom he had formed. <verse-number id="Ge 2:9">9</verse-number>And Yahweh God caused to grow every tree <supplied>that</supplied> was pleasing to the sight and good for food. And the tree of life <supplied>was</supplied> in the midst of the garden, <idiom-start/>along with<idiom-end/><note>Or “and”</note> the tree of the knowledge of good and evil. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 2:10">10</verse-number>Now<note>Or “And”</note> a river flowed out from Eden that watered the garden, and from there it diverged and became four branches. <verse-number id="Ge 2:11">11</verse-number>The name of the first <supplied>is</supplied> the Pishon. It went around all the land of Havilah, where <supplied>there is</supplied> gold. <verse-number id="Ge 2:12">12</verse-number>(The gold of that land <supplied>is</supplied> good; bdellium and onyx stones <supplied>are</supplied> there.) <verse-number id="Ge 2:13">13</verse-number>And the name of the second <supplied>is</supplied> Gihon. It went around all the land of Cush. <verse-number id="Ge 2:14">14</verse-number>And the name of the third <supplied>is</supplied> Tigris. It flows east of Assyria. And the fourth river <supplied>is</supplied> the Euphrates. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 2:15">15</verse-number>And Yahweh God took the man<note>“The man” indicates the noun is singular and occurs with the definite article</note> and set him in the garden of Eden to cultivate it and to keep it. <verse-number id="Ge 2:16">16</verse-number>And Yahweh God commanded the man,<note>“The man” indicates the noun is singular and occurs with the definite article</note> saying, “From every tree of the garden <idiom-start/>you may freely eat<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “eating you may eat”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 2:17">17</verse-number>but from the tree of the knowledge of good and evil you shall not eat, for in the day <idiom-start/>that you eat<idiom-end/><note>Literally “of your eating”</note> from it <idiom-start/>you shall surely die<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “dying you shall die”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 2:18">18</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Yahweh God said, “<supplied>it is</supplied> not good <supplied>that</supplied> the man<note>“The man” indicates the noun is singular and occurs with the definite article</note> is alone. I will make for him a helper <idiom-start/>as his counterpart<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “as his opposite”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 2:19">19</verse-number>And out of the ground Yahweh God formed every beast of the field and every bird of the sky,<note>Or “the heavens”</note> and he brought <supplied>each</supplied> to the man<note>“The man” indicates the noun is singular and occurs with the definite article</note> to see what he would call it. And whatever the man<note>“The man” indicates the noun is singular and occurs with the definite article</note> called that living creature <supplied>was</supplied> its name. <verse-number id="Ge 2:20">20</verse-number>And the man<note>“The man” indicates the noun is singular and occurs with the definite article</note> <idiom-start/>gave names<idiom-end/><note>Literally “called names”</note> to every domesticated animal and to the birds of heaven<note>Or “the sky”</note> and to all the wild animals.<note>Literally “animals of the earth/land”</note> But for <supplied>the</supplied> man there was not found a helper <idiom-start/>as his counterpart<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “as his opposite”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 2:21">21</verse-number>And Yahweh God caused a deep sleep to fall upon the man.<note>“The man” indicates the noun is singular and occurs with the definite article</note> While<note>Or “And”</note> he slept, he took one of his ribs, and closed up <idiom-start/>the flesh where it had been<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the flesh in the place of it”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 2:22">22</verse-number>And Yahweh God fashioned the rib which he had taken from the man<note>“The man” indicates the noun is singular and occurs with the definite article</note> into a woman and brought her to the man.<note>“The man” indicates the noun is singular and occurs with the definite article</note> <verse-number id="Ge 2:23">23</verse-number>And the man<note>“The man” indicates the noun is singular and occurs with the definite article</note> said, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“<idiom-start/>She is now<idiom-end/><note>Literally “this <supplied>one</supplied> the time”</note> bone from my bones </li1>
				<li2>and flesh from my flesh; </li2>
				<li1><idiom-start/>she<idiom-end/><note>Literally “this <supplied>one</supplied>”</note> shall be called ‘Woman,’ </li1>
				<li2>for <idiom-start/>she was taken<idiom-end/><note>Literally “this <supplied>one</supplied> was taken”</note> from man.” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 2:24">24</verse-number>Therefore a man shall leave his father and his mother and shall cling to his wife, and they shall be as one flesh. <verse-number id="Ge 2:25">25</verse-number>And the man<note>“The man” indicates the noun is singular and occurs with the definite article</note> and his wife, both of them, were naked, and they were not ashamed. </p>
		</chapter>