<chapter id="Ge 3">
			<pericope>The Fall</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 3:1">1</verse-number>Now the serpent was more crafty than any other <idiom-start/>wild animal<idiom-end/><note>Literally “animal of the field”</note> which Yahweh God had made. He said to the woman, “Did God indeed say, ‘You shall not eat from any tree in the garden’?” <verse-number id="Ge 3:2">2</verse-number>The woman said to the serpent, “From the fruit of the trees of the garden we may eat, <verse-number id="Ge 3:3">3</verse-number>but from the tree that is in the midst of the garden, God said, ‘You shall not eat from it, nor shall you touch it, lest you die’.” <verse-number id="Ge 3:4">4</verse-number>But the serpent said to the woman, “You shall not surely die. <verse-number id="Ge 3:5">5</verse-number>For God knows that on the day you <supplied>both</supplied> eat from it, then your eyes will be opened and you <supplied>both</supplied> shall be like gods,<note>The plural is in the context of v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Ge 3:22">22</cite> <supplied>“one of us”</supplied> and the plural suffix pronouns 〚“you <supplied>all</supplied>”〛 throughout the verse</note> knowing good and evil.” <verse-number id="Ge 3:6">6</verse-number>When<note>Or “And”</note> the woman saw that the tree <supplied>was</supplied> good for food and that it <supplied>was</supplied> a delight to the eyes, and the tree was desirable to make <supplied>one</supplied> wise, then<note>Or “and”</note> she took from its fruit and she ate. And she gave <supplied>it</supplied> also to her husband with her, and he ate. <verse-number id="Ge 3:7">7</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> the eyes of both of them were opened, and they knew that they <supplied>were</supplied> naked. And they sewed together fig leaves and they made for themselves coverings. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 3:8">8</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> they heard the sound of Yahweh God walking in the garden <idiom-start/>at the windy time of day<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “at the wind of the day”</note> And the man<note>“The man” indicates the noun is singular and occurs with the definite article</note> and his wife hid themselves from the presence of Yahweh God among the trees of the garden. <verse-number id="Ge 3:9">9</verse-number>And Yahweh God called to the man<note>“The man” indicates the noun is singular and occurs with the definite article</note> and said to him, “Where <supplied>are</supplied> you?” <verse-number id="Ge 3:10">10</verse-number>And he replied,<note>Literally “And he said”; “replied” distinguishes Adam as the speaker</note> “I heard the sound of you in the garden, and I was afraid because I <supplied>am</supplied> naked, so I hid myself.” <verse-number id="Ge 3:11">11</verse-number>Then he<note>That is, Yahweh God</note> asked,<note>Or “said”</note> “Who told you that you <supplied>were</supplied> naked? Have you eaten from <idiom-start/>the tree from which I forbade you to eat<idiom-end/>?”<note>Literally “the tree which I commanded to not eat from it”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 3:12">12</verse-number>And the man<note>“The man” indicates the noun is singular and occurs with the definite article</note> replied,<note>Or “said”</note> “The woman whom you gave <supplied>to be</supplied> with me—she gave to me from the tree and I ate.” <verse-number id="Ge 3:13">13</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Yahweh God said to the woman, “What <supplied>is</supplied> this you have done?” And the woman said, “The serpent deceived me, and I ate.” <verse-number id="Ge 3:14">14</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Yahweh God said to the serpent, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Because you have done this, </li1>
				<li2>you <supplied>will be</supplied> cursed </li2>
				<li2>more than any domesticated animal </li2>
				<li2>and more than any wild animal.<note>Literally “animal of the earth/land”</note> </li2>
				<li1>On your belly you shall go </li1>
				<li2>and dust you shall eat </li2>
				<li2>all the days of your life. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ge 3:15">15</verse-number>And I will put hostility </li1>
				<li2>between you and between the woman, </li2>
				<li2>and between your offspring<note>Literally “seed”</note> and between her offspring;<note>Literally “seed”</note> </li2>
				<li1>he will strike you <supplied>on the</supplied> head, </li1>
				<li2>and you will strike him <supplied>on the</supplied> heel.” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 3:16">16</verse-number>To the woman he said, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“I will greatly increase </li1>
				<li2><idiom-start/>your pain in childbearing<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “your pain and your childbearing”</note> </li2>
				<li2>in pain you shall bear children. </li2>
				<li1>And to your husband <supplied>shall be</supplied> your desire. </li1>
				<li2>And he shall rule over you.” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 3:17">17</verse-number>And to Adam<note>The noun lacks the definite article and is taken as a proper noun in this context</note> he said, “Because you listened to the voice of your wife and you ate from the tree <idiom-start/>from which I forbade you to eat<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from the tree which I commanded saying not to eat from it”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>the ground <supplied>shall be</supplied> cursed on your account. </li1>
				<li2>In pain you shall eat <supplied>from</supplied> it </li2>
				<li2>all the days of your life. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ge 3:18">18</verse-number>And thorns and thistles shall sprout for you, </li1>
				<li2>and you shall eat the plants of the field. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ge 3:19">19</verse-number>By the sweat of your brow<note>Literally “your face”</note> </li1>
				<li2>you shall eat bread, </li2>
				<li1>until your return to the ground. </li1>
				<li2>For from it you were taken; </li2>
				<li1>for you are dust, </li1>
				<li2>and to dust you shall return.” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 3:20">20</verse-number>And the man<note>“The man” indicates the noun is singular and occurs with the definite article</note> <idiom-start/>named<idiom-end/><note>Literally “called the name”</note> his wife Eve, because she was the mother of all life. <verse-number id="Ge 3:21">21</verse-number>And Yahweh God made for Adam<note>The noun lacks the definite article and is taken as a proper noun in this context</note> and for his wife garments of skin, and he clothed them. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 3:22">22</verse-number>And Yahweh God said, “Look—the man has become as one of us, to know good and evil. <idiom-start/>What if<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And now lest”</note> he stretches out his hand and takes also from the tree of life and eats, and lives forever?” <verse-number id="Ge 3:23">23</verse-number>And Yahweh God sent him out from the garden of Eden, to till the ground from which he was taken. <verse-number id="Ge 3:24">24</verse-number>So<note>Or “And”</note> he drove the man out, and placed cherubim east of the garden of Eden, and <idiom-start/>a flaming, turning sword<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a flame of the sword which was turning”</note> to guard the way to the tree of life. </p>
		</chapter>