<chapter id="Ge 4">
			<pericope>Cain and Abel</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 4:1">1</verse-number>Now Adam knew<note>Or “had intercourse with”</note> Eve his wife, and she conceived and bore Cain. And she said, “I have given birth to a man with <supplied>the help of</supplied> Yahweh.” <verse-number id="Ge 4:2">2</verse-number><idiom-start/>Then she bore<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And she added to bear”</note> his brother Abel. And Abel became a keeper of sheep, and Cain became a tiller of the ground. <verse-number id="Ge 4:3">3</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>in the course of time<idiom-end/><note>Literally “it came to pass at the end of days”</note> Cain brought an offering from the fruit of the ground to Yahweh, <verse-number id="Ge 4:4">4</verse-number>and Abel also brought <supplied>an offering</supplied> from <idiom-start/>the choicest firstlings of his flock<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “from the firstlings of his flock and from their fat”</note> And Yahweh looked with favor to Abel and to his offering, <verse-number id="Ge 4:5">5</verse-number>but to Cain and to his offering he did not look with favor. And Cain became very angry, and his face fell. <verse-number id="Ge 4:6">6</verse-number>And Yahweh said to Cain, “Why are you angry, and why is your face fallen? <verse-number id="Ge 4:7">7</verse-number>If you do well <idiom-start/>will I not accept you<idiom-end/>?<note>Literally “a lifting up”; this is an abbreviation of the Hebrew idiom “to lift up the face,” which means “to accept or regard with favor”</note> But if you do not do well, sin is crouching at the door. And its desire <supplied>is</supplied> for you, but you must rule over it.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 4:8">8</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Cain said to his brother Abel, <supplied>“Let us go out into the field.”</supplied><note>This phrase is not present in the Hebrew; it is supplied in other versions <supplied>Samaritan, Septuagint, Syriac, Vulgate</supplied></note> And when they were in the field, Cain rose up against his brother Abel and killed him. <verse-number id="Ge 4:9">9</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Yahweh said to Cain, “Where <supplied>is</supplied> Abel your brother?” And he said, “I do not know; am I my brother’s keeper?” <verse-number id="Ge 4:10">10</verse-number>And he said, “What have you done? The voice of your brother’s blood is crying out to me from the ground. <verse-number id="Ge 4:11">11</verse-number>So now you are cursed from the ground, which has opened its mouth to receive the blood of your brother from your hand. <verse-number id="Ge 4:12">12</verse-number>When you till the ground <idiom-start/>it shall no longer yield its strength to you<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “it shall not add to give its strength to you”</note> You shall be a wanderer and a fugitive on the earth.” <verse-number id="Ge 4:13">13</verse-number>And Cain said to Yahweh, “My punishment <supplied>is</supplied> greater than <supplied>I can</supplied> bear. <verse-number id="Ge 4:14">14</verse-number>Look, you have driven me out today from the face of the ground, and from your face I must hide. I will be a wanderer and a fugitive on the earth, and it will happen that whoever finds me will kill me.” <verse-number id="Ge 4:15">15</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Yahweh said to him, “Therefore, whoever kills Cain will be avenged sevenfold.” Then<note>Or “And”</note> Yahweh put a sign on Cain so that whoever found him would not kill him. <verse-number id="Ge 4:16">16</verse-number>And Cain went out from the presence of Yahweh, and he settled in the land of Nod, east of Eden. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 4:17">17</verse-number>And Cain knew<note>Or “had intercourse with”</note> his wife, and she conceived and gave birth to Enoch. And when he built a city <idiom-start/>he named the city after his son, Enoch<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “he called the name of the city as the name of his son, Enoch”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 4:18">18</verse-number>And to Enoch was born Irad, and Irad fathered Mehujael, and Mehujael fathered Methushael, and Methushael fathered Lamech. <verse-number id="Ge 4:19">19</verse-number>And Lamech took to himself two wives.<note>Or “women”</note> The name of the first <supplied>was</supplied> Adah, and the name of the second <supplied>was</supplied> Zillah. <verse-number id="Ge 4:20">20</verse-number>And Adah gave birth to Jabal; he was the father of those who live in tents and <supplied>those who have</supplied> livestock. <verse-number id="Ge 4:21">21</verse-number>And the name of his brother <supplied>was</supplied> Jubal; he was the father of all who play stringed instruments and wind instruments. <verse-number id="Ge 4:22">22</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Zillah also gave birth to Tubal-Cain who forged all <supplied>kinds of</supplied> tools of bronze and iron. And the sister of Tubal-Cain <supplied>was</supplied> Naamah. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 4:23">23</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Lamech said to his wives, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Adah and Zillah, listen to my voice; </li1>
				<li2>O wives of Lamech, hear my words. </li2>
				<li1>I have killed a man for wounding me, </li1>
				<li2>Even a young man for injuring me. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ge 4:24">24</verse-number>If Cain is avenged sevenfold, </li1>
				<li2>Then Lamech <supplied>will be avenged</supplied> seventy and seven <supplied>times</supplied>. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 4:25">25</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Adam knew<note>Or “had intercourse with”</note> his wife again, and she gave birth to a son. And she called his name Seth, for <supplied>she said</supplied> “God has appointed to me another child in the place of Abel, because Cain killed him.” <verse-number id="Ge 4:26">26</verse-number>And as for Seth, he also fathered a son, and he called his name Enosh. At that time he<note>Or “humankind,” if the 3ms form is considered collective</note> began to call on the name of Yahweh. </p>
		</chapter>