<chapter id="Ge 5">
			<pericope>Adam’s Descendants to Noah</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 5:1">1</verse-number>This is the record of the generations<note>Or “family records”</note> of Adam. When<note>Literally “On the day”</note> God created Adam,<note>Or “humankind”</note> he made him in the likeness of God. <verse-number id="Ge 5:2">2</verse-number>Male and female he created them. And he blessed them. And he called their name “Humankind” when<note>Literally “on the day”</note> they were created. <verse-number id="Ge 5:3">3</verse-number>And when Adam had lived one hundred and thirty years, he fathered a child in his likeness, according to his image. And he called his name Seth. <verse-number id="Ge 5:4">4</verse-number>And the days of Adam after he fathered Seth were eight hundred years. And he fathered sons and daughters. <verse-number id="Ge 5:5">5</verse-number>And all the days of Adam which he lived were nine hundred and thirty years, and he died. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 5:6">6</verse-number>When<note>Literally “On the day”</note> Seth had lived one hundred and five years, he fathered Enosh. <verse-number id="Ge 5:7">7</verse-number>And after Seth had fathered Enosh he lived eight hundred and seven years, and fathered sons and daughters. <verse-number id="Ge 5:8">8</verse-number>And all the days of Seth were nine hundred and twelve years, and he died. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 5:9">9</verse-number>When<note>Literally “On the day”</note> Enosh lived ninety years, he fathered Kenan. <verse-number id="Ge 5:10">10</verse-number>And after Enosh fathered Kenan he lived eight hundred and fifteen years, and fathered sons and daughters. <verse-number id="Ge 5:11">11</verse-number>And all the days of Enosh were nine hundred and five years, and he died. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 5:12">12</verse-number>When<note>Literally “On the day”</note> Kenan had lived seventy years, he fathered Mahalalel. <verse-number id="Ge 5:13">13</verse-number>And after Kenan had fathered Mahalalel, he lived eight hundred and forty years, and fathered sons and daughters. <verse-number id="Ge 5:14">14</verse-number>And all the days of Kenan were nine hundred and ten years, and he died. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 5:15">15</verse-number>When<note>Literally “On the day”</note> Mahalalel had lived sixty-five years, he fathered Jared. <verse-number id="Ge 5:16">16</verse-number>And after Mahalalel had fathered Jared, he lived eight hundred and thirty years, and fathered sons and daughters. <verse-number id="Ge 5:17">17</verse-number>And all the days of Mahalalel were eight hundred and ninety-five years, and he died. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 5:18">18</verse-number>When<note>Literally “On the day”</note> Jared had lived one hundred and sixty-two years, he fathered Enoch. <verse-number id="Ge 5:19">19</verse-number>And after Jared had fathered Enoch, he lived eight hundred years, and fathered sons and daughters. <verse-number id="Ge 5:20">20</verse-number>And all the days of Jared were nine hundred and sixty-two years, and he died. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 5:21">21</verse-number>When<note>Literally “On the day”</note> Enoch had lived sixty-five years, he fathered Methuselah. <verse-number id="Ge 5:22">22</verse-number>And Enoch walked with God after he fathered Methuselah three hundred years, and fathered sons and daughters. <verse-number id="Ge 5:23">23</verse-number>And all the days of Enoch were three hundred and sixty-five years. <verse-number id="Ge 5:24">24</verse-number>And Enoch walked with God, and he was no more, for God took him. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 5:25">25</verse-number>When<note>Literally “On the day”</note> Methuselah had lived one hundred and eighty-seven years, he fathered Lamech. <verse-number id="Ge 5:26">26</verse-number>And after Methuselah had fathered Lamech, he lived seven hundred and eighty-two years, and fathered sons and daughters. <verse-number id="Ge 5:27">27</verse-number>And all the days of Methuselah were nine hundred and sixty-nine years, and he died. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 5:28">28</verse-number>When<note>Literally “On the day”</note> Lamech had lived one hundred and eighty-two years, he fathered a son. <verse-number id="Ge 5:29">29</verse-number>And he called his name Noah, saying, “This one <idiom-start/>shall relieve us<idiom-end/><note>Literally “shall comfort us”</note> from our work, and from the hard labor of our hands, from the ground which Yahweh had cursed. <verse-number id="Ge 5:30">30</verse-number>And after Lamech had fathered Noah he lived five hundred and ninety-five years, and he fathered sons and daughters. <verse-number id="Ge 5:31">31</verse-number>All the days of Lamech were seven hundred and seventy-seven years, and he died. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 5:32">32</verse-number>When<note>Literally “On the day”</note> Noah <idiom-start/>was five hundred years old<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “was a son of five hundred years”</note> Noah fathered Shem, Ham, and Japheth. </p>
		</chapter>