<chapter id="Ge 6">
			<pericope>Prelude to the Flood</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 6:1">1</verse-number>And it happened <supplied>that</supplied>, when humankind began to multiply on the face of the ground, daughters were born to them. <verse-number id="Ge 6:2">2</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> the sons of God saw the daughters of humankind, that they <supplied>were</supplied> beautiful. And they took for themselves wives from all that they chose. <verse-number id="Ge 6:3">3</verse-number>And Yahweh said, “My Spirit shall not abide with humankind forever in that he <supplied>is</supplied> also flesh. And his days <supplied>shall be</supplied> one hundred and twenty years.” <verse-number id="Ge 6:4">4</verse-number>The Nephilim <supplied>were</supplied> upon the earth in those days, and also afterward, when the sons of God went into the daughters of humankind, and they bore children to them. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 6:5">5</verse-number>And Yahweh saw that the evil of humankind <supplied>was</supplied> great upon the earth, and every inclination of the thoughts of his heart <supplied>was</supplied> always<note>Literally “every day”</note> only evil. <verse-number id="Ge 6:6">6</verse-number>And Yahweh regretted that he had made humankind on the earth, and <idiom-start/>he was grieved in his heart<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “he was grieved to his heart”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 6:7">7</verse-number>And Yahweh said, “I will destroy humankind whom I created from upon the face of the earth, from humankind, to animals, to creeping things, and to the birds of heaven,<note>Or “the sky”</note> for I regret that I have made them.” <verse-number id="Ge 6:8">8</verse-number>But Noah found favor in the eyes of Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 6:9">9</verse-number>These <supplied>are</supplied> the generations<note>Or “family records”</note> of Noah. Noah <supplied>was</supplied> a righteous man, without defect in his generations. Noah walked with God. <verse-number id="Ge 6:10">10</verse-number>And Noah fathered three sons: Shem, Ham, and Japheth. <verse-number id="Ge 6:11">11</verse-number>And the earth <supplied>was</supplied> corrupted before God, and the earth was filled <supplied>with</supplied> violence. <verse-number id="Ge 6:12">12</verse-number>And God saw the earth, and behold, it was corrupt, for all flesh had corrupted its way upon the earth. <verse-number id="Ge 6:13">13</verse-number>And God said to Noah, “The end of all flesh <supplied>has</supplied> come before me, for the earth was filled <supplied>with</supplied> violence because of them. Now, look, I <supplied>am going</supplied> to destroy them <supplied>along</supplied> with the earth. <verse-number id="Ge 6:14">14</verse-number>Make for yourself an ark of cypress wood; you must make the ark <supplied>with</supplied> rooms, then<note>Or “and”</note> you must cover it with pitch, inside and outside. <verse-number id="Ge 6:15">15</verse-number>And this <supplied>is</supplied> how you must make it: the length of the ark, three hundred cubits; its width fifty cubits; its height, thirty cubits. <verse-number id="Ge 6:16">16</verse-number>You must make a roof for the ark, and <idiom-start/>finish it to a cubit above<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to one cubit you must finish it from above”</note> And <supplied>as for</supplied> the door of the ark, you must put <supplied>it</supplied> in its side. You must make it <supplied>with</supplied> a lower, second, and a third <supplied>deck</supplied>. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 6:17">17</verse-number>And I, behold, I <supplied>am</supplied> about to bring the flood waters over the earth to destroy all flesh in which <supplied>is</supplied> the breath of life from under the heaven;<note>Or “the sky”</note> everything that <supplied>is</supplied> on the earth shall perish. <verse-number id="Ge 6:18">18</verse-number>And I will establish my covenant with you, and you must go into the ark—you, and your sons, and your wife, and the wives of your sons with you. <verse-number id="Ge 6:19">19</verse-number>And of every living thing, from all flesh, you must bring two from every <supplied>kind</supplied> into the ark to keep <supplied>them</supplied> alive with you; they shall be male and female. <verse-number id="Ge 6:20">20</verse-number>From the birds according to their<note>Or “its”</note> kind, and from the animals according to their<note>Or “its”</note> kind, from every creeping thing <supplied>on</supplied> the ground according to its<note>Or “their”</note> kind—two from every kind shall come to you to keep <supplied>them</supplied> alive. <verse-number id="Ge 6:21">21</verse-number>And <supplied>as for</supplied> you, take for yourself from every kind of food that is eaten. And you must gather <supplied>it</supplied> to yourself. And it shall be for you and for them for food.” <verse-number id="Ge 6:22">22</verse-number>And Noah did according to all that God commanded him; thus he did. </p>
		</chapter>