<chapter id="Ge 7">
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 7">7</verse-number><verse-number id="Ge 7:1">1</verse-number> Then<note>Or “And”</note> Yahweh said to Noah, “Go—you and all your household—into the ark, for I have seen you <supplied>are</supplied> righteous before me in this generation. <verse-number id="Ge 7:2">2</verse-number>From all the clean animals you must take for yourself <idiom-start/>seven pairs<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “seven, seven”</note> a male and its mate. And from the animals that <supplied>are</supplied> not clean <supplied>you must take</supplied> two, a male and its mate, <verse-number id="Ge 7:3">3</verse-number>as well as from the birds of heaven<note>Or “the sky”</note> <idiom-start/>seven pairs<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “seven, seven”</note> male and female, <idiom-start/>to keep their kind alive<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to keep seed alive”</note> on the face of the earth. <verse-number id="Ge 7:4">4</verse-number>For <idiom-start/>within seven days<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to seven days still”</note> I will send rain upon the earth <supplied>for</supplied> forty days and forty nights. And I will blot out all the living creatures that I have made from upon the face of the ground.” <verse-number id="Ge 7:5">5</verse-number>And Noah did according to all that Yahweh commanded him. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Flood</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 7:6">6</verse-number>Noah <idiom-start/>was six hundred years old<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was a son of six hundred years”</note> when<note>Or “and”</note> the flood waters came upon the earth. <verse-number id="Ge 7:7">7</verse-number>And Noah and his sons and his wife, and the wives of his sons with him, went into the ark because of the waters of the flood. <verse-number id="Ge 7:8">8</verse-number>Of clean animals, and of animals which <supplied>are</supplied> not clean, and of the birds, and everything that creeps upon the ground, <verse-number id="Ge 7:9">9</verse-number><idiom-start/>two of each<idiom-end/><note>Literally “two, two”</note> went to Noah, into the ark, male and female, as God had commanded Noah. <verse-number id="Ge 7:10">10</verse-number>And it happened <supplied>that</supplied> after seven days the waters of the flood came over the earth. <verse-number id="Ge 7:11">11</verse-number>In the six hundredth year of the life of Noah, in the second month, on the seventeenth day of the month—on that day all the springs of the great deep were split open, and the windows of heaven were opened. <verse-number id="Ge 7:12">12</verse-number>And the rain came upon the earth forty days and forty nights. <verse-number id="Ge 7:13">13</verse-number>On this same day, Noah, Shem, Ham, and Japheth, the sons of Noah, and the wife of Noah and the three wives of his sons with them, went into the ark, <verse-number id="Ge 7:14">14</verse-number>they and all the living creatures according to their<note>Or “its”</note> kind, and all the domesticated animals according to their<note>Or “its”</note> kind, and all the creatures that creep upon the earth according to their<note>Or “its”</note> kind, all the birds according to their<note>Or “its”</note> kind, every winged creature. <verse-number id="Ge 7:15">15</verse-number>And they came to Noah to the ark, <idiom-start/>two of each<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “two, two”</note> from every living thing in which <supplied>was</supplied> the breath of life. <verse-number id="Ge 7:16">16</verse-number>And those that came, male and female, of every living thing, came as God had commanded him. And Yahweh shut the door behind him. <verse-number id="Ge 7:17">17</verse-number>And the flood came forty days and forty nights upon the earth. And the waters increased, and lifted the ark, and it rose up from the earth. <verse-number id="Ge 7:18">18</verse-number>And the waters prevailed and increased greatly upon the earth. And the ark went upon the surface<note>Hebrew “face”</note> of the waters. <verse-number id="Ge 7:19">19</verse-number>And the waters prevailed <idiom-start/>overwhelmingly<idiom-end/><note>Literally “very very”</note> upon the earth, and they covered all the high mountains which were under the entire heaven.<note>Or “the sky”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 7:20">20</verse-number><idiom-start/>The waters swelled fifteen cubits above the mountains, covering them<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “Fifteen cubits above the waters swelled, and they covered the mountains”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 7:21">21</verse-number>And every living thing that moved on the earth perished—the birds, and the domesticated animals, and the wild animals, and everything that swarmed on the earth, and all humankind. <verse-number id="Ge 7:22">22</verse-number>Everything in whose nostrils <supplied>was</supplied> <idiom-start/>the breath of life<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “a breath of spirit of life”</note> among all that <supplied>was</supplied> on dry land, died. <verse-number id="Ge 7:23">23</verse-number>And he<note>In context, God</note> blotted out every living thing upon the surface of the ground, from humankind, to animals, to creeping things, and to the birds of heaven;<note>Or “the sky”</note> they were blotted out from the earth. Only Noah and those who <supplied>were</supplied> with him in the ark remained. <verse-number id="Ge 7:24">24</verse-number>And the waters prevailed over the earth one hundred and fifty days. </p>
		</chapter>