<chapter id="Ge 8">
			<pericope>The Flood Subsides</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 8:1">1</verse-number>And God remembered Noah and all the wild animals, and all the domesticated animals that <supplied>were</supplied> with him in the ark. And God caused a wind to blow<note>Or “go”</note> over the earth, and the waters subsided. <verse-number id="Ge 8:2">2</verse-number>And the fountains of the deep and the windows of the heavens<note>Or “the sky”</note> were closed, and the rain from the heavens<note>Or “the sky”</note> was restrained. <verse-number id="Ge 8:3">3</verse-number>And the waters receded from the earth <idiom-start/>gradually<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “going and returning”</note> and the waters abated at the end of one hundred and fifty days. <verse-number id="Ge 8:4">4</verse-number>And the ark came to rest in the seventh month, on the seventeenth day of the month, on the mountains of Ararat. <verse-number id="Ge 8:5">5</verse-number>And the waters <idiom-start/>continued to recede<idiom-end/><note>Literally “going and receding”</note> to the tenth month; in the tenth month, on the first of the month, the tops of the mountains appeared. <verse-number id="Ge 8:6">6</verse-number>And it happened <supplied>that</supplied> at the end of forty days Noah opened the window of the ark that he had made. <verse-number id="Ge 8:7">7</verse-number>And he sent out a<note>Or “the”</note> raven;<note>Or “crow”</note> <idiom-start/>it went to and fro<idiom-end/><note>Literally “it went out, going out and returning”</note> until the waters were dried up from upon the earth. <verse-number id="Ge 8:8">8</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>he sent out a<note>Or “the”</note> dove<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and he sent out a dove from him”</note> to see <supplied>whether</supplied> the waters had subsided from upon the ground. <verse-number id="Ge 8:9">9</verse-number>But the dove did not find a resting place for the sole of her foot, and she returned to him into the ark, for the waters <supplied>were still</supplied> on the face of the earth. And he stretched out his hand and took her, and brought her to himself into the ark. <verse-number id="Ge 8:10">10</verse-number>And he waited another seven days, and <idiom-start/>again he sent out<idiom-end/><note>Literally “he added to send”</note> the dove from the ark. <verse-number id="Ge 8:11">11</verse-number>And the dove came to him <idiom-start/>in the evening<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “at the time of the evening”</note> and behold, a freshly-picked olive tree leaf <supplied>was</supplied> in her mouth. And Noah knew that the waters had subsided from upon the earth. <verse-number id="Ge 8:12">12</verse-number>And he waited <idiom-start/>seven more days<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “again another seven days”</note> and he sent out the dove. But it did not return again to him. <verse-number id="Ge 8:13">13</verse-number>And it happened that, in the six hundred and first year, in the first <supplied>month</supplied>, on the first <supplied>day</supplied> of the month, the waters dried up from upon the earth. And Noah removed the covering of the ark and looked. And behold, the face of the ground was dried up. <verse-number id="Ge 8:14">14</verse-number>And in the second month, on the twenty-seventh day of the month, the earth was dry. <verse-number id="Ge 8:15">15</verse-number>And God spoke to Noah, saying: <verse-number id="Ge 8:16">16</verse-number>“Go out from the ark, you and your wife, and your sons, and your sons’ wives with you. <verse-number id="Ge 8:17">17</verse-number>Bring out with you all the living things which <supplied>are</supplied> with you, from all the living creatures—birds, and animals, and everything that creeps on the earth, and let them swarm on the earth and be fruitful and multiply on the earth.” <verse-number id="Ge 8:18">18</verse-number>So<note>Or “And”</note> Noah went out, with<note>Or “and”</note> his sons and his wife, and the wives of his sons with him. <verse-number id="Ge 8:19">19</verse-number>Every animal, every creeping thing, and every bird, <supplied>and</supplied> everything <supplied>that</supplied> moves upon the earth, according to its families, went out from the ark. <verse-number id="Ge 8:20">20</verse-number>And Noah built an altar to Yahweh, and he took from all the clean animals and from all the clean birds, and offered burnt offerings on the altar. <verse-number id="Ge 8:21">21</verse-number>And Yahweh smelled the soothing fragrance, and Yahweh said <idiom-start/>to himself<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to his heart”</note> “<idiom-start/>Never again will I curse<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I will not add to curse again”</note> the ground for the sake of humankind, because the inclination of the heart of humankind <supplied>is</supplied> evil from his youth. <idiom-start/>Nor will I ever again destroy<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And I will not add again to destroy”</note> all life as I have done. <verse-number id="Ge 8:22">22</verse-number><idiom-start/>As long as the earth endures<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “While all the days of the earth”</note> seed and harvest, cold and heat, summer and winter, day and night will not cease. </p>
		</chapter>