<chapter id="Ge 9">
			<pericope>God’s Covenant with Noah and Humankind</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 9:1">1</verse-number>And God blessed Noah and his sons, and said to them, “Be fruitful and multiply, and fill the earth. <verse-number id="Ge 9:2">2</verse-number>And fear of you and dread of you shall be upon every animal of the earth, and on every bird of heaven,<note>Or “the sky”</note> <supplied>and</supplied> on everything that moves upon the ground, and on all the fish of the sea. Into your hand they shall be given. <verse-number id="Ge 9:3">3</verse-number>Every moving thing that lives shall be for you as food. As <supplied>I gave</supplied> the green plants to you, I have <supplied>now</supplied> given you everything. <verse-number id="Ge 9:4">4</verse-number>Only you shall not eat <idiom-start/>raw flesh with blood in it<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “flesh with its life, its blood”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 9:5">5</verse-number>And<note>Or “only”; the same word that occurs at the beginning of v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Ge 9:4">4</cite></note> <idiom-start/>your lifeblood<idiom-end/><note>Literally “your blood belonging to your life”</note> I will require; from <idiom-start/>every animal<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from the hand of every animal”</note> I will require it. And from the hand of humankind, from the hand of <supplied>each</supplied> man to his brother I will require the life of humankind. </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ge 9:6">6</verse-number>“<supplied>As for</supplied> the one shedding the blood of humankind, </li1>
				<li2>by humankind his blood shall be shed, </li2>
				<li1>for God made humankind in his own image. </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 9:7">7</verse-number>“And you, be fruitful and multiply, swarm on the earth and multiply in it.” <verse-number id="Ge 9:8">8</verse-number>And God said to Noah and to his sons with him, <verse-number id="Ge 9:9">9</verse-number>“As for me, behold, I am establishing my covenant with you and with your seed after you, <verse-number id="Ge 9:10">10</verse-number>and with every living creature that <supplied>is</supplied> with you—the birds, the animals, and every animal of the earth with you, from all <supplied>that</supplied> came out of the ark to all the animals of the earth. <verse-number id="Ge 9:11">11</verse-number>I am establishing my covenant with you, that never again will all flesh be cut off by the waters of a flood, nor will there ever be a flood that destroys the earth.” <verse-number id="Ge 9:12">12</verse-number>And God said, “This <supplied>is</supplied> the sign of the covenant that I am making between me and you, and between every living creature that <supplied>is</supplied> with you for future generations. <verse-number id="Ge 9:13">13</verse-number>My bow I have set in the clouds, and it shall be for a sign of <supplied>the</supplied> covenant between me and between the earth. <verse-number id="Ge 9:14">14</verse-number>And when I make clouds appear over the earth the bow shall be seen in the clouds. <verse-number id="Ge 9:15">15</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> I will remember my covenant that <supplied>is</supplied> between me and you, and between every living creature, with all flesh. And the waters of a flood will never again <idiom-start/>cause the destruction<idiom-end/><note>Literally “be to destroy”</note> of all flesh. <verse-number id="Ge 9:16">16</verse-number>The bow shall be in the clouds, and I will see it, so as to remember <supplied>the</supplied> everlasting covenant between God and between every living creature, with all flesh that <supplied>is</supplied> upon the earth.” <verse-number id="Ge 9:17">17</verse-number>And God said to Noah, “This <supplied>is</supplied> the sign of the covenant which I am establishing between me and all flesh that <supplied>is</supplied> upon the earth. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Noah’s Descendants</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 9:18">18</verse-number>Now<note>Or “And”</note> the sons of Noah who came out of the ark <supplied>were</supplied> Shem, Ham, and Japheth. (Ham <supplied>was</supplied> the father of Canaan.) <verse-number id="Ge 9:19">19</verse-number>These three <supplied>were</supplied> the sons of Noah, and from these <idiom-start/>the whole earth was populated<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “all the earth branched out”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 9:20">20</verse-number>And Noah began <supplied>to be</supplied> a man of the ground, and he planted a vineyard. <verse-number id="Ge 9:21">21</verse-number>And he drank some of the wine and became drunk, and he exposed himself in the midst of his tent. <verse-number id="Ge 9:22">22</verse-number>And Ham, the father of Canaan, saw the nakedness of his father, and he told his two brothers outside. <verse-number id="Ge 9:23">23</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Shem and Japheth took a garment, and the two of them put <supplied>it</supplied> on <supplied>their</supplied> shoulders and, walking backward, they covered the nakedness of their father. And their faces <supplied>were turned</supplied> backward, so that<note>Or “and”</note> they did not see the nakedness of their father. <verse-number id="Ge 9:24">24</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Noah awoke from his drunkenness,<note>Or “his wine”</note> and he knew what his youngest son had done to him. <verse-number id="Ge 9:25">25</verse-number>And he said, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Cursed <supplied>be</supplied> Canaan, </li1>
				<li2>a slave of slaves he shall be to his brothers.” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 9:26">26</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> he said, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Blessed <supplied>be</supplied> Yahweh, the God of Shem, </li1>
				<li2>and let Canaan be a slave to them. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ge 9:27">27</verse-number>May God make space for Japheth, </li1>
				<li2>and let him dwell in the tents of Shem, </li2>
				<li2>and let Canaan be a slave for him.” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 9:28">28</verse-number>And Noah lived three hundred and fifty years after the flood. <verse-number id="Ge 9:29">29</verse-number>And all the days of Noah were nine hundred and fifty years, and he died. </p>
		</chapter>