<chapter id="Ge 10">
			<pericope>The Descendants of the Sons of Noah</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 10:1">1</verse-number>These <supplied>are</supplied> the generations<note>Or “family records”</note> of the sons of Noah—Shem, Ham, and Japheth. Children<note>Or “sons”</note> were born to them after the flood. <verse-number id="Ge 10:2">2</verse-number>The sons of Japheth: Gomer, Magog, Madai, Javan, Tubal, Meshech, and Tiras. <verse-number id="Ge 10:3">3</verse-number>And the sons of Gomer: Ashkenaz, Riphath, and Togarmah. <verse-number id="Ge 10:4">4</verse-number>And the sons of Javan: Elishah, Tarshish, Kittim, and Dodanim. <verse-number id="Ge 10:5">5</verse-number>From these the coastland peoples spread out through their lands, each according to his own language by their own families, in their nations. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 10:6">6</verse-number>And the sons of Ham: Cush, Egypt, Put, and Canaan. <verse-number id="Ge 10:7">7</verse-number>And the sons of Cush: Seba, Havilah, Sabtah, Raamah, and Sabteca. The sons of Raamah: Sheba and Dedan. <verse-number id="Ge 10:8">8</verse-number>And Cush fathered Nimrod. <idiom-start/>He was the first on earth to be a mighty warrior<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “He began to be a mighty warrior on the earth”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 10:9">9</verse-number>He was a mighty hunter before Yahweh. Therefore it was said, “Like Nimrod a mighty hunter before Yahweh.” <verse-number id="Ge 10:10">10</verse-number>Now,<note>Or “And”</note> the beginning of his kingdom <supplied>was</supplied> Babel, Erech, Akkad, and Calneh, in the land of Shinar. <verse-number id="Ge 10:11">11</verse-number>From that land he went out <supplied>to</supplied> Assyria, and he built Nineveh, Rehoboth-Ir, Calah, <verse-number id="Ge 10:12">12</verse-number>Resen between Nineveh and Calah; that <supplied>is</supplied> the great city. <verse-number id="Ge 10:13">13</verse-number>And Egypt fathered Ludim, Anamim, Lehabim, Naphtuhim, <verse-number id="Ge 10:14">14</verse-number>Pathrusim, and Casluhim (from whom the Philistines came), and Caphtorim. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 10:15">15</verse-number>Canaan fathered Sidon, his firstborn, and Heth, <verse-number id="Ge 10:16">16</verse-number>and the Jebusites, the Amorites, the Girgashites, <verse-number id="Ge 10:17">17</verse-number>the Hivites, the Arkites, the Sinites, <verse-number id="Ge 10:18">18</verse-number>the Arvadites, the Zemarites, and the Hamathites. Afterward the families of the Canaanites were spread abroad. <verse-number id="Ge 10:19">19</verse-number>And the territory of the Canaanites <supplied>was</supplied> from Sidon <idiom-start/>in the direction of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in your going”</note> Gerar as far as Gaza, and <idiom-start/>in the direction of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in your going”</note> Sodom, Gomorrah, Admah, and Zeboiim, as far as Lasha. <verse-number id="Ge 10:20">20</verse-number>These <supplied>are</supplied> the descendants<note>Or “sons” (“descendants” was chosen since the proper names in this section are gentilic in form—that is, they indicate one’s place of origin—and have the definite article)</note> of Ham, according to their families and their languages, in their lands, and in their nations. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 10:21">21</verse-number>And to Shem, the father of all the children of Eber, the older brother of Japheth, <supplied>children</supplied> were also born. <verse-number id="Ge 10:22">22</verse-number>The sons of Shem: Elam, Asshur, Arphaxad, Lud, and Aram. <verse-number id="Ge 10:23">23</verse-number>And the sons of Aram: Uz, Hul, Gether, and Mash. <verse-number id="Ge 10:24">24</verse-number>And Arphaxad fathered Shelah, and Shelah fathered Eber. <verse-number id="Ge 10:25">25</verse-number>And to Eber two sons were born. The name of the one was Peleg, for in his days the earth was divided, and the name of his brother <supplied>was</supplied> Joktan. <verse-number id="Ge 10:26">26</verse-number>And Joktan fathered Almodad, Sheleph, Hazarmaveth, Jerah, <verse-number id="Ge 10:27">27</verse-number>Hadoram, Uzal, Diklah, <verse-number id="Ge 10:28">28</verse-number>Obal, Abimael, Sheba, <verse-number id="Ge 10:29">29</verse-number>Ophir, Havilah, and Jobab. All these <supplied>were</supplied> the sons of Joktan. <verse-number id="Ge 10:30">30</verse-number>And their dwelling <supplied>place</supplied> <idiom-start/>extended from<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was from”</note> Mesha <idiom-start/>in the direction of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in your going”</note> Sephar <supplied>to</supplied> the hill country of the east. <verse-number id="Ge 10:31">31</verse-number>These <supplied>are</supplied> the sons of Shem, according to their families, according to their languages, in their lands, and according to their nations. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 10:32">32</verse-number>These are the families of the sons of Noah, according to their generations<note>Or “family records”</note> <supplied>and</supplied> in their nations. And from these the nations spread abroad on the earth after the flood. </p>
		</chapter>