<chapter id="Ge 11">
			<pericope>The Tower of Babel</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 11:1">1</verse-number>Now<note>Or “And”</note> the whole earth <supplied>had</supplied> one language and the same words. <verse-number id="Ge 11:2">2</verse-number>And as people migrated<note>Or “set out”</note> from the east they found a plain in the land of Shinar and settled there. <verse-number id="Ge 11:3">3</verse-number>And they said <idiom-start/>to each other<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “each to his companion”</note> “Come, let us make bricks and <idiom-start/>burn them thoroughly<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “burn to burning”</note> And they had brick for stone and they had tar for mortar. <verse-number id="Ge 11:4">4</verse-number>And they said, “Come, let us build ourselves a city and a tower whose top <supplied>reaches to</supplied> the heavens. And let us make a name for ourselves, lest we be scattered over the face of the whole earth.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 11:5">5</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Yahweh came down to see the city and the tower that <idiom-start/>humankind<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons of Adam” or “sons of humankind”</note> was building. <verse-number id="Ge 11:6">6</verse-number>And Yahweh said, “Behold, <idiom-start/>they are one people with one language<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “one people and one language to all of them”</note> and <idiom-start/>this is only the beginning of what they will do<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “and this they begin to do”</note> So<note>Or “And”</note> now nothing that they intend to do will be impossible for them. <verse-number id="Ge 11:7">7</verse-number>Come, let us go down and confuse their language there, so that they will not understand <idiom-start/>each other’s language<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “each the language of his companion”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 11:8">8</verse-number>So Yahweh scattered them from there over the face of the whole earth, and they stopped building the city. <verse-number id="Ge 11:9">9</verse-number>Therefore its name was called Babel, for there Yahweh confused the language of the whole earth, and there Yahweh scattered them over the face of the whole earth. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Descendants of Shem</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 11:10">10</verse-number>These are the generations<note>Or “family records”</note> of Shem. When Shem <idiom-start/>was one hundred years old<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the son of one hundred years”</note> he fathered Arphaxad, two years after the flood. <verse-number id="Ge 11:11">11</verse-number>And Shem lived five hundred years after he fathered Arphaxad, and he fathered <supplied>other</supplied> sons and daughters. <verse-number id="Ge 11:12">12</verse-number>When Arphaxad had lived thirty-five years, he fathered Shelah. <verse-number id="Ge 11:13">13</verse-number>And Arphaxad lived four hundred and three years after he fathered Shelah, and he fathered <supplied>other</supplied> sons and daughters. <verse-number id="Ge 11:14">14</verse-number>When Shelah had lived thirty years, he fathered Eber. <verse-number id="Ge 11:15">15</verse-number>And Shelah lived four hundred and three years after he fathered Eber, and he fathered <supplied>other</supplied> sons and daughters. <verse-number id="Ge 11:16">16</verse-number>When Eber had lived thirty-four years, he fathered Peleg. <verse-number id="Ge 11:17">17</verse-number>And Eber lived four hundred and thirty years after he fathered Peleg, and he fathered <supplied>other</supplied> sons and daughters. <verse-number id="Ge 11:18">18</verse-number>When Peleg had lived thirty years, he fathered Reu. <verse-number id="Ge 11:19">19</verse-number>And Peleg lived two hundred and nine years after he fathered Reu, and he fathered <supplied>other</supplied> sons and daughters. <verse-number id="Ge 11:20">20</verse-number>When Reu had lived thirty-two years, he fathered Serug. <verse-number id="Ge 11:21">21</verse-number>And Reu lived two hundred and seven years after he fathered Serug, and he fathered <supplied>other</supplied> sons and daughters. <verse-number id="Ge 11:22">22</verse-number>When Serug had lived thirty years, he fathered Nahor. <verse-number id="Ge 11:23">23</verse-number>And Serug lived two hundred years after he fathered Nahor, and he fathered <supplied>other</supplied> sons and daughters. <verse-number id="Ge 11:24">24</verse-number>When Nahor had lived twenty-nine years, he fathered Terah. <verse-number id="Ge 11:25">25</verse-number>And Nahor lived one hundred and nineteen years after he fathered Terah, and he fathered <supplied>other</supplied> sons and daughters. <verse-number id="Ge 11:26">26</verse-number>When Terah had lived seventy years, he fathered Abram, Nahor, and Haran. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Descendants of Terah</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 11:27">27</verse-number>Now<note>Or “And”</note> these are the generations<note>Or “family records”</note> of Terah. Terah fathered Abram, Nahor, and Haran, and Haran fathered Lot. <verse-number id="Ge 11:28">28</verse-number>And Haran died in the presence of Terah his father in the land of his birth, in Ur of the Chaldeans. <verse-number id="Ge 11:29">29</verse-number>And Abram and Nahor took wives for themselves. The name of the wife of Abram <supplied>was</supplied> Sarai, and the name of the wife of Nahor <supplied>was</supplied> Milcah, the daughter of Haran, the father of Milcah and Iscah. <verse-number id="Ge 11:30">30</verse-number>And Sarai was barren; she had no child. <verse-number id="Ge 11:31">31</verse-number>And Terah took Abram his son, and Lot, the son of Haran, <idiom-start/>his grandson<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the son of his son”</note> and Sarai his daughter-in-law, the wife of Abram his son, and went out with them from Ur of the Chaldeans to go to the land of Canaan. And they went to Haran, and they settled there. <verse-number id="Ge 11:32">32</verse-number>And the days of Terah <supplied>were</supplied> two hundred and five years, and Terah died in Haran. </p>
		</chapter>