<chapter id="Ge 13">
			<pericope>The Parting of Abram and Lot</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 13:1">1</verse-number>Then Abram went up from Egypt, he and his wife and all that <supplied>was</supplied> with him. And Lot <supplied>went</supplied> with him to the Negev. <verse-number id="Ge 13:2">2</verse-number>Now Abram <supplied>was</supplied> very wealthy in livestock, in silver, and in gold. <verse-number id="Ge 13:3">3</verse-number>And he went according to his journey from the Negev, then to Bethel, to the place where his tent was at the beginning, between Bethel and Ai, <verse-number id="Ge 13:4">4</verse-number>to the place where he had made an altar at the beginning. And Abram called on the name of Yahweh there. <verse-number id="Ge 13:5">5</verse-number>And Lot, who went with Abram, also had herds and tents. <verse-number id="Ge 13:6">6</verse-number>And the land could not <idiom-start/>support them<idiom-end/><note>Literally “lift them up”</note> <supplied>so as</supplied> to live together, because their possessions were <supplied>so</supplied> many that<note>Or “and”</note> they were not able to live together. <verse-number id="Ge 13:7">7</verse-number>And there was a quarrel between the herdsmen of the livestock of Abram and the herdsmen of the livestock of Lot. Now at that time the Canaanites and the Perizzites were living in the land. <verse-number id="Ge 13:8">8</verse-number>Then Abram said to Lot, “Please, let there not be quarreling between me and you, and between my shepherds and your shepherds, for we men <supplied>are</supplied> brothers. <verse-number id="Ge 13:9">9</verse-number>Is not the whole land before you? Separate yourself from me. If <supplied>you want what is on</supplied> the left, then I will go right; if <supplied>you want what is on</supplied> the right, I will go left.” <verse-number id="Ge 13:10">10</verse-number>And Lot lifted up his eyes and saw the whole plain of the Jordan, that all of it <supplied>was</supplied> well-watered land—<supplied>this was</supplied> before Yahweh destroyed Sodom and Gomorrah—like the garden of Yahweh, like the land of Egypt <idiom-start/>in the direction of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “your going”</note> Zoar. <verse-number id="Ge 13:11">11</verse-number>So<note>Or “And”</note> Lot chose for himself all the plain of the Jordan. And Lot journeyed from the east, and so they separated <idiom-start/>from each other<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “each from his brother”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 13:12">12</verse-number>Abram settled in the land of Canaan, and Lot settled in the cities of the plain. And he pitched his tent toward Sodom. <verse-number id="Ge 13:13">13</verse-number>Now the men of Sodom <idiom-start/>were extremely wicked sinners against Yahweh<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “<supplied>were</supplied> wicked and sinners against Yahweh very”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 13:14">14</verse-number>And Yahweh said to Abram after Lot had separated from him, “Now, lift up your eyes and look from the place where you <supplied>are</supplied> to the north, and to the south, and to the east and to the west, <verse-number id="Ge 13:15">15</verse-number>for all the land which you see I will give to you, and to your descendants, forever. <verse-number id="Ge 13:16">16</verse-number>I will make your descendants like the dust of the earth which, if anyone were able to count the dust of the earth, your descendants would be <supplied>so</supplied> counted. <verse-number id="Ge 13:17">17</verse-number>Arise, go through the length of the land and through its breadth, for I will give it to you.” <verse-number id="Ge 13:18">18</verse-number>So<note>Or “And”</note> Abram pitched his tent, and he came and settled at the oaks of Mamre, which <supplied>were</supplied> at Hebron. And there he built an altar to Yahweh. </p>
		</chapter>