<chapter id="Ge 14">
			<pericope>Abram Rescues Lot</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 14:1">1</verse-number>And it happened <supplied>that</supplied> in the days of Amraphel, the king of Shinar, Arioch, the king of Ellasar, Kedorlaomer, the king of Elam, and Tidal, the king of Goiim, <verse-number id="Ge 14:2">2</verse-number>made war with Bera, the king of Sodom, and Birsha, the king of Gomorrah, Shinab, the king of Admah, and Shemeber, the king of Zeboiim, and the king of Bela (that <supplied>is</supplied>, Zoar). <verse-number id="Ge 14:3">3</verse-number>All these joined forces at the valley of Siddim (that <supplied>is</supplied>, the sea of the salt). <verse-number id="Ge 14:4">4</verse-number>Twelve years they had served Kedorlaomer, but in the thirteenth year they rebelled. <verse-number id="Ge 14:5">5</verse-number>In the fourteenth year Kedorlaomer and the kings who <supplied>were</supplied> with him came and defeated the Rephaim in Ashteroth-Karnaim, and the Zuzim in Ham, and the Emim in Shaveh-Kiriathaim, <verse-number id="Ge 14:6">6</verse-number>And the Horites in their hill country of Seir, as far as El-Paran, which is at the wilderness. <verse-number id="Ge 14:7">7</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> they turned back and came to En-Mishpat (that <supplied>is</supplied>, Kadesh). And they defeated the whole territory of the Amalekites, and also the Amorites who were living in Hazazon-Tamar. <verse-number id="Ge 14:8">8</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> the king of Sodom, the king of Gomorrah, the king of Admah, the king of Zeboiim, and the king of Bela (that <supplied>is</supplied>, Zoar) went out, and <idiom-start/>they took up battle position<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And they took up position with them for battle”</note> in the Valley of Siddim <verse-number id="Ge 14:9">9</verse-number>with Kedorlaomer, king of Elam, and Tidal, king of Goiim, and Amraphel, king of Shinar, and Arioch, king of Ellasar, four kings against five. <verse-number id="Ge 14:10">10</verse-number>Now<note>Or “And”</note> the Valley of Siddim <idiom-start/>was full of tar pits<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “pits, pits of tar”</note> And the kings of Sodom and Gomorrah fled and <idiom-start/>fell into them<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “they fell there”</note> but the rest fled to the mountains. <verse-number id="Ge 14:11">11</verse-number>So<note>Or “And”</note> they<note>In context, the enemy</note> took all the possessions of Sodom and Gomorrah and all their provisions, and they left. <verse-number id="Ge 14:12">12</verse-number>And they<note>In context, the enemy</note> took Lot, the son of the brother of Abram, and his possessions, and left. (Now he had been living in Sodom.) <verse-number id="Ge 14:13">13</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> one who escaped came and told Abram the Hebrew. And he was living at the oaks of Mamre the Amorite, brother of Eshcol and brother of Aner. <idiom-start/>They were allies with Abram<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “And they <supplied>were</supplied> owners of a covenant of Abram”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 14:14">14</verse-number>When<note>Or “And”</note> Abram heard that his <idiom-start/>relative<idiom-end/><note>Literally “brother”</note> was taken captive, he summoned his trained men, born in his house, three hundred and eighteen <supplied>of them</supplied>, and he went in pursuit up to Dan. <verse-number id="Ge 14:15">15</verse-number>And he divided <supplied>his trained men</supplied> against them at night, he and his servants. And he defeated them and pursued them to Hobah, which <supplied>is</supplied> north of Damascus. <verse-number id="Ge 14:16">16</verse-number>And he brought back all the possessions. And he also brought back Lot, his <idiom-start/>relative<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “brother”</note> and his possessions, and the women and the people as well. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Abram Meets Melchizedek</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 14:17">17</verse-number>After his return from defeating Kedorlaomer and the kings who <supplied>were</supplied> with him, the king of Sodom went out to meet him at the Valley of Shaveh (that <supplied>is</supplied>, the Valley of the King). <verse-number id="Ge 14:18">18</verse-number>And Melchizedek, the king of Salem, brought out bread and wine. (He was the priest of God Most High). <verse-number id="Ge 14:19">19</verse-number>And he blessed him and said, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Blessed <supplied>be</supplied> Abram by God Most High, </li1>
				<li2>Maker of heaven and earth. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ge 14:20">20</verse-number>And blessed <supplied>be</supplied> God Most High </li1>
				<li2>who delivered your enemies into your hand.” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p>And he<note>That is, Abram</note> gave to him a tenth of everything. <verse-number id="Ge 14:21">21</verse-number>And the king of Sodom said to Abram, “Give me the people, but the possessions take for yourself.” <verse-number id="Ge 14:22">22</verse-number>And Abram said to the king of Sodom, “I have raised my hand to Yahweh, God Most High, Maker of heaven and earth, <verse-number id="Ge 14:23">23</verse-number><idiom-start/>that neither a thread nor<idiom-end/><note>Literally “that not from a thread and up to”</note> a thong of a sandal would I take from all that <supplied>belongs</supplied> to you, that you might not say, ‘I made Abram rich.’ <verse-number id="Ge 14:24">24</verse-number><idiom-start/>Nothing besides what<idiom-end/><note>Literally “besides me only which”</note> the servants have eaten and the share of the men who went out with me <supplied>will I take.</supplied> Let Aner, Eshcol, and Mamre take their share.” </p>
		</chapter>