<chapter id="Ge 15">
			<pericope>Yahweh’s Covenant with Abram</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 15:1">1</verse-number>After these things the word of Yahweh came<note>Literally “was”</note> to Abram in a vision, saying: “Do not be afraid, Abram; I <supplied>am</supplied> your shield, <supplied>and</supplied> your reward <supplied>shall be</supplied> very great.” <verse-number id="Ge 15:2">2</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Abram said, “O Yahweh, my Lord, what will you give me? <idiom-start/>I continue to be<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I am going”</note> childless, and <idiom-start/>my heir<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the son of the inheritance of my house”</note> is Eliezer of Damascus.” <verse-number id="Ge 15:3">3</verse-number>And Abram said, “Look, you have not given me a descendant, and here, <idiom-start/>a member of my household<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a son of my house”</note> <supplied>is</supplied> <idiom-start/>my heir<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “inheriting me”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 15:4">4</verse-number>And behold, the word of Yahweh <supplied>came</supplied> to him saying, “This <supplied>person</supplied> will not <idiom-start/>be your heir<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “inherit you”</note> but <idiom-start/>your own son will be your heir<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “he who goes out from your body, he will inherit you”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 15:5">5</verse-number>And he brought him outside and said, “Look toward the heavens and count the stars if you are able to count them.” And he said to him, “So shall your offspring be.” <verse-number id="Ge 15:6">6</verse-number>And he believed in Yahweh, and he reckoned it to him <supplied>as</supplied> righteousness. <verse-number id="Ge 15:7">7</verse-number>And he said to him, “I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh, who brought you out from Ur of the Chaldeans to give this land to you, to possess it.” <verse-number id="Ge 15:8">8</verse-number>And he said, “O Yahweh God, how shall I know <supplied>that</supplied> I will possess it?” <verse-number id="Ge 15:9">9</verse-number>And he said to him, “Take for me a three-year-old heifer, and a three-year-old female goat, and a three-year-old ram, and a turtledove and a young pigeon.” <verse-number id="Ge 15:10">10</verse-number>And he took for him all these and cut them in pieces down the middle. And he put each piece opposite <idiom-start/>the other<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “its companion”</note> but the birds he did not cut. <verse-number id="Ge 15:11">11</verse-number>And the birds of prey came down on the carcasses, but Abram drove them away. <verse-number id="Ge 15:12">12</verse-number>And it happened, as the sun <idiom-start/>went down<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to go”</note> then a deep sleep fell upon Abram and, behold, a great terrifying darkness fell upon him. <verse-number id="Ge 15:13">13</verse-number>And he said to Abram, “<idiom-start/>You must surely know<idiom-end/><note>Literally “knowing you must know”</note> that your descendants shall be <supplied>as</supplied> aliens in a land <idiom-start/>not their own<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “not to them”</note> And they shall serve them<note>Some nation hostile to Abram’s descendants (Egypt in later history)</note> and they<note>Some nation hostile to Abram’s descendants (Egypt in later history)</note> shall oppress them four hundred years. <verse-number id="Ge 15:14">14</verse-number>And also the nation that they<note>That is, Abram’s descendants</note> serve I will judge. Then<note>Or “And”</note> afterward they shall go out with great possessions. <verse-number id="Ge 15:15">15</verse-number>And <supplied>as for</supplied> you, you shall go to your ancestors<note>Or “fathers”</note> in peace; you shall be buried in a good old age. <verse-number id="Ge 15:16">16</verse-number>And the fourth generation shall return here, for the guilt of the Amorites <idiom-start/>is not yet complete<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “is not complete up to now”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 15:17">17</verse-number>And after the sun had gone down and it <supplied>was</supplied> dusk, behold, a smoking firepot and a flaming torch passed between those half pieces. <verse-number id="Ge 15:18">18</verse-number>On that day Yahweh <idiom-start/>made<idiom-end/><note>Literally “cut”</note> a covenant with Abram saying, “To your offspring I will give this land, from the river of Egypt to the great river, the Euphrates river, <verse-number id="Ge 15:19">19</verse-number><supplied>the land of</supplied> the Kenites, the Kenizzites, the Kadmonites, <verse-number id="Ge 15:20">20</verse-number>the Hittites, the Perizzites, the Rephaim, <verse-number id="Ge 15:21">21</verse-number>the Amorites, the Canaanites, the Girgashites, and the Jebusites.” </p>
		</chapter>