<chapter id="Ge 16">
			<pericope>Sarai and Hagar</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 16:1">1</verse-number>Now<note>Or “And”</note> Sarai, the wife of Abram, had borne him no children. And she had a female Egyptian servant, and her name <supplied>was</supplied> Hagar. <verse-number id="Ge 16:2">2</verse-number>And Sarai said to Abram, “Look, please, Yahweh has prevented me from bearing children. Please go in to my servant; perhaps <idiom-start/>I will have children by her<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “I will be built from her”</note> And Abram listened to the voice of Sarai. <verse-number id="Ge 16:3">3</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Sarai, the wife of Abram, took Hagar, her Egyptian servant, after Abram had lived ten years in the land of Canaan, and gave her to Abram her husband as his wife. <verse-number id="Ge 16:4">4</verse-number>And he went in to Hagar, and she conceived. And <supplied>when</supplied> she<note>That is, Hagar</note> saw that she had conceived, then her mistress grew small in her eyes. <verse-number id="Ge 16:5">5</verse-number>And Sarai said to Abram, “may my harm <supplied>be</supplied> upon you. <idiom-start/>I had my servant sleep with you<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “I put my servant in your lap”</note> and <supplied>when</supplied> she saw that she had conceived, <idiom-start/>she no longer respected me<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “I grew small in her eyes”</note> May Yahweh judge between me and you!” <verse-number id="Ge 16:6">6</verse-number>And Abram said to Sarai, “Look, your servant <supplied>is</supplied> <idiom-start/>under your authority<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “in your hand”</note> Do to her that which <supplied>is</supplied> good in your eyes.” And Sarai mistreated her, and she<note>That is, Hagar</note> fled from her presence. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Hagar and the Angel of Yahweh</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 16:7">7</verse-number>And the angel of Yahweh found her at a spring of water in the wilderness, at the spring by the road of Shur. <verse-number id="Ge 16:8">8</verse-number>And he said to Hagar, the servant of Sarai, “<idiom-start/>From where<idiom-end/><note>Literally “where from this”</note> have you come, and where are you going?” And she said, “I am fleeing from the presence of Sarai my mistress.” <verse-number id="Ge 16:9">9</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> the angel of Yahweh said to her, “Return to your mistress and submit yourself under <idiom-start/>her authority<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “her hand”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 16:10">10</verse-number>And the angel of Yahweh said to her, “<idiom-start/>I will greatly multiply<idiom-end/><note>Literally “multiplying I will multiply”</note> your offspring, so that they cannot be counted for <supplied>their</supplied> abundance.” <verse-number id="Ge 16:11">11</verse-number>And the angel of Yahweh said to her: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Behold, you are pregnant </li1>
				<li2>and shall have a son. </li2>
				<li1>And you shall call his name Ishmael, </li1>
				<li2>for Yahweh has listened to your suffering. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ge 16:12">12</verse-number>And he shall be a wild donkey of a man, </li1>
				<li2>his hand <supplied>will be</supplied> against everyone, </li2>
				<li2>and the hand of everyone <supplied>will be</supplied> against him, </li2>
				<li1>and he will live <idiom-start/>in hostility with all his brothers<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “against the face of all his brothers”</note> </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 16:13">13</verse-number>So<note>Or “And”</note> she called the name of Yahweh who spoke to her, “You <supplied>are</supplied> El-Roi,”<note>“God of seeing”</note> for she said, “Here I have seen after he who sees me.” <verse-number id="Ge 16:14">14</verse-number>Therefore the well was called Beer-Lahai-Roi; behold, it <supplied>is</supplied> between Kadesh and Bered. <verse-number id="Ge 16:15">15</verse-number>And Hagar had a child for Abram, a son. And Abram called the name of his son whom Hagar bore to him, Ishmael. <verse-number id="Ge 16:16">16</verse-number>And Abram <supplied>was</supplied> eighty-six years old when Hagar bore Ishmael to Abram. </p>
		</chapter>