<chapter id="Ge 17">
			<pericope>Abram and Circumcision, the Sign of the Covenant</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 17:1">1</verse-number>When<note>Literally “And it happened that”</note> Abram <supplied>was</supplied> ninety-nine years old Yahweh appeared to Abram. And he said to him, “I <supplied>am</supplied> El-Shaddai;<note>Often translated, “God Almighty”</note> walk before me and be blameless <verse-number id="Ge 17:2">2</verse-number>so that<note>Or “and”</note> I may make my covenant between me and you, and may multiply you <idiom-start/>exceedingly<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “with very very”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 17:3">3</verse-number>Then Abram fell upon his face and God spoke with him, saying, <verse-number id="Ge 17:4">4</verse-number>“<supplied>As for</supplied> me, behold, my covenant <supplied>shall be</supplied> with you, and you shall be the father of a multitude of nations. <verse-number id="Ge 17:5">5</verse-number>Your name shall no longer be called Abram, but your name shall be Abraham, for I will make you the father of a multitude of nations. <verse-number id="Ge 17:6">6</verse-number>And I will make you <idiom-start/>exceedingly<idiom-end/><note>Literally “with very very”</note> fruitful. I will make you a nation, and kings shall go out from you. <verse-number id="Ge 17:7">7</verse-number>And I will establish my covenant between me and you, and between your offspring after you, throughout their generations as an everlasting covenant to be as God for you and to your offspring after you. <verse-number id="Ge 17:8">8</verse-number>And I will give to you and to your offspring after you <idiom-start/>the land in which you are living as an alien<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “a land of your sojournings”</note> all the land of Canaan, as an everlasting property. And I will be to them as God.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 17:9">9</verse-number>And God said to Abraham, “Now <supplied>as for</supplied> you, you must keep my covenant, you and your offspring after you, throughout their generations. <verse-number id="Ge 17:10">10</verse-number>This <supplied>is</supplied> my covenant which you shall keep, between me and you, and <supplied>also</supplied> with<note>Or “between”</note> your offspring after you: Every male among you shall be circumcised. <verse-number id="Ge 17:11">11</verse-number>And you shall circumcise the flesh of your foreskin, and it shall be a sign of the covenant between me and you. <verse-number id="Ge 17:12">12</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>at eight days of age<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a son of eight days”</note> you shall yourselves circumcise every male <supplied>belonging</supplied> to your generations <supplied>and</supplied> <idiom-start/>the servant born in your house and the one bought from any foreigner<idiom-end/><note>Literally “those born of house and acquisition of money from every son of a foreigner”</note> who is not from your offspring. <verse-number id="Ge 17:13">13</verse-number><idiom-start/>You must certainly circumcise<idiom-end/><note>Literally “circumcising you will circumcise”</note> <idiom-start/>the servant born in your house and the one bought from any foreigner<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “those born of house and acquisition of money from every son of a foreigner”</note> And my covenant shall be with your flesh as an everlasting covenant. <verse-number id="Ge 17:14">14</verse-number>And <supplied>as for any</supplied> uncircumcised male who has not circumcised the flesh of his foreskin, that person shall be cut off from his<note>Literally “her”; the reference is still to a male; the pronoun is feminine because “person” (<i>nephesh</i>) is grammatically feminine</note> people. He has broken my covenant. <verse-number id="Ge 17:15">15</verse-number>And God said to Abraham, “<supplied>as for</supplied> Sarai your wife, you shall not call her name Sarai, for Sarah <supplied>shall be</supplied> her name. <verse-number id="Ge 17:16">16</verse-number>And I will bless her; moreover, I give to you from her a son. And I will bless her, and <idiom-start/>she shall give rise to nations<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “she shall become to nations”</note> Kings of peoples shall come<note>Or “be”</note> from her.” <verse-number id="Ge 17:17">17</verse-number>And Abraham fell upon his face and laughed. And he said in his heart, “<idiom-start/>Can a child be born to a man a hundred years old<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to a man one hundred years old can he be born?”</note> or <idiom-start/>can Sarah bear a child at ninety<idiom-end/>?”<note>Literally “can ninety-year-old Sarah bear a child?”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 17:18">18</verse-number>And Abraham said to God, “Oh that Ishmael might live before you!” <verse-number id="Ge 17:19">19</verse-number>And God said, “No, but Sarah your wife shall bear a son for you, and you shall call his name Isaac. And I will establish my covenant with him as an everlasting covenant to his offspring after him. <verse-number id="Ge 17:20">20</verse-number>And <supplied>as for</supplied> Ishmael, I have heard you. Behold, I will bless him and I will make him fruitful, and I will multiply him <idiom-start/>exceedingly<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “with very very”</note> He shall father twelve princes, and I will make him a great nation. <verse-number id="Ge 17:21">21</verse-number>But my covenant I will establish with Isaac, whom Sarah shall bear to you at this appointed time next year.” <verse-number id="Ge 17:22">22</verse-number>When<note>Or “And”</note> he finished speaking with him, God went up from Abraham. <verse-number id="Ge 17:23">23</verse-number>And Abraham took Ishmael his son and all who were born of his house, and all <supplied>those</supplied> acquired by his money, every male among the men of Abraham’s house, and he circumcised the flesh of their foreskin on the same day that God spoke with him. <verse-number id="Ge 17:24">24</verse-number>Abraham <supplied>was</supplied> ninety-nine years old when he circumcised the flesh of his foreskin. <verse-number id="Ge 17:25">25</verse-number>And Ishmael his son <supplied>was</supplied> thirteen years old when he circumcised the flesh of his foreskin. <verse-number id="Ge 17:26">26</verse-number>Abraham and his son Ishmael <supplied>were</supplied> circumcised on the same day. <verse-number id="Ge 17:27">27</verse-number>And all the men of his house, <idiom-start/>those born in the house, and those acquired by money from a foreigner<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “born of house and acquisition of money from the son of a foreigner”</note> were circumcised with him. </p>
		</chapter>