<chapter id="Ge 19">
			<pericope>The Rescue of Lot from Sodom</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 19:1">1</verse-number>And the two angels came to Sodom in the evening. And Lot was sitting in the gateway of Sodom. Then Lot saw <supplied>them</supplied> and stood up to meet them. And he bowed down <supplied>with his</supplied> face to the ground. <verse-number id="Ge 19:2">2</verse-number>And he said, “Behold, my lords, please turn aside into the house of your servant and spend the night and wash your feet. Then you can rise early and go on your way.” And they said, “No, but we will spend the night in the square.” <verse-number id="Ge 19:3">3</verse-number>But <idiom-start/>he urged them strongly<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “he pressed upon them very”</note> and they turned aside with him and came into his house. And he made a meal for them and baked unleavened bread, and they ate. <verse-number id="Ge 19:4">4</verse-number>Before they laid down, the men of the city, the men of Sodom, both young and old, all the people <idiom-start/>to the last man<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from the end”</note> surrounded the house. <verse-number id="Ge 19:5">5</verse-number>And they called to Lot and said to him, “Where <supplied>are</supplied> the men who came to you tonight? Bring them out to us so that we may know<note>Hebrew idiom for sexual intercourse (cp. <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ge 4:1">Gen 4:1</cite>)</note> them.” <verse-number id="Ge 19:6">6</verse-number>But Lot went out to them at the entrance, and he shut the door behind him. <verse-number id="Ge 19:7">7</verse-number>And he said, “No, my brothers, please do not do <supplied>such a</supplied> wrong <supplied>thing</supplied>. <verse-number id="Ge 19:8">8</verse-number>Behold, I have two daughters who have not known<note>Hebrew idiom for sexual intercourse (cp. <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ge 4:1">Gen 4:1</cite>)</note> a man. Please, let me bring them out to you; then do to them as <supplied>it seems</supplied> good in your eyes. Only to these men do not do <supplied>this</supplied> thing, since they came under<idiom-start/> my roof<idiom-end/><note>Literally “my beam”</note> for protection.” <verse-number id="Ge 19:9">9</verse-number>But they said, “Step aside!” Then they said, “<idiom-start/>This fellow<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the one”</note> came to dwell as a foreigner and he acts as a judge! Now we shall do worse to you than them!” And they pressed very hard against the man, against Lot, and they drew near to break the door. <verse-number id="Ge 19:10">10</verse-number>Then the men reached out <supplied>with</supplied> their hands and brought Lot in to them, into the house, and they shut the door. <verse-number id="Ge 19:11">11</verse-number>And the men who <supplied>were</supplied> at the entrance of the house they struck with blindness, both small and great, and they were unable to find the entrance. <verse-number id="Ge 19:12">12</verse-number>Then the men said to Lot, “Who <supplied>is</supplied> here with you? Bring out from the place <supplied>your</supplied> sons-in-law, and your sons and your daughters, and all who <supplied>are</supplied> with you in the city. <verse-number id="Ge 19:13">13</verse-number>For we are <supplied>about to</supplied> destroy this place, because their cry has become great before Yahweh. Yahweh sent us to destroy it.” <verse-number id="Ge 19:14">14</verse-number>Then Lot went out and spoke to his sons-in-law <supplied>who were</supplied> taking<note>That is, marrying</note> his daughters and said, “Get up! Go out from this place, because Yahweh <supplied>is going</supplied> to destroy the city!” But <idiom-start/>it seemed like a joke<idiom-end/><note>Literally “it was as one making fun”</note> in the eyes of his sons-in-law. <verse-number id="Ge 19:15">15</verse-number>And as the dawn came up the angels urged Lot saying, “Get up, take your wife and your two daughters <idiom-start/>who are staying with you<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “who are found”</note> lest you be destroyed with the punishment of the city.” <verse-number id="Ge 19:16">16</verse-number>But <supplied>when</supplied> he lingered, the men seized him by his hand and his wife’s hand, and his two daughters by hand, on account of the mercy of Yahweh upon him. And they brought him out and set him outside of the city. <verse-number id="Ge 19:17">17</verse-number>And after bringing them outside <supplied>one</supplied> said, “Flee for your life; do not look behind you, and do not stand anywhere in the plain. Flee to the mountains lest you be destroyed.” <verse-number id="Ge 19:18">18</verse-number>And Lot said to them, “No, please, my lords. <verse-number id="Ge 19:19">19</verse-number>Behold, your servant has found favor in your eyes and <idiom-start/>you have shown me great kindness<idiom-end/><note>Literally “your kindness which you have done to me you have made great”</note> in saving my life. But I cannot flee to the mountains, lest the disaster overtake me and I die. <verse-number id="Ge 19:20">20</verse-number>Behold, this city <supplied>is</supplied> near <supplied>enough</supplied> to flee there, and it <supplied>is a</supplied> little <supplied>one</supplied>. Please, let me flee there. Is it not a little <supplied>one</supplied>? Then my life shall be saved.” <verse-number id="Ge 19:21">21</verse-number>And he said to him, “Behold, <idiom-start/>I will grant this favor as well<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “I am lifting up your face also concerning this thing”</note> that I will not overthrow the city of which you have spoken. <verse-number id="Ge 19:22">22</verse-number>Escape there quickly, for I cannot do <supplied>this</supplied> thing until you get there.” Therefore, there name of the city was called Zoar. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Destruction of Sodom</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 19:23">23</verse-number><supplied>After</supplied> the sun <idiom-start/>had risen<idiom-end/><note>Literally “had gone out”</note> upon the earth and Lot had entered Zoar, <verse-number id="Ge 19:24">24</verse-number>Yahweh rained down from heaven upon Sodom and Gomorrah brimstone and fire from Yahweh. <verse-number id="Ge 19:25">25</verse-number>And he overthrew those cities and the whole plain, and the inhabitants of the cities and the vegetation of the ground. <verse-number id="Ge 19:26">26</verse-number>But his<note>That is, Lot’s</note> wife looked <idiom-start/>back<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “behind him”</note> and she became a pillar of salt. <verse-number id="Ge 19:27">27</verse-number>And Abraham arose early in the morning <supplied>and went</supplied> to the place where he had stood before Yahweh. <verse-number id="Ge 19:28">28</verse-number>And he looked down upon the surface of Sodom and Gomorrah, and upon the whole surface of the land, the plain. And he saw that,<note>Or “and”</note> behold, the smoke of the land went up like the smoke of a smelting furnace. <verse-number id="Ge 19:29">29</verse-number>So it was, when God destroyed the cities of the plain that God remembered Abraham and sent Lot out from the midst of the overthrow, when he overthrew the cities in which Lot lived. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Lot and His Daughters</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 19:30">30</verse-number>And Lot went out from Zoar and settled in the hill country<note>Or “mountain”</note> with his two daughters, for he was afraid to stay in Zoar. So he lived in a cave, he and his two daughters. <verse-number id="Ge 19:31">31</verse-number>And the firstborn <supplied>daughter</supplied> said to the younger one, “Our father is old, and there is no man in the land to come in to us according to the manner of all the land. <verse-number id="Ge 19:32">32</verse-number>Come, let us give our father wine to drink and let us lie with him<note>Idiom for “have sexual intercourse with him”</note> that <idiom-start/>we may secure descendants through our father<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “that we might preserve offspring from our father”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 19:33">33</verse-number>And they gave their father wine to drink that night, and the firstborn went and lay with her father, but he did not know when she lay down or when she got up. <verse-number id="Ge 19:34">34</verse-number>And it happened <supplied>that</supplied>, the next day the firstborn said to the younger one, “Look, I laid with my father last night. Let us give him wine to drink also tonight, then go and lie with him that <idiom-start/>we may secure descendants through our father<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “that we might preserve offspring from our father”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 19:35">35</verse-number>And they gave their father wine to drink again that night, and the younger got up and lay with him, but he did not know when she lay down or when she got up. <verse-number id="Ge 19:36">36</verse-number>And the two daughters of Lot became pregnant by their father. <verse-number id="Ge 19:37">37</verse-number>The firstborn gave birth to a son, and she called his name Moab. He <supplied>is</supplied> the father of Moab until this day. <verse-number id="Ge 19:38">38</verse-number>And the younger, she also gave birth to a son, and she called his name Ben-Ammi. He <supplied>is</supplied> the father of the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Ammon”</note> until this day. </p>
		</chapter>