<chapter id="Ge 20">
			<pericope>Abraham and Abimelech</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 20:1">1</verse-number>And Abraham journeyed from there to the land of the Negev, and he settled between Kadesh and Shur. And he dwelled as an alien in Gerar. <verse-number id="Ge 20:2">2</verse-number>And Abraham said about Sarah his wife, “She <supplied>is</supplied> my sister.” And Abimelech king of Gerar sent and took Sarah. <verse-number id="Ge 20:3">3</verse-number>And God came to Abimelech in a dream at night. And he said to him, “Look, you <supplied>are</supplied> a dead man on account of the woman you have taken. For she <supplied>is</supplied> <idiom-start/>a married woman<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “married of a husband” or “a woman owned by a husband”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 20:4">4</verse-number>Now Abimelech had not approached her, so he said, “my Lord, will you even kill a righteous people?” <verse-number id="Ge 20:5">5</verse-number>Did not he himself say to me, ‘She <supplied>is</supplied> my sister’? And she herself said, ‘He <supplied>is</supplied> my brother.’ With integrity of my heart and with cleanness of my hands I did this.” <verse-number id="Ge 20:6">6</verse-number>Then God said to him in the dream, “Yes,<note>Or “Also”</note> I know that in the integrity of your heart you did this, and I also <idiom-start/>kept you from sinning<idiom-end/><note>Literally “kept back from sinning”</note> against me. Therefore, I did not allow you to touch her. <verse-number id="Ge 20:7">7</verse-number>So now, return the wife of the man, for he <supplied>is</supplied> a prophet, so that he will pray for you and you will live. And <idiom-start/>if you do not return her<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “If there is not for you a returning”</note> know that you will certainly die, and all that <supplied>are</supplied> yours.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 20:8">8</verse-number>So Abimelech rose early in the morning. And he called all his servants and <idiom-start/>told them all these things<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “said all these things in their ears”</note> and the men were very afraid. <verse-number id="Ge 20:9">9</verse-number>And Abimelech called for Abraham and said to him, “What have you done to us? And how have I sinned against you that you brought upon me and upon my kingdom a great sin? You have done things to me that should not be done.” <verse-number id="Ge 20:10">10</verse-number>And Abimelech said to Abraham, “<idiom-start/>What were you thinking<idiom-end/><note>Literally “What have you seen?”</note> that you did this thing?” <verse-number id="Ge 20:11">11</verse-number>And Abraham said, “Because I thought, surely there is no fear of God in this place; they will kill me on account of the matter of my wife. <verse-number id="Ge 20:12">12</verse-number><idiom-start/>Besides<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “And also moreover”</note> she <supplied>is</supplied> my sister, the daughter of my father, but not the daughter of my mother. And she became my wife. <verse-number id="Ge 20:13">13</verse-number>And it happened <supplied>that</supplied> as God caused me to wander from the house of my father I said to her, ‘This <supplied>is</supplied> your loyal kindness that you must do for me at every place where we come: say concerning me, “He <supplied>is</supplied> my brother.” ’ ” <verse-number id="Ge 20:14">14</verse-number>And Abimelech took sheep and cattle and male slaves and female slaves, and he gave <supplied>them</supplied> to Abraham. And he returned Sarah his wife to him. <verse-number id="Ge 20:15">15</verse-number>And Abimelech said, “Here <supplied>is</supplied> my land before you; settle <idiom-start/>where it pleases you<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “in the good in your eyes”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 20:16">16</verse-number>And to Sarah he said, “Look, I have given a thousand <supplied>pieces of</supplied> silver to your brother. It <supplied>shall be</supplied> <idiom-start/>an exoneration<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “a covering of the eyes”</note> <idiom-start/>You are vindicated before all who are with you<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “to all who are with you and with all you are vindicated”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 20:17">17</verse-number>And Abraham prayed to God, and God healed Abimelech and his wife and his female servants so that they <supplied>could</supplied> bear children <supplied>again</supplied>. <verse-number id="Ge 20:18">18</verse-number>For Yahweh had completely closed up all the wombs of the house of Abimelech because of the matter of Sarah, the wife of Abraham. </p>
		</chapter>