<chapter id="Ge 21">
			<pericope>The Birth of Isaac</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 21:1">1</verse-number>And Yahweh visited Sarah as he had said. And Yahweh did to Sarah as he had promised. <verse-number id="Ge 21:2">2</verse-number>And she conceived, and Sarah bore to Abraham a son in his old age at the appointed time that God had told him. <verse-number id="Ge 21:3">3</verse-number>And Abraham called the name of his son who was born to him, whom Sarah bore to him, Isaac. <verse-number id="Ge 21:4">4</verse-number>And Abraham circumcised Isaac his son <supplied>when he was</supplied> eight days old, as God had commanded him. <verse-number id="Ge 21:5">5</verse-number>And Abraham <supplied>was</supplied> one hundred years old when Isaac his son was born to him. <verse-number id="Ge 21:6">6</verse-number>And Sarah said, “God has made laughter for me; all who hear will laugh for me.” <verse-number id="Ge 21:7">7</verse-number>And she said, “Who would announce to Abraham <supplied>that</supplied> Sarah would nurse children? Yet I have borne a son <supplied>to Abraham</supplied> in his old age.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Hagar and Ishmael</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 21:8">8</verse-number>And the child grew and was weaned. And Abraham made a great feast on the day Isaac was weaned. <verse-number id="Ge 21:9">9</verse-number>And Sarah saw the son of Hagar the Egyptian, whom she had borne Abraham, mocking. <verse-number id="Ge 21:10">10</verse-number>Then she said to Abraham, “Drive out this slave woman and her son, for the son of this slave woman will not be heir with my son, with Isaac.” <verse-number id="Ge 21:11">11</verse-number>And the matter <idiom-start/>displeased Abraham very much<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was very bad in the eyes of Abraham”</note> on account of his son. <verse-number id="Ge 21:12">12</verse-number>Then God said to Abraham, “<idiom-start/>Do not be displeased<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Do not let it be bad”</note> on account of the boy and on account of the slave woman. <idiom-start/>Listen to everything that Sarah said to you<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “Everything Sarah said to you, listen with respect to her voice”</note> for through Isaac <supplied>your</supplied> offspring will be named. <verse-number id="Ge 21:13">13</verse-number>And I will also make the son of the slave woman into a nation, for he is your offspring.” <verse-number id="Ge 21:14">14</verse-number>Then Abraham rose up early in the morning and took bread and a skin of water and gave <supplied>it</supplied> to Hagar, putting <supplied>it</supplied> on her shoulder. And he sent her away with the child, and she went, wandering about in the wilderness, in Beersheba. <verse-number id="Ge 21:15">15</verse-number>And when the water was finished from the skin, she put the child under one of the bushes. <verse-number id="Ge 21:16">16</verse-number>And she went and <idiom-start/>she sat a good distance away<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “she sat with respect to her, opposite, far away, as the shooting of a bow”</note> for she said, “Let me not see the child’s death.” So she sat away from him and lifted up her voice and wept. <verse-number id="Ge 21:17">17</verse-number>And God heard the cry<note>Or “voice”</note> of the boy and the angel of God called to Hagar from the heavens and said to her, “<idiom-start/>What is the matter<idiom-end/><note>Literally “What to you”</note> Hagar? Do not be afraid, for God has heard the cry<note>Or “voice”</note> of the boy <idiom-start/>from where he is<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “in which he <supplied>is</supplied> there”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 21:18">18</verse-number>Get up, take up the boy and take him with your hand, for I will make him a great nation.” <verse-number id="Ge 21:19">19</verse-number>And God opened her eyes, and she saw a well of water. And she went and filled the skin with water and gave a drink to the boy. <verse-number id="Ge 21:20">20</verse-number>And God was with the boy, and he grew and lived in the wilderness. And he became <idiom-start/>an expert with a bow<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “an archer with the bow”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 21:21">21</verse-number>And he lived in the wilderness of Paran. And his mother took a wife for him from the land of Egypt. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Covenant Between Abraham and Abimelech</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 21:22">22</verse-number>And it happened <supplied>that</supplied> at that time, Abimelech and Phicol, the commander of his army, said to Abraham, “God <supplied>is</supplied> with you, in all that you do. <verse-number id="Ge 21:23">23</verse-number>So now, swear to me here by God <supplied>that</supplied> you will not deal with me falsely, or with my descendants, or my posterity. According to the kindness that I have done to you, you shall <supplied>pledge</supplied> to do with me and with the land where you have dwelled as an alien.” <verse-number id="Ge 21:24">24</verse-number>And Abraham said, “I swear.” <verse-number id="Ge 21:25">25</verse-number>Then Abraham complained to Abimelech on account of the well of water that servants of Abimelech had seized. <verse-number id="Ge 21:26">26</verse-number>And Abimelech said, “I do not know who did this thing, neither did you tell me, nor have I heard <supplied>of it</supplied> except for today.” <verse-number id="Ge 21:27">27</verse-number>And Abraham took sheep and cattle and gave <supplied>them</supplied> to Abimelech. And the two of them <idiom-start/>made<idiom-end/><note>Literally “cut”</note> a covenant. <verse-number id="Ge 21:28">28</verse-number>Then Abraham set <supplied>off</supplied> seven ewe-lambs of the flock by themselves. <verse-number id="Ge 21:29">29</verse-number>And Abimelech said to Abraham, “What <supplied>is the meaning of</supplied> these seven ewe-lambs that you have set <supplied>off</supplied> by themselves?” <verse-number id="Ge 21:30">30</verse-number>And he said, “You shall take the seven ewe-lambs from my hand <idiom-start/>as proof on my behalf<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for the sake that it shall be a witness for me”</note> that I dug this well.” <verse-number id="Ge 21:31">31</verse-number>Therefore that place is called Beersheba, because there the two of them swore an oath. <verse-number id="Ge 21:32">32</verse-number>And they <idiom-start/>made<idiom-end/><note>Literally “cut”</note> a covenant at Beersheba. And Abimelech, and Phicol his army commander stood and returned to the land of the Philistines. <verse-number id="Ge 21:33">33</verse-number>And he<note>That is, Abraham</note> planted a tamarisk tree in Beersheba, and there he called on the name of Yahweh, <idiom-start/>the everlasting God<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “El-Olam”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 21:34">34</verse-number>And Abraham dwelled as an alien in the land of the Philistines many days. </p>
		</chapter>