<chapter id="Ge 23">
			<pericope>Sarah’s Death and Burial</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 23:1">1</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>Sarah lived<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the lives of Sarah were”</note> one hundred and twenty-seven years; <supplied>these were</supplied> the years of the life of Sarah. <verse-number id="Ge 23:2">2</verse-number>And Sarah died in Kiriath Arba; that <supplied>is</supplied> Hebron, in the land of Canaan. <verse-number id="Ge 23:3">3</verse-number>And Abraham went to mourn for Sarah and to weep for her. And Abraham rose up from his dead, and he spoke to the Hittites<note>Or “sons of Heth”</note> <supplied>and</supplied> said, <verse-number id="Ge 23:4">4</verse-number>“I <supplied>am</supplied> a stranger and an alien among you; give to me <idiom-start/>my own burial site<idiom-end/><note>Literally “ownership of a grave”</note> among you so that I may bury my dead from before me.” <verse-number id="Ge 23:5">5</verse-number>And the Hittites<note>Or “sons of Heth”</note> answered Abraham <supplied>and</supplied> said to him, <verse-number id="Ge 23:6">6</verse-number>“Hear us, my lord, you <supplied>are</supplied> a mighty prince<note>Or “prince of God”</note> in our midst. Bury your dead in the choicest of our burial sites. None of us <idiom-start/>will withhold his burial site<idiom-end/><note>Literally “will withhold from himself his burial site</note> from you <supplied>for</supplied> burying your dead.” <verse-number id="Ge 23:7">7</verse-number>And Abraham rose up and bowed to the people of the land, to the Hittites.<note>Or “sons of Heth”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 23:8">8</verse-number>And he spoke with them, saying, “<idiom-start/>If you are willing<idiom-end/><note>Literally “if there is with your inner selves / souls”</note> <supplied>that</supplied> I bury my dead from before me, hear me and intercede for me with Ephron the son of Zohar, <verse-number id="Ge 23:9">9</verse-number>that he may sell<note>Or “give”</note> to me the cave of Machpelah which <idiom-start/>belongs to him<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “which <supplied>is</supplied> to him”</note> which <supplied>is</supplied> at the end of his field. At full value let him sell<note>Or “give”</note> <supplied>it</supplied> to me in your midst as <idiom-start/>a burial site<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “ownership of a grave”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 23:10">10</verse-number>Now Ephron was sitting among the Hittites.<note>Or “sons of Heth”</note> And Ephron the Hittite answered Abraham in the hearing of the Hittites<note>Or “sons of Heth”</note> with respect to all <supplied>who were</supplied> entering the gate of his city, <supplied>and</supplied> said, <verse-number id="Ge 23:11">11</verse-number>“No, my lord, hear me. I give you the field and the cave which <supplied>is</supplied> in it, I <supplied>also</supplied> give it to you in the sight of the children of my people I give it to you. Bury your dead.” <verse-number id="Ge 23:12">12</verse-number>And Abraham bowed before the people of the land. <verse-number id="Ge 23:13">13</verse-number>And he spoke to Ephron in the hearing of the people of the land, saying, “<idiom-start/>If only you will hear me<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Only if you perhaps hear me”</note>—I give the price of the field. Take <supplied>it</supplied> from me that I may bury my dead there.” <verse-number id="Ge 23:14">14</verse-number>And Ephron answered Abraham, saying to him, <verse-number id="Ge 23:15">15</verse-number>“My lord, hear me. A <supplied>piece of</supplied> land <supplied>worth</supplied> four hundred shekels of silver—what <supplied>is</supplied> that between me and you? Bury your dead.” <verse-number id="Ge 23:16">16</verse-number>Then Abraham listened to Ephron, and Abraham weighed for Ephron the silver that he had named<note>Or “spoken”</note> in the hearing of the Hittites:<note>Or “sons of Heth”</note> four hundred shekels of silver <idiom-start/>at the merchants’ current rate<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “passing to the merchant”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 23:17">17</verse-number>So the field of Ephron which <supplied>was</supplied> in the Machpelah, which <supplied>was</supplied> near Mamre—the field and the cave which <supplied>was</supplied> in it, with all the trees that <supplied>were</supplied> in the field, which <supplied>were</supplied> within all its surrounding boundaries—<idiom-start/>passed<idiom-end/><note>Literally “went up”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 23:18">18</verse-number>to Abraham as a property in the presence of the Hittites,<note>Or “sons of Heth”</note> with respect to all <supplied>who were</supplied> entering the gate of his city. <verse-number id="Ge 23:19">19</verse-number>And thus afterward Abraham buried Sarah his wife in the cave of the field of Machpelah near Mamre; that <supplied>is</supplied> Hebron, in the land of Canaan. <verse-number id="Ge 23:20">20</verse-number>And the field and the cave which <supplied>was</supplied> in it <idiom-start/>passed<idiom-end/><note>Literally “went up”</note> to Abraham as <idiom-start/>a burial site<idiom-end/><note>Literally “ownership of a grave”</note> from the Hittites.<note>Or “sons of Heth”</note> </p>
		</chapter>