<chapter id="Ge 25">
			<pericope>The Death and Descendants of Abraham</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 25:1">1</verse-number>Now Abraham again took a wife, and her name <supplied>was</supplied> Keturah. <verse-number id="Ge 25:2">2</verse-number>And she bore to him Zimran, Jokshan, Medan, Midian, Ishbak, and Shuah. <verse-number id="Ge 25:3">3</verse-number>And Jokshan fathered Sheba and Dedan. And the sons of Dedan were Asshurim and Letushim and Leummim. <verse-number id="Ge 25:4">4</verse-number>And the sons of Midian <supplied>were</supplied> Ephah, Epher, Hanoch, Abidah, and Eldaah. All of these <supplied>were</supplied> the children of Keturah. <verse-number id="Ge 25:5">5</verse-number>And Abraham gave all he had to Isaac. <verse-number id="Ge 25:6">6</verse-number>But to the sons of Abraham’s concubines Abraham gave gifts. And while he <supplied>was</supplied> still living he sent them away eastward, <supplied>away</supplied> from his son Isaac, to the land of the east. <verse-number id="Ge 25:7">7</verse-number>Now these <supplied>are</supplied> the days of the years of <idiom-start/>the life of Abraham<idiom-end/>:<note>Literally “the years of the life of Abraham which he lived”</note> one hundred and seventy-five years. <verse-number id="Ge 25:8">8</verse-number>And Abraham passed away and died in a good old age, old and full of years. And he was gathered to his people. <verse-number id="Ge 25:9">9</verse-number>And Isaac and Ishmael his sons buried him in the cave of Machpelah, in the field of Ephron, son of Zohar the Hittite, that <supplied>was</supplied> east of Mamre, <verse-number id="Ge 25:10">10</verse-number>the field that Abraham had bought from the Hittites.<note>Or “sons of Heth”</note> There Abraham was buried and Sarah his wife. <verse-number id="Ge 25:11">11</verse-number>And it happened <supplied>that</supplied> after the death of Abraham God blessed Isaac his son, and Isaac settled at Beer-Lahai-Roi. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 25:12">12</verse-number>Now these <supplied>are</supplied> the generations<note>Or “family records”</note> of Ishmael, the son of Abraham, that Hagar the Egyptian, the maidservant of Sarah, bore to Abraham. <verse-number id="Ge 25:13">13</verse-number>And these are the names of the sons of Ishmael, by their names according to their family records. The firstborn of Ishmael <supplied>was</supplied> Nebaioth, then Kedar, Adbeel, Mibsam, <verse-number id="Ge 25:14">14</verse-number>Mishma, Dumah, Massa, <verse-number id="Ge 25:15">15</verse-number>Hadad, Tema, Jetur, Naphish, and Kedemah.<verse-number id="Ge 25:16">16</verse-number>These <supplied>are</supplied> the sons of Ishmael, and these <supplied>are</supplied> their names by their villages and by their encampments—12 leaders according to their tribes. <verse-number id="Ge 25:17">17</verse-number>Now these <supplied>are</supplied> the years of the life of Ishmael: 137 years. And he passed away and died, and was gathered to his people.<verse-number id="Ge 25:18">18</verse-number>They settled from Havilah to Shur, which <supplied>was</supplied> opposite<note>Or “upon the face of”</note> Egypt, going toward Asshur, opposite;<note>Or “upon the face of”</note> he <idiom-start/>settled<idiom-end/><note>Literally “fell”</note> opposite<note>Or “upon the face of”</note> all his brothers. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jacob and Esau</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 25:19">19</verse-number>Now these <supplied>are</supplied> the generations<note>Or “family records”</note> of Isaac, the son of Abraham. Abraham fathered Isaac, <verse-number id="Ge 25:20">20</verse-number>And Isaac was <idiom-start/>forty years old<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a son of forty years”</note> when he took Rebekah, the daughter of Bethuel the Aramean of Paddan-Aram, the sister of Laban the Aramean, as his wife. <verse-number id="Ge 25:21">21</verse-number>And Isaac prayed to Yahweh on behalf of his wife, for she <supplied>was</supplied> barren. And Yahweh responded to his prayer, and Rebekah his wife conceived. <verse-number id="Ge 25:22">22</verse-number>And the children in her womb jostled each other, and she said, “<idiom-start/>If it is going to be like this, why be pregnant<idiom-end/>?”<note>Literally “if so, why this I?”</note> And she went to inquire of Yahweh. <verse-number id="Ge 25:23">23</verse-number>And Yahweh said to her, “Two nations <supplied>are</supplied> in your womb, and two peoples <idiom-start/>from birth<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from your bowels”</note> shall be divided. And <idiom-start/>one people shall be stronger than the other<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “people than people shall be stronger”</note> And <supplied>the</supplied> elder shall serve <supplied>the</supplied> younger.” <verse-number id="Ge 25:24">24</verse-number>And when her days to give birth were completed,<note>Or “full”</note> then—behold—twins <supplied>were</supplied> in her womb. <verse-number id="Ge 25:25">25</verse-number>And the first came out red, all <idiom-start/>his body<idiom-end/><note>Literally “of him”</note> <supplied>was</supplied> like a hairy coat, so they called his name Esau. <verse-number id="Ge 25:26">26</verse-number>And afterward his brother came out, and his hand grasped the heel of Esau, so his name was called Jacob. And Isaac <idiom-start/>was sixty years old<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a son of sixty years”</note> at their birth. <verse-number id="Ge 25:27">27</verse-number>And the boys grew up. And Esau <supplied>was</supplied> a skilled<note>Or “knowing” (knowledgeable)</note> hunter, a man of the field, but Jacob <supplied>was</supplied> a peaceful man, living <supplied>in</supplied> tents. <verse-number id="Ge 25:28">28</verse-number>And Isaac loved Esau because <idiom-start/>he could eat of his game<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “game in his mouth”</note> but Rebekah loved Jacob. <verse-number id="Ge 25:29">29</verse-number>Once<note>Or “and”</note> Jacob cooked a thick stew, and Esau came in from the field, and he was exhausted. <verse-number id="Ge 25:30">30</verse-number>And Esau said to Jacob, “Give me <idiom-start/>some of that red stuff<idiom-end/><note>Literally “some of the red, this red”</note> to gulp down, for I am exhausted!” (Therefore his name was called Edom). <verse-number id="Ge 25:31">31</verse-number>Then Jacob said, “Sell me your birthright <idiom-start/>first<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “as the day”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 25:32">32</verse-number>And Esau said, “Look, I am going to die; now what <supplied>is</supplied> this birthright to me?” <verse-number id="Ge 25:33">33</verse-number>Then Jacob said, “Swear to me <idiom-start/>first<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “as the day”</note> And he swore to him, and sold his birthright to Jacob. <verse-number id="Ge 25:34">34</verse-number>Then Jacob gave Esau bread, and thick lentil stew, and he ate and drank. Then he got up and went away. So Esau despised his birthright. </p>
		</chapter>