<chapter id="Ge 27">
			<pericope>Jacob Steals Esau’s Blessing</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 27:1">1</verse-number>And it happened <supplied>that</supplied> when Isaac <supplied>was</supplied> old and <idiom-start/>his eyesight was weak<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “his eyes were weak from seeing”</note> he called Esau his older son and said to him, “My son.” And he<note>That is, Esau</note> said to him, “Here I <supplied>am</supplied>.” <verse-number id="Ge 27:2">2</verse-number>And he said, “Look, I <supplied>am</supplied> old; I do not know the day of my death. <verse-number id="Ge 27:3">3</verse-number>So now, take your weapons, your quiver and your bow, and go out to the field and hunt food for me. <verse-number id="Ge 27:4">4</verse-number>Then make for me tasty food like I love, and bring <supplied>it</supplied> to me. And I will eat <supplied>it</supplied> so that I<note>Or “my soul”</note> can bless you before I die. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 27:5">5</verse-number>Now Rebekah <supplied>was</supplied> listening as Isaac spoke to Esau his son, and <supplied>when</supplied> Esau went to the field to hunt wild game to bring <supplied>back</supplied>, <verse-number id="Ge 27:6">6</verse-number>Rebekah said to Jacob her son, “Look, I heard your father speaking to Esau your brother saying, <verse-number id="Ge 27:7">7</verse-number>‘Bring wild game to me and prepare tasty food so I can eat <supplied>it</supplied> and bless you before Yahweh before my death.’ <verse-number id="Ge 27:8">8</verse-number>So now, my son, listen to my voice, to what I command you. <verse-number id="Ge 27:9">9</verse-number>Go to the flock and take two good young goats from it for me, and I will prepare them <supplied>as</supplied> tasty food for your father, just as he likes. <verse-number id="Ge 27:10">10</verse-number>Then you must take it to your father and he will eat <supplied>it</supplied> so that he may bless you before his death.” <verse-number id="Ge 27:11">11</verse-number>Then Jacob said to his mother, “Behold, Esau my brother <supplied>is</supplied> a hairy man, but I <supplied>am</supplied> a smooth man. <verse-number id="Ge 27:12">12</verse-number>Perhaps my father will feel me and I will be in his eyes <supplied>as</supplied> a mocker, and he will bring upon me a curse and not a blessing.” <verse-number id="Ge 27:13">13</verse-number>Then his mother said to him, “Your curse be upon me, my son, only listen to my voice—go and get <supplied>them</supplied> for me.” <verse-number id="Ge 27:14">14</verse-number>So he went and took <supplied>them</supplied>, and brought <supplied>them</supplied> to his mother, and his mother prepared tasty food as his father liked. <verse-number id="Ge 27:15">15</verse-number>Then Rebekah took <supplied>some of</supplied> her older son Esau’s best garments that <supplied>were</supplied> with her in the house, and she put <supplied>them</supplied> on Jacob her younger son. <verse-number id="Ge 27:16">16</verse-number>And she put the skins of the young goats over his hands and over the smooth <supplied>part of</supplied> his neck.<verse-number id="Ge 27:17">17</verse-number>And she put the tasty food and the bread that she had made into the hand of Jacob, her son. <verse-number id="Ge 27:18">18</verse-number>And he went to his father and said, “My father.” And he said, “Here I <supplied>am</supplied>. Who <supplied>are</supplied> you, my son?” <verse-number id="Ge 27:19">19</verse-number>And Jacob said to his father, “I <supplied>am</supplied> Esau, your firstborn. I have done as you told me. Please get up, sit up and eat from my wild game so that you<note>Or “your soul”</note> may bless me.” <verse-number id="Ge 27:20">20</verse-number>Then Isaac said to his son, “<idiom-start/>How<idiom-end/><note>Literally “what is this?”</note> did you find <supplied>it</supplied> so quickly, my son?” And he said, “Because Yahweh your God <idiom-start/>caused me to find it<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “made it to happen before me”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 27:21">21</verse-number>Then Isaac said to Jacob, “Please, come near and let me feel you, my son. <idiom-start/>Are you really<idiom-end/><note>Literally “are you this one?”</note> my son Esau or not?” <verse-number id="Ge 27:22">22</verse-number>And Jacob drew near to Isaac his father. And he felt him and said, “The voice <supplied>is</supplied> the voice of Jacob, but the hands <supplied>are</supplied> the hands of Esau.” <verse-number id="Ge 27:23">23</verse-number>And he did not recognize him because his hands were hairy like the hands of Esau his brother. And he blessed him. <verse-number id="Ge 27:24">24</verse-number>And he said, “<idiom-start/>Are you really<idiom-end/><note>Literally “are you this one?”</note> my son Esau?” And he said, “I <supplied>am</supplied>.” <verse-number id="Ge 27:25">25</verse-number>Then he said, “Bring <supplied>it</supplied> near to me that I may eat from the game of my son, so that I<note>Or “my soul”</note> may bless you.” And he brought <supplied>it</supplied> to him, and he ate. And he brought wine to him, and he drank. <verse-number id="Ge 27:26">26</verse-number>Then his father Isaac said to him, “Come near and kiss me, my son.” <verse-number id="Ge 27:27">27</verse-number>And he drew near and kissed him. And he<note>That is, Isaac</note> smelled the smell of his garments, and he blessed him and said, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Look, the smell of my son <supplied>is</supplied> like the smell of a field that Yahweh has blessed! </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ge 27:28">28</verse-number>May God give you of the dew of heaven </li1>
				<li2>and of the fatness of the earth, </li2>
				<li2>and abundance of grain and new wine. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ge 27:29">29</verse-number>Let peoples serve you, </li1>
				<li2>and nations bow down to you; </li2>
				<li1>Be lord of your brothers, </li1>
				<li2>and may the sons of your mother bow down to you. </li2>
				<li1>Cursed be those cursing you, </li1>
				<li2>and blessed be those blessing you.” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 27:30">30</verse-number>And as soon as Isaac had finished blessing Jacob, <idiom-start/>immediately after<idiom-end/><note>Literally “it was only”</note> Jacob had gone out from the presence of Isaac his father, Esau his brother came <supplied>back</supplied> from his hunting. <verse-number id="Ge 27:31">31</verse-number>He too prepared tasty food and brought <supplied>it</supplied> to his father. And he said to his father, “Let my father arise and eat from the wild game of his son, that you<note>Or “your soul”</note> may bless me.” <verse-number id="Ge 27:32">32</verse-number>And Isaac his father said to him, “Who <supplied>are</supplied> you?” And he said, “I <supplied>am</supplied> your son, your firstborn, Esau.” <verse-number id="Ge 27:33">33</verse-number>Then Isaac <idiom-start/>trembled violently<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “trembled a great trembling unto exceeding”</note> Then he said, “Who then <supplied>was</supplied> he that hunted wild game and brought <supplied>it</supplied> to me, and I ate <supplied>it</supplied> all before you came, and I blessed him? Moreover, he will be blessed!” <verse-number id="Ge 27:34">34</verse-number>When Esau heard the words of his father he cried out <supplied>with</supplied> a great and exceedingly bitter cry of distress. And he said to his father, “Bless me as well, my father!” <verse-number id="Ge 27:35">35</verse-number>And he said, “Your brother came in deceit and took your blessing.” <verse-number id="Ge 27:36">36</verse-number>Then he said, “<idiom-start/>Isn’t that why he is named Jacob<idiom-end/>?<note>Literally “that his name is called Jacob?”</note> He has deceived me these two times. He took my birthright and, look, now he has taken my blessing!” Then he said, “Have you not reserved a blessing for me?” <verse-number id="Ge 27:37">37</verse-number>Then Isaac answered and said to Esau, “Behold, I have made him lord over you and I have given him all his brothers as servants, and <supplied>with</supplied> grain and wine I have sustained him. Now what can I do for you, my son?” <verse-number id="Ge 27:38">38</verse-number>And Esau said to his father, “Have you only one blessing, my father? Bless me also, my father!” And Esau lifted up his voice and wept. <verse-number id="Ge 27:39">39</verse-number>Then Isaac his father answered and said to him, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Your home shall be from<note>Or “away from”</note> the fatness of the land, </li1>
				<li2>and from the dew of heaven above. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ge 27:40">40</verse-number>But by your sword you shall live, </li1>
				<li2>and you shall serve your brother. </li2>
				<li1>But it shall be <supplied>that</supplied> when free yourself </li1>
				<li2>you shall tear off his yoke from your neck. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 27:41">41</verse-number>Then Esau held a grudge against Jacob on account of the blessing with which his father had blessed him. And Esau said in his heart,<note>That is, “to himself”</note> “The days of mourning for my father are coming, then I will kill Jacob my brother.” <verse-number id="Ge 27:42">42</verse-number>But the words of Esau her older son were told to Rebekah. And she sent and called for her younger son Jacob. And she said to him, “Look, Esau your brother <supplied>is</supplied> consoling himself concerning you, <supplied>intending</supplied> to kill you. <verse-number id="Ge 27:43">43</verse-number>Now then, my son, listen to my voice; arise and flee to Haran to Laban my brother. <verse-number id="Ge 27:44">44</verse-number>Stay with him a few days until the wrath of your brother has turned—<verse-number id="Ge 27:45">45</verse-number>until the anger of your brother turns from you and he has forgotten what you have done to him. Then I will send and bring you from there. Why should I lose the two of you in one day?” <verse-number id="Ge 27:46">46</verse-number>Then Rebekah said to Isaac, “I loathe my life because of the Hittite women.<note>Or “daughters of the Hittites”</note> If Jacob takes a wife from Hittite women<note>Or “daughters of the Hittites”</note> like these, from the <idiom-start/>native women<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “daughters of the land”</note> <idiom-start/>what am I living for<idiom-end/>?”<note>Literally “What is life to me?”</note> </p>
		</chapter>