<chapter id="Ge 32">
			<pericope>Jacob Fears Esau</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 32:1">1</verse-number>And Jacob went on his way, and angels of God met him. <verse-number id="Ge 32:2">2</verse-number>And when he saw them, Jacob said, “This <supplied>is</supplied> the camp of God!” And he called the name of that place Mahanaim. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 32:3">3</verse-number>Then Jacob sent messengers before him to Esau his brother, to the land of Seir, the territory of Edom. <verse-number id="Ge 32:4">4</verse-number>And he instructed them, saying, “Thus you must say to my lord, to Esau, ‘Thus says your servant Jacob, I have dwelled as an alien with Laban, and I have remained <supplied>there</supplied> until now. <verse-number id="Ge 32:5">5</verse-number>And I have acquired cattle, male donkeys, flocks, and male and female slaves, and I have sent to tell my lord, to find favor in your eyes.’ ” <verse-number id="Ge 32:6">6</verse-number>And the messengers returned to Jacob <supplied>and</supplied> said, “We came to your brother, to Esau, and he is coming to meet you, and four hundred men <supplied>are</supplied> with him.” <verse-number id="Ge 32:7">7</verse-number>Then Jacob was very frightened and distressed. So he divided the people, flocks, cattle, and camels that <supplied>were</supplied> with him into two companies. <verse-number id="Ge 32:8">8</verse-number>And he thought, “If Esau comes to one company and destroys it, the remaining company will be <supplied>able</supplied> to escape.” <verse-number id="Ge 32:9">9</verse-number>Then Jacob said, “O God of my father Abraham, and God of my father Isaac, O Yahweh, who said to me, ‘Return to your land and to your family, and I will deal well with you.’ <verse-number id="Ge 32:10">10</verse-number><idiom-start/>I am not worthy<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I am small”</note> of all the loyal love and all the faithfulness that you have shown<note>Or “done”</note> your servant, for with <supplied>only</supplied> my staff I crossed this Jordan, and now I have become two camps. <verse-number id="Ge 32:11">11</verse-number>Please rescue me from the hand of my brother, from the hand of Esau, for I fear him, lest he come and attack mother and children <supplied>alike</supplied>. <verse-number id="Ge 32:12">12</verse-number>Now you yourself said, ‘I will surely deal well with you and make your offspring as the sand of the sea that cannot be counted for abundance.’ ” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 32:13">13</verse-number>And he lodged there that night. Then he took <idiom-start/>from what he had with him<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from that which was going from his hand”</note> a gift for Esau his brother: <verse-number id="Ge 32:14">14</verse-number>two hundred female goats, twenty male goats, two hundred ewes, twenty rams, <verse-number id="Ge 32:15">15</verse-number>thirty milk camels with their young, forty cows, ten bulls, twenty female donkeys, and ten male donkeys. <verse-number id="Ge 32:16">16</verse-number>And he put <supplied>them</supplied> under the hand of his servants, <idiom-start/>herd by herd<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “every herd by its own”</note> and said to his servants, “Cross on ahead before me, and put some distance <idiom-start/>between herds<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “between a herd and between a herd”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 32:17">17</verse-number>And he instructed the foremost, saying, “When Esau my brother comes upon you and asks you, saying, ‘Whose <supplied>are</supplied> you and where are you going? To whom do these <supplied>animals</supplied> belong ahead of you?’ <verse-number id="Ge 32:18">18</verse-number>Then you must say, ‘To your servant, to Jacob. It <supplied>is</supplied> a gift sent to my lord, to Esau. Now behold, he <supplied>is</supplied> also <supplied>coming</supplied> after us.’ ” <verse-number id="Ge 32:19">19</verse-number>And he also instructed the second <supplied>servant</supplied> and the third, and everyone <supplied>else</supplied> who <supplied>was</supplied> behind the herds, saying, “You must speak to Esau according to this word when you find him. <verse-number id="Ge 32:20">20</verse-number>And moreover, you shall say, ‘Look, your servant Jacob <supplied>is</supplied> behind us.’ ” For he thought, “<idiom-start/>Let me appease him<idiom-end/><note>Literally “let me cover his face”</note> with the gift going before me, and afterward I will see his face. Perhaps he will <idiom-start/>show me favor<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “lift up my face”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 32:21">21</verse-number>So the gift passed on before him, but he himself spent that night in the camp. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jacob Wrestles with God</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 32:22">22</verse-number>That night he arose and took his two wives, his two female servants, and his eleven children and crossed the ford of the Jabbok. <verse-number id="Ge 32:23">23</verse-number>And he took them and sent them across the stream. Then he sent across all his possessions. <verse-number id="Ge 32:24">24</verse-number>And Jacob remained alone, and a man wrestled with him until the breaking of the dawn. <verse-number id="Ge 32:25">25</verse-number>And when he<note>That is, the man</note> saw that he could not prevail against him, he struck his hip socket, so that Jacob’s hip socket was sprained as he wrestled with him. <verse-number id="Ge 32:26">26</verse-number>Then he<note>That is, the man</note> said, “Let me go, for dawn is breaking.” But he answered, “I will not let you go unless you bless me.” <verse-number id="Ge 32:27">27</verse-number>Then he said to him, “What <supplied>is</supplied> your name?” And he said, “Jacob.” <verse-number id="Ge 32:28">28</verse-number>And he said, “Your name shall no longer be called Jacob, but Israel,<note>“Israel” means “he struggles with God,” or “God struggles”</note> for you have struggled with God and with men and have prevailed.” <verse-number id="Ge 32:29">29</verse-number>Then Jacob asked and said, “Please tell me your name.” And he said, “Why do you ask this—for my name?” And he blessed him there. <verse-number id="Ge 32:30">30</verse-number>Then Jacob called the name of the place Peniel <supplied>which means</supplied> “I have seen God face to face and my life was spared.” <verse-number id="Ge 32:31">31</verse-number>Then the sun rose upon him as he passed Penuel, and he was limping because of his hip. <verse-number id="Ge 32:32">32</verse-number>Therefore the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> do not eat the sinew of the sciatic nerve that <supplied>is</supplied> upon the socket of the hip unto this day, because he struck the socket of the thigh of Jacob at the sinew of the sciatic nerve. </p>
		</chapter>