<chapter id="Ge 33">
			<pericope>Jacob Meets Esau and Settles at Shechem</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 33:1">1</verse-number>And Jacob lifted up his eyes and looked. And behold, Esau <supplied>was</supplied> coming and four hundred men <supplied>were</supplied> with him. And he<note>That is, Jacob</note> divided the children among Leah and among Rachel, and among the two of his female servants. <verse-number id="Ge 33:2">2</verse-number>And he put the female slaves and their children first, then Leah and her children next, then Rachel with Joseph last. <verse-number id="Ge 33:3">3</verse-number>And he himself passed on before them and bowed down to the ground seven times until he came to his brother. <verse-number id="Ge 33:4">4</verse-number>But Esau ran to meet him, and embraced him, and fell upon his neck and kissed him, and they wept. <verse-number id="Ge 33:5">5</verse-number>Then Esau lifted up his eyes and saw the women and the children and said, “Who <supplied>are</supplied> these with you?” And he said, “The children whom God has graciously given your servant.” <verse-number id="Ge 33:6">6</verse-number>Then the female servants drew near, they and their children, and they bowed down. <verse-number id="Ge 33:7">7</verse-number>Then Leah and her children drew near and bowed down, and afterward Joseph and Rachel drew near and they bowed down. <verse-number id="Ge 33:8">8</verse-number>And he<note>That is, Esau</note> said, “<idiom-start/>What do you mean by<idiom-end/><note>Literally “What to you?”</note> all this company that I have met?” Then he said, “To find favor in the eyes of my lord.” <verse-number id="Ge 33:9">9</verse-number>Then Esau said, “<idiom-start/>I have enough<idiom-end/><note>Literally “There is to me abundance”</note> my brother; <idiom-start/>keep what you have<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “let what is to you be to you”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 33:10">10</verse-number>And Jacob said, “No, please, if I have found favor in your eyes, you must take my gift from my hand, for then I have seen your face <supplied>which is</supplied> like seeing the face of God, and you have received me. <verse-number id="Ge 33:11">11</verse-number>Please take my gift which has been brought to you, for God has dealt graciously with me, and because <idiom-start/>I have enough<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “There is to me abundance”</note> And he urged him, so he took <supplied>it</supplied>. <verse-number id="Ge 33:12">12</verse-number>Then he<note>That is, Esau</note> said, “Let us journey and go <supplied>on</supplied>, and I will go ahead of you.” <verse-number id="Ge 33:13">13</verse-number>But he said to him, “My lord knows that the children <supplied>are</supplied> frail, and the flocks and the cattle <supplied>which are</supplied> nursing <supplied>are a concern</supplied> to me. Now <supplied>if</supplied> they drove them hard for a day all the flocks would die. <verse-number id="Ge 33:14">14</verse-number>Let my lord pass on before his servant and I will move along slowly at the pace<note>Or “foot”</note> of the livestock that are ahead of me, and at the pace<note>Or “foot”</note> of the children until I come to my lord in Seir.” <verse-number id="Ge 33:15">15</verse-number>And Esau said, “Let me leave some of my people with you.” But he said, “<idiom-start/>What need is there<idiom-end/>?<note>Literally “What is this?”</note> Let me find favor in the eyes of my lord.” <verse-number id="Ge 33:16">16</verse-number>So Esau turned that day on his way to Seir. <verse-number id="Ge 33:17">17</verse-number>But Jacob traveled on to Succoth, and he built for himself a house, and he made shelters for his livestock. Therefore he called the name of the place Succoth. <verse-number id="Ge 33:18">18</verse-number>And Jacob came safely to the city of Shechem which <supplied>is</supplied> in the land of Canaan, <idiom-start/>on his way<idiom-end/><note>Literally “at his coming”</note> from Paddan-Aram. And he camped before the city. <verse-number id="Ge 33:19">19</verse-number>And he bought a piece of land where he pitched his tent for one hundred pieces of money<note>Hebrew <i>kesitah</i></note> from the hand of the sons of Hamor, father of Shechem. <verse-number id="Ge 33:20">20</verse-number>And there he erected an altar and called it “El Elohe Israel.”<note>That is, “<i>El</i> the God of Israel”</note> </p>
		</chapter>