<chapter id="Ge 36">
			<pericope>The Descendants of Esau</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 36:1">1</verse-number>Now these <supplied>are</supplied> the descendants of Esau (that <supplied>is</supplied>, Edom). <verse-number id="Ge 36:2">2</verse-number>Esau took his wives from the daughters of Canaan: Adah, daughter of Elon, the Hittite, and Oholibamah, daughter of Anah, the daughter of Zibeon, the Hivite, <verse-number id="Ge 36:3">3</verse-number>and Basemath, the daughter of Ishmael, the sister of Nebaioth. <verse-number id="Ge 36:4">4</verse-number>And Adah bore to Esau Eliphaz; and Basemath bore Reuel; <verse-number id="Ge 36:5">5</verse-number>and Oholibamah bore Jeush and Jalam, and Korah. These <supplied>are</supplied> the sons of Esau who were born to him in the land of Canaan. <verse-number id="Ge 36:6">6</verse-number>And Esau took his wives and his sons and his daughters, and all the persons of his household, and his sheep and goats, and all his cattle, and all the goods that he had acquired in the land of Canaan, and went to a land away from his brother Jacob. <verse-number id="Ge 36:7">7</verse-number>For their possessions were <idiom-start/>too many to live together<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “much from living together”</note> so that the land of their sojourning was not able to support them on account of their livestock. <verse-number id="Ge 36:8">8</verse-number>So Esau dwelled in the hill country of Seir (Esau, that <supplied>is</supplied> Edom). </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 36:9">9</verse-number>Now these <supplied>are</supplied> the descendants of Esau, the father of Edom, in the hill country of Seir. <verse-number id="Ge 36:10">10</verse-number>These <supplied>are</supplied> the names of the sons of Esau: Eliphaz, the son of Adah, the wife of Esau; Reuel, the son of Basemath, the wife of Esau. <verse-number id="Ge 36:11">11</verse-number>The sons of Eliphaz were Teman, Omar, Zepho, Gatam, and Kenaz. <verse-number id="Ge 36:12">12</verse-number>(Now Timnah was the concubine of Eliphaz, the son of Esau. And she bore Amalek to Eliphaz.) These <supplied>are</supplied> the sons of Adah, the wife of Esau. <verse-number id="Ge 36:13">13</verse-number>Now these <supplied>are</supplied> the sons of Reuel: Nahath, Zerah, Shammah, and Mizzah. These <supplied>are</supplied> the sons of Basemath, the wife of Esau. <verse-number id="Ge 36:14">14</verse-number>Now these <supplied>are</supplied> the sons of Oholibamah, the daughter of Anah, daughter of Zibeon, the wife of Esau: She bore to Esau Jeush, Jalam, and Korah. <verse-number id="Ge 36:15">15</verse-number>These <supplied>are</supplied> the chiefs of the sons of Esau. The sons of Eliphaz, the firstborn of Esau: the chiefs of Teman, Omar, Zepho, Kenaz, <verse-number id="Ge 36:16">16</verse-number>Korah, Gatam, and Amalek. These <supplied>are</supplied> the chiefs of Eliphaz in the land of Edom. These <supplied>are</supplied> the sons of Adah. <verse-number id="Ge 36:17">17</verse-number>Now these <supplied>are</supplied> the sons Reuel, the son of Esau: the chiefs Nahath, Zerah, Shammah, and Mizzah. These <supplied>are</supplied> the chiefs of Reuel in the land of Edom. These <supplied>are</supplied> the sons of Basemath, the wife of Esau. <verse-number id="Ge 36:18">18</verse-number>Now these <supplied>are</supplied> the sons of Oholibamah, the wife of Esau: the chiefs Jeush, Jalam, and Korah. These <supplied>are</supplied> the chiefs born of Oholibamah, the daughter of Anah, the wife of Esau. <verse-number id="Ge 36:19">19</verse-number>These <supplied>are</supplied> the sons of Esau, and these <supplied>are</supplied> their chiefs (that <supplied>is</supplied>, Edom). <verse-number id="Ge 36:20">20</verse-number>These <supplied>are</supplied> the sons of Seir, the Horite, the inhabitants of the land: Lotan, Shobal, Zibeon, Anah, <verse-number id="Ge 36:21">21</verse-number>Dishon, Ezer, and Dishan. These <supplied>are</supplied> the chiefs of the Horites, the sons of Seir in the land of Edom. <verse-number id="Ge 36:22">22</verse-number>And the sons of Lotan were Hori and Hemam. And Lotan’s sister <supplied>was</supplied> Timna. <verse-number id="Ge 36:23">23</verse-number>Now these <supplied>are</supplied> the sons of Shobal: Alvan, Manahath, Ebal, Shepho, and Onam. <verse-number id="Ge 36:24">24</verse-number>Now these <supplied>are</supplied> the sons of Zibeon: Aiah and Anah—he <supplied>is</supplied> Anah who found the hot springs in the desert while he pastured the donkeys of Zibeon his father. <verse-number id="Ge 36:25">25</verse-number>Now these <supplied>are</supplied> the sons of Anah: Dishon and Oholibamah, the daughter of Anah. <verse-number id="Ge 36:26">26</verse-number>Now these <supplied>are</supplied> the sons of Dishon: Hemdan, Eshban, Ithran, and Keran. <verse-number id="Ge 36:27">27</verse-number>These <supplied>are</supplied> the sons of Ezer: Bilhan, Zaavan, and Akan. <verse-number id="Ge 36:28">28</verse-number>These <supplied>are</supplied> the sons of Dishan: Uz and Aran. <verse-number id="Ge 36:29">29</verse-number>These <supplied>are</supplied> the chiefs of the Horites: the chiefs Lotan, Shobal, Zibeon, Anah, <verse-number id="Ge 36:30">30</verse-number>Dishon, Ezer, and Dishan. These <supplied>are</supplied> the chiefs of the Horites, according to their chiefs in the land of Seir. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Kings of Edom</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 36:31">31</verse-number>Now these <supplied>are</supplied> the kings who reigned in the land of Edom before any king ruled over the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 36:32">32</verse-number>Bela the son of Beor reigned in Edom. And the name of his city <supplied>was</supplied> Dinhabah. <verse-number id="Ge 36:33">33</verse-number>And Bela died, and Jobab, the son of Zerah from Bozrah, reigned in his place. <verse-number id="Ge 36:34">34</verse-number>And Jobab died, and Husham from the land of the Temanites reigned in his place. <verse-number id="Ge 36:35">35</verse-number>And Husham died, and Hadad, son of Bedad, who defeated Midian in the field<note>Or “country”</note> of Moab reigned in his place. And the name of his city <supplied>was</supplied> Avith. <verse-number id="Ge 36:36">36</verse-number>And Hadad died, and Samlah from Masrekah reigned in his place. <verse-number id="Ge 36:37">37</verse-number>And Samlah died, and Shaul from Rehoboth <supplied>on</supplied> the Euphrates<note>Or “the River”</note> reigned in his place. <verse-number id="Ge 36:38">38</verse-number>And Shaul died, and Baal-Hanan, the son of Acbor, reigned in his place. <verse-number id="Ge 36:39">39</verse-number>And Baal-Hanan the son of Acbor died, and Hadar reigned in his place. And the name of his city <supplied>was</supplied> Pau, and the name of his wife <supplied>was</supplied> Mehetabel, the daughter of Matred, daughter of Mezahab. <verse-number id="Ge 36:40">40</verse-number>Now these <supplied>are</supplied> the names of the chiefs of Esau according to their families, according to their dwelling places, by their names: the chiefs Timna, Alvah, Jetheth, <verse-number id="Ge 36:41">41</verse-number>Oholibamah, Elah, Pinon, <verse-number id="Ge 36:42">42</verse-number>Kenaz, Teman, Mibzar, <verse-number id="Ge 36:43">43</verse-number>Magdiel, and Iram. These <supplied>are</supplied> the chiefs of Edom (that <supplied>is</supplied>, Esau, the father of Edom) according to their settlements in the land of their possession. </p>
		</chapter>