<chapter id="Ge 37">
			<pericope>The Dreams of Joseph</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 37:1">1</verse-number>And Jacob settled in the land of the sojourning of his father, in the land of Canaan. <verse-number id="Ge 37:2">2</verse-number>These <supplied>are</supplied> the generations<note>Or “family records”</note> of Jacob. Joseph, <supplied>being</supplied> seventeen years old, was shepherding the flock with his brothers. Now he <supplied>was</supplied> a helper with the sons of Bilhah and the sons of Zilpah, the wives of his father. And Joseph brought a bad report of them to his father. <verse-number id="Ge 37:3">3</verse-number>Now Israel loved Joseph more than all his sons, for he <supplied>was</supplied> a son of his old age. And he made a robe with long sleeves<note>Or “of many colors”</note> for him. <verse-number id="Ge 37:4">4</verse-number>When his brothers saw that their father loved him more than all his brothers, they hated him and were not able to speak peaceably to him. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 37:5">5</verse-number>And Joseph dreamed a dream, and he told <supplied>it</supplied> to his brothers. And <idiom-start/>they hated him even more<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “they added still to hate him”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 37:6">6</verse-number>And he said to them, “Listen now to this dream that I dreamed. <verse-number id="Ge 37:7">7</verse-number>Now behold, we were binding sheaves in the midst of the field and, behold, my sheaf stood up and it remained standing. Then behold, your sheaves gathered around and bowed down to my sheaf.” <verse-number id="Ge 37:8">8</verse-number>Then his brothers said to him, “Will you really rule over us?” And <idiom-start/>they hated him even more<idiom-end/><note>Literally “they added still to hate him”</note> on account of his dream and because of his words. <verse-number id="Ge 37:9">9</verse-number>Then he dreamed yet another dream and told it to his brothers. And he said, “Behold, I dreamed a dream again, and behold, the sun and the moon and eleven stars were bowing down to me.” <verse-number id="Ge 37:10">10</verse-number>And he told <supplied>it</supplied> to his father and to his brothers. And his father rebuked him and said to him, “What <supplied>is</supplied> this dream that you have dreamed? Will I and your mother and your brothers indeed come to bow down to the ground to you?” <verse-number id="Ge 37:11">11</verse-number>And his brothers were jealous of him, but his father kept the matter <supplied>in mind</supplied>. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Joseph Sold Into Slavery by his Brothers</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 37:12">12</verse-number>Now his brothers went to pasture the flock of their father in Shechem. <verse-number id="Ge 37:13">13</verse-number>And Israel said to Joseph, “Are not your brothers pasturing in Shechem? Come, let me send you to them.” And he said, “Here I <supplied>am</supplied>.” <verse-number id="Ge 37:14">14</verse-number>Then he said to him, “Go now, see <idiom-start/>if it goes well for your brothers and for the flock<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “see the peace of your brothers and the peace of the flock”</note> then return word to me.” And he sent him from the valley of Hebron, and he arrived at Shechem. <verse-number id="Ge 37:15">15</verse-number>And a man found him, and behold, he<note>That is, Joseph</note> was wandering about in a field. And the man asked him, “What do you seek?” <verse-number id="Ge 37:16">16</verse-number>And he said, “I am seeking my brothers. Tell me, please, where they are pasturing.” <verse-number id="Ge 37:17">17</verse-number>And the man said, “They have moved on from here, for I heard <supplied>them</supplied> saying, ‘Let us go to Dothan.’ ” Then Joseph went after his brothers and found them in Dothan. <verse-number id="Ge 37:18">18</verse-number>And they saw him from a distance. And before he drew near to them, they conspired against him to kill him. <verse-number id="Ge 37:19">19</verse-number>And each said to his brothers, “Look, this master of dreams is coming. <verse-number id="Ge 37:20">20</verse-number>Now then, come, let us kill him and throw him in one of the pits. Then we will say a wild animal devoured him. Then we will see what his dreams become.” <verse-number id="Ge 37:21">21</verse-number>And Reuben heard <supplied>it</supplied> and delivered him from their hand and said, “We must not take his life.” <verse-number id="Ge 37:22">22</verse-number>And Reuben said to them, “You must not shed blood. Throw him into this pit that <supplied>is</supplied> in the desert, but do not lay a hand on him”—so that he might rescue him from their hand to return him to his father. <verse-number id="Ge 37:23">23</verse-number>And it happened <supplied>that</supplied> as Joseph came to his brothers they stripped Joseph of his robe, the robe with long sleeves,<note>Or “of many colors”</note> that <supplied>was</supplied> upon him. <verse-number id="Ge 37:24">24</verse-number>And they took him and threw him into the pit (the pit <supplied>was</supplied> empty; there was no water in it). <verse-number id="Ge 37:25">25</verse-number>Then they sat down to eat <supplied>some</supplied> food. And they lifted up their eyes and looked, and behold, a caravan of Ishmaelites was coming from Gilead. And their camels were carrying aromatic gum and balm and spices <idiom-start/>on the way<idiom-end/><note>Literally “going to bring down”</note> to Egypt. <verse-number id="Ge 37:26">26</verse-number>Then Judah said to his brothers, “What profit <supplied>is there</supplied> if we kill our brother and conceal his blood? <verse-number id="Ge 37:27">27</verse-number>Come, let us sell him to the Ishmaelites, but our hand shall not be against him, for he <supplied>is</supplied> our brother, our own flesh.” And his brothers agreed. <verse-number id="Ge 37:28">28</verse-number>Then Midianite traders passed by. And they<note>That is, the brothers</note> drew Joseph up and brought <supplied>him</supplied> up from the pit, and they sold Joseph to the Ishmaelites for twenty <supplied>pieces of</supplied> silver. And they brought Joseph to Egypt. <verse-number id="Ge 37:29">29</verse-number>Then Reuben returned to the pit and, behold, Joseph was not in the pit. And he tore his clothes. <verse-number id="Ge 37:30">30</verse-number>And he returned to his brothers and said, “The boy <idiom-start/>is gone<idiom-end/>!<note>Literally “is not”</note> Now I, <idiom-start/>what can I do<idiom-end/>?”<note>Literally “where am I going?”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 37:31">31</verse-number>Then they took the robe of Joseph and slaughtered a goat, and dipped the robe in the blood. <verse-number id="Ge 37:32">32</verse-number>Then they sent the robe with long sleeves<note>Or “of many colors”</note> and they brought <supplied>it</supplied> to their father and said, “We found this; please examine <supplied>it</supplied>. <supplied>Is</supplied> it the robe of your son or not?” <verse-number id="Ge 37:33">33</verse-number>And he recognized it and said, “The robe of my son! A wild animal has devoured him! Joseph <supplied>is</supplied> surely torn to pieces!” <verse-number id="Ge 37:34">34</verse-number>And Jacob tore his clothes and put sackcloth on his loins and mourned for his son many days. <verse-number id="Ge 37:35">35</verse-number>And all his sons and daughters tried to console him, but he refused to be consoled. And he said, “No, I shall go down to my son, to Sheol, mourning.” And his father wept for him. <verse-number id="Ge 37:36">36</verse-number>And the Midianites sold him in Egypt to Potiphar, a court official of Pharaoh, a commander of the imperial guard. </p>
		</chapter>