<chapter id="Ge 38">
			<pericope>Judah and Tamar</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 38:1">1</verse-number>And it happened <supplied>that</supplied> at that time Judah went down from his brothers and pitched his tent near a certain Adullamite, whose name <supplied>was</supplied> Hirah. <verse-number id="Ge 38:2">2</verse-number>And Judah saw the daughter of a certain Canaanite there whose name <supplied>was</supplied> Shua. And he took her and went in to her. <verse-number id="Ge 38:3">3</verse-number>And she conceived and bore a son, and he called his name Er. <verse-number id="Ge 38:4">4</verse-number>And she conceived again and bore a son, and he called his name Onan. <verse-number id="Ge 38:5">5</verse-number>And once again she bore a son, and she called his name Shelah. And he<note>That is, Judah</note> was in Chezib when she bore him. <verse-number id="Ge 38:6">6</verse-number>And Judah took a wife for Er his firstborn, and her name <supplied>was</supplied> Tamar. <verse-number id="Ge 38:7">7</verse-number>And Er, the firstborn of Judah, was evil in the eyes of Yahweh, and Yahweh killed him. <verse-number id="Ge 38:8">8</verse-number>Then Judah said to Onan, “Go in to the wife of your brother and perform the duty of a brother-in-law to her, and raise up offspring for your brother.” <verse-number id="Ge 38:9">9</verse-number>But Onan knew that the offspring would not be for him, so whenever he went in to the wife of his brother he would waste <supplied>it</supplied> on the ground<note>Meaning he would spill his semen on the ground</note> so as not to give offspring to his brother. <verse-number id="Ge 38:10">10</verse-number>And what he did was evil in the sight of Yahweh, so he killed him also. <verse-number id="Ge 38:11">11</verse-number>Then Judah said to Tamar, his daughter-in-law, “Stay a widow in your father’s house until Shelah my son grows up,” for <idiom-start/>he feared he would also die<idiom-end/><note>Literally “he thought lest he also will die”</note> like his brother. So Tamar went and stayed in the house of her father. <verse-number id="Ge 38:12">12</verse-number><idiom-start/>And in the course of time<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And the days increased”</note> the daughter of Shua, the wife of Judah, died. When Judah was consoled he went up to his sheepshearers, he and his friend Hirah the Adullamite, to Timnah. <verse-number id="Ge 38:13">13</verse-number>And it was told to Tamar, saying, “Look, your father-in-law is going up to Timnah to shear his sheep.” <verse-number id="Ge 38:14">14</verse-number>So she removed the clothes of her widowhood and covered <supplied>herself</supplied> with the veil and disguised herself. And she sat at the entrance to Eynayim, which <supplied>is</supplied> on the way to Timnah, for she saw that Shelah was grown but she had not been given to him as a wife. <verse-number id="Ge 38:15">15</verse-number>And Judah saw her and reckoned her to <supplied>be</supplied> a prostitute, for she had covered her face. <verse-number id="Ge 38:16">16</verse-number>And he turned aside to her at the roadside and said, “Please come, let me come in to you,” for he did not know that she <supplied>was</supplied> his daughter-in-law. And she said, “What will you give to me that you may come in to me?” <verse-number id="Ge 38:17">17</verse-number>And he said, “I will send a kid from the goats of the flock.” And she said, “<supplied>Only</supplied> if you give a pledge until you send <supplied>it</supplied>.” <verse-number id="Ge 38:18">18</verse-number>And he said, “What <supplied>is</supplied> the pledge that I must give to you?” And she said, “your seal, your cord, and your staff that <supplied>is</supplied> in your hand.” And he gave <supplied>them</supplied> to her and went in to her. And she conceived by him. <verse-number id="Ge 38:19">19</verse-number>And she arose and left, and she removed her veil from herself and put on the garments of her widowhood. <verse-number id="Ge 38:20">20</verse-number>And Judah sent the kid from the goats by the hand of his friend the Adullamite to take <supplied>back</supplied> the pledge from the hand of the woman, but he could not find her. <verse-number id="Ge 38:21">21</verse-number>So he asked the men of her place, saying, “Where <supplied>is</supplied> that cult prostitute <supplied>that was</supplied> at Eynayim by the roadside?” And they said, “There is no cult prostitute here.” <verse-number id="Ge 38:22">22</verse-number>Then he returned to Judah and said, “I could not find her. Morever, the men of the place said, ‘There is no cult prostitute here.’ ” <verse-number id="Ge 38:23">23</verse-number>And Judah said, “Let her take <supplied>them</supplied> for herself, lest we be <idiom-start/>laughed at<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “as contempt”</note> Behold, I sent this kid, but you could not find her.” <verse-number id="Ge 38:24">24</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>about three months later<idiom-end/><note>Literally “it happened about three months”</note> it was told to Judah, “Tamar your daughter-in-law has played the whore, and now, behold, she has conceived by prostitution.” And Judah said, “Bring her out and let her be burned.” <verse-number id="Ge 38:25">25</verse-number>She was brought out, but she sent to her father-in-law saying, “By the man to whom these <supplied>belong</supplied> I have conceived.” And she said, “Now discern<note>Or “examine”</note> to whom these <supplied>belong</supplied>: the seal and cord and the staff.” <verse-number id="Ge 38:26">26</verse-number>Then Judah recognized <supplied>them</supplied> and said, “She is more righteous than I, since I did not give her to my son Shelah.” And he did not know<note>“Know” is a euphemism for “have sexual relations with”</note> her again. <verse-number id="Ge 38:27">27</verse-number>And it happened <supplied>that</supplied> at the time she gave birth that, behold, twins <supplied>were</supplied> in her womb. <verse-number id="Ge 38:28">28</verse-number>And it happened <supplied>that</supplied> at her labor one <supplied>child</supplied> put out a hand. And the midwife took <supplied>it</supplied> and tied a crimson thread on his hand saying, “This <supplied>one</supplied> came out first.” <verse-number id="Ge 38:29">29</verse-number>Then his hand drew back and, behold, his brother came out, and she said, “What a breach you have made for yourself!” And she called his name Perez. <verse-number id="Ge 38:30">30</verse-number>And afterward his brother who <supplied>had</supplied> the crimson thread on his hand came out. And his name was called Zerah. </p>
		</chapter>