<chapter id="Ge 39">
			<pericope>Joseph in Potiphar’s House</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 39:1">1</verse-number>Now Joseph had been brought down to Egypt, and Potiphar, a court official of Pharaoh, commander of the guard, an Egyptian, bought him from the hand of the Ishmaelites who had brought him down there. <verse-number id="Ge 39:2">2</verse-number>And Yahweh was with Joseph, and he became a successful man. And he was in the house of his master, the Egyptian. <verse-number id="Ge 39:3">3</verse-number>And his master observed that Yahweh <supplied>was</supplied> with him, and everything that <supplied>was</supplied> in his hand to do Yahweh made successful. <verse-number id="Ge 39:4">4</verse-number>And Joseph found favor in his eyes and he served him. Then he appointed him<note>That is, Joseph</note> over his house and all that he owned he put into his hand. <verse-number id="Ge 39:5">5</verse-number>And it happened <supplied>that</supplied> from the time he appointed him over his house and over all that he had, Yahweh blessed the house of the Egyptian on account of Joseph. And the blessing of Yahweh was upon all that he had in the house and in the field. <verse-number id="Ge 39:6">6</verse-number>And he left all that he had in the hand of Joseph, and <idiom-start/>he did not worry about anything<idiom-end/><note>Literally “he did not know with him anything”</note> except the food that he ate. Now Joseph was <idiom-start/>well built and handsome<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “beautiful of form and beautiful of appearance”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 39:7">7</verse-number>And it happened <supplied>that</supplied> after these things his master’s wife cast her eyes on Joseph, and she said, “Lie with me.” <verse-number id="Ge 39:8">8</verse-number>But he refused and said to his master’s wife, “Look, my master <idiom-start/>does not worry about<idiom-end/><note>Literally “does not know with me”</note> what <supplied>is</supplied> in the house, and everything he owns he has put in my hand. <verse-number id="Ge 39:9">9</verse-number>He has no greater <supplied>authority</supplied> in this house than me, and he has not withheld anything from me except you, since you <supplied>are</supplied> his wife. Now how could I do this great wickedness and sin against God?” <verse-number id="Ge 39:10">10</verse-number>And it happened <supplied>that</supplied> as she spoke to Joseph <idiom-start/>day after day<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “day, day”</note> he did not heed her to lie beside her or to be with her. <verse-number id="Ge 39:11">11</verse-number><idiom-start/>But one particular day<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and it happened as this day”</note> he came into the house to do his work and none of the men of the house were there in the house, <verse-number id="Ge 39:12">12</verse-number>she seized him by his garment <supplied>and</supplied> said, “Lie with me!” And he left his garment in her hand and fled, and he went outside. <verse-number id="Ge 39:13">13</verse-number>And it happened <supplied>that</supplied> when she saw that he left his garment in her hand and fled outside, <verse-number id="Ge 39:14">14</verse-number>she called to the men of her house and said to them, “Look! He<note>That is, Potiphar</note> brought a Hebrew man to us to mock us! He came to me to lie with me, and I cried out with a loud voice. <verse-number id="Ge 39:15">15</verse-number>And when he heard <supplied>me</supplied>, that I raised my voice and called out, he left his garment beside me and fled, and he went outside.” <verse-number id="Ge 39:16">16</verse-number>Then she put his garment beside her until his master came to his house. <verse-number id="Ge 39:17">17</verse-number>Then she spoke to him according to these words, saying, “The Hebrew slave that you brought to us came to me to make fun of me. <verse-number id="Ge 39:18">18</verse-number>And it happened <supplied>that</supplied> as I raised my voice and called out, he left his garment beside me and fled outside.” <verse-number id="Ge 39:19">19</verse-number>And when his master heard the words of his wife that she spoke to him, “<idiom-start/>This is what your servant did to me<idiom-end/>,”<note>Literally “according to these words your servant did to me”</note> <idiom-start/>he became very angry<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “his nostrils became hot”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 39:20">20</verse-number>And Joseph’s master took him and put him into prison, the place that the king’s prisoners were confined. And he was there in prison. <verse-number id="Ge 39:21">21</verse-number>And Yahweh was with Joseph, and showed loyal love to him, and gave him favor in the eyes of the chief of the prison. <verse-number id="Ge 39:22">22</verse-number>And the chief of the prison put all the prisoners that <supplied>were</supplied> in the prison into the hand of Joseph. And everything that was done there, he <supplied>was</supplied> the one who did <supplied>it</supplied>. <verse-number id="Ge 39:23">23</verse-number>The chief of the prison <idiom-start/>did not worry about<idiom-end/><note>Literally “did not pay heed to”</note> anything in his<note>That is, Joseph’s</note> hand, since Yahweh <supplied>was</supplied> with him. And whatever he did Yahweh made <supplied>it</supplied> successful. </p>
		</chapter>