<chapter id="Ge 40">
			<pericope>Joseph Interprets Dreams in Prison</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 40:1">1</verse-number>And it happened <supplied>that</supplied> after these things the cupbearer of the king of Egypt and <supplied>his</supplied> baker did wrong against their lord, against the king of Egypt. <verse-number id="Ge 40:2">2</verse-number>And Pharaoh was angry with his two officials, with the chief cupbearer and chief baker. <verse-number id="Ge 40:3">3</verse-number>And he put them in custody in the house of the chief of the guard, into the prison where Joseph was confined. <verse-number id="Ge 40:4">4</verse-number>And the chief of the guard appointed Joseph <supplied>to be</supplied> with them, and he attended them. And they were in custody <idiom-start/>many days<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “days”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 40:5">5</verse-number>And the two of them, the cupbearer and the baker of the king of Egypt, who <supplied>were</supplied> confined in the prison, dreamed a dream, each his own dream, with its own interpretation. <verse-number id="Ge 40:6">6</verse-number>When Joseph came to them in the morning he looked at them, and behold, they were troubled. <verse-number id="Ge 40:7">7</verse-number>And he asked the court officials of Pharaoh that <supplied>were</supplied> with him in the custody of his master’s house, “Why <supplied>are</supplied> your faces sad today?” <verse-number id="Ge 40:8">8</verse-number>And they said to him, “We <supplied>each</supplied> dreamed a dream, but there is no one to interpret it.” And Joseph said to them, “Do not interpretations belong to God? Please tell <supplied>them</supplied> to me.” <verse-number id="Ge 40:9">9</verse-number>Then the chief cupbearer told his dream to Joseph, and he said to him, “In my dream, now behold, <supplied>there was</supplied> a vine before me, <verse-number id="Ge 40:10">10</verse-number>and on the vine <supplied>were</supplied> three branches. And as it budded, its blossoms came up, <supplied>and</supplied> its clusters of grapes grew ripe. <verse-number id="Ge 40:11">11</verse-number>And the cup of Pharaoh <supplied>was</supplied> in my hand, and I took the grapes and squeezed them into the cup of Pharaoh. Then I placed the cup into the hand of Pharaoh.” <verse-number id="Ge 40:12">12</verse-number>Then Joseph said to him, “This <supplied>is</supplied> its interpretation: The three branches, they <supplied>are</supplied> three days. <verse-number id="Ge 40:13">13</verse-number>In three days Pharaoh will lift up your head and will restore you to your office. And you shall put the cup of Pharaoh into his hand as <supplied>was</supplied> formerly the custom, when you were his cupbearer. <verse-number id="Ge 40:14">14</verse-number>But remember me when it goes well with you, and please may you show kindness with respect to me, and mention me to Pharaoh, and bring me out of this house. <verse-number id="Ge 40:15">15</verse-number>For I was surely kidnapped from the land of the Hebrews, and here also I have done nothing that they should put me in this pit.” <verse-number id="Ge 40:16">16</verse-number>And when the chief baker saw that the interpretation <supplied>was</supplied> good he said to Joseph, “I also <supplied>dreamed</supplied>. In my dream, now behold, <supplied>there were</supplied> three baskets of bread upon my head. <verse-number id="Ge 40:17">17</verse-number>And in the upper basket <supplied>were</supplied> all sorts of baked foods for Pharaoh, but the birds were eating them out of the basket upon my head.” <verse-number id="Ge 40:18">18</verse-number>Then Joseph answered and said, “This <supplied>is</supplied> its interpretation: The three baskets, they <supplied>are</supplied> three days. <verse-number id="Ge 40:19">19</verse-number>In three days Pharaoh will lift your head from you and hang you on a pole,<note>Or “tree”</note> and the birds will eat your flesh from you.” <verse-number id="Ge 40:20">20</verse-number>And it happened <supplied>that</supplied> on the third day, <supplied>which was</supplied> Pharaoh’s birthday, he made a feast for all his servants. And he lifted up the head of the chief cupbearer and the head of the chief baker in the midst of his servants. <verse-number id="Ge 40:21">21</verse-number>And he restored the chief cupbearer to his cupbearing <supplied>position</supplied>. And he placed the cup in the hand of Pharaoh. <verse-number id="Ge 40:22">22</verse-number>But the chief baker he hanged as Joseph had interpreted to them. <verse-number id="Ge 40:23">23</verse-number>But the chief cupbearer did not remember Joseph, but forgot him. </p>
		</chapter>