<chapter id="Ge 41">
			<pericope>Joseph Interprets Pharaoh’s Dreams</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 41:1">1</verse-number>And it happened <supplied>that</supplied> after <idiom-start/>two full years<idiom-end/><note>Literally “two years of days”</note> Pharaoh dreamed, and behold, he was standing by the Nile. <verse-number id="Ge 41:2">2</verse-number>And behold, seven cows, <idiom-start/>well built and fat<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “beautiful of appearance and healthy of flesh”</note> were coming up from the Nile, and they grazed among the reeds. <verse-number id="Ge 41:3">3</verse-number>And behold, seven other cows came up after them from the Nile, <idiom-start/>ugly and gaunt<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “Poor of appearance and thin of flesh”</note> and they stood beside those<note>Or “the”</note> cows on the bank of the Nile. <verse-number id="Ge 41:4">4</verse-number>And the <idiom-start/>ugly and gaunt<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Poor of appearance and thin of flesh”</note> cows ate the seven <idiom-start/>well built and fat<idiom-end/><note>Literally “beautiful of appearance and healthy of flesh”</note> cows. Then Pharaoh awoke. <verse-number id="Ge 41:5">5</verse-number>And he fell asleep and dreamed a second time, and behold, seven ears of grain, plump and good, were coming out of one stalk. <verse-number id="Ge 41:6">6</verse-number>And behold, seven thin ears of grain, scorched by the east wind, sprouted up after them. <verse-number id="Ge 41:7">7</verse-number>And the thin ears of grain swallowed up the seven plump and full ears of grain. Then Pharaoh awoke, and behold, <supplied>it was</supplied> a dream. <verse-number id="Ge 41:8">8</verse-number>And it happened <supplied>that</supplied> in the morning his spirit was troubled, and he sent and called all of the magicians<note>Or “soothsayer priests”</note> of Egypt, and all its wise men, and Pharaoh told his dream to them. But <idiom-start/>they had no interpretation<idiom-end/><note>Literally “there was no interpretation with them”</note> for Pharaoh. <verse-number id="Ge 41:9">9</verse-number>Then the chief of the cupbearers spoke with Pharaoh, saying, “I remember my sins today. <verse-number id="Ge 41:10">10</verse-number>Pharaoh was angry with his servants, and he put me and the chief baker in the custody of the house of the chief of the guard. <verse-number id="Ge 41:11">11</verse-number>And we dreamed a dream one night, I and he, <idiom-start/>each with a dream that had a meaning<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “each according to his dream we dreamed”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 41:12">12</verse-number>And there with us <supplied>was</supplied> a young man, a Hebrew servant of the chief of the guard, and we told him <supplied>the dream</supplied>, and he interpreted our dreams for us, each according to his dream he interpreted. <verse-number id="Ge 41:13">13</verse-number>And it happened just as he interpreted to us, so it was. He<note>That is, Pharaoh</note> restored me to my office, and him<note>That is, the chief baker</note> he<note>That is, Pharaoh</note> hanged.” <verse-number id="Ge 41:14">14</verse-number>Then Pharaoh sent and called <supplied>for</supplied> Joseph, and they brought him quickly from the prison. And he shaved and changed his clothing, and came to Pharaoh. <verse-number id="Ge 41:15">15</verse-number>Then Pharaoh said to Joseph, “I dreamed a dream, but there is none to interpret it. Now, I have heard concerning you <supplied>that when</supplied> you hear a dream <supplied>you can</supplied> interpret it.” <verse-number id="Ge 41:16">16</verse-number>Then Joseph answered Pharaoh saying, “<idiom-start/>It is not in my power<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “besides me”</note> God will answer <supplied>concerning</supplied> the well-being of Pharaoh.” <verse-number id="Ge 41:17">17</verse-number>And Pharaoh said to Joseph, “<supplied>Now</supplied> in my dream, behold, I was standing on the bank of the Nile, <verse-number id="Ge 41:18">18</verse-number>and behold, seven cows, <idiom-start/>well built and fat<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “beautiful of appearance and healthy of flesh”</note> were coming up from the Nile, and they grazed among the reeds. <verse-number id="Ge 41:19">19</verse-number>And behold, seven other cows came up after them from the Nile, very <idiom-start/>ugly and gaunt<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Poor of appearance and thin of flesh”</note>—never have I seen <supplied>any</supplied> as them in all the land of Egypt for ugliness. <verse-number id="Ge 41:20">20</verse-number>And the thin and ugly cows ate the former seven healthy cows. <verse-number id="Ge 41:21">21</verse-number>But <supplied>when</supplied> they went into their bellies<note>Or “inner parts”</note> it could not be known that they went into their bellies,<note>Or “inner parts”</note> for their appearance <supplied>was</supplied> as ugly as at the beginning. Then I awoke. <verse-number id="Ge 41:22">22</verse-number>Then I saw in my dream and behold, seven ears of grain were coming out of one stalk, full and good. <verse-number id="Ge 41:23">23</verse-number>And behold, seven withered ears of grain, thin <supplied>and</supplied> scorched by the east wind, sprouted up after them. <verse-number id="Ge 41:24">24</verse-number>And the thin ears of grain swallowed up the seven good ears of grain. And I told the magicians,<note>Or “soothsayer priests”</note> but there was none to explain <supplied>it</supplied> to me.” <verse-number id="Ge 41:25">25</verse-number>Then Joseph said to Pharaoh, “The dreams of Pharaoh <supplied>are</supplied> one. God has revealed to Pharaoh what he is about to do. <verse-number id="Ge 41:26">26</verse-number>The seven good cows, they are seven years, and the seven good ears of grain, they <supplied>are</supplied> seven years. The dreams <supplied>are</supplied> one. <verse-number id="Ge 41:27">27</verse-number>And the seven thin and ugly cows coming up after them, they <supplied>are</supplied> seven years, and the seven empty ears of grain, scorched by the east wind, they are <supplied>also</supplied> seven years of famine. <verse-number id="Ge 41:28">28</verse-number>This <supplied>is</supplied> the word that I have spoken to Pharaoh; God has shown Pharaoh what he is about to do. <verse-number id="Ge 41:29">29</verse-number>Behold, seven years of great abundance are coming throughout the whole land of Egypt. <verse-number id="Ge 41:30">30</verse-number>Then seven years of famine will arise after them, and all the abundance in the land of Egypt will be forgotten. The famine will consume the land. <verse-number id="Ge 41:31">31</verse-number>Abundance in the land will not be known because of the famine <idiom-start/>that follows<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “that thus afterwards”</note> for it will be very heavy. <verse-number id="Ge 41:32">32</verse-number>Now concerning the repetition of the dream twice to Pharaoh, <supplied>it is</supplied> because the matter <supplied>is</supplied> established by God, and God will do <supplied>it</supplied> quickly. <verse-number id="Ge 41:33">33</verse-number>Now then, let Pharaoh select a man <supplied>who is</supplied> discerning and wise, and let him set him over the land of Egypt. <verse-number id="Ge 41:34">34</verse-number>Let Pharaoh do <supplied>this</supplied>, and let him appoint supervisors over the land, and let him take one-fifth from the land of Egypt in the seven years of abundance. <verse-number id="Ge 41:35">35</verse-number>Then let them gather all the food of these coming good years and let them pile up grain under the hand of Pharaoh <supplied>for</supplied> food in the cities, and let them keep <supplied>it</supplied>. <verse-number id="Ge 41:36">36</verse-number>Then the food shall be as a deposit for the land for the seven years of the famine that will be in the land of Egypt, that the land will not perish on account of the famine.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Joseph Rises to Power</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 41:37">37</verse-number>And the plan<note>Or “word”</note> was good in the eyes of Pharaoh and in the eyes of all his servants. <verse-number id="Ge 41:38">38</verse-number>Then Pharaoh said to his servants, “Can we find a man like this in whom is the spirit of God?” <verse-number id="Ge 41:39">39</verse-number>Then Pharaoh said to Joseph, “Since God has made all of this known to you there is no one as discerning and wise as you. <verse-number id="Ge 41:40">40</verse-number>You shall be over my house, and to your word<note>Or “mouth”</note> all my people shall submit. Only <supplied>with respect to</supplied> the throne will I be greater than you.” <verse-number id="Ge 41:41">41</verse-number>Then Pharaoh said to Joseph, “See, I have set you over all the land of Egypt.” <verse-number id="Ge 41:42">42</verse-number>Then Pharaoh removed his signet ring from his finger and put it on the finger of Joseph. And he clothed him with garments of fine linen, and he put a chain of gold around his neck. <verse-number id="Ge 41:43">43</verse-number>And he had him ride in his second chariot. And they cried out before him, “Kneel!” And Pharaoh set him over all the land of Egypt. <verse-number id="Ge 41:44">44</verse-number>Then Pharaoh said to Joseph, “I <supplied>am</supplied> Pharaoh, but without your consent no one will lift his hand or his foot in all the land of Egypt.” <verse-number id="Ge 41:45">45</verse-number>And Pharaoh called the name of Joseph Zaphenath-paneah and gave him Asenath, the daughter of Potiphera, priest of On, as a wife. And Joseph went out over the land of Egypt. <verse-number id="Ge 41:46">46</verse-number>Now Joseph <idiom-start/>was thirty years old<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a son of thirty years”</note> when he stood before Pharaoh, the king of Egypt. And Joseph went out from the presence of Pharaoh and traveled through the whole land of Egypt. <verse-number id="Ge 41:47">47</verse-number>And the land produced a plenty in the seven years of abundance. <verse-number id="Ge 41:48">48</verse-number>And he gathered all the food of the seven years which <supplied>occurred</supplied> in the land of Egypt. And he stored the food in the cities. The food of the field that surrounded <supplied>each</supplied> city he stored in its midst. <verse-number id="Ge 41:49">49</verse-number>And Joseph piled up grain like the sand of the sea in great abundance until he stopped counting <supplied>it</supplied>, for <idiom-start/>it could not be counted<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “there was no number”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 41:50">50</verse-number>Before the years of famine came, Asenath, daughter of Potiphera priest of On, bore two sons to him. <verse-number id="Ge 41:51">51</verse-number>And Joseph called the name of the firstborn Manasseh, for <supplied>he said</supplied>, “God has caused me to forget all my hardship and all my father’s house.” <verse-number id="Ge 41:52">52</verse-number>And the name of the second he called Ephraim, for <supplied>he said</supplied>, “God has made me fruitful in the land of my misfortune.” <verse-number id="Ge 41:53">53</verse-number>And the seven years of abundance which <supplied>were</supplied> in the land of Egypt came to an end. <verse-number id="Ge 41:54">54</verse-number>And the seven years of famine began to come as Joseph had said. And there was famine in all of the countries, but in the land of Egypt there was food. <verse-number id="Ge 41:55">55</verse-number>And when all the land of Egypt was hungry the people cried out to Pharaoh for food. And Pharaoh said to all the land of Egypt, “Go to Joseph; what he says to you, you must do.” <verse-number id="Ge 41:56">56</verse-number>And the famine was over the whole land, and Joseph opened all the storehouses<note>Hebrew “that which was in them”</note> and sold <supplied>food</supplied> to the Egyptians. And the famine was severe in the land of Egypt. <verse-number id="Ge 41:57">57</verse-number>And every land came to Egypt to Joseph to buy grain, for the famine was severe in every land. </p>
		</chapter>