<chapter id="Ge 43">
			<pericope>Joseph’s Brothers Return to Egypt</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 43:1">1</verse-number>Now the famine in the land <supplied>was</supplied> severe. <verse-number id="Ge 43:2">2</verse-number>And it happened <supplied>that</supplied> as they finished eating the grain which they had brought from Egypt their father said to them, “Return and buy a little food for us.” <verse-number id="Ge 43:3">3</verse-number>Then Judah said to him, “The man solemnly admonished us, saying, ‘You shall not see my face unless your brother <supplied>is</supplied> with you.’ <verse-number id="Ge 43:4">4</verse-number><idiom-start/>If you will send<idiom-end/><note>Literally “if there is a sending”</note> our brother with us, we will go down and buy food for you, <verse-number id="Ge 43:5">5</verse-number>but <idiom-start/>if you will not send<idiom-end/><note>Literally “if there is no sending”</note> <supplied>him</supplied>, we will not go down, for the man said to us, ‘You shall not see my face unless your brother <supplied>is</supplied> with you.’ ” <verse-number id="Ge 43:6">6</verse-number>Then Israel said, “Why did you bring trouble to me by telling the man you still had a brother?” <verse-number id="Ge 43:7">7</verse-number>And they said, “The man asked explicitly about us and about our family, saying, ‘Is your father still alive? Do you have a brother?’ And we answered him according to these words. How could we know that he would say, ‘Bring down your brother’?” <verse-number id="Ge 43:8">8</verse-number>Then Judah said to his father Israel, “Send the boy with me, and let us arise and go, so that we will live and not die—you, we, and our children. <verse-number id="Ge 43:9">9</verse-number>I myself will be surety for him. You may seek him from my hand. If I do not bring him back to you and present him before you, then I will stand guilty before you forever. <verse-number id="Ge 43:10">10</verse-number>Surely if we had not hesitated by this <supplied>time</supplied> we would have returned twice.” <verse-number id="Ge 43:11">11</verse-number>Then their father Israel said to them, “If <supplied>it must be</supplied> so then do this. Take some of the best products of the land in your bags and take them down to the man as a gift—a little balm and honey, aromatic gum and myrrh, and pistachios and almonds. <verse-number id="Ge 43:12">12</verse-number>And take double <supplied>the</supplied> money in your hands. Take back the money that was returned in the mouth of your sacks. Perhaps it <supplied>was</supplied> a mistake. <verse-number id="Ge 43:13">13</verse-number>And take your brother. Now arise and return to the man. <verse-number id="Ge 43:14">14</verse-number>And may El-Shaddai<note>Often translated “God Almighty”</note> grant you compassion before the man that he may release your other brother to you and Benjamin. As for me, if I am bereaved, I am bereaved.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 43:15">15</verse-number>So the men took this gift, and they took double money in their hands, and Benjamin, and they rose up and went down to Egypt and stood before Joseph. <verse-number id="Ge 43:16">16</verse-number>When Joseph saw Benjamin with them he said to the one who <supplied>was</supplied> over his household, “Bring the men into the house and slaughter and prepare <supplied>an animal</supplied>, for the men shall eat with me at noon.” <verse-number id="Ge 43:17">17</verse-number>And the man did as Joseph had said, and the man brought the men into the house of Joseph. <verse-number id="Ge 43:18">18</verse-number>And the men were afraid when they were brought into the house of Joseph. And they said “We were brought <supplied>here</supplied> on account of the money that was returned to our sacks the first time, that he might attack us and fall upon us to take us as slaves with our donkeys.” <verse-number id="Ge 43:19">19</verse-number>So they approached the man who <supplied>was</supplied> over Joseph’s house and spoke to him at the doorway of the house. <verse-number id="Ge 43:20">20</verse-number>And they said, “Please, my lord, we surely came down once before to buy food, <verse-number id="Ge 43:21">21</verse-number>but when we came to the place of lodging and we opened our sacks, then behold, each one’s money <supplied>was</supplied> in the mouth of his sack—our money in its <supplied>full</supplied> weight—so we have returned <supplied>with</supplied> it in our hands. <verse-number id="Ge 43:22">22</verse-number>Now, other money we have brought down in our hand to buy food. We do not know who put our money in our sacks.” <verse-number id="Ge 43:23">23</verse-number>And he said, “Peace to you; do not be afraid. Your God and the God of your father must have given you a treasure in your sacks; your money came to me.” And he brought Simeon out to them. <verse-number id="Ge 43:24">24</verse-number>Then the man brought the men into Joseph’s house and he gave them water and washed their feet, and gave fodder to their donkeys. <verse-number id="Ge 43:25">25</verse-number>Then they laid out<note>Or “prepared”</note> the gift until Joseph came at noon, for they had heard that they were to eat food there. <verse-number id="Ge 43:26">26</verse-number>And when Joseph came into the house they brought the gift that <supplied>was</supplied> in their hand into the house to him, and they bowed down before him to the ground. <verse-number id="Ge 43:27">27</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>he greeted them<idiom-end/><note>Literally “he asked peace for them”</note> and said, “Is your father well, the old man of whom you spoke? Is he still alive?” <verse-number id="Ge 43:28">28</verse-number>And they said, “Your servant our father <supplied>is</supplied> well; he is still alive.” And they knelt and bowed down. <verse-number id="Ge 43:29">29</verse-number>Then he lifted up his eyes and saw Benjamin his brother, the son of his mother, and said, “Is this your youngest brother of whom you told me?” And he continued,<note>Or “said”</note> “God be gracious to you, my son.” <verse-number id="Ge 43:30">30</verse-number>Then Joseph <idiom-start/>hurried away<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “made haste”</note> <idiom-start/>being overcome with emotion<idiom-end/><note>Literally “his compassion boiled up”</note> toward his brother, and sought for <supplied>a place</supplied> to cry. Then he went into a room and wept there. <verse-number id="Ge 43:31">31</verse-number>Then he washed his face and went out, now controlling himself, and said, “Serve the food.” <verse-number id="Ge 43:32">32</verse-number>And they served him<note>That is, Joseph</note> by himself, and them by themselves, and the Egyptians who were eating with him by themselves, for Egyptians <idiom-start/>could not dine<idiom-end/><note>Literally “were not able to eat food”</note> with Hebrews, because that <supplied>was</supplied> a detestable thing to Egyptians. <verse-number id="Ge 43:33">33</verse-number>And they were seated before him <supplied>from</supplied> the firstborn according to his birthright <supplied>to</supplied> the youngest according to his youth. And the men <idiom-start/>looked at one another<idiom-end/><note>Literally “each to his companion”</note> amazed. <verse-number id="Ge 43:34">34</verse-number>And portions were served to them from <idiom-start/>his table<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “his presence”</note> and the portion of Benjamin was five times greater than the portion of any of them. And they drank and became drunk with him. </p>
		</chapter>