<chapter id="Ge 44">
			<pericope>Joseph Tests His Brothers</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 44:1">1</verse-number>Then he commanded <supplied>the one</supplied> who <supplied>was</supplied> over his household, saying, “Fill the sacks of the men <supplied>with</supplied> food as much as they are able to carry, and put each one’s money in the mouth of his sack. <verse-number id="Ge 44:2">2</verse-number>And my cup—the cup of silver—you shall put into the mouth of the sack of the youngest, and the money for his grain. And he did according to the word of Joseph that he had commanded. <verse-number id="Ge 44:3">3</verse-number><supplied>When</supplied> the morning light <supplied>came</supplied> the men were sent away, they and their donkeys. <verse-number id="Ge 44:4">4</verse-number>They went out of the city, <supplied>and</supplied> had not gone far when Joseph said to <supplied>the one</supplied> who <supplied>was</supplied> over his house, “Arise! Pursue after the men and overtake them. Then you shall say to them, ‘Why have you repaid evil for good? <verse-number id="Ge 44:5">5</verse-number>Is this not that from which my master drinks? Now he himself certainly practices divination with it. You have done evil <supplied>in</supplied> what you have done.’ ” <verse-number id="Ge 44:6">6</verse-number>When he overtook them he spoke these words to them. <verse-number id="Ge 44:7">7</verse-number>And they said to him, “Why has my lord spoken according to these words? Far be it from your servants to do such a thing! <verse-number id="Ge 44:8">8</verse-number>Behold, the money that we found in the mouth of our sacks we returned to you from the land of Canaan. Now why would we steal silver or gold from the house of my lord? <verse-number id="Ge 44:9">9</verse-number>Whoever is found with it from among your servants shall die. And moreover, we will become slaves to my lord.” <verse-number id="Ge 44:10">10</verse-number>Then he said, “Now also according to your words, thus will it be. He who is found with it shall be my slave, but you shall be innocent.” <verse-number id="Ge 44:11">11</verse-number>Then each man quickly brought down his sack to the ground, and each one opened his sack. <verse-number id="Ge 44:12">12</verse-number>And he searched, beginning with the oldest and finishing with the youngest. And the cup was found in the sack of Benjamin. <verse-number id="Ge 44:13">13</verse-number>Then they tore their clothes, and each one loaded his donkey and they returned to the city. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 44:14">14</verse-number>And Judah and his brothers came to the house of Joseph—now he <supplied>was</supplied> still there—they fell before him to the ground. <verse-number id="Ge 44:15">15</verse-number>Then Joseph said to them, “What is this deed that you have done? Did you not know that a man who <supplied>is</supplied> like me surely practices divination?” <verse-number id="Ge 44:16">16</verse-number>And Judah said, “What can we say to my lord? What can we speak? Now how can we show ourselves innocent? God has found the guilt of your servants! Behold, we <supplied>are</supplied> slaves to my lord, both we and also he in whose hand the cup was found.” <verse-number id="Ge 44:17">17</verse-number>But he said, “Far be it from me to do this! The man in whose hand the cup was found, he will become my slave. But as for you, go up in peace to your father.” <verse-number id="Ge 44:18">18</verse-number>But Judah drew near to him and said, “Please my lord, let your servant speak a word in the ears of my lord, and <idiom-start/>let not your anger burn<idiom-end/><note>Literally “let not your nose become hot”</note> against your servant, for <idiom-start/>you are like Pharaoh himself<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “like you like Pharaoh”</note> <verse-number id="Ge 44:19">19</verse-number>My lord had asked his servants, saying, ‘Do you have a father or a brother?’ <verse-number id="Ge 44:20">20</verse-number>And we said to my lord, ‘We have an aged father, and a younger <supplied>brother</supplied>, the child of his old age, and his brother died, and he alone remains from his mother, and his father loves him.’ <verse-number id="Ge 44:21">21</verse-number>Then you said to your servants, ‘Bring him down to me that I may set my eyes upon him.’ <verse-number id="Ge 44:22">22</verse-number>Then we said to my lord, ‘The boy cannot leave his father; if he should leave his father, then he<note>That is, the father (Jacob/Israel)</note> would die.’ <verse-number id="Ge 44:23">23</verse-number>Then you said to your servants, ‘Unless your youngest brother comes down with you, you shall not again see my face.’ <verse-number id="Ge 44:24">24</verse-number>And it happened <supplied>that</supplied> we went up to your servant, my father, and told him the words of my lord. <verse-number id="Ge 44:25">25</verse-number>And when our father said, ‘Buy a little food for us,’ <verse-number id="Ge 44:26">26</verse-number>then we said, ‘We cannot go down. If our youngest brother <supplied>is</supplied> with us, then we shall go down. For we will not be able to see the face of the man unless our youngest brother <supplied>is</supplied> with us.’ <verse-number id="Ge 44:27">27</verse-number>Then your servant, my father, said to us, ‘You yourselves know that my wife bore two sons to me. <verse-number id="Ge 44:28">28</verse-number>One went out from me, and I said, “Surely he must have been torn to pieces,” and I have never seen him since. <verse-number id="Ge 44:29">29</verse-number>And if you take this one also from me, and he encounters harm, you will bring down my gray head in sorrow to Sheol.’ <verse-number id="Ge 44:30">30</verse-number>So now, when I come to your servant, my father, and the boy is not with us—now his life is bound up with his life—<verse-number id="Ge 44:31">31</verse-number>it shall happen <supplied>that</supplied> when he sees that the boy is gone, he will die. And your servants will bring down the gray head of your servant, our father, to Sheol with sorrow. <verse-number id="Ge 44:32">32</verse-number>For your servant is pledged as surety for the boy by my father, saying, If I do not bring him to you, then I shall be culpable to my father forever. <verse-number id="Ge 44:33">33</verse-number>So then, please let your servant remain in place of the boy as a slave to my lord, and let the boy go up with his brothers. <verse-number id="Ge 44:34">34</verse-number>For how can I go up to my father if the boy is not with me? <idiom-start/>I do not want to see<idiom-end/><note>Literally “lest I see”</note> the misery which will find my father.” </p>
		</chapter>