<chapter id="Ge 45">
			<pericope>Joseph Reveals His Identity</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 45:1">1</verse-number>Then Joseph was not able to control himself before all who were standing by him. And he cried out, “Make every man go out from me!” So no one stood with him when Joseph made himself known to his brothers. <verse-number id="Ge 45:2">2</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>he wept loudly<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “he gave his voice with weeping”</note> so that the Egyptians heard <supplied>it</supplied> and the household of Pharaoh heard <supplied>it</supplied>. <verse-number id="Ge 45:3">3</verse-number>Then Joseph said to his brothers, “I <supplied>am</supplied> Joseph! Is my father still alive?” And his brothers were unable to answer him, for they were dismayed at his presence. <verse-number id="Ge 45:4">4</verse-number>So Joseph said to his brothers, “Come near to me, please.” And they drew near. And he said, “I <supplied>am</supplied> Joseph, your brother, whom you sold into Egypt. <verse-number id="Ge 45:5">5</verse-number>So now, do not be distressed and do not be angry <idiom-start/>with yourselves<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in your eyes”</note> that you sold me here, for God sent me as deliverance before you. <verse-number id="Ge 45:6">6</verse-number>For these two years the famine <supplied>has been</supplied> in the midst of the land, but <supplied>there will be</supplied> five more years where there is no plowing or harvest. <verse-number id="Ge 45:7">7</verse-number>And God sent me before you <supplied>all</supplied> to preserve for you a remnant in the land and to keep alive among you many survivors. <verse-number id="Ge 45:8">8</verse-number>So now, you yourselves did not send me here, but God put me here as father to Pharaoh and as master of all his household, and a ruler over all the land of Egypt. <verse-number id="Ge 45:9">9</verse-number>Hurry, and go up to my father and say to him, ‘Thus says your son Joseph, God has made me lord of all Egypt. Come down to me and do not delay. <verse-number id="Ge 45:10">10</verse-number>You shall settle in the land of Goshen so that you will be near me, you and your children and your grandchildren, and your flocks and your herds and all that you have. <verse-number id="Ge 45:11">11</verse-number>And I will provide for you there, because <supplied>there are</supplied> still five years of famine—lest you and your household and all that you have become destitute.’ <verse-number id="Ge 45:12">12</verse-number>Now behold, your eyes see, and the eyes of my brother Benjamin see, that <idiom-start/>it is I<idiom-end/><note>Literally “it is my mouth”</note> who am speaking to you. <verse-number id="Ge 45:13">13</verse-number>And you must tell my father of all my honor in Egypt and all that you have seen. Now hurry and bring my father here.” <verse-number id="Ge 45:14">14</verse-number>Then he fell upon the neck of his brother Benjamin and wept, and Benjamin wept upon his neck. <verse-number id="Ge 45:15">15</verse-number>And he kissed all his brothers and wept upon them. And afterward his brothers spoke with him. <verse-number id="Ge 45:16">16</verse-number>Then the report was heard <supplied>in</supplied> the house of Pharaoh, saying, “Joseph’s brothers have come.” And it pleased Pharaoh and his servants. <verse-number id="Ge 45:17">17</verse-number>Then Pharaoh said to Joseph, “Say to your brothers: ‘Do this—load your donkeys and go back to the land of Canaan, <verse-number id="Ge 45:18">18</verse-number>and take your father and your households and come to me, and I will give you the best of the land of Egypt, and you shall eat the fat of the land.’ <verse-number id="Ge 45:19">19</verse-number>And you <supplied>Joseph</supplied>, are commanded <supplied>to say</supplied> this: ‘Do this! Take wagons from the land of Egypt for your little ones and your wives, and bring your father and come! <verse-number id="Ge 45:20">20</verse-number><idiom-start/>Do not worry<idiom-end/><note>Literally “let not your eyes be troubled”</note> about your possessions, for the best of all the land of Egypt is yours.’ ” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 45:21">21</verse-number>And the sons of Israel did so. And Joseph gave them wagons at the word of Pharaoh, and gave them provisions for the journey. <verse-number id="Ge 45:22">22</verse-number>To each and to all of them he gave sets of clothing, but to Benjamin he gave three hundred pieces of silver and five sets of clothing. <verse-number id="Ge 45:23">23</verse-number>And to his father he sent <idiom-start/>as follows<idiom-end/>:<note>Literally “according to this”</note> ten donkeys carrying the best of Egypt, and ten donkeys carrying grain and food and provisions for his father for the journey. <verse-number id="Ge 45:24">24</verse-number>Then he sent his brothers away, and when they departed he said to them, “Do not be agitated on the journey.” <verse-number id="Ge 45:25">25</verse-number>So they went up from Egypt and came to the land of Canaan to Jacob their father. <verse-number id="Ge 45:26">26</verse-number>And they spoke to him, saying, “Joseph <supplied>is</supplied> still alive, and he <supplied>is</supplied> ruler over all the land of Egypt.” And his heart <idiom-start/>went numb<idiom-end/>,<note>Or “became cold”</note> because he did not believe him. <verse-number id="Ge 45:27">27</verse-number>Then they told him all the words of Joseph that he had spoken to them. And when he saw the wagons that Joseph had sent to carry him, then the spirit of Jacob their father revived. <verse-number id="Ge 45:28">28</verse-number>And Israel said, “<supplied>It is</supplied> enough. Joseph my son <supplied>is</supplied> still alive. I will go and see him before I die.” </p>
		</chapter>