<chapter id="Ge 49">
			<pericope>Jacob Blesses His Twelve Sons</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 49:1">1</verse-number>Then Jacob called his sons and said, “Gather together so that I can tell you what will happen with you in <idiom-start/>days to come<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the latter days”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ge 49:2">2</verse-number>Assemble and hear, O sons of Jacob! </li1>
				<li2>Listen to Israel your father! </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ge 49:3">3</verse-number>Reuben, you <supplied>are</supplied> my firstborn, </li1>
				<li2>my strength, and the firstfruit of my vigor, </li2>
				<li2>excelling in rank and excelling in power. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ge 49:4">4</verse-number>Unstable<note>Or “reckless”</note> as water, you shall not excel <supplied>any longer</supplied>, </li1>
				<li2>for you went up upon the bed of your father, </li2>
				<li2>then defiled <supplied>it</supplied>. You went up upon my couch! </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ge 49:5">5</verse-number>Simeon and Levi <supplied>are</supplied> brothers; </li1>
				<li2>weapons of violence <supplied>are</supplied> their swords. </li2>
				<li2>Let me<note>Or “my soul”</note> not come into their council. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ge 49:6">6</verse-number>Let not my person<note>Or “my glory”</note> be joined to their company. </li1>
				<li2>For in their anger they killed men, </li2>
				<li2>and at their pleasure they hamstrung cattle. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ge 49:7">7</verse-number>Cursed be their anger, for <supplied>it is</supplied> fierce, </li1>
				<li2>and their wrath, for <supplied>it is</supplied> cruel. </li2>
				<li1>I will divide them in Jacob, </li1>
				<li2>and I will scatter them in Israel. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ge 49:8">8</verse-number>Judah, <supplied>as for</supplied> you, your brothers shall praise you. </li1>
				<li2>Your hand <supplied>shall be</supplied> on the neck of your enemies. </li2>
				<li2>The sons of your father shall bow down to you. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ge 49:9">9</verse-number>Judah <supplied>is</supplied> a lion’s cub. </li1>
				<li2>From the prey, my son, you have gone up. </li2>
				<li1>He bowed down; he crouched like a lion and as a lioness. </li1>
				<li2>Who shall rouse him? </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ge 49:10">10</verse-number>The scepter shall not depart from Judah, </li1>
				<li2>nor the ruler’s staff between his feet, </li2>
				<li1>until Shiloh comes. </li1>
				<li2>And to him shall be the obedience of nations. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ge 49:11">11</verse-number>Binding his donkey to the vine </li1>
				<li2>and his donkey’s colt to the choice vine, </li2>
				<li1>he washes his clothing in the wine </li1>
				<li2>and his garment in the blood of grapes. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ge 49:12">12</verse-number>The eyes <supplied>are</supplied> darker than wine, </li1>
				<li2>and the teeth whiter than milk. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ge 49:13">13</verse-number>Zebulun shall settle by the shore of the sea. </li1>
				<li2>He <supplied>shall become</supplied> a haven for ships, </li2>
				<li2>and his border <supplied>shall be</supplied> at Sidon. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ge 49:14">14</verse-number>Issachar <supplied>is</supplied> a strong donkey, </li1>
				<li2>crouching between the sheepfolds. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ge 49:15">15</verse-number>He saw a resting place that <supplied>was</supplied> good, </li1>
				<li2>and land that <supplied>was</supplied> pleasant. </li2>
				<li1>So he bowed his shoulder to the burden </li1>
				<li2>and became a servant of forced labor. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ge 49:16">16</verse-number>Dan shall judge his people </li1>
				<li2>as one of the tribes of Israel. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ge 49:17">17</verse-number>Dan shall be a serpent on the way, </li1>
				<li2>a viper on the road </li2>
				<li1>that bites the heels of a horse, </li1>
				<li2>so that its rider falls backward. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ge 49:18">18</verse-number>I wait for your salvation, O Yahweh. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ge 49:19">19</verse-number>Bandits shall attack Gad, </li1>
				<li2>but he shall attack <supplied>their</supplied> heels. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ge 49:20">20</verse-number>Asher’s food <supplied>is</supplied> delicious, </li1>
				<li2>and he shall provide from the king’s delicacies. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ge 49:21">21</verse-number>Naphtali <supplied>is</supplied> a doe running free </li1>
				<li2>that puts forth beautiful words. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ge 49:22">22</verse-number>Joseph <supplied>is</supplied> the bough<note>Or “son”</note> of a fruitful vine, </li1>
				<li2>a fruitful bough<note>Or “son”</note> by a spring. </li2>
				<li2>His branches climb over the wall. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ge 49:23">23</verse-number><idiom-start/>The archers<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the masters of the bow”</note> fiercely attacked him. </li1>
				<li2>They shot arrows <supplied>at him</supplied> and were hostile to him. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ge 49:24">24</verse-number>But his bow remained in a steady position; </li1>
				<li2><idiom-start/>his arms<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the arms of his hands”</note> were made agile </li2>
				<li1>by the hands of the Mighty One of Jacob. </li1>
				<li2>From there <supplied>is</supplied> the Shepherd, the Rock of Israel. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ge 49:25">25</verse-number>Because of the God of your father he will help you </li1>
				<li2>and <supplied>by</supplied> Shaddai<note>Or “the Almighty”</note> he will bless you </li2>
				<li2>with the blessings of heaven above, </li2>
				<li1>blessings of the deep that crouches beneath, </li1>
				<li2>blessings of the breasts and the womb. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ge 49:26">26</verse-number>The blessings of your father </li1>
				<li2>are superior to the blessings of my ancestors, </li2>
				<li2>to the bounty of the everlasting hills. </li2>
				<li1>May they be on the head of Joseph, </li1>
				<li2>and on the forehead of the prince of his brothers. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ge 49:27">27</verse-number>Benjamin <supplied>is</supplied> a devouring wolf, </li1>
				<li2>devouring the prey in the morning, </li2>
				<li2>and dividing the plunder in the evening. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Death and Burial of Jacob</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ge 49:28">28</verse-number>All these <supplied>are</supplied> the twelve tribes of Israel, and this <supplied>is</supplied> what their father said to them when he blessed them, each according to their blessing. <verse-number id="Ge 49:29">29</verse-number>Then he instructed them and said to them, “I am <supplied>about to be</supplied> gathered to my people. Bury me among my ancestors<note>Or “fathers”</note> in the cave that <supplied>is</supplied> in the field of Ephron the Hittite, <verse-number id="Ge 49:30">30</verse-number>in the cave that <supplied>is</supplied> in the field of Machpelah that <supplied>is</supplied> before<note>Or “east of”</note> Mamre in the land of Canaan, which Abraham bought with the field from Ephron the Hittite as a burial site. <verse-number id="Ge 49:31">31</verse-number>There they buried Abraham and Sarah his wife. There they buried Isaac and Rebekah his wife. And there I buried Leah—<verse-number id="Ge 49:32">32</verse-number>the purchase of the field and the cave which <supplied>was</supplied> in it from the Hittites.” <verse-number id="Ge 49:33">33</verse-number>When Jacob finished instructing his sons he drew his feet up to the bed. Then he took his last breath and was gathered to his people. </p>
		</chapter>