<chapter id="1 Ch 1">
			<pericope>From Adam to Abraham</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 1:1">1</verse-number>Adam, Seth, Enosh; <verse-number id="1 Ch 1:2">2</verse-number>Kenan, Mahalalel, Jared; <verse-number id="1 Ch 1:3">3</verse-number>Enoch, Methuselah, Lamech; <verse-number id="1 Ch 1:4">4</verse-number>Noah, Shem, Ham, and Japheth. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 1:5">5</verse-number>The sons of Japheth: Gomer, Magog, Madai, Javan, Tubal, Meshech, and Tiras. <verse-number id="1 Ch 1:6">6</verse-number>The sons of Gomer: Ashkenaz, Diphath, and Togarmah. <verse-number id="1 Ch 1:7">7</verse-number>The sons of Javan: Elishah, Tarshish, Kittim, and Rhodanim. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 1:8">8</verse-number>The sons of Ham: Cush, Mizraim, Put, and Canaan. <verse-number id="1 Ch 1:9">9</verse-number>The sons of Cush: Seba, Havilah, Sabta, Raamah, and Sabteca. And the sons of Raamah: Sheba and Dedan. <verse-number id="1 Ch 1:10">10</verse-number>And Cush fathered Nimrod; he himself began to be mighty on earth. <verse-number id="1 Ch 1:11">11</verse-number>And Mizraim fathered the Ludim, the Anamim, the Lehabim, the Naphtuhim, <verse-number id="1 Ch 1:12">12</verse-number>the Pathrusim, the Casluhim (from whence the Philistines descended), and the Caphtorim. <verse-number id="1 Ch 1:13">13</verse-number>And Canaan fathered Zidon his firstborn, and Heth, <verse-number id="1 Ch 1:14">14</verse-number>and the Jebusites, the Amorites, the Girgashites, <verse-number id="1 Ch 1:15">15</verse-number>the Hivites, the Arkites, the Sinites, <verse-number id="1 Ch 1:16">16</verse-number>the Arvadites, the Zemarites, and the Hamathites. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 1:17">17</verse-number>The sons of Shem: Elam, Asshur, Arphaxad, Lud, Aram, Uz, Hul, Gether, and Meshech. <verse-number id="1 Ch 1:18">18</verse-number>And Arphaxad fathered Shelah; and Shelah fathered Eber. <verse-number id="1 Ch 1:19">19</verse-number>And two sons were born to Eber: the name of the one <supplied>was</supplied> Peleg (for in his days the earth was divided), and the name of his brother <supplied>was</supplied> Joktan. <verse-number id="1 Ch 1:20">20</verse-number>And Joktan fathered Almodad, Sheleph, Hazarmaveth, Jerah, <verse-number id="1 Ch 1:21">21</verse-number>Hadoram, Uzal, Diklah, <verse-number id="1 Ch 1:22">22</verse-number>Ebal,<note>Spelled “Obal” in <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ge 10:28">Genesis 10:28</cite></note> Abimael, Sheba, <verse-number id="1 Ch 1:23">23</verse-number>Ophir, Havilah, and Jobab; all these were the sons of Joktan. <verse-number id="1 Ch 1:24">24</verse-number>Shem, Arphaxad, Shelah; <verse-number id="1 Ch 1:25">25</verse-number>Eber, Peleg, Reu; <verse-number id="1 Ch 1:26">26</verse-number>Serug, Nahor, Terah; <verse-number id="1 Ch 1:27">27</verse-number>Abram, that is, Abraham. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 1:28">28</verse-number>The sons of Abraham: Isaac and Ishmael. <verse-number id="1 Ch 1:29">29</verse-number>These <supplied>are</supplied> their generations: the firstborn of Ishmael, Nebaioth, and Kedar, Abdeel, Mibsam, <verse-number id="1 Ch 1:30">30</verse-number>Mishma, Dumah, Massa, Hadad, Tema, <verse-number id="1 Ch 1:31">31</verse-number>Jetur, Naphish, and Kedmah. These <supplied>are</supplied> the sons of Ishmael. <verse-number id="1 Ch 1:32">32</verse-number>And the sons of Keturah, Abraham’s concubine: she gave birth to Zimran, Jokshan, Medan, Midian, Ishbak, and Shuah. And the sons of Jokshan: Sheba and Dedan. <verse-number id="1 Ch 1:33">33</verse-number>And the sons of Midian: Ephah, Epher, Enoch, Abida, and Eldaah. All these <supplied>were</supplied> the sons of Keturah. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 1:34">34</verse-number>Abraham fathered Isaac. The sons of Isaac: Esau and Israel. <verse-number id="1 Ch 1:35">35</verse-number>The sons of Esau: Eliphaz, Reuel, Jeush, Jalam, and Korah. <verse-number id="1 Ch 1:36">36</verse-number>The sons of Eliphaz: Teman, Omar, Zephi,<note>Spelled “Zepho” in <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ge 36:11">Genesis 36:11</cite></note> Gatam, Kenaz, Timna, and Amalek. <verse-number id="1 Ch 1:37">37</verse-number>The sons of Reuel: Nahath, Zerah, Shammah, and Mizzah. <verse-number id="1 Ch 1:38">38</verse-number>And the sons of Seir: Lotan, Shobal, Zibeon, Anah, Dishon, Ezer, and Dishan. <verse-number id="1 Ch 1:39">39</verse-number>And the sons of Lotan: Hori and Homam; and the sister of Lotan <supplied>was</supplied> Timna. <verse-number id="1 Ch 1:40">40</verse-number>The sons of Shobal: Alian, Manahath, Ebal, Shephi, and Onam. And the sons of Zibeon: Aiah and Anah. <verse-number id="1 Ch 1:41">41</verse-number>The sons of Anah: Dishon. And the sons of Dishon: Hamran, Eshban, Ithran, and Keran. <verse-number id="1 Ch 1:42">42</verse-number>The sons of Ezer: Bilhan, Zaavan, and Jaakan. The sons of Dishan: Uz and Aran. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 1:43">43</verse-number>These <supplied>are</supplied> the kings who reigned in the land of Edom before any king reigned over the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>:<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> Bela son of Beor, and the name of his city <supplied>was</supplied> Dinhabah. <verse-number id="1 Ch 1:44">44</verse-number>When Bela died, Jobab son of Zerah from Bozrah reigned in his place. <verse-number id="1 Ch 1:45">45</verse-number>When Jobab died, Husham from the land of the Temanites reigned in his place. <verse-number id="1 Ch 1:46">46</verse-number>When Husham died, Hadad son of Bedad, who defeated the Midianites in the country of Moab, reigned in his place. And the name of his city was Avith.<note>According to the reading tradition (<i>Qere)</i>; <i>Kethib</i> has “Avuth”</note> <verse-number id="1 Ch 1:47">47</verse-number>When Hadad died, Samlah from Masrekah reigned in his place. <verse-number id="1 Ch 1:48">48</verse-number>When Samlah died, Shaul from Rehoboth-by-the-River reigned in his place. <verse-number id="1 Ch 1:49">49</verse-number>When Shaul died, Baal-Hanan son of Achbor reigned in his place. <verse-number id="1 Ch 1:50">50</verse-number>When Baal-Hanan died, Hadad reigned in his place, and the name of his city <supplied>was</supplied> Pai.<note>Spelled “Pau” in <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ge 36:39">Genesis 36:39</cite></note> And the name of his wife <supplied>was</supplied> Mehetabel, daughter of Matred, daughter of Me-Zahab. <verse-number id="1 Ch 1:51">51</verse-number>And Hadad died. And the chiefs of Edom were: chiefs Timna, Aliah, Jetheth, <verse-number id="1 Ch 1:52">52</verse-number>Oholibamah, Elah, Pinon, <verse-number id="1 Ch 1:53">53</verse-number>Kenaz, Teman, Mibzar, <verse-number id="1 Ch 1:54">54</verse-number>Magdiel, and Iram. These <supplied>are</supplied> the chiefs of Edom. </p>
		</chapter>