<chapter id="1 Ch 2">
			<pericope>The Genealogy of David</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 2:1">1</verse-number>These <supplied>are</supplied> the sons of Israel: Reuben, Simeon, Levi, Judah, Issachar, Zebulun, <verse-number id="1 Ch 2:2">2</verse-number>Dan, Joseph, Benjamin, Naphtali, Gad, and Asher. <verse-number id="1 Ch 2:3">3</verse-number>The sons of Judah: Er, Onan and Shelah; <supplied>these</supplied> three were born to him from Bathshua the Canaanite. Now Er, Judah’s firstborn, <supplied>was</supplied> evil in the sight of Yahweh, and he put him to death. <verse-number id="1 Ch 2:4">4</verse-number>And Tamar his daughter-in-law bore Perez and Zerah to him. The sons of Judah <supplied>were</supplied> five in all. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 2:5">5</verse-number>The sons of Perez: Hezron and Hamul. <verse-number id="1 Ch 2:6">6</verse-number>The sons of Zerah: Zimri, Ethan, Heman, Calcol, and Dara, five in all. <verse-number id="1 Ch 2:7">7</verse-number>The son of Carmi: Achar, the troubler of Israel, who acted unfaithfully in the matter of the devoted thing. <verse-number id="1 Ch 2:8">8</verse-number>And the son of Ethan <supplied>was</supplied> Azariah. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 2:9">9</verse-number>The sons of Hezron who were born to him: Jerahmeel, Ram, and Caleb. <verse-number id="1 Ch 2:10">10</verse-number>And Ram fathered Amminadab, and Amminadab fathered Nahshon, prince of the sons of Judah. <verse-number id="1 Ch 2:11">11</verse-number>And Nahshon fathered Salma, and Salma fathered Boaz. <verse-number id="1 Ch 2:12">12</verse-number>And Boaz fathered Obed, and Obed fathered Jesse. <verse-number id="1 Ch 2:13">13</verse-number>And Jesse fathered Eliab his firstborn, Abinadab the second, Shimea the third, <verse-number id="1 Ch 2:14">14</verse-number>Nethanel the fourth, Raddai the fifth, <verse-number id="1 Ch 2:15">15</verse-number>Ozem the sixth, David the seventh. <verse-number id="1 Ch 2:16">16</verse-number>And their sisters <supplied>were</supplied> Zeruiah and Abigail. The sons of Zeruiah: Abishai, Joab, and Asahel, three. <verse-number id="1 Ch 2:17">17</verse-number>And Abigail bore Amasa, and the father of Amasa <supplied>was</supplied> Jether the Ishmaelite. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 2:18">18</verse-number>And Caleb the son of Hezron fathered children by Azubah his wife and by Jerioth. And these <supplied>were</supplied> her sons: Jesher, Shobab, and Ardon. <verse-number id="1 Ch 2:19">19</verse-number>And when Azubah died, Caleb married<note>Or “took”</note> Ephrathah, and she bore Hur to him. <verse-number id="1 Ch 2:20">20</verse-number>And Hur fathered Uri, and Uri fathered Bezalel. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 2:21">21</verse-number>And afterward Hezron went in to the daughter of Makir the father of Gilead. And he married<note>Or “took”</note> her when he was sixty years old. And she bore Segub to him. <verse-number id="1 Ch 2:22">22</verse-number>And Segub fathered Jair, and he had twenty-three cities in the land of Gilead. <verse-number id="1 Ch 2:23">23</verse-number>And Geshur and Aram took Havvoth-Jair from them, Kenath and its villages, sixty cities. All these <supplied>were</supplied> the <idiom-start/>descendants<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons”</note> of Makir, the father of Gilead. <verse-number id="1 Ch 2:24">24</verse-number>And after the death of Hezron in Caleb-Ephrathah, Abijah the wife of Hezron bore to him Ashhur, the father of Tekoa. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 2:25">25</verse-number>And the sons of Jerahmeel the firstborn of Hezron were Ram his firstborn, Bunah, Oren, Ozem, and Ahijah. <verse-number id="1 Ch 2:26">26</verse-number>And Jerahmeel had another wife, and her name <supplied>was</supplied> Atarah. She <supplied>was</supplied> the mother of Onam. <verse-number id="1 Ch 2:27">27</verse-number>The sons of Ram the firstborn of Jerahmeel were Maaz, Jamin, and Eker. <verse-number id="1 Ch 2:28">28</verse-number>And the sons of Onam were Shammai and Jada. And the sons of Shammai <supplied>were</supplied> Nadab and Abishur. <verse-number id="1 Ch 2:29">29</verse-number>And the name of the wife of Abishur <supplied>was</supplied> Abihail, and she bore to him Ahban and Molid. <verse-number id="1 Ch 2:30">30</verse-number>And the sons of Nadab <supplied>were</supplied> Seled and Appaim. And Seled died without children. <verse-number id="1 Ch 2:31">31</verse-number>And the sons of Appaim: Ishi. The sons of Ishi: Sheshan. The sons of Sheshan: Ahlai. <verse-number id="1 Ch 2:32">32</verse-number>And the sons of Jada the brother of Shammai: Jether and Jonathan. And Jether died without children. <verse-number id="1 Ch 2:33">33</verse-number>And the sons of Jonathan: Peleth and Zaza. These were the children of Jerahmeel. <verse-number id="1 Ch 2:34">34</verse-number>And Sheshan had no sons, only daughters, but Sheshan had an Egyptian slave, and his name <supplied>was</supplied> Jarha. <verse-number id="1 Ch 2:35">35</verse-number>So Sheshan gave his daughter to Jarha his slave for a wife, and she bore to him Attai. <verse-number id="1 Ch 2:36">36</verse-number>And Attai fathered Nathan, and Nathan fathered Zabad. <verse-number id="1 Ch 2:37">37</verse-number>And Zabad fathered Ephlal, and Ephlal fathered Obed. <verse-number id="1 Ch 2:38">38</verse-number>And Obed fathered Jehu, and Jehu fathered Azariah. <verse-number id="1 Ch 2:39">39</verse-number>And Azariah fathered Helez, and Helez fathered Eleasah. <verse-number id="1 Ch 2:40">40</verse-number>And Eleasah fathered Sismai, and Sismai fathered Shallum. <verse-number id="1 Ch 2:41">41</verse-number>And Shallum fathered Jekamiah, and Jekamiah fathered Elishama. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 2:42">42</verse-number>And the sons of Caleb the brother of Jerahmeel were Mesha his firstborn; he <supplied>was</supplied> the father of Ziph. The sons of Mareshah: Hebron. <verse-number id="1 Ch 2:43">43</verse-number>And the sons of Hebron <supplied>were</supplied> Korah, Tappuah, Rekem, and Shema. <verse-number id="1 Ch 2:44">44</verse-number>And Shema fathered Raham, the father of Jorkeam. And Rekem fathered Shammai. <verse-number id="1 Ch 2:45">45</verse-number>And the son of Shammai <supplied>was</supplied> Maon, and Maon <supplied>was</supplied> the father of Beth-Zur. <verse-number id="1 Ch 2:46">46</verse-number>And Ephah, the concubine of Caleb, gave birth to Haran, Moza, and Gazez. And Haran fathered Gazez. <verse-number id="1 Ch 2:47">47</verse-number>And the sons of Jahdai <supplied>were</supplied> Regem, Jotham, Geshan, Pelet, Ephah, and Shaaph. <verse-number id="1 Ch 2:48">48</verse-number>Maacah, the concubine of Caleb, gave birth to Sheber and Tirhanah. <verse-number id="1 Ch 2:49">49</verse-number>She also gave birth to Shaaph the father of Madmannah, Sheva the father of Machbenah and the father of Gibea; and the daughter of Caleb <supplied>was</supplied> Acsah. <verse-number id="1 Ch 2:50">50</verse-number>These were the <idiom-start/>descendants<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons”</note> of Caleb. </p>
			<p>The sons of Hur the firstborn of Ephrathah: Shobal the father of Kiriath-Jearim, <verse-number id="1 Ch 2:51">51</verse-number>Salma the father of Bethlehem, <supplied>and</supplied> Hareph the father of Beth-Gader. <verse-number id="1 Ch 2:52">52</verse-number>And Shobal the father of Kiriath-Jearim had <supplied>other</supplied> sons: Haroeh, half of the Menuhoth. <verse-number id="1 Ch 2:53">53</verse-number>And the families of Kiriath-Jearim: the Ithrites, the Puthites, the Shumathites, and the Mishraites. From these descended the Zorathites and the Eshtaolites. <verse-number id="1 Ch 2:54">54</verse-number>The sons of Salma: Bethlehem, the Netophathites, Ataroth-Beth-Joab, and half of the Manahathites, the Zorites. <verse-number id="1 Ch 2:55">55</verse-number>And the families of the scribes who lived <supplied>at</supplied> Jabez: the Tirathites, the Shimeathites, and the Sucathites. These <supplied>were</supplied> the Kenites who came from Hammath, the father of the house of Recab. </p>
		</chapter>