<chapter id="1 Ch 3">
			<pericope>The Descendants of David</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 3:1">1</verse-number>These were the sons of David who were born to him in Hebron: the firstborn, Amnon, by Ahinoam the Jezreelite; the second, Daniel, by Abigail the Carmelite; <verse-number id="1 Ch 3:2">2</verse-number>the third, Absalom, the son of Maacah the daughter of Talmai, king of Geshur; the fourth, Adonijah, the son of Haggith; <verse-number id="1 Ch 3:3">3</verse-number>the fifth, Shephatiah, by Abital; the sixth, Ithream, by his wife Eglah. <verse-number id="1 Ch 3:4">4</verse-number>Six were born to him in Hebron. And he reigned there seven years and six months. And he reigned thirty-three years in Jerusalem. <verse-number id="1 Ch 3:5">5</verse-number>And these were born to him in Jerusalem: Shimea, Shobab, Nathan, and Solomon, four by Bathshua the daughter of Ammiel; <verse-number id="1 Ch 3:6">6</verse-number>then Ibhar, Elishama, Eliphelet, <verse-number id="1 Ch 3:7">7</verse-number>Nogah, Nepheg, Japhia, <verse-number id="1 Ch 3:8">8</verse-number>Elishama, Eliada, and Eliphelet, nine. <verse-number id="1 Ch 3:9">9</verse-number>All these <supplied>were</supplied> the sons of David, besides the sons of the concubines. And Tamar was their sister. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 3:10">10</verse-number>Now the son of Solomon <supplied>was</supplied> Rehoboam; Abijah <supplied>was</supplied> his son, Asa <supplied>was</supplied> his son, Jehoshaphat <supplied>was</supplied> his son, <verse-number id="1 Ch 3:11">11</verse-number>Joram <supplied>was</supplied> his son, Ahaziah <supplied>was</supplied> his son, Joash <supplied>was</supplied> his son, <verse-number id="1 Ch 3:12">12</verse-number>Amaziah <supplied>was</supplied> his son, Azariah <supplied>was</supplied> his son, Jotham <supplied>was</supplied> his son, <verse-number id="1 Ch 3:13">13</verse-number>Ahaz <supplied>was</supplied> his son, Hezekiah <supplied>was</supplied> his son, Manasseh <supplied>was</supplied> his son, <verse-number id="1 Ch 3:14">14</verse-number>Amon <supplied>was</supplied> his son, Josiah <supplied>was</supplied> his son. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 3:15">15</verse-number>And the sons of Josiah: Johanan the firstborn, the second Jehoiakim, the third Zedekiah, the fourth Shallum. <verse-number id="1 Ch 3:16">16</verse-number>And the <idiom-start/>descendants<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons”</note> of Jehoiakim: Jeconiah his son, Zedekiah his son. <verse-number id="1 Ch 3:17">17</verse-number>And the sons of Jeconiah, the captive: Shealtiel his son, <verse-number id="1 Ch 3:18">18</verse-number>Malchiram, Pedaiah, Shenazzar, Jekamiah, Hoshama, and Nedabiah. <verse-number id="1 Ch 3:19">19</verse-number>And the sons of Pedaiah: Zerubbabel and Shimei. And the sons of Zerubbabel: Meshullam and Hananiah, and Shelomith their sister, <verse-number id="1 Ch 3:20">20</verse-number>and Hashubah, Ohel, Berekiah, Hasadiah, and Jushab-Hesed, five. <verse-number id="1 Ch 3:21">21</verse-number>And the sons of Hananiah: Pelatiah and Jeshaiah. The sons of Rephaiah, the sons of Arnan, the sons of Obadiah, the sons of Shecaniah. <verse-number id="1 Ch 3:22">22</verse-number>And the sons of Shecaniah: Shemaiah. And the sons of Shemaiah: Hattush, Igal, Bariah, Neariah, and Shaphat, six. <verse-number id="1 Ch 3:23">23</verse-number>And the sons of Neariah: Elioenai, Hezekiah, and Azrikam, three. <verse-number id="1 Ch 3:24">24</verse-number>And the sons of Elioenai: Hodaviah, Eliashib, Pelaiah, Akkub, Johanan, Delaiah, and Anani, seven. </p>
		</chapter>