<chapter id="1 Ch 4">
			<pericope>The Descendants of David</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 4:1">1</verse-number>The sons of Judah: Perez, Hezron, Carmi, Hur, and Shobal. <verse-number id="1 Ch 4:2">2</verse-number>And Reaiah the son of Shobal fathered Jahath, and Jahath fathered Ahumai and Lahad. These <supplied>were</supplied> the clans of the Zorathites. <verse-number id="1 Ch 4:3">3</verse-number>And these <supplied>were</supplied> the sons of Etam: Jezreel, Ishma, and Idbash. And the name of their sister <supplied>was</supplied> Hazzelelponi, <verse-number id="1 Ch 4:4">4</verse-number>and Penuel <supplied>was</supplied> the father of Gedor, and Ezer <supplied>was</supplied> the father of Hushah. These <supplied>were</supplied> the sons of Hur, the firstborn of Ephrathah, the father of Bethlehem. <verse-number id="1 Ch 4:5">5</verse-number>And Ashhur, the father of Tekoa, had two wives: Helah and Naarah. <verse-number id="1 Ch 4:6">6</verse-number>And Naarah bore him Ahuzzam, Hepher, Temeni, and Haahashtari. These <supplied>were</supplied> the sons of Naarah. <verse-number id="1 Ch 4:7">7</verse-number>The sons of Helah: Zereth, Izhar, and Ethnan. <verse-number id="1 Ch 4:8">8</verse-number>And Koz fathered Anub, Zobebah, and the clans of Aharhel, the son of Harum. <verse-number id="1 Ch 4:9">9</verse-number>And Jabez was more honorable than his brothers. And his mother called his name Jabez, saying, “Because I bore him in pain.” <verse-number id="1 Ch 4:10">10</verse-number>And Jabez called upon the God of Israel, saying, “Oh that you would surely bless me and enlarge my border. And may your hand be with me, that you would keep me from evil so that it might not harm me!” And God granted what he asked. <verse-number id="1 Ch 4:11">11</verse-number>Chelub, the brother of Shuhah, fathered Mehir. He <supplied>was</supplied> the father of Eshton. <verse-number id="1 Ch 4:12">12</verse-number>And Eshton fathered Beth-Rapha, Paseah, and Tehinnah, the father of the city of Nahash. These <supplied>are</supplied> the men of Recah. <verse-number id="1 Ch 4:13">13</verse-number>The sons of Kenaz: Othniel and Seraiah. And the sons of Othniel: Hathath. <verse-number id="1 Ch 4:14">14</verse-number>And Meonothai fathered Ophrah; and Seraiah fathered Joab, the father of Ge-Harashim, because they <supplied>were</supplied> craftsmen. <verse-number id="1 Ch 4:15">15</verse-number>The sons of Caleb, the son of Jephunneh: Iru, Elah, and Naam. And the sons of Elah: Kenaz. <verse-number id="1 Ch 4:16">16</verse-number>The sons of Jehallelel: Ziph, Ziphah, Tiria, and Asarel. <verse-number id="1 Ch 4:17">17</verse-number>The sons of Ezrah: Jether, Mered, Epher, and Jalon. And she became pregnant with Miriam, Shammai, and Ishbah, the father of Eshtemoa. <verse-number id="1 Ch 4:18">18</verse-number>And his Judahite wife bore Jered the father of Gedor, Heber the father of Soco, and Jekuthiel the father of Zanoah. And these <supplied>were</supplied> the sons of Bithiah daughter of Pharaoh, whom Mered married. <verse-number id="1 Ch 4:19">19</verse-number>The sons of the wife of Hodiah, the sister of Naham, <supplied>were</supplied> the fathers of Keilah the Garmite and Eshtemoa the Maacathite. <verse-number id="1 Ch 4:20">20</verse-number>The sons of Shimon: Amnon, Rinnah, Ben-Hanan, and Tolon. The sons of Ishi: Zoheth and Ben-Zoheth. <verse-number id="1 Ch 4:21">21</verse-number>The sons of Shelah, the son of Judah: Er the father of Lecah, Laadah the father of Mareshah, and the families of the house of linen workers at Beth Ashbea; <verse-number id="1 Ch 4:22">22</verse-number>and Jokim, and the men of Cozeba, and Joash, and Saraph, who ruled in Moab and returned to Lehem. (Now the records are ancient). <verse-number id="1 Ch 4:23">23</verse-number>These <supplied>were</supplied> the potters and inhabitants of Netaim and Gederah. They lived there with the king in his service. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Descendants of Simeon</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 4:24">24</verse-number>The sons of Simeon: Nemuel, Jamin, Jarib, Zerah, Shaul. <verse-number id="1 Ch 4:25">25</verse-number>Shallum his son, Mibsam his son, Mishma his son. <verse-number id="1 Ch 4:26">26</verse-number>The sons of Mishma: Hammuel his son, Zaccur his son, Shimei his son. <verse-number id="1 Ch 4:27">27</verse-number>Shimei had sixteen sons and six daughters, but his brothers did not have many children. But all their families did not multiply like the men of Judah. <verse-number id="1 Ch 4:28">28</verse-number>And they lived in Beersheba, Moladah, Hazar Shual, <verse-number id="1 Ch 4:29">29</verse-number>Bilhah, Ezem, Tolad, <verse-number id="1 Ch 4:30">30</verse-number>Bethuel, Hormah, Ziklag, <verse-number id="1 Ch 4:31">31</verse-number>Beth-Marcaboth, Hazar-Susim, Beth-Biri, and Shaaraim. These <supplied>were</supplied> their cities until David reigned. <verse-number id="1 Ch 4:32">32</verse-number>And their villages <supplied>were</supplied> Etam, Ain, Rimmon, Token, and Ashan, five cities <verse-number id="1 Ch 4:33">33</verse-number>and all their villages that surrounding these cities as far as Baal. These <supplied>were</supplied> their settlements, and they kept a genealogical record for them. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 4:34">34</verse-number>Meshobab, Jamlech, and Joshah the son of Amaziah, <verse-number id="1 Ch 4:35">35</verse-number>Joel, and Jehu the son of Joshibiah, son of Seraiah, son of Asiel. <verse-number id="1 Ch 4:36">36</verse-number>And Elioenai, Jaakobah, Jeshohaiah, Asaiah, Adiel, Jesimiel, Benaiah, <verse-number id="1 Ch 4:37">37</verse-number>and Ziza the son of Shiphi, son of Allon, son of Jedaiah, son of Shimri, son of Shemaiah. <verse-number id="1 Ch 4:38">38</verse-number>These <idiom-start/>mentioned by name<idiom-end/><note>Literally “coming in the names”</note> <supplied>were</supplied> leaders in their families, and their fathers’ households increased greatly. <verse-number id="1 Ch 4:39">39</verse-number>And they went to the entrance of Gedor, up to the east side of the valley, to seek pasture for their flocks. <verse-number id="1 Ch 4:40">40</verse-number>And they found fertile and good pasture, and the land <supplied>was</supplied> very broad, quiet, and at ease, for the former inhabitants there <supplied>were</supplied> from Ham. <verse-number id="1 Ch 4:41">41</verse-number>These, mentioned by name, came in the days of Hezekiah, king of Judah, and attacked their tents and the Meunites who were found there. And they devoted them to destruction to this day, and they settled among them because <supplied>there was</supplied> pasture there for their flocks. <verse-number id="1 Ch 4:42">42</verse-number>And some of them from the Simeonites went to Mount Seir, five hundred men. And Pelatiah, Neariah, Rephaiah, and Uzziel, the sons of Ishi, <supplied>were</supplied> under their leadership. <verse-number id="1 Ch 4:43">43</verse-number>And they destroyed the remainder of the Amalekites who had escaped, and they have lived there to this day. </p>
		</chapter>