<chapter id="1 Ch 8">
			<pericope>The Genealogy of Saul</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 8:1">1</verse-number>Now Benjamin fathered Bela his firstborn, Ashbel the second, Aharah the third, <verse-number id="1 Ch 8:2">2</verse-number>Nohah the fourth, and Rapha the fifth. <verse-number id="1 Ch 8:3">3</verse-number>And Bela had sons: Addar, Gera, Abihud, <verse-number id="1 Ch 8:4">4</verse-number>Abishua, Naaman, Ahoah, <verse-number id="1 Ch 8:5">5</verse-number>Gera, Shephuphan, and Huram. <verse-number id="1 Ch 8:6">6</verse-number>And these <supplied>are</supplied> the sons of Ehud (these were heads of the <idiom-start/>families<idiom-end/><note>Literally “fathers”</note> for the inhabitants of Geba, and they took them away to Manahath): <verse-number id="1 Ch 8:7">7</verse-number>Naaman, Ahijah, and Gera, who took them away. And he fathered Uzza and Ahihud. <verse-number id="1 Ch 8:8">8</verse-number>And Shaharaim fathered <supplied>children</supplied> in the fields of Moab after he had sent them away—Hushim and Baara, his wives. <verse-number id="1 Ch 8:9">9</verse-number>And he fathered by Hodesh his wife Jobab, Zibia, Mesha, Malcam, <verse-number id="1 Ch 8:10">10</verse-number>Jeuz, Sakia, and Mirmah. These <supplied>were</supplied> his sons, heads of the <idiom-start/>families<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “fathers”</note> <verse-number id="1 Ch 8:11">11</verse-number>And by Husham he fathered Abitub and Elpaal. <verse-number id="1 Ch 8:12">12</verse-number>The sons of Elpaal: Eber, Misham, Shemed (he built Ono and Lod with <idiom-start/>its towns<idiom-end/>),<note>Literally “her daughters”</note> <verse-number id="1 Ch 8:13">13</verse-number>and Beriah and Shema who <supplied>were</supplied> the heads of the <idiom-start/>families<idiom-end/><note>Literally “fathers”</note> of the inhabitants of Aijalon (they themselves chased away the inhabitants of Gath). <verse-number id="1 Ch 8:14">14</verse-number>Now Ahio, Shashak, Jeremoth, <verse-number id="1 Ch 8:15">15</verse-number>Zebadiah, Arad, Eder, <verse-number id="1 Ch 8:16">16</verse-number>Michael, Ishpah, and Joha <supplied>were</supplied> sons of Beriah. <verse-number id="1 Ch 8:17">17</verse-number>And Zebadiah, Meshullam, Hizki, Heber, <verse-number id="1 Ch 8:18">18</verse-number>Ishmerai, Izliah, and Jobab <supplied>were</supplied> the sons of Elpaal. <verse-number id="1 Ch 8:19">19</verse-number>And Jakim, Zikri, Zabdi, <verse-number id="1 Ch 8:20">20</verse-number>Elienai, Zillethai, Eliel, <verse-number id="1 Ch 8:21">21</verse-number>Adaiah, Beraiah, and Shimrath <supplied>were</supplied> the sons of Shimei. <verse-number id="1 Ch 8:22">22</verse-number>And Ishpan, Eber, Eliel, <verse-number id="1 Ch 8:23">23</verse-number>Abdon, Zikri, Hanan, <verse-number id="1 Ch 8:24">24</verse-number>Hananiah, Elam, Antothijah, <verse-number id="1 Ch 8:25">25</verse-number>Iphdeiah, and Peniel <supplied>were</supplied> the sons of Shashak. <verse-number id="1 Ch 8:26">26</verse-number>And Shamsherai, Shehariah, Athaliah, <verse-number id="1 Ch 8:27">27</verse-number>Jaareshiah, Elijah, and Zikri <supplied>were</supplied> the sons of Jeroham. <verse-number id="1 Ch 8:28">28</verse-number>These <supplied>were</supplied> the heads of the <idiom-start/>families<idiom-end/><note>Literally “fathers”</note> according to their generations, chiefs. These lived in Jerusalem. <verse-number id="1 Ch 8:29">29</verse-number>And <supplied>Jeiel</supplied><note>The name Jeiel comes from <cite title="BibleLEB2: 1 Ch 9:35">1 Chronicles 9:35; </cite>it has dropped out of the text here</note> the father of Gibeon lived in Gibeon. And the name of his wife <supplied>was</supplied> Maacah. <verse-number id="1 Ch 8:30">30</verse-number>And his firstborn son <supplied>was</supplied> Abdon, then Zur, Kish, Baal, Nadab, <verse-number id="1 Ch 8:31">31</verse-number>Gedor, Ahio, Zeker, <verse-number id="1 Ch 8:32">32</verse-number>and Mikloth (he fathered Shimeah). Now these also lived nearby their brothers in Jerusalem with their kinsmen. <verse-number id="1 Ch 8:33">33</verse-number>And Ner fathered Kish, and Kish fathered Saul, and Saul fathered Jonathan, Malchi-Shua, Abinadab, and Eshbaal. <verse-number id="1 Ch 8:34">34</verse-number>And the son of Jonathan <supplied>was</supplied> Merib-baal, and Merib-baal fathered Micah. <verse-number id="1 Ch 8:35">35</verse-number>And the sons of Micah: Pithon, Melech, Tarea, and Ahaz. <verse-number id="1 Ch 8:36">36</verse-number>And Ahaz fathered Jehoaddah, and Jehoaddah fathered Alemeth, Azmaveth, and Zimri. And Zimri fathered Moza. <verse-number id="1 Ch 8:37">37</verse-number>And Moza fathered Binea; Raphah <supplied>was</supplied> his son, Eleasah his son, and Azel his son. <verse-number id="1 Ch 8:38">38</verse-number>And Azel had six sons, and these <supplied>are</supplied> their names: Azrikam, Bokeru, Ishmael, Sheariah, Obadiah, and Hanan. All these <supplied>were</supplied> the sons of Azel. <verse-number id="1 Ch 8:39">39</verse-number>And the sons of Eshek his brother: Ulam his firstborn, Jeush the second, and Eliphelet the third. <verse-number id="1 Ch 8:40">40</verse-number>And the sons of Ulam were men <supplied>who were</supplied> mighty warriors, bowmen, and <supplied>they had</supplied> many sons and grandsons, one hundred and fifty. All these were Benjaminites. </p>
		</chapter>