<chapter id="1 Ch 9">
			<pericope>The Genealogy of Returned Exiles</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 9:1">1</verse-number>So all Israel was enrolled in genealogy. And behold, they were written in the book of the kings of Israel. And Judah was taken away to Babylon on account of their sin. <verse-number id="1 Ch 9:2">2</verse-number>Now the first inhabitants who <supplied>were settled</supplied> on their property in their cities <supplied>in</supplied> Israel <supplied>were</supplied> the priests, the Levites, and the temple servants. <verse-number id="1 Ch 9:3">3</verse-number>And some of the people of Judah, Benjamin, Ephraim, and Manasseh lived in Jerusalem: <verse-number id="1 Ch 9:4">4</verse-number>Uthai the son of Ammihud, son of Omri, son of Imri, son of Bani,<note>According to the reading tradition (<i>Qere</i>)</note> from the sons of Perez,<note>According to the reading tradition (<i>Qere</i>)</note> the son of Judah. <verse-number id="1 Ch 9:5">5</verse-number>And from the Shilonites: Asaiah the firstborn and his sons. <verse-number id="1 Ch 9:6">6</verse-number>And from the sons of Zerah: Jeuel and their brethren, six hundred and ninety. <verse-number id="1 Ch 9:7">7</verse-number>And from the sons of Benjamin: Sallu the son of Meshullam, son of Hodaviah, the son of Hassenuah; <verse-number id="1 Ch 9:8">8</verse-number>Ibneah the son of Jeroham; Elah the son of Uzzi, son of Michri; Meshullam the son of Shephatiah, son of Reuel, son of Ibnijah; <verse-number id="1 Ch 9:9">9</verse-number>and their brethren according to their generations, nine hundred and fifty-six. All these men <supplied>were</supplied> the heads of the <idiom-start/>families<idiom-end/><note>Literally “fathers”</note> in the house of their fathers. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 9:10">10</verse-number>And from the priests: Jedaiah; Jehoiarib; Jakin; <verse-number id="1 Ch 9:11">11</verse-number>Azariah son of Hilkiah, son of Meshullam, son of Zadok, son of Meraioth, son of Ahitub, the commander of the house of God; <verse-number id="1 Ch 9:12">12</verse-number>Adaiah son of Jeroham, son of Pashhur, son of Malkijah; Maasai the son of Adiel, son of Jahzerah, son of Meshullam, son of Meshillemith, son of Immer; <verse-number id="1 Ch 9:13">13</verse-number>and their kinsmen, heads of the house of their fathers, one thousand seven hundred and sixty mighty men <supplied>for</supplied> the work of the service of the house of God. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 9:14">14</verse-number>And from the Levites: Shemaiah son of Hasshub, son of Azrikam, son of Hashabiah, from the sons of Merari; <verse-number id="1 Ch 9:15">15</verse-number>Bakbakkar; Heresh; Galal; Mattaniah the son of Mica, son of Zicri, son of Asaph; <verse-number id="1 Ch 9:16">16</verse-number>Obadiah the son of Shemaiah, son of Galal, son of Jeduthun; and Berechiah the son of Asa, son of Elkanah, who lived in the villages of Netophathite. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 9:17">17</verse-number>And the gatekeepers <supplied>were</supplied> Shallum, Akkub, Talmon, Ahiman, and their brethren (Shallum <supplied>was</supplied> the chief); <verse-number id="1 Ch 9:18">18</verse-number>until then they <supplied>were</supplied> gatekeepers at the gate of the king on the east <supplied>side</supplied> toward the camps of the Levites. <verse-number id="1 Ch 9:19">19</verse-number>And Shallum the son of Kore, son of Ebiasaph, son of Korah, and his kinsmen of the house of his fathers, the Korahites, <supplied>were</supplied> over the work of the service, the guardians of the entrances to the tent, and their fathers <supplied>were</supplied> over the camp of Yahweh, guardians of the entrance. <verse-number id="1 Ch 9:20">20</verse-number>And Phinehas the son of Eleazar was the leader over them <idiom-start/>in time past<idiom-end/>;<note>Or “before”</note> Yahweh <supplied>was</supplied> with him. <verse-number id="1 Ch 9:21">21</verse-number>Zechariah the son of Meshelemiah <supplied>was</supplied> gatekeeper at the doorway to the tent of assembly.<note>Or “meeting”</note> <verse-number id="1 Ch 9:22">22</verse-number>All of them were chosen as gatekeepers at the entrances, two hundred and twelve. They were enrolled by genealogies in their villages. They <supplied>were</supplied> established <supplied>by</supplied> David and Samuel the seer on account of their faithfulness. <verse-number id="1 Ch 9:23">23</verse-number>So they and their sons <supplied>were</supplied> over the gates of the house of Yahweh at the house of the tent as guards. <verse-number id="1 Ch 9:24">24</verse-number>The gatekeepers <supplied>were</supplied> on four sides: east, west, north, and south. <verse-number id="1 Ch 9:25">25</verse-number>And their brethren in their villages <supplied>were</supplied> to come <supplied>every</supplied> seven days <idiom-start/>by turn<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from time to time”</note> <supplied>to be</supplied> with these. <verse-number id="1 Ch 9:26">26</verse-number>For the four mighty gatekeepers, they who <supplied>were</supplied> Levites, <idiom-start/>were entrusted<idiom-end/><note>Literally “they in their faithfulness”</note> and <supplied>were</supplied> over the chambers and over the storerooms of the house of God. <verse-number id="1 Ch 9:27">27</verse-number>And they lodged all around the house of God, for upon them <supplied>was</supplied> a responsibility. And <idiom-start/>they had charge of opening <supplied>the house of God</supplied> every morning<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “they <supplied>were</supplied> over the key and to morning to morning”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 9:28">28</verse-number>And some of them <supplied>were</supplied> over the utensils of the service, for <idiom-start/>they count them<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in number”</note> <supplied>when</supplied> they are brought in and <idiom-start/>they count them<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in number”</note> <supplied>when</supplied> they are brought out. <verse-number id="1 Ch 9:29">29</verse-number>And some of them were appointed over the objects, over the objects of the sanctuary, and over the wheat flour and the wine, the olive oil, the frankincense, and the spices. <verse-number id="1 Ch 9:30">30</verse-number>And some of the sons of the priests mixed the fragrant ointment for the spices. <verse-number id="1 Ch 9:31">31</verse-number>And Mattithiah, one of the Levites, was the firstborn of Shallum the Korahite and <idiom-start/>was entrusted<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in faithfulness”</note> with the work of the pan breads. <verse-number id="1 Ch 9:32">32</verse-number>And from the sons of the Kohathites, some of their kinsmen <supplied>were</supplied> over the <idiom-start/>showbread<idiom-end/><note>Literally “bread of the rows”</note> to prepare <supplied>it</supplied> <idiom-start/>every Sabbath<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “Sabbath Sabbath”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 9:33">33</verse-number>Now these <supplied>were</supplied> the singers; the heads of the <idiom-start/>families<idiom-end/><note>Literally “fathers”</note> of the Levites <supplied>were</supplied> in the chambers free from other service, for day and night <supplied>they were</supplied> over them on the service. <verse-number id="1 Ch 9:34">34</verse-number>These <supplied>were</supplied> the heads of the <idiom-start/>families<idiom-end/><note>Literally “fathers”</note> of the Levites according to their genealogies, leaders. These lived in Jerusalem. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Saul’s Genealogy Repeated</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 9:35">35</verse-number>And <supplied>these</supplied> lived in Gibeon: Jeiel the father of Gibeon. And the name of his wife <supplied>was</supplied> Maacah. <verse-number id="1 Ch 9:36">36</verse-number>And his firstborn son Abdon, and Zur, Kish, Baal, Ner, Nadab, <verse-number id="1 Ch 9:37">37</verse-number>Gedor, Ahio, Zechariah, and Mikloth. <verse-number id="1 Ch 9:38">38</verse-number>And Mikloth fathered Shimeam. And they also lived nearby their brothers in Jerusalem with their brothers. <verse-number id="1 Ch 9:39">39</verse-number>And Ner fathered Kish, and Kish fathered Saul, and Saul fathered Jonathan, Malchi-Shua, Abinadab, and Eshbaal. <verse-number id="1 Ch 9:40">40</verse-number>And the son of Jonathan <supplied>was</supplied> Meribaal. And Meribaal fathered Micah. <verse-number id="1 Ch 9:41">41</verse-number>And the sons of Micah <supplied>were</supplied> Pithon, Melech, Tahrea, <supplied>and Ahaz.</supplied><note>The name is drawn from <cite title="BibleLEB2: 1 Ch 8:35">1 Chronicles 8:35; </cite>it has dropped out of the text here</note> <verse-number id="1 Ch 9:42">42</verse-number>And Ahaz fathered Jarah, and Jarah fathered Alemeth, Azmaveth, and Zimri. And Zimri fathered Moza, <verse-number id="1 Ch 9:43">43</verse-number>and Moza fathered Binea; and Rephaiah <supplied>was</supplied> his son, Eleasah his son, Azel his son. <verse-number id="1 Ch 9:44">44</verse-number>And Azel had six sons, and these <supplied>are</supplied> their names: Azrikam, Bokeru, Ishmael, Sheariah, Obadiah, and Hanan. These <supplied>were</supplied> the sons of Azel. </p>
		</chapter>