<chapter id="1 Ch 10">
			<pericope>The Death of Saul and His Sons</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 10:1">1</verse-number>Now the Philistines fought against Israel, and every Israelite fled away from before the Philistines. And they fell slain upon Mount Gilboa. <verse-number id="1 Ch 10:2">2</verse-number>And the Philistines <idiom-start/>overtook<idiom-end/><note>Literally “caught up behind”</note> Saul and his sons. And the Philistines killed Jonathan, Abinadab, and Malki-Shua, the sons of Saul. <verse-number id="1 Ch 10:3">3</verse-number>And the battle was heavy against Saul, and the <idiom-start/>archers<idiom-end/><note>Literally “shooters with the bow”</note> found him, and he was wounded by the <idiom-start/>archers<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “shooters”</note> <verse-number id="1 Ch 10:4">4</verse-number>And Saul said to his armor-bearer, “Draw your sword and thrust me through with it, lest these uncircumcised come and deal harshly with me.” But he was very afraid. Then Saul took the sword and fell upon it. <verse-number id="1 Ch 10:5">5</verse-number>When his armor-bearer saw that Saul <supplied>was</supplied> dead, he also fell upon the sword, and he died. <verse-number id="1 Ch 10:6">6</verse-number>So Saul died. And his three sons and all his house died together. <verse-number id="1 Ch 10:7">7</verse-number>And when all the men of Israel who <supplied>were</supplied> in the valley saw that they<note>That is, the army</note> had fled and that Saul and his sons were dead, they abandoned their cities and fled. Then the Philistines came and dwelled in them. <verse-number id="1 Ch 10:8">8</verse-number>And it happened <supplied>that</supplied> on the next day when the Philistines came to strip the dead, they found Saul and his sons fallen on Mount Gilboa. <verse-number id="1 Ch 10:9">9</verse-number>And they stripped him and took his head and his weapons, and they sent <supplied>them</supplied> throughout the land of the Philistines to bring news to their idols and the nation. <verse-number id="1 Ch 10:10">10</verse-number>And they put his weapons in the temple of their gods, and they fastened his skull to the temple of Dagon. <verse-number id="1 Ch 10:11">11</verse-number>When all Jabesh-Gilead heard all that the Philistines had done to Saul, <verse-number id="1 Ch 10:12">12</verse-number>every strong man arose and took the dead body of Saul and the dead bodies of his sons and brought them to Jabesh. And they buried their bones under the oak in Jabesh and fasted seven days. <verse-number id="1 Ch 10:13">13</verse-number>So Saul died on account of his sin which he had sinned against Yahweh concerning the command of Yahweh that he did not keep. He also consulted a medium to seek <supplied>guidance</supplied>. <verse-number id="1 Ch 10:14">14</verse-number>But he did not seek Yahweh. So Yahweh put him to death and turned over the kingship to David, the son of Jesse. </p>
		</chapter>