<chapter id="1 Ch 11">
			<pericope>The Anointing of David as King</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 11:1">1</verse-number>Then all Israel gathered to David in Hebron, saying, “Look—we are your flesh and bones. <verse-number id="1 Ch 11:2">2</verse-number><idiom-start/>For some time now<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “also yesterday also in the past”</note> even when Saul was king, you were <idiom-start/>the one who led the army of Israel in battle<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the one who went out and brought in Israel”</note> And Yahweh your God said to you, ‘You will shepherd my people Israel and will be leader over my people Israel.’ ” <verse-number id="1 Ch 11:3">3</verse-number>Then all the elders of Israel came to the king at Hebron, and David made a covenant with them at Hebron in the presence of Yahweh. And they anointed David as king over Israel according to the word of Yahweh by the hand of Samuel. <verse-number id="1 Ch 11:4">4</verse-number>And David and all Israel went to Jerusalem (that <supplied>is</supplied> Jebus). And the Jebusites, the inhabitants of the land, <supplied>were</supplied> there. <verse-number id="1 Ch 11:5">5</verse-number>And the inhabitants of Jebus said to David, “You will not enter here.” But David captured the stronghold of Zion; that <supplied>is,</supplied> the city of David. <verse-number id="1 Ch 11:6">6</verse-number>Then David said, “Whoever strikes the Jebusites first will be chief and commander.” And Joab the son of Zeruiah went up first and became chief. <verse-number id="1 Ch 11:7">7</verse-number>And David lived in the fortress. Therefore they called it the city of David. <verse-number id="1 Ch 11:8">8</verse-number>And he built the city all around from the Millo and up to the circuit. And Joab restored the remainder of the city. <verse-number id="1 Ch 11:9">9</verse-number>And David <idiom-start/>became greater and greater<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “increased certainly and <supplied>in</supplied> greatness”</note> And Yahweh of hosts <supplied>was</supplied> with him. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>David’s Mighty Men</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 11:10">10</verse-number>Now these <supplied>are</supplied> the chiefs of the mighty men who <supplied>were</supplied> for David, who gave him strong support in his kingdom, together with all Israel to make him king according to the word of Yahweh concerning Israel. <verse-number id="1 Ch 11:11">11</verse-number>And this <supplied>is</supplied> the numbering of the mighty warriors who <supplied>were</supplied> for David: Jashobeam son of Hachmoni <supplied>was</supplied> chief of the three. He himself raised his spear against three hundred <supplied>whom he</supplied> killed on one occasion. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 11:12">12</verse-number>And after him <supplied>was</supplied> Eleazar son of Dodo the Ahohite. He <supplied>was</supplied> among the three mighty warriors. <verse-number id="1 Ch 11:13">13</verse-number>He himself <supplied>was</supplied> with David at Pas-Dammim when the Philistines were gathered there for the battle. And there was a plot of the field filled with barley, and the people fled before the Philistines. <verse-number id="1 Ch 11:14">14</verse-number>But they took their stand in the middle of the plot and defended it. And they killed the Philistines. And Yahweh saved <supplied>them</supplied> <supplied>with</supplied> a great victory. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 11:15">15</verse-number>And three of the thirty chiefs went down toward the rock to David at the cave of Adullam when the army of the Philistines was encamped in the valley of Rephaim. <verse-number id="1 Ch 11:16">16</verse-number>And David <supplied>was</supplied> then in the stronghold, and the garrison of the Philistines <supplied>was</supplied> then in Bethlehem. <verse-number id="1 Ch 11:17">17</verse-number>And David had a craving, and he said, “Who could give me a drink of water from the well of Bethlehem that <supplied>is</supplied> by the gate!” <verse-number id="1 Ch 11:18">18</verse-number>Then the three broke through into the camp of the Philistines and drew water from the well of Bethlehem that <supplied>was</supplied> by the gate and brought <supplied>it</supplied> and came to David. But David would not drink it and poured it out before Yahweh. <verse-number id="1 Ch 11:19">19</verse-number>And he said, “Far be it from me <supplied>that</supplied> I would do this before my God. Shall I drink the lifeblood of these men? For <idiom-start/>at the risk of their lives<idiom-end/><note>Literally “against their lives”</note> they brought it.” And he was not willing to drink it. These things the three mighty men did. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 11:20">20</verse-number>Now Abishai the brother of Joab was himself the head of the three.<note>Other manuscripts have “thirty” which makes better sense in the context</note> And he roused himself with his spear against three hundred <supplied>whom he</supplied> killed and <supplied>made</supplied> a name for himself<note>According to the reading tradition (<i>Qere</i>)</note> among the three. <verse-number id="1 Ch 11:21">21</verse-number><idiom-start/>He was twice as renowned<idiom-end/><note>Literally “he was glorified double”</note> among the three<note>Other manuscripts have “thirty,” which makes better sense in the context</note> and was their commander. But he did not attain to the three. <verse-number id="1 Ch 11:22">22</verse-number><supplied>And</supplied> Benaiah the son of Jehoiada <supplied>was</supplied> <idiom-start/>a strong man<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a son of a strong man”</note> from Kabzeel, <supplied>one who did</supplied> great deeds. He himself struck down two <supplied>sons of</supplied> Ariel of Moab. And he himself went down and struck down a lion within a pit on a snowy day. <verse-number id="1 Ch 11:23">23</verse-number>And he himself struck down an Egyptian man, a large man five cubits <supplied>tall</supplied>. And in the hand of the Egyptian <supplied>was</supplied> a spear like a weaver’s beam. But he went down to him with a club and seized the spear from the hand of the Egyptian and killed him with his own spear. <verse-number id="1 Ch 11:24">24</verse-number>These things Benaiah son of Jehoiada did and had a name among the three mighty warriors. <verse-number id="1 Ch 11:25">25</verse-number>He himself was certainly distinguished among the thirty, but he did not attain to the three. And David appointed him over his bodyguard. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 11:26">26</verse-number>Now the mighty warriors of the troops <supplied>were</supplied> Asahel the brother of Joab, Elhanan the son of Dodo from Bethlehem, <verse-number id="1 Ch 11:27">27</verse-number>Shammoth the Harorite, Helez the Pelonite, <verse-number id="1 Ch 11:28">28</verse-number>Ira the son of Ikkesh the Tekoite, Abiezer the Anathothite, <verse-number id="1 Ch 11:29">29</verse-number>Sibbecai the Hushathite, Ilai the Ahohite, <verse-number id="1 Ch 11:30">30</verse-number>Maharai the Netophathite, Heled the son of Baanah the Netophathite, <verse-number id="1 Ch 11:31">31</verse-number>Ittai the son of Ribai from Gibeah of the people of Benjamin, Benaiah the Pirathonite, <verse-number id="1 Ch 11:32">32</verse-number>Hurai of the valleys of Gaash, Abiel the Arbathite, <verse-number id="1 Ch 11:33">33</verse-number>Azmaveth the Baharumite, Eliahba the Shaalbonite, <verse-number id="1 Ch 11:34">34</verse-number>the sons of Hashem the Gizonite, Jehonathan the son of Shagee the Hararite, <verse-number id="1 Ch 11:35">35</verse-number>Ahiam the son of Sacar the Hararite, Eliphal the son of Ur, <verse-number id="1 Ch 11:36">36</verse-number>Hepher the Mekerathite, Ahijah the Pelonite, <verse-number id="1 Ch 11:37">37</verse-number>Hezro the Carmelite, Naari the son of Ezbai, <verse-number id="1 Ch 11:38">38</verse-number>Joel the brother of Nathan, Mibhar the son of Hagri, <verse-number id="1 Ch 11:39">39</verse-number>Zelek the Ammonite, Naharai the Beerothite, the bearer of the weapons of Joab the son of Zeruiah, <verse-number id="1 Ch 11:40">40</verse-number>Ira the Ithrite, Gareb the Ithrite, <verse-number id="1 Ch 11:41">41</verse-number>Uriah the Hittite, Zabad the son of Ahlai, <verse-number id="1 Ch 11:42">42</verse-number>Adina the son of Shiza the Reubenite, a leader of the Reubenites, and thirty with him, <verse-number id="1 Ch 11:43">43</verse-number>Hanan the son of Maacah, Jehoshaphat the Mithnite, <verse-number id="1 Ch 11:44">44</verse-number>Uzzia the Ashterathite, Shama and Jeiel the sons of Hotham the Aroerite, <verse-number id="1 Ch 11:45">45</verse-number>Jediael the son of Shimri and Joha his brother the Tizite, <verse-number id="1 Ch 11:46">46</verse-number>Eliel the Mahavite, Jeribai and Joshaviah the sons of Elnaam, Ithmah the Moabite, <verse-number id="1 Ch 11:47">47</verse-number>Eliel, Obed, and Jaasiel the Mezobaite. </p>
		</chapter>