<chapter id="1 Ch 13">
			<pericope>The Ark of the Covenant Brought from Kiriath-Jearim</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 13:1">1</verse-number>And David consulted with the commanders of thousands and hundreds, with every leader. <verse-number id="1 Ch 13:2">2</verse-number>And David said to all the assembly of Israel, “<idiom-start/>If it seems good to you<idiom-end/><note>Literally “If to you good”</note> and before Yahweh our God, <idiom-start/>let us send word abroad<idiom-end/><note>Literally “let us spread out, let us send”</note> to our brothers who remain in all the land of Israel and <supplied>to</supplied> the priests and Levites with them in the cities with their pasturelands that they might be gathered to us. <verse-number id="1 Ch 13:3">3</verse-number>Then let us bring around the ark of our God to us, for we did not seek it in the days of Saul.” <verse-number id="1 Ch 13:4">4</verse-number>And all the assembly agreed to do so, for the word was pleasing in the eyes of all the people. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 13:5">5</verse-number>And David summoned all Israel from Shihor of Egypt up to Lebo-Hamath to bring the ark of God from Kiriath-Jearim. <verse-number id="1 Ch 13:6">6</verse-number>And David and all Israel went up to Baalah, Kiriath-Jearim of Judah, to bring up from there the ark of Yahweh God <supplied>who</supplied> is enthroned <supplied>between</supplied> the cherubim, which is called the name. <verse-number id="1 Ch 13:7">7</verse-number>And they carried the ark of God upon a new cart from the house of Abinadab, and Uzza and Ahio were driving the cart. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 13:8">8</verse-number>Now David and all Israel were celebrating before God with all <supplied>their</supplied> strength, and with songs, lyres, harps, tambourines, cymbals, and trumpets. <verse-number id="1 Ch 13:9">9</verse-number>And when they came to the threshing floor of Kidon, Uzza reached out his hand to hold the ark because the cattle had stumbled. <verse-number id="1 Ch 13:10">10</verse-number>And Yahweh <idiom-start/>was angry<idiom-end/><note>Literally “nostrils became hot”</note> with Uzza, and he struck him down because he reached his hand upon the ark. And he died there before God. <verse-number id="1 Ch 13:11">11</verse-number>And David <idiom-start/>was angry<idiom-end/><note>Literally “it was hot”</note> because Yahweh had broken out in wrath against Uzza. And that place is called Perez Uzza unto this day. <verse-number id="1 Ch 13:12">12</verse-number>And David feared God on that day, saying, “How can I bring the ark of God <supplied>home</supplied> to me?” <verse-number id="1 Ch 13:13">13</verse-number>So David did not move the ark to himself into the city of David but diverted it to the house of Obed-Edom the Gittite. <verse-number id="1 Ch 13:14">14</verse-number>And the ark of God remained with the household of Obed-Edom in his house three months. And Yahweh blessed the household of Obed-Edom and all that he had. </p>
		</chapter>