<chapter id="1 Ch 16">
			<pericope>The Ark of the Covenant Placed in Its Tent</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 16:1">1</verse-number>And they brought the ark of God and set it inside the tent that David had pitched for it. And they offered burnt offerings and fellowship offerings before God. <verse-number id="1 Ch 16:2">2</verse-number>And when David had finished offering the burnt offerings and fellowship offerings, he blessed the people in the name of Yahweh. <verse-number id="1 Ch 16:3">3</verse-number>And he distributed to every man of Israel, both men and women, to each <supplied>person</supplied> a loaf of bread, a cake of dates, and a cake of raisins. <verse-number id="1 Ch 16:4">4</verse-number>Then he appointed some of the Levites as ministers before the ark of Yahweh, to invoke, thank, and praise Yahweh the God of Israel. <verse-number id="1 Ch 16:5">5</verse-number>Asaph <supplied>was</supplied> chief, and his second <supplied>was</supplied> Zechariah; Jeiel, Shemiramoth, Jehiel, Mattithiah, Eliab, Benaiah, Obed-Edom, and Jeiel <supplied>were</supplied> on harps and lyres. And Asaph played on the cymbals. <verse-number id="1 Ch 16:6">6</verse-number>And Benaiah and Jahaziel the priests <supplied>blew</supplied> on the trumpets continually before the ark of the covenant of God. <verse-number id="1 Ch 16:7">7</verse-number>Then on that day David first appointed to give thanks to Yahweh by the hand of Asaph and his brothers. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>David’s Song of Thanks</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="1 Ch 16:8">8</verse-number>Give thanks to Yahweh; call upon his name; </li1>
				<li2>make known his deeds among the nations! </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="1 Ch 16:9">9</verse-number>Sing to him; sing praises to him; </li1>
				<li2>tell of his wondrous works! </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="1 Ch 16:10">10</verse-number>Glory in his holy name; </li1>
				<li2>let the hearts of those seeking Yahweh rejoice! </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="1 Ch 16:11">11</verse-number>Seek Yahweh and his strength; </li1>
				<li2>seek his face continually! </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="1 Ch 16:12">12</verse-number>Remember his wonderful works that he has done, </li1>
				<li2>his wonders and the judgments of his mouth, </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="1 Ch 16:13">13</verse-number>O offspring of Israel, his servant, </li1>
				<li2>O sons of Jacob, his chosen ones! </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="1 Ch 16:14">14</verse-number>He <supplied>is</supplied> Yahweh our God; </li1>
				<li2>his judgments <supplied>are</supplied> in all the earth. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="1 Ch 16:15">15</verse-number>Remember his covenant forever, </li1>
				<li2>the word he commanded for a thousand generations, </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="1 Ch 16:16">16</verse-number>that he <idiom-start/>made<idiom-end/><note>Literally “cut”</note> with Abraham, </li1>
				<li2>his sworn oath to Isaac. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="1 Ch 16:17">17</verse-number>And he confirmed it to Jacob as a statute, </li1>
				<li2>an everlasting covenant to Israel, </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="1 Ch 16:18">18</verse-number>saying, “To you I will give the land of Canaan, </li1>
				<li2>the portion of your inheritance.” </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="1 Ch 16:19">19</verse-number>When you were few in number, little, </li1>
				<li2>and sojourners <supplied>were</supplied> in it, </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="1 Ch 16:20">20</verse-number>when they wandered from nation to nation, </li1>
				<li2>and from one kingdom to another people, </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="1 Ch 16:21">21</verse-number>he did not allow anyone to oppress them, </li1>
				<li2>and he rebuked kings on their account, </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="1 Ch 16:22">22</verse-number><supplied>saying,</supplied> “You must not touch my anointed </li1>
				<li2>nor do harm to my prophets!” </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="1 Ch 16:23">23</verse-number>Sing to Yahweh, all the earth! </li1>
				<li2>Proclaim his salvation from day to day! </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="1 Ch 16:24">24</verse-number>Proclaim his glory among the nations, </li1>
				<li2>his wondrous works among the peoples! </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="1 Ch 16:25">25</verse-number>For Yahweh <supplied>is</supplied> great and greatly praised, </li1>
				<li2>and he is feared among all gods. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="1 Ch 16:26">26</verse-number>For all the gods of the nations <supplied>are</supplied> idols, </li1>
				<li2>but Yahweh made the heavens. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="1 Ch 16:27">27</verse-number>Splendor and majesty <supplied>are</supplied> before him; </li1>
				<li2>strength and joy <supplied>are</supplied> in his place. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="1 Ch 16:28">28</verse-number>Ascribe to Yahweh, O clans of the nations, </li1>
				<li2>ascribe to Yahweh glory and strength! </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="1 Ch 16:29">29</verse-number>Ascribe to Yahweh the glory of his name! </li1>
				<li2>Lift up an offering and come before him! </li2>
				<li2>Bow down to Yahweh in the splendor of holiness! </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="1 Ch 16:30">30</verse-number>Tremble before him, all the earth; </li1>
				<li2>surely the world shall not be shaken. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="1 Ch 16:31">31</verse-number>Let the heavens rejoice, and let the earth be glad, </li1>
				<li2>and let them tell the peoples, “Yahweh reigns!” </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="1 Ch 16:32">32</verse-number>Let the sea roar and its fullness; </li1>
				<li2>let the field rejoice and all that <supplied>is</supplied> in it. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="1 Ch 16:33">33</verse-number>Then the trees of the forest shall sing for joy before Yahweh, </li1>
				<li2>for he comes to judge the earth. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="1 Ch 16:34">34</verse-number>Oh give thanks to Yahweh, for he <supplied>is</supplied> good; </li1>
				<li2>his loyal love <supplied>is</supplied> everlasting. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="1 Ch 16:35">35</verse-number>Then say, “Save us, O God of our salvation; </li1>
				<li2>gather us and rescue us from the nations </li2>
				<li2>that <supplied>we may</supplied> give thanks to your holy name </li2>
				<li2><supplied>and</supplied> glory in your praise. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="1 Ch 16:36">36</verse-number>Blessed be Yahweh the God of Israel, </li1>
				<li2>from everlasting to everlasting!” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p>Then all the people said, “Amen!” and praised Yahweh. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Worship and the Ark</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 16:37">37</verse-number>So he<note>That is, David</note> left Asaph and his brothers there before the ark of the covenant of Yahweh to minister before the ark regularly <idiom-start/>as each day required<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “according to the word of a day with respect to its day”</note> <verse-number id="1 Ch 16:38">38</verse-number>and <supplied>he left</supplied> Obed-Edom with his sixty-eight brothers. And Obed-Edom, the son of Jeduthun, and Hosah <supplied>were</supplied> gatekeepers. <verse-number id="1 Ch 16:39">39</verse-number>And <supplied>he left</supplied> Zadok the priest and his brothers the priests before the tabernacle of Yahweh at the high place which <supplied>was</supplied> at Gibeon <verse-number id="1 Ch 16:40">40</verse-number>to offer burnt offerings regularly to Yahweh on the altar of burnt offering, morning and evening, according to all that was written in the law of Yahweh that he commanded concerning Israel. <verse-number id="1 Ch 16:41">41</verse-number>And with them <supplied>were</supplied> Heman and Jeduthun and the remainder of those chosen, who were designated by name to give thanks to Yahweh, for his loyal love <supplied>is</supplied> everlasting. <verse-number id="1 Ch 16:42">42</verse-number>And Heman and Jeduthun with them <supplied>had</supplied> trumpets and cymbals for making music, along with instruments for the song of God. And the sons of Jeduthun <supplied>were</supplied> at the gate. <verse-number id="1 Ch 16:43">43</verse-number>Then all the people went each to his house, and David turned to bless his household. </p>
		</chapter>