<chapter id="1 Ch 17">
			<pericope>Yahweh’s Covenant with David</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 17:1">1</verse-number>And as David lived in his house, David said to Nathan the prophet, “Look, I live in a house of cedar, but the ark of the covenant of Yahweh <supplied>is</supplied> under tent curtains.” <verse-number id="1 Ch 17:2">2</verse-number>And Nathan said to David, “Whatever <supplied>is</supplied> in your heart, do, for God <supplied>is</supplied> with you.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 17:3">3</verse-number>And it happened that same night the word of God came to Nathan, saying, <verse-number id="1 Ch 17:4">4</verse-number>“Go and say to David my servant, ‘Thus says Yahweh, “You <supplied>are</supplied> not to build a house for me to live <supplied>in</supplied>, <verse-number id="1 Ch 17:5">5</verse-number>for I have not lived in a house from the day that I brought out Israel unto this day. I have been from tent to tent and from tabernacle <supplied>to tabernacle</supplied>. <verse-number id="1 Ch 17:6">6</verse-number>In every <supplied>place</supplied> I have moved about, did I say one word <supplied>with</supplied> the judges of Israel I commanded to shepherd my people, saying, ‘Why have you not built for me a house of cedar?’ ” ’ <verse-number id="1 Ch 17:7">7</verse-number>So now, thus you shall say to my servant David, ‘Thus says Yahweh of hosts, “I took you from the pasture, from following the sheep, to be leader over my people Israel, <verse-number id="1 Ch 17:8">8</verse-number>and I have been with you wherever you went and have cut down your enemies from before you and will make a name for you, like the name of the great ones on the earth. <verse-number id="1 Ch 17:9">9</verse-number>And I will appoint a place for my people Israel, and I will plant them,<note>Or “him” (i.e., the nation)</note> and they<note>Or “he”</note> shall dwell in their<note>Or “his”</note> place and be in anguish no longer. And wicked men will no longer wear them down as before, <verse-number id="1 Ch 17:10">10</verse-number>from the day that I commanded judges over my people Israel. And I will subdue your enemies, and I declare to you <supplied>that</supplied> Yahweh will build for you a house.<note>Or “household” (that is, a dynasty)</note> <verse-number id="1 Ch 17:11">11</verse-number>And it shall be that when your days are fulfilled to go <supplied>and sleep</supplied> with your ancestors,<note>Or “fathers”</note> then I will raise up your seed after you, who will be one of your sons, and I will establish his kingdom. <verse-number id="1 Ch 17:12">12</verse-number>He himself will build for me a house, and I will establish his throne forever. <verse-number id="1 Ch 17:13">13</verse-number>I myself will be a father to him, and he himself will be a son to me. And I will not remove my steadfast love from him as I took it away from whoever was before you. <verse-number id="1 Ch 17:14">14</verse-number>And I will establish him in my house and in my kingdom forever, and his throne will be established forever.” ’ ” <verse-number id="1 Ch 17:15">15</verse-number>According to all these words and according to all this revelation, thus did Nathan speak to David. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>David’s Prayer</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 17:16">16</verse-number>Then King David went and sat before Yahweh and said, “Who <supplied>am</supplied> I, O Yahweh God, and what <supplied>is</supplied> my house that you have brought me thus far? <verse-number id="1 Ch 17:17">17</verse-number>And this was a small <supplied>matter</supplied> in your eyes, O God. And you have spoken concerning the house of your servant for a long <supplied>time</supplied> and have shown me <idiom-start/>future generations to come<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “with a turn of humankind ascending”</note> O Yahweh God. <verse-number id="1 Ch 17:18">18</verse-number><idiom-start/>What more<idiom-end/><note>Literally “What to add again”</note> can David <supplied>do</supplied> to you for honoring your servant? Now you know your servant. <verse-number id="1 Ch 17:19">19</verse-number>O Yahweh, for the sake of your servant and according to your heart you have done all this greatness, to make known all <supplied>these</supplied> great things. <verse-number id="1 Ch 17:20">20</verse-number>O Yahweh, there is none like you, and there is no God except you, according to all that we have heard with our ears. <verse-number id="1 Ch 17:21">21</verse-number>And who <supplied>is</supplied> like your people Israel, <supplied>the</supplied> one nation upon earth whom God went to redeem for himself, to establish for you a reputation<note>Or “name”</note> for great and awesome things, to drive out nations from before your people whom you redeemed from Egypt? <verse-number id="1 Ch 17:22">22</verse-number>And you made your people Israel an everlasting nation for yourself. And you, O Yahweh, became their God. <verse-number id="1 Ch 17:23">23</verse-number>So now, O Yahweh, let the word that you spoke to your servant and to his house be established forever, that you might do what you have spoken. <verse-number id="1 Ch 17:24">24</verse-number>And let your name be established and be magnified forever, saying, ‘Yahweh of hosts, the God of Israel, is Israel’s God, and may the house of David your servant be established before you.’ <verse-number id="1 Ch 17:25">25</verse-number>For you, my God, <idiom-start/>have informed<idiom-end/><note>Literally “have opened the ear of”</note> your servant <supplied>that</supplied> you will build a house for him. Therefore, your servant has found <supplied>courage</supplied> to pray before you. <verse-number id="1 Ch 17:26">26</verse-number>So now, O Yahweh, you yourself <supplied>are</supplied> God, and you have spoken to your servant this good thing. <verse-number id="1 Ch 17:27">27</verse-number>And now may you begin to bless the house of your servant <idiom-start/>to continue forever<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to be forever”</note> before you, for you, O Yahweh, have blessed. And it will be blessed forever.” </p>
		</chapter>