<chapter id="1 Ch 18">
			<pericope>David’s Victory over His Enemies</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 18:1">1</verse-number>And it happened <supplied>that</supplied> after David struck the Philistines and subdued them, he captured Gath and its villages out of the hand of the Philistines. <verse-number id="1 Ch 18:2">2</verse-number>And he struck Moab, and the Moabites became servants to David, bearing tribute. <verse-number id="1 Ch 18:3">3</verse-number>And David struck Hadadezer, king of Zobah-Hamath, as he set up his monument at the Euphrates River. <verse-number id="1 Ch 18:4">4</verse-number>And David captured from him one thousand chariots, seven thousand horsemen, and twenty thousand foot soldiers. And David hamstrung all the chariot horses but left one hundred of them <supplied>to</supplied> remain <supplied>for</supplied> chariots. <verse-number id="1 Ch 18:5">5</verse-number>And when the Arameans of Damascus came to help Hadadezer king of Zobah-Hamath, David struck down twenty-two thousand men of Aram. <verse-number id="1 Ch 18:6">6</verse-number>Then David set up <supplied>garrisons</supplied> in Aram of Damascus, and the Arameans became servants to David, bearing tribute. And Yahweh delivered David wherever he went. <verse-number id="1 Ch 18:7">7</verse-number>And David took small round shields of gold that were upon the servants of Hadadezer and brought them <supplied>to</supplied> Jerusalem. <verse-number id="1 Ch 18:8">8</verse-number>And from Tibhath and from Cun, cities of Hadadezer, David captured very much bronze. Solomon made the bronze sea with it along with the columns and objects of bronze. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 18:9">9</verse-number>And when Tou the king of Hamath heard that David had defeated the whole army of Hadadezer the king of Zobah, <verse-number id="1 Ch 18:10">10</verse-number>he sent Hadoram his son to King David to ask him for peace and to bless him because he had fought against Hadadezer and defeated him, for Tou <idiom-start/>had been at war<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a man of battles”</note> with Hadadezer. And <supplied>he brought with him</supplied> all the objects of gold, silver, and bronze. <verse-number id="1 Ch 18:11">11</verse-number>King David dedicated these also to Yahweh, along with the silver and gold that he had taken from all the nations, from Edom, Moab, the sons of Ammon, the Philistines, and Amalek. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 18:12">12</verse-number>And Abishai son of Zeruiah defeated eighteen thousand of Edom in the Valley of Salt. <verse-number id="1 Ch 18:13">13</verse-number>And he put garrisons in Edom, and all Edom became servants to David. And Yahweh delivered David wherever he went. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>David’s Administration</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 18:14">14</verse-number>So David reigned over all Israel, and <idiom-start/>he administered justice<idiom-end/><note>Literally “he was a doer of justice”</note> and righteousness to all his people. <verse-number id="1 Ch 18:15">15</verse-number>And Joab son of Zeruiah <supplied>was</supplied> over the army, and Jehoshaphat son of Ahilud <supplied>was</supplied> recorder. <verse-number id="1 Ch 18:16">16</verse-number>And Zadok son of Ahitub and Abimelech son of Abiathar <supplied>were</supplied> priests, and Shavsha <supplied>was</supplied> secretary. <verse-number id="1 Ch 18:17">17</verse-number>And Benaiah son of Jehoiada <supplied>was</supplied> over the Kerethites and the Pelethites. And the sons of David <supplied>were</supplied> chief officials under the hand of the king. </p>
		</chapter>