<chapter id="1 Ch 19">
			<pericope>The Ammonites Humiliate David’s Messengers</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 19:1">1</verse-number>And it happened <supplied>that</supplied> after this Nahash the king of the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons of Ammon”</note> died, and his son reigned in his place. <verse-number id="1 Ch 19:2">2</verse-number>And David said, “I will deal kindly with Hanun the son of Nahash because his father showed kindness to me.” So David sent messengers to comfort him concerning his father. And the servants of David came to the land of the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons of Ammon”</note> to Hanun, to comfort him. <verse-number id="1 Ch 19:3">3</verse-number>But the princes of the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons of Ammon”</note> said to Hanun, “<idiom-start/>Do you think<idiom-end/><note>Literally “In your eyes”</note> because David sent comforters to you <supplied>that</supplied> David honors your father? Is it not for the purpose of exploring <supplied>so as</supplied> to overthrow and spy out the land that his servants have come to you?” <verse-number id="1 Ch 19:4">4</verse-number>So Hanun took the servants of David and shaved them and cut off their garments at the middle, up to the buttocks, and sent them away. <verse-number id="1 Ch 19:5">5</verse-number>And they went and told David concerning the men, and he inquired of them, for the men were very disgraced. And the king said, “Dwell in Jericho until your beards grow out; then return.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 19:6">6</verse-number>And when the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons of Ammon”</note> saw that they made themselves odious to David, Hanun and the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons of Ammon”</note> sent one thousand talents of silver to hire for themselves horses and chariots from Aram-Naharaim, Aram-Maacah, and Zobah. <verse-number id="1 Ch 19:7">7</verse-number>And they hired for themselves thirty-two thousand chariots and the king of Maacah and his people, and they came and encamped before Medeba. And the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons of Ammon”</note> were gathered from their cities and came to the battle. <verse-number id="1 Ch 19:8">8</verse-number>And when David heard, he sent Joab and the entire army of mighty warriors. <verse-number id="1 Ch 19:9">9</verse-number>And the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons of Ammon”</note> went out and took up positions for battle at the entrance of the city. And the kings who had come <supplied>were</supplied> alone in the field. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 19:10">10</verse-number>When Joab saw that <supplied>there was</supplied> <idiom-start/>a battle line<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the face of the battle”</note> against him at the front and the back, he chose from among the chosen <supplied>men</supplied> in Israel and arranged <supplied>them</supplied> to meet Aram. <verse-number id="1 Ch 19:11">11</verse-number>And the remainder of the people he put in the hand of Abishai his brother, and they were arranged to meet the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sons of Ammon”</note> <verse-number id="1 Ch 19:12">12</verse-number>And he said, “If Aram is too strong for me, then you must be a help to me, but if the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons of Ammon”</note> are too strong for you, then I will help you. <verse-number id="1 Ch 19:13">13</verse-number>Be strong! Let us strengthen ourselves on behalf of our people and on behalf of the cities of our God. And may Yahweh do <supplied>what is</supplied> good in his eyes.” <verse-number id="1 Ch 19:14">14</verse-number>And Joab and the people who <supplied>were</supplied> with him drew near before Aram for battle, and they fled before him. <verse-number id="1 Ch 19:15">15</verse-number>And when the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons of Ammon”</note> saw that Aram had fled, they also fled before Abishai his brother, and they came to the city. Then Joab came to Jerusalem. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 19:16">16</verse-number>And when Aram saw that they were defeated before Israel, they sent messengers and brought out Aram, who <supplied>was from</supplied> beyond the Euphrates,<note>Or “the river”</note> with Shophach the commander of the army of Hadadezer before them. <verse-number id="1 Ch 19:17">17</verse-number>And when it was told to David, he gathered all Israel and crossed the Jordan. And he came to them and was arrayed against them. Then David was arrayed to meet Aram in battle, and they fought with him. <verse-number id="1 Ch 19:18">18</verse-number>And Aram fled before Israel. And David killed from Aram <supplied>the men of</supplied> seven thousand chariots and forty thousand foot soldiers, and he put to death Shophach the commander of the army. <verse-number id="1 Ch 19:19">19</verse-number>And when the servants of Hadadezer saw that they were defeated before Israel, they made peace with David and became servants to him. So Aram was no longer willing to help the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sons of Ammon”</note> </p>
		</chapter>