<chapter id="1 Ch 20">
			<pericope>The Capture of Rabbah</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 20:1">1</verse-number>And it happened <supplied>that</supplied> <idiom-start/>in the spring time of year<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “at the time of the returning of the year”</note> the time <supplied>when</supplied> kings go out <supplied>to battle</supplied>, Joab led the troops of the army and destroyed the land of the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sons of Ammon”</note> And he came and besieged Rabbah, but David remained in Jerusalem. And Joab struck Rabbah and destroyed it. <verse-number id="1 Ch 20:2">2</verse-number>And David took the crown of their king from his head and found it to weigh a talent of gold. And in it <supplied>was</supplied> a precious stone. Then it was <supplied>placed</supplied> upon the head of David. And he brought out the booty of the city, a large amount. <verse-number id="1 Ch 20:3">3</verse-number>And the people who <supplied>were</supplied> in it he brought out, and <idiom-start/>he set them to work with saws and iron implements and axes<idiom-end/>.<note>The translation comes from <cite title="BibleLEB2: 2 Sa 12:31">2 Samuel 12:31 </cite>since the Hebrew text here is uncertain</note> Thus David did to all the cities of the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sons of Ammon”</note> Then David returned, and all the nation <supplied>went</supplied> with him. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Philistine Giants Slain</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 20:4">4</verse-number>And after this there arose a war in Gezer with the Philistines. Then Sibbecai the Hushathite struck down Sippai, one of the descendants of the Rephaim. And they were subdued. <verse-number id="1 Ch 20:5">5</verse-number>And again there was war with the Philistines. And Elhanan son of Jair struck down Lahmi, the brother of Goliath the Gittite, the shaft of whose spear <supplied>was</supplied> like a weaver’s beam. <verse-number id="1 Ch 20:6">6</verse-number>And again there was war in Gath. And there was a <idiom-start/>very tall<idiom-end/><note>Literally “measured”</note> man <supplied>there</supplied>, and <idiom-start/>he had six fingers on each hand and six toes on each foot, twenty-four in all<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “and his fingers, six and six, twenty-four”</note> He himself <supplied>was</supplied> also a descendant of the Rephaim. <verse-number id="1 Ch 20:7">7</verse-number>And he taunted Israel, but Jehonathan son of Shimea, brother of David, struck him down. <verse-number id="1 Ch 20:8">8</verse-number>These were born to the giants in Gath, and they fell by the hand of David and by the hand of his servants. </p>
		</chapter>