<chapter id="1 Ch 23">
			<pericope>David Organizes the Levites</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 23:1">1</verse-number>Now David <supplied>was</supplied> old and full of days. And he made Solomon his son king over Israel. <verse-number id="1 Ch 23:2">2</verse-number>And he assembled all the commanders of Israel and the priests and the Levites. <verse-number id="1 Ch 23:3">3</verse-number>And the Levites thirty years old and above were counted, and their number according to their head count for the men <supplied>was</supplied> thirty-eight thousand. <verse-number id="1 Ch 23:4">4</verse-number>Of these, <supplied>David said,</supplied> “Twenty-four thousand <supplied>are</supplied> to direct the work of the house of Yahweh, along with six thousand judges and officials, <verse-number id="1 Ch 23:5">5</verse-number>four thousand gatekeepers, <supplied>and</supplied> four thousand offering praise with the instruments that I have made for praise.” <verse-number id="1 Ch 23:6">6</verse-number>And David organized them <supplied>in</supplied> divisions according to the sons of Levi: to Gershon, Kohath, and Merari. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 23:7">7</verse-number>For the Gershonites <supplied>were</supplied> Ladan and Shimei. <verse-number id="1 Ch 23:8">8</verse-number>The sons of Ladan: Jehiel the chief and Zetham and Joel, three. <verse-number id="1 Ch 23:9">9</verse-number>The sons of Shimei: Shelomoth, Haziel, and Haran, three. These <supplied>were</supplied> the heads of the <idiom-start/>families<idiom-end/><note>Literally “fathers”</note> of Ladan. <verse-number id="1 Ch 23:10">10</verse-number>And the sons of Shimei: Jahath, Zina, Jeush, and Beriah; these four <supplied>were</supplied> the sons of Shimei. <verse-number id="1 Ch 23:11">11</verse-number>And Jahath was the chief, and Zizah the second, but Jeush and Beriah did not have many sons. They were enrolled as one for the house of a father. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 23:12">12</verse-number>The sons of Kohath: Amram, Izhar, Hebron, and Uzziel, four. <verse-number id="1 Ch 23:13">13</verse-number>The sons of Amram: Aaron and Moses. And Aaron was set apart to consecrate the most holy things. He and his sons <supplied>were</supplied> to burn offerings forever before Yahweh to serve him and to bless in his name forever. <verse-number id="1 Ch 23:14">14</verse-number>But Moses the man of God <supplied>and</supplied> his sons were reckoned among the tribe of Levi. <verse-number id="1 Ch 23:15">15</verse-number>The sons of Moses: Gershom and Eliezer. <verse-number id="1 Ch 23:16">16</verse-number>The sons of Gershom: Shebuel the chief. <verse-number id="1 Ch 23:17">17</verse-number>And the sons of Eliezer were Rehabiah, the head. And Eliezer had no other sons, but the sons of Rehabiah were very many. <verse-number id="1 Ch 23:18">18</verse-number>The sons of Izhar: Shelomith the chief. <verse-number id="1 Ch 23:19">19</verse-number>The sons of Hebron: Jeriah the chief, Amariah the second, Jahaziel the third, and Jekameam the fourth. <verse-number id="1 Ch 23:20">20</verse-number>The sons of Uzziel: Micah the chief and Isshiah the second. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 23:21">21</verse-number>The sons of Merari: Mahli and Mushi. The sons of Mahli: Eleazar and Kish. <verse-number id="1 Ch 23:22">22</verse-number>And Eleazar died, and he did not have sons, but only daughters. And the sons of Kish, their relatives, married them. <verse-number id="1 Ch 23:23">23</verse-number>The sons of Mushi: Mahli, Eder, and Jeremoth, three. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 23:24">24</verse-number>These <supplied>were</supplied> the sons of Levi according to the house of their fathers, the heads of the <idiom-start/>families<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “fathers”</note> according to their enrollment, by the number of the names, according to their head count, <supplied>who were to</supplied> do the work of the service of the house of Yahweh, from twenty years old and above. <verse-number id="1 Ch 23:25">25</verse-number>For David said, “Yahweh, the God of Israel, has given rest to his people, and he dwells in Jerusalem forever. <verse-number id="1 Ch 23:26">26</verse-number>And also, the Levites do not <supplied>need</supplied> to carry the tabernacle and all its vessels for its service.” <verse-number id="1 Ch 23:27">27</verse-number>For by the last words of David, they <supplied>are</supplied> the number of the sons of Levi, from twenty years old and above. <verse-number id="1 Ch 23:28">28</verse-number>For their station <supplied>was</supplied> <idiom-start/>to assist<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for the hand of”</note> the sons of Aaron with the service of the house of Yahweh, over the courtyards, over the chambers, and over the cleansing of all the sanctified objects, and <supplied>with</supplied> the work of the service of the house of God, <verse-number id="1 Ch 23:29">29</verse-number>and with the rows of bread, the flour, the grain offering, the wafers of unleavened bread, the baked offering, the offering mixed with oil, and for all the amounts and measurements. <verse-number id="1 Ch 23:30">30</verse-number>And <supplied>they were</supplied> to stand <idiom-start/>every morning<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “in the morning, in the morning”</note> thanking and praising Yahweh, and likewise in the evening, <verse-number id="1 Ch 23:31">31</verse-number>and for every burnt offering offered to Yahweh, on Sabbaths, on new moon festivals, and at the appointed feasts, according to the customary number <idiom-start/>required of them<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “over them”</note> regularly before Yahweh. <verse-number id="1 Ch 23:32">32</verse-number>And they shall keep the responsibility of the tent of assembly,<note>Or “meeting”</note> the responsibility of the sanctified objects, and the responsibility of the sons of Aaron, their brothers, to serve the house of Yahweh. </p>
		</chapter>