<chapter id="1 Ch 24">
			<pericope>David Organizes the Priests</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 24:1">1</verse-number>And as for the sons of Aaron, <supplied>these were</supplied> their divisions. The sons of Aaron <supplied>were</supplied> Nadab and Abihu, Eleazar and Ithamar. <verse-number id="1 Ch 24:2">2</verse-number>And Nadab and Abihu died before their father, and <idiom-start/>they had no sons<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons were not to them”</note> so Eleazar and Ithamar served as priests. <verse-number id="1 Ch 24:3">3</verse-number>And David, with Zadok of the sons of Eleazar and Ahimelech of the sons of Ithamar, divided them according to their appointments for their service. <verse-number id="1 Ch 24:4">4</verse-number>And more sons of Eleazar were found as heads of the men than the sons of Ithamar, so they divided them to the sons of Eleazar <supplied>to be</supplied> sixteen heads over the house of the fathers, and to the sons of Ithamar over the house of the fathers <supplied>were</supplied> eight <supplied>heads</supplied>. <verse-number id="1 Ch 24:5">5</verse-number>They divided them by lot <idiom-start/>all alike<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “these with those”</note> for they were commanders of the sanctuary and commanders of God from among the sons of Eleazar and the sons of Ithamar. <verse-number id="1 Ch 24:6">6</verse-number>And Shemaiah the son of Nethanel, the scribe, from the Levites, recorded them before the king, the princes, Zadok the priest, Ahimelech the son of Abiathar, and the heads of the <idiom-start/>families<idiom-end/><note>Literally “fathers”</note> of the priests and Levites, one father’s house drawn by Lot for Eleazar and one drawn by lot for Ithamar. <verse-number id="1 Ch 24:7">7</verse-number>And the first lot went out to Jehoiarib, the second to Jedaiah, <verse-number id="1 Ch 24:8">8</verse-number>the third to Harim, the fourth to Seorim, <verse-number id="1 Ch 24:9">9</verse-number>the fifth to Malkijah, the sixth to Mijamin, <verse-number id="1 Ch 24:10">10</verse-number>the seventh to Hakkoz, the eighth to Abijah, <verse-number id="1 Ch 24:11">11</verse-number>the ninth to Jeshua, the tenth to Shekaniah, <verse-number id="1 Ch 24:12">12</verse-number>the eleventh to Eliashib, the twelfth to Jakim, <verse-number id="1 Ch 24:13">13</verse-number>the thirteenth to Huppah, the fourteenth to Jeshebeab, <verse-number id="1 Ch 24:14">14</verse-number>the fifteenth to Bilgah, the sixteenth to Immer, <verse-number id="1 Ch 24:15">15</verse-number>the seventeenth to Hezir, the eighteenth to Ha-Pizzez, <verse-number id="1 Ch 24:16">16</verse-number>the nineteenth to Pethahiah, the twentieth to Ezekiel, <verse-number id="1 Ch 24:17">17</verse-number>the twenty-first to Jakin, the twenty-second to Gamul, <verse-number id="1 Ch 24:18">18</verse-number>the twenty-third to Delaiah, the twenty-fourth to Maaziah. <verse-number id="1 Ch 24:19">19</verse-number>These <supplied>were</supplied> their appointments for their service to come into the house of Yahweh according to their custom by the hand of Aaron their father, as Yahweh the God of Israel had commanded him. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 24:20">20</verse-number>And as for the remainder of the sons of Levi: of the sons of Amram, Shubael; of the sons of Shubael, Jehdeiah. <verse-number id="1 Ch 24:21">21</verse-number>Of Rehabiah: of the sons of Rehabiah, Isshiah the chief. <verse-number id="1 Ch 24:22">22</verse-number>Of the Izharites, Shelomoth; of the sons Shelomoth, Jahath. <verse-number id="1 Ch 24:23">23</verse-number>Of the sons of Jeriah, Amariah the second, Jahaziel the third, Jekameam the fourth. <verse-number id="1 Ch 24:24">24</verse-number>The sons of Uzziel, Micah; the sons of Micah, Shamur. <verse-number id="1 Ch 24:25">25</verse-number>The brother of Micah, Isshiah; of the sons of Isshiah, Zechariah. <verse-number id="1 Ch 24:26">26</verse-number>The sons of Merari: Mahli and Mushi; the sons of Jaaziah, his son.<note>Or “Beno”</note> <verse-number id="1 Ch 24:27">27</verse-number>The sons of Merari: of Jaaziah, his son,<note>Or “Beno”</note> Shoham, Zakkur, and Ibri. <verse-number id="1 Ch 24:28">28</verse-number>Of Mahli: Eleazar, who had no sons. <verse-number id="1 Ch 24:29">29</verse-number>Of Kish: the sons of Kish, Jerahmeel. <verse-number id="1 Ch 24:30">30</verse-number>And the sons of Mushi: Mahli, Eder, and Jerimoth. These <supplied>were</supplied> the sons of the Levites according to the house of their fathers. <verse-number id="1 Ch 24:31">31</verse-number>And lots were also cast <supplied>for</supplied> these, just as their brothers, the sons of Aaron, before David the king, Zadok, Ahimelech, and the heads of the <idiom-start/>families<idiom-end/><note>Literally “fathers”</note> for the priests and for the Levites the fathers, <idiom-start/>on the principle of the chief and younger brother alike<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the head like his brother the younger”</note> </p>
		</chapter>