<chapter id="1 Ch 25">
			<pericope>David Organizes the Musicians</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 25:1">1</verse-number>And David and the commanders of the army set apart for the service the sons of Asaph, <supplied>of</supplied> Heman, and <supplied>of</supplied> Jeduthun, who prophesied with stringed instruments, with harps, and with cymbals. And their inventory of the men of the work <supplied>and</supplied> for their duty was: <verse-number id="1 Ch 25:2">2</verse-number>for the sons of Asaph: Zakkur, Joseph, Nethaniah, and Asarelah, sons of Asaph, under the hand<note>That is, under the direction</note> of Asaph, who prophesied under the hands<note>That is, under the direction</note> of the king. <verse-number id="1 Ch 25:3">3</verse-number>Of Jeduthun, the sons of Jeduthun: Gedaliah, Zeri, Jeshaiah,<note>One Hebrew manuscript and the LXX add “Shimei” between Jeshaiah and Heshabiah (see verse <cite title="BibleLEB2:1 Ch 25:17">17</cite>)</note> Heshabiah, and Mattithiah, six, under the hands<note>That is, under the direction</note> of their father Jeduthun, who prophesied with the stringed instrument with thanksgiving and praise to Yahweh. <verse-number id="1 Ch 25:4">4</verse-number>Of Heman, the sons of Heman: Bukkiah, Mattaniah, Uzziel, Shebuel and Jerimoth, Hananiah, Hanani, Eliathah, Giddalti and Romamti-ezer, Joshbekashah, Mallothi, Hothir, Mahazioth. <verse-number id="1 Ch 25:5">5</verse-number>All these <supplied>were</supplied> sons to Heman, the seer of the king, according to the words of God to raise a horn.<note>That is, to exalt Heman</note> And God had given to Heman fourteen sons and three daughters. <verse-number id="1 Ch 25:6">6</verse-number>All these <supplied>were</supplied> under the <idiom-start/>direction<idiom-end/><note>Literally “hands”</note> of their father in the music of the house of Yahweh, with cymbals, harps, and stringed instruments for the service of the house of God. Asaph, Jeduthun, and Heman <supplied>were</supplied> under the <idiom-start/>direction<idiom-end/><note>Literally “hands”</note> of the king. <verse-number id="1 Ch 25:7">7</verse-number>And their number, along with their brothers, trained singers, all the skilled people for Yahweh, were two hundred and eighty-eight. <verse-number id="1 Ch 25:8">8</verse-number>And they cast lots <supplied>for</supplied> responsibilities <idiom-start/>on the principle of small and great alike<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “for like the small, like the great”</note> teacher with student. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 25:9">9</verse-number>And the first lot for Asaph went out to Joseph; the second to Gedaliahu; he and his brothers and his twelve sons. <verse-number id="1 Ch 25:10">10</verse-number>The third, Zakkur, his sons and his brothers, twelve; <verse-number id="1 Ch 25:11">11</verse-number>the fourth to Izri, his sons and his brothers, twelve; <verse-number id="1 Ch 25:12">12</verse-number>the fifth, Nethaniah, his sons and his brothers, twelve; <verse-number id="1 Ch 25:13">13</verse-number>the sixth, Bukkiah, his sons and his brothers, twelve; <verse-number id="1 Ch 25:14">14</verse-number>the seventh, Jesarelah, his sons and his brothers, twelve; <verse-number id="1 Ch 25:15">15</verse-number>the eighth, Jeshaiah, his sons and his brothers, twelve; <verse-number id="1 Ch 25:16">16</verse-number>the ninth, Mattaniah, his sons and his brothers, twelve; <verse-number id="1 Ch 25:17">17</verse-number>the tenth, Shimei, his sons and his brothers, twelve; <verse-number id="1 Ch 25:18">18</verse-number>eleventh, Azarel, his sons and his brothers, twelve; <verse-number id="1 Ch 25:19">19</verse-number>the twelfth to Hashabiah, his sons and his brothers, twelve; <verse-number id="1 Ch 25:20">20</verse-number>to <supplied>the</supplied> thirteenth, Shubael, his sons and his brothers, twelve; <verse-number id="1 Ch 25:21">21</verse-number>to <supplied>the</supplied> fourteenth, Mattithiah, his sons and his brothers, twelve; <verse-number id="1 Ch 25:22">22</verse-number>to <supplied>the</supplied> fifteenth, to Jeremoth, his sons and his brothers, twelve; <verse-number id="1 Ch 25:23">23</verse-number>to <supplied>the</supplied> sixteenth, to Hananiah, his sons and his brothers, twelve; <verse-number id="1 Ch 25:24">24</verse-number>to <supplied>the</supplied> seventeenth, to Joshbekashah, his sons and his brothers, twelve; <verse-number id="1 Ch 25:25">25</verse-number>to <supplied>the</supplied> eighteenth, to Hanani, his sons and his brothers, twelve; <verse-number id="1 Ch 25:26">26</verse-number>to <supplied>the</supplied> nineteenth, to Mallothi, his sons and his brothers, twelve; <verse-number id="1 Ch 25:27">27</verse-number>to <supplied>the</supplied> twentieth, to Eliathah, his sons and his brothers, twelve; <verse-number id="1 Ch 25:28">28</verse-number>to <supplied>the</supplied> twenty-first, to Hothir, his sons and his brothers, twelve; <verse-number id="1 Ch 25:29">29</verse-number>to <supplied>the</supplied> twenty-second, to Giddalti, his sons and his brothers, twelve; <verse-number id="1 Ch 25:30">30</verse-number>to <supplied>the</supplied> twenty-third, to Mahazioth, his sons and his brothers, twelve; <verse-number id="1 Ch 25:31">31</verse-number>to <supplied>the</supplied> twenty-fourth, to Romamti-ezer, his sons and his brothers, twelve. </p>
		</chapter>