<chapter id="1 Ch 26">
			<pericope>The Divisions of the Gatekeepers</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 26:1">1</verse-number>As for the working groups of the gatekeepers: of the Korahites, Meshelemiah the son of Kore, from the sons of Asaph. <verse-number id="1 Ch 26:2">2</verse-number>And Meshelemiah had sons: Zechariah the firstborn, Jediael the second, Zebadiah the third, Jathniel the fourth, <verse-number id="1 Ch 26:3">3</verse-number>Elam the fifth, Jehohana the sixth, Eliehoenai the seventh. <verse-number id="1 Ch 26:4">4</verse-number>And Obed-Edom had sons: Shemaiah the firstborn, Jehozabad the second, Joah the third, Sachar the fourth, Nethanel the fifth, <verse-number id="1 Ch 26:5">5</verse-number>Ammiel the sixth, Issachar the seventh, Peullethai the eighth; for God blessed him. <verse-number id="1 Ch 26:6">6</verse-number>And to Shemaiah his son were sons born who <supplied>were</supplied> rulers in the house of their father, for they <supplied>were</supplied> mighty warriors of ability. <verse-number id="1 Ch 26:7">7</verse-number>The sons of Shemaiah: Othni, Rephael, Obed, and Elzabad, whose brothers <supplied>were</supplied> sons of ability, Elihu and Semakiah. <verse-number id="1 Ch 26:8">8</verse-number>All these from the sons of Obed-Edom, they and their sons, and their brothers <supplied>were</supplied> men of ability with strength for service; sixty-two of Obed-Edom. <verse-number id="1 Ch 26:9">9</verse-number>And Meshelemiah had sons and brothers, sons of ability, eighteen. <verse-number id="1 Ch 26:10">10</verse-number>And Hosah, from the sons of Merari, had sons: Shimri the chief (though he was not firstborn, his father appointed him as chief), <verse-number id="1 Ch 26:11">11</verse-number>Hilkiah the second, Tabaliah the third, Zechariah the fourth: all the sons and brothers of Hosah <supplied>were</supplied> thirteen. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 26:12">12</verse-number>These working groups of gatekeepers, corresponding to the chief men, had responsibilities like their brothers to serve in the house of Yahweh. <verse-number id="1 Ch 26:13">13</verse-number>And they cast lots, small and great alike, by their fathers’ houses, <idiom-start/>for their gates<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “for gate and gate”</note> <verse-number id="1 Ch 26:14">14</verse-number>And the lot fell to the east to Shelemiah. As for Zechariah his son, <idiom-start/>a wise counselor<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “giving counsel with understanding”</note> they cast lots. And his lot came out for the north. <verse-number id="1 Ch 26:15">15</verse-number>To Obed-Edom <supplied>went out</supplied> the south, and to his sons, the storehouses. <verse-number id="1 Ch 26:16">16</verse-number>For Shuppim and Hosah <supplied>it went out</supplied> for the west, at the gate of Shalleketh, on the road that goes up, guard for guard. <verse-number id="1 Ch 26:17">17</verse-number>To the east, six Levites; to the north, four daily; to the south, four daily; and at the storerooms, two <supplied>by</supplied> two. <verse-number id="1 Ch 26:18">18</verse-number>For the court to the west, four at the road, two at the court. <verse-number id="1 Ch 26:19">19</verse-number>These <supplied>were</supplied> the working groups of the gatekeepers among the sons of the Korahites and among the sons of Merari. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Treasurers and Other Officials</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 26:20">20</verse-number>And of the Levites: Ahijah <supplied>was</supplied> over the treasuries of the house of God and over the treasuries of the sanctified objects. <verse-number id="1 Ch 26:21">21</verse-number>The sons of Ladan: the sons of the Gershonites belonging to Ladan, the heads of the <idiom-start/>families<idiom-end/><note>Literally “fathers”</note> belonging to Ladan the Gershonite: Jehieli. <verse-number id="1 Ch 26:22">22</verse-number>The sons of Jehieli, Zetham and Joel his brother, <supplied>were</supplied> over the treasuries of the house of Yahweh. <verse-number id="1 Ch 26:23">23</verse-number>Of the Amramites, the Izharites, the Hebronites, <supplied>and</supplied> the Ozzielites: <verse-number id="1 Ch 26:24">24</verse-number>Shebuel the son of Gershom, the son of Moses, <supplied>was</supplied> commander over the treasuries. <verse-number id="1 Ch 26:25">25</verse-number>And his brothers: from Eliezer <supplied>were</supplied> Rehabiah his son, and Jeshaiah his son, and Joram his son, and Zikri his son, and Shelomoth his son. <verse-number id="1 Ch 26:26">26</verse-number>That Shelomoth and his brothers <supplied>were</supplied> over all the treasuries of the sanctified objects that King David and the heads of the <idiom-start/>families<idiom-end/><note>Literally “fathers”</note> to the commanders of thousands and hundreds and the commanders of the army had dedicated. <verse-number id="1 Ch 26:27">27</verse-number>From the battles and from the spoil they had dedicated <supplied>these things</supplied> to strengthen the house of Yahweh. <verse-number id="1 Ch 26:28">28</verse-number>And all that Samuel the seer, and Saul the son of Kish, and Abner the son of Ner, and Joab the son of Zeruiah had dedicated—all the dedicated gifts <supplied>were</supplied> under the hand of Shelomith and his brothers. <verse-number id="1 Ch 26:29">29</verse-number>For the Izharites: Kenaniah and his sons <supplied>were appointed</supplied> to the duties outside of Israel as officials and as judges. <verse-number id="1 Ch 26:30">30</verse-number>For the Hebronites: Hashabiah and his brothers, one thousand seven hundred men of ability, <supplied>were</supplied> over the administration of Israel beyond the Jordan westward, for all the work of Yahweh and for the service of the king. <verse-number id="1 Ch 26:31">31</verse-number>For the Hebronites: Jeriah the chief of the Hebronites for the genealogy for the <idiom-start/>families<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “fathers”</note> (In the fortieth year of the reign of David they were examined, and there was found among them mighty warriors of strength at Jazer in Gilead.) <verse-number id="1 Ch 26:32">32</verse-number>And his brothers, sons of ability, <supplied>were</supplied> two thousand seven hundred heads of the <idiom-start/>families<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “fathers”</note> and King David appointed them over the Reubenites, the Gadites, and the half-tribe of Manasseh, for every matter of God and matter of the king. </p>
		</chapter>