<chapter id="1 Ch 27">
			<pericope>Military Divisions</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 27:1">1</verse-number>And as for the number of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> the heads of <idiom-start/>families<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “fathers”</note> the commanders of thousands and hundreds, and their officials who serve the king in all matters of the working groups that came and went, month by month, throughout all the months of the year, each working group: twenty-four thousand. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 27:2">2</verse-number>Over the first working group for the first month: Jashobeam the son of Zabdiel. And <supplied>he was</supplied> over his working group <supplied>of</supplied> twenty-four thousand. <verse-number id="1 Ch 27:3">3</verse-number>From the sons of Perez <supplied>who was</supplied> the chief of the commanders of the armies for the first month. <verse-number id="1 Ch 27:4">4</verse-number>And over the working groups of the second month: Dodai the Ahohite and his working group, and Mikloth the commander. And <supplied>he was</supplied> over his working group <supplied>of</supplied> twenty-four thousand. <verse-number id="1 Ch 27:5">5</verse-number>The third commander of the army for the third month <supplied>was</supplied> Benaiah son of Jehoiada the chief priest. And <supplied>he was</supplied> over his working group <supplied>of</supplied> twenty-four thousand. <verse-number id="1 Ch 27:6">6</verse-number>This <supplied>was</supplied> Benaiah <supplied>who was</supplied> a mighty warrior of thirty, and over the thirty and his working group <supplied>was</supplied> Ammizabad his son. <verse-number id="1 Ch 27:7">7</verse-number>The fourth, for the fourth month, <supplied>was</supplied> Asahel the brother of Joab and his son Zebadiah after him. And <supplied>he was</supplied> over his working group <supplied>of</supplied> twenty-four thousand. <verse-number id="1 Ch 27:8">8</verse-number>The fifth, for the fifth month, the commander <supplied>was</supplied> Shamhuth the Izrahite. And <supplied>he was</supplied> over his working group <supplied>of</supplied> twenty-four thousand. <verse-number id="1 Ch 27:9">9</verse-number>The sixth, for the sixth month, <supplied>was</supplied> Ira the son of Ikkesh the Tekoite. And <supplied>he was</supplied> over his working group <supplied>of</supplied> twenty-four thousand. <verse-number id="1 Ch 27:10">10</verse-number>The seventh, for the seventh month, <supplied>was</supplied> Helez the Pelonite, from the sons of Ephraim. And <supplied>he was</supplied> over his working group <supplied>of</supplied> twenty-four thousand. <verse-number id="1 Ch 27:11">11</verse-number>The eighth, for the eighth month, <supplied>was</supplied> Sibbecai the Hushathite of the Zerahites. And <supplied>he was</supplied> over his working group <supplied>of</supplied> twenty-four thousand. <verse-number id="1 Ch 27:12">12</verse-number>The ninth, for the ninth month, <supplied>was</supplied> Abiezer the Anathothite of the Benjamites. And <supplied>he was</supplied> over his working group <supplied>of</supplied> twenty-four thousand. <verse-number id="1 Ch 27:13">13</verse-number>The tenth, for the tenth month, <supplied>was</supplied> Maharai the Netophathite of the Zerahites. And <supplied>he was</supplied> over his working group <supplied>of</supplied> twenty-four thousand. <verse-number id="1 Ch 27:14">14</verse-number>The eleventh, for the eleventh month, <supplied>was</supplied> Benaiah the Pirathonite from the sons of Ephraim. And <supplied>he was</supplied> over his working group <supplied>of</supplied> twenty-four thousand. <verse-number id="1 Ch 27:15">15</verse-number>The twelfth, for the twelfth month, <supplied>was</supplied> Heldai the Netophathite, of Othniel. And <supplied>he was</supplied> over his working group <supplied>of</supplied> twenty-four thousand. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Leaders of the Tribes and Other High Ranking Officials</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 27:16">16</verse-number>And over the tribes of Israel, for the Reubenites: the commander <supplied>was</supplied> Eliezer the son of Zikri. For the Simeonites: Shephatiah the son of Maacah. <verse-number id="1 Ch 27:17">17</verse-number>For Levi: Hashabiah the son of Kemuel. For Aaron, Zadok. <verse-number id="1 Ch 27:18">18</verse-number>For Judah: Elihu, from the brothers of David. For Issachar: Omri the son of Michael. <verse-number id="1 Ch 27:19">19</verse-number>For Zebulun: Ishmaiah the son of Obadiah. For Naphtali: Jerimoth the son of Azriel. <verse-number id="1 Ch 27:20">20</verse-number>For the Ephraimites: Hoshea the son of Azaziah. For the half-tribe of Manasseh: Joel the son of Pedaiah. <verse-number id="1 Ch 27:21">21</verse-number>For the half-tribe of Manasseh in Gilead: Iddo the son of Zechariah. For Benjamin: Jaasiel son of Abner. <verse-number id="1 Ch 27:22">22</verse-number>For Dan: Azarel the son of Jeroham. These <supplied>were</supplied> the commanders of the tribes of Israel. <verse-number id="1 Ch 27:23">23</verse-number>And David did not <idiom-start/>take a census of those twenty years old or under<idiom-end/><note>Literally “take up their count from a son of twenty years and to less”</note> because Yahweh promised<note>Or “said”</note> to make Israel more numerous than the stars of heaven. <verse-number id="1 Ch 27:24">24</verse-number>Joab the son of Zeruiah began to count, but he did not finish. But wrath came upon Israel concerning this, and the number was not included in <idiom-start/>the chronicles<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the numbering of the words of the days”</note> of King David. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 27:25">25</verse-number>And over the treasury rooms of the king <supplied>was</supplied> Azmaveth the son of Adiel. And over the treasuries in the country, in the cities, in the unwalled villages, and in the towers <supplied>was</supplied> Jonathan the son of Uzziah. <verse-number id="1 Ch 27:26">26</verse-number>And over those who did the work in the field to till the soil <supplied>was</supplied> Ezri the son of Kelub. <verse-number id="1 Ch 27:27">27</verse-number>And over the vineyards <supplied>was</supplied> Shemei the Ramathite. And over the produce in the vineyards for the storehouses of the wine <supplied>was</supplied> Zabdi the Shiphmite. <verse-number id="1 Ch 27:28">28</verse-number>And over the olive trees and the sycamore trees that <supplied>were</supplied> in the Shephelah <supplied>was</supplied> Baal-Hanan the Gederite. And over the treasury houses of olive oil <supplied>was</supplied> Joash. <verse-number id="1 Ch 27:29">29</verse-number>And over the cattle pastured in the Sharon <supplied>was</supplied> Shitrai the Sharonite. And over the cattle in the valley <supplied>was</supplied> Shaphat the son of Adlai. <verse-number id="1 Ch 27:30">30</verse-number>And over the camels <supplied>was</supplied> Obil the Ishmaelite. And over the female donkeys <supplied>was</supplied> Jehdeiah the Meronothite.<note><cite title="BibleLEB2: 1 Ch 27:31">1 Chronicles 27:31 </cite>begins here in the Hebrew Bible</note> And over the sheep <supplied>was</supplied> Jaziz the Hagrite. <verse-number id="1 Ch 27:31">31</verse-number>All of these <supplied>were</supplied> officials of the property of King David. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 27:32">32</verse-number>And Jehonathan the uncle of David <supplied>was</supplied> an adviser, a man of insight, and he was a scribe. And Jehiel the son of Hachmoni <supplied>was</supplied> with the sons of the king. <verse-number id="1 Ch 27:33">33</verse-number>And Ahithophel <supplied>was</supplied> an adviser to the king, and Hushai the Arkite <supplied>was</supplied> a friend of the king. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 27:34">34</verse-number>And after Ahithophel <supplied>came</supplied> Jehoiada, the son of Benaiah, and Abiathar. And Joab <supplied>was</supplied> the commander of the king’s army. </p>
		</chapter>