<chapter id="1 Ch 29">
			<pericope>Offerings for the Temple</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 29:1">1</verse-number>Then David the king said to all the assembly, “God has chosen Solomon my son alone, a young man and inexperienced, and the work <supplied>is</supplied> great, for the citadel <supplied>is</supplied> not for humankind, but for Yahweh God. <verse-number id="1 Ch 29:2">2</verse-number>So I have provided for the house of my God according to all my strength, the gold for the things of gold, the silver for the things of silver, the bronze for the things of bronze, the iron for the things of iron, and the wood for the things of wood, <supplied>along with</supplied> an abundance of onyx stones, stones for settings, stones of turquoise, and variegated stones, and all <supplied>kinds of</supplied> precious stones and alabaster stones. <verse-number id="1 Ch 29:3">3</verse-number>And moreover, with respect to my provisions for the house of my God I have a treasure of gold and silver that I have given to the house of my God above all that I have provided for the holy house: <verse-number id="1 Ch 29:4">4</verse-number>three thousand talents of gold from the gold of Ophir and seven thousand talents of refined silver to overlay the walls of the houses, <verse-number id="1 Ch 29:5">5</verse-number>gold for the golden things and silver for the silver things, for all the work by the hand of skilled craftsmen. Now who will offer willingly, <idiom-start/>consecrating himself<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to consecrate his hand”</note> today to Yahweh?” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 29:6">6</verse-number>Then the commanders of the <idiom-start/>families<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “fathers”</note> the commanders of the tribes of Israel, and the commanders of thousands and hundreds, and the commanders of the work of the king offered themselves willingly. <verse-number id="1 Ch 29:7">7</verse-number>And they gave for the service of the house of God five thousand talents and ten thousand darics of gold, ten thousand talents of silver, eighteen thousand talents of bronze, and one hundred thousand talents of iron. <verse-number id="1 Ch 29:8">8</verse-number>And whoever had <supplied>precious</supplied> stones gave <supplied>them</supplied> to the treasury of the house of Yahweh under the authority<note>Or “hand”</note> of Jehiel the Gershonite. <verse-number id="1 Ch 29:9">9</verse-number>And the people rejoiced over their freewill offering, for with a whole heart they had willingly offered to Yahweh, and King David also rejoiced with great joy. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 29:10">10</verse-number>Then David blessed Yahweh in the sight of all the assembly, and David said, “Blessed <supplied>are</supplied> you, O Yahweh, God of Israel, our father forever and ever! <verse-number id="1 Ch 29:11">11</verse-number>To you, O Yahweh, <supplied>is</supplied> the greatness and the power and the splendor and the glory and the strength, for everything in the heavens and in the earth. Yours, O Yahweh, <supplied>is</supplied> the kingdom and exaltation over all as head! <verse-number id="1 Ch 29:12">12</verse-number>And wealth and glory <supplied>are</supplied> from you, and you rule over all. And in your hand <supplied>is</supplied> power and might. And in your hand <supplied>is power</supplied> to make great and to give strength to all. <verse-number id="1 Ch 29:13">13</verse-number>And now, our God, we give thanks to you and offer praise to the name of your splendor. <verse-number id="1 Ch 29:14">14</verse-number>And indeed, who <supplied>am</supplied> I, and who <supplied>are</supplied> my people that we retain power to offer according to these <supplied>offerings</supplied> willingly? For everything <supplied>is</supplied> from you, and from your hand we have given to you. <verse-number id="1 Ch 29:15">15</verse-number>For we <supplied>are</supplied> strangers before you and sojourners like all our ancestors.<note>Or “fathers”</note> Our days <supplied>are</supplied> like the shadow upon earth, and there is no hope <supplied>of abiding</supplied>. <verse-number id="1 Ch 29:16">16</verse-number>O Yahweh our God, all this abundance that we have provided to build for you a house for your holy name is from your hand, and all <supplied>of it</supplied> is yours. <verse-number id="1 Ch 29:17">17</verse-number>And I know, my God, that you yourself test the heart and are pleased with uprightness. I, in the uprightness of my heart, have willingly offered all these <supplied>things</supplied>, and now I have seen your people who are found here willingly offer to you. <verse-number id="1 Ch 29:18">18</verse-number>O Yahweh, God of Abraham, Isaac, and Israel, our ancestors,<note>Or “fathers”</note> keep this forever as a plan <supplied>and</supplied> thoughts of the heart of your people, and establish their heart toward you. <verse-number id="1 Ch 29:19">19</verse-number>Grant to Solomon my son a heart of peace to keep your commands, your statutes, and your regulations to do everything, and to build the citadel for which I have provided.” <verse-number id="1 Ch 29:20">20</verse-number>And David said to all the assembly, “Bless Yahweh your God!” And all the assembly blessed Yahweh, the God of their ancestors.<note>Or “fathers”</note> And they bowed down and prostrated themselves before Yahweh and the king. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Solomon’s Coronation</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 29:21">21</verse-number>And they offered sacrifices to Yahweh, and on that next day they offered burnt offerings to Yahweh: one thousand bulls, one thousand rams, one thousand lambs, with their libations and sacrifices in abundance for all Israel. <verse-number id="1 Ch 29:22">22</verse-number>And they ate and drank before Yahweh on that day with great joy. And they made Solomon the son of David king the second time, and they anointed <supplied>him</supplied> commander for Yahweh, and Zadok the priest. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 29:23">23</verse-number>Then Solomon sat upon the throne of Yahweh as king in place of David his father. And he prospered, and all Israel obeyed him. <verse-number id="1 Ch 29:24">24</verse-number>And all the officials and mighty warriors, and also all the sons of King David, <idiom-start/>pledged allegiance to<idiom-end/><note>Literally “placed a hand under”</note> King Solomon. <verse-number id="1 Ch 29:25">25</verse-number>And Yahweh made Solomon exceedingly great in the sight of all Israel, and he bestowed upon him royal splendor that was not <supplied>bestowed</supplied> upon any king before him in Israel. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Death of King David</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ch 29:26">26</verse-number>And David the son of Jesse reigned over all Israel. <verse-number id="1 Ch 29:27">27</verse-number>And the days that he reigned over Israel <supplied>were</supplied> forty years. In Hebron he reigned seven years, and in Jerusalem he reigned thirty-three years. <verse-number id="1 Ch 29:28">28</verse-number>And he died in a good old age, full of days, wealth, and honor. And Solomon his son reigned in his place. <verse-number id="1 Ch 29:29">29</verse-number>Now the words of King David, <supplied>from</supplied> the first to the last, see, they are written among the words of Samuel the seer, and among the words of Nathan the prophet, and among the words of Gad the seer, <verse-number id="1 Ch 29:30">30</verse-number>with all <supplied>the accounts of</supplied> his kingdom, his power, and the times that came upon him, and upon Israel, and upon all the kingdoms of the earth. </p>
		</chapter>