<chapter id="1 Th 1">
			<pericope>Greeting</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Th 1:1">1</verse-number> Paul and Silvanus and Timothy, to the church of the Thessalonians in God the Father and the Lord Jesus Christ. Grace to you and peace. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Thanksgiving for the Thessalonian Believers</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Th 1:2">2</verse-number>We give thanks to God always concerning all of you, making mention constantly in our prayers, <verse-number id="1 Th 1:3">3</verse-number><supplied>because we</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“remember”) which is understood as causal</note> remember your work of faith and labor of love and steadfastness of hope in our Lord Jesus Christ in the presence of our God and Father, <verse-number id="1 Th 1:4">4</verse-number>knowing, brothers <supplied>dearly</supplied> loved by God, <idiom-start/>that he has chosen you<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the choice of you”</note>, <verse-number id="1 Th 1:5">5</verse-number>because our gospel did not come to you with word only, but also with power and with the Holy Spirit and with much certainty, just as you know what sort of <supplied>people</supplied> we became among you for your sake. <verse-number id="1 Th 1:6">6</verse-number>And you became imitators of us and of the Lord, receiving the word in much affliction, with the joy of the Holy Spirit, <verse-number id="1 Th 1:7">7</verse-number>so that you became an example to all those who believe in Macedonia and in Achaia, <verse-number id="1 Th 1:8">8</verse-number>for from you the word of the Lord has sounded forth, not only in Macedonia and Achaia,<note>Some manuscripts have “and in Achaia”</note> but in every place your faith toward God has gone out, so that we have no need to say anything. <verse-number id="1 Th 1:9">9</verse-number>For <supplied>they</supplied> themselves report about us, what sort of welcome we had with you, and how you turned to God from idols to serve <supplied>the</supplied> living and true God, <verse-number id="1 Th 1:10">10</verse-number>and to await his Son from heaven, whom he raised from the dead, Jesus, the one who delivers us from the coming wrath. </p>
		</chapter>