<chapter id="1 Th 2">
			<pericope>Paul’s Approach to Ministry in Thessalonica</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Th 2:1">1</verse-number> For <supplied>you</supplied> yourselves know, brothers, our reception with you, that it was not in vain, <verse-number id="1 Th 2:2">2</verse-number>but <supplied>after we</supplied> had already suffered and been mistreated in Philippi, just as you know, we had the courage in our God to speak to you the gospel of God amid much opposition. <verse-number id="1 Th 2:3">3</verse-number>For our exhortation <supplied>is</supplied> not from error or from impurity or with deceit, <verse-number id="1 Th 2:4">4</verse-number>but just as we have been approved by God to be entrusted with the gospel, thus we speak, not as pleasing people but God, who examines our hearts. <verse-number id="1 Th 2:5">5</verse-number><idiom-start/>For never<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for neither ever”</note> did we come with a word of flattery, just as you know, nor with a pretext of greediness (God <supplied>is</supplied> witness), <verse-number id="1 Th 2:6">6</verse-number>nor seeking glory from people, neither from you nor from others. <verse-number id="1 Th 2:7">7</verse-number><idiom-start/>Although we could have insisted on our own importance<idiom-end/><note>Literally “being able to be with a claim of importance”</note><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the participle (“being able”) is understood as concessive</note> as apostles of Christ, yet we became infants in your midst, like a nursing mother cherishes her own children. <verse-number id="1 Th 2:8">8</verse-number>Longing for you in this way, we determined to share with you not only the gospel of God but also our own souls, because you had become dear to us. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Th 2:9">9</verse-number>For you remember, brothers, our labor and hardship: working by night and day in order not to be a burden to any of you, we proclaimed to you the gospel of God. <verse-number id="1 Th 2:10">10</verse-number>You <supplied>are</supplied> witnesses, and <supplied>so is</supplied> God, how devoutly and righteously and blamelessly we became to you who believe, <verse-number id="1 Th 2:11">11</verse-number>just as you know how <supplied>we treated</supplied> each one of you, like a father his own children, <verse-number id="1 Th 2:12">12</verse-number>exhorting and consoling you and insisting that you live in a manner worthy of God, who calls you to his own kingdom and glory. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Thessalonians’ Response to Paul’s Message</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Th 2:13">13</verse-number>And because of this we also give thanks to God constantly, that <supplied>when you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“received”) which is understood as temporal</note> received God’s word <idiom-start/>that you heard<idiom-end/><note>Literally “of hearing”</note> from us, you accepted <supplied>it</supplied> not <supplied>as the</supplied> word of men, but as <supplied>it</supplied> truly is, <supplied>the</supplied> word of God, which also is at work in you who believe. <verse-number id="1 Th 2:14">14</verse-number>For you became imitators, brothers, of the churches of God <supplied>which</supplied> are in Judea in Christ Jesus, because you also suffered the same <supplied>things</supplied> at the hands of your own people, just as <supplied>they</supplied> themselves <supplied>did</supplied> also at the hands of the Jews, <verse-number id="1 Th 2:15">15</verse-number>who killed both the Lord Jesus and the prophets, and who persecuted us, and <supplied>who are</supplied> not pleasing to God and <supplied>are</supplied> opposed to all people, <verse-number id="1 Th 2:16">16</verse-number>hindering us from speaking to the Gentiles in order that they may be saved, so that <supplied>they</supplied> always fill up their sins. But wrath has come upon them to the end.<note>Or “has come upon them at last”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Paul’s Desire to Revisit the Thessalonians</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Th 2:17">17</verse-number>But <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“were made orphans by separation”) which is understood as temporal</note> we were made orphans by separation from you, brothers, for <idiom-start/>a short time<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the time of an hour”</note> (in face, not in heart), <supplied>we were</supplied> even more eager with great desire to see your face, <verse-number id="1 Th 2:18">18</verse-number>because we wanted to come to you—I, Paul, <idiom-start/>on more than one occasion<idiom-end/><note>Literally “both once and twice”</note>—and Satan hindered us. <verse-number id="1 Th 2:19">19</verse-number>For who <supplied>is</supplied> our hope or joy or crown of boasting? <supplied>Is it</supplied> not even you, in the presence of our Lord Jesus at his coming? <verse-number id="1 Th 2:20">20</verse-number>For you are our glory and joy. </p>
		</chapter>