<chapter id="1 Th 3">
			<pericope>Paul Sends Timothy to Thessalonica</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Th 3:1">1</verse-number> Therefore <supplied>when we</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“could bear”) which is understood as temporal</note> could bear <supplied>it</supplied> no longer, we determined to be left behind in Athens alone, <verse-number id="1 Th 3:2">2</verse-number>and we sent Timothy, our brother and fellow worker for God in the gospel of Christ, in order to strengthen and to encourage you about your faith, <verse-number id="1 Th 3:3">3</verse-number><supplied>so that</supplied> no one would be shaken by these afflictions. For <supplied>you</supplied> yourselves know that we are appointed for this, <verse-number id="1 Th 3:4">4</verse-number>for indeed when we were with you we told you beforehand that we were about to be afflicted, just as indeed it happened, and you know. <verse-number id="1 Th 3:5">5</verse-number>Because of this, I also, <supplied>when I</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“could endure”) which is understood as temporal</note> could endure <supplied>it</supplied> no longer, sent in order to know your faith, lest somehow the tempter tempted you and our labor should be in vain. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Timothy’s Positive Report</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Th 3:6">6</verse-number>But now, <supplied>because</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“has come”) which is understood as causal</note> Timothy has come to us from you and has brought good news to us of your faith and love, and that <idiom-start/>you always think kindly of us<idiom-end/><note>Literally “that you have kindly remembrance of us always”</note>, desiring to see us just as also we <supplied>desire to see</supplied> you, <verse-number id="1 Th 3:7">7</verse-number>because of this, brothers, we have been comforted because of you in all our distress and affliction through your faith, <verse-number id="1 Th 3:8">8</verse-number>because now we live, if you stand firm in the Lord. <verse-number id="1 Th 3:9">9</verse-number>For what thanks can we repay to God concerning you, because of all the joy <supplied>with</supplied> which we rejoice because of you before our God, <verse-number id="1 Th 3:10">10</verse-number>night and day praying beyond all measure that <supplied>we</supplied> may see your face and complete what is lacking in your faith? </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Th 3:11">11</verse-number>Now <supplied>may</supplied> our God and Father himself and our Lord Jesus direct our way to you, <verse-number id="1 Th 3:12">12</verse-number>and <supplied>may</supplied> the Lord <supplied>cause</supplied> you to increase and to abound in love for one another and for all, just as also we <supplied>do</supplied> for you, <verse-number id="1 Th 3:13">13</verse-number>so that your hearts may be established blameless in holiness before our God and Father at the coming of our Lord Jesus with all his saints.<note>Some manuscripts have “his saints. Amen.”</note> </p>
		</chapter>