<chapter id="1 Th 4">
			<pericope>Appeal for Continuing Sanctification</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Th 4:1">1</verse-number> Finally therefore, brothers, we ask you and appeal to <supplied>you</supplied> in the Lord Jesus that, just as you have received from us how it is necessary for you to live and to please God, just as indeed you are living, that you progress even more. <verse-number id="1 Th 4:2">2</verse-number>For you know what commands we gave to you through the Lord Jesus. <verse-number id="1 Th 4:3">3</verse-number>For this is the will of God, your sanctification: <supplied>that</supplied> you abstain from sexual immorality; <verse-number id="1 Th 4:4">4</verse-number><supplied>that</supplied> each of you know how to possess his own vessel in sanctification and honor, <verse-number id="1 Th 4:5">5</verse-number>not in lustful passion, just as also the Gentiles who do not know God; <verse-number id="1 Th 4:6">6</verse-number>not to transgress and to exploit his brother in the matter, because the Lord <supplied>is</supplied> the one who avenges concerning all these <supplied>things</supplied>, just as also we told you beforehand and testified solemnly. <verse-number id="1 Th 4:7">7</verse-number>For God did not call us to impurity, but in holiness. <verse-number id="1 Th 4:8">8</verse-number>Therefore the one who rejects <supplied>this</supplied> <supplied>is</supplied> not rejecting man, but God, <supplied>who</supplied> also gives his Holy Spirit to you. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Affirmation of Continuing Love</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Th 4:9">9</verse-number>But concerning brotherly love, I do not have need to write to you, for you yourselves are taught by God to love one another, <verse-number id="1 Th 4:10">10</verse-number>for indeed you are practicing it toward all the brothers in all of Macedonia. But we urge you, brothers, to progress even more, <verse-number id="1 Th 4:11">11</verse-number>and to aspire to live a quiet life, and to attend to <idiom-start/>your own business<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “your own things”</note> and to work with your hands,<note>Some manuscripts have “your own hands”</note> just as we commanded you, <verse-number id="1 Th 4:12">12</verse-number>so that you may live decently toward those outside, and may have need of nothing. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Comfort of the Lord’s Return</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Th 4:13">13</verse-number>Now we do not want you to be ignorant, brothers, concerning those who have fallen asleep, so that you will not grieve as also the rest, who have no hope. <verse-number id="1 Th 4:14">14</verse-number>For if we believe that Jesus died and rose <supplied>again</supplied>, thus also God will bring those who have fallen asleep through Jesus together with him. <verse-number id="1 Th 4:15">15</verse-number>For this we say to you by the word of the Lord, that we who are alive, who remain until the Lord’s coming, will not possibly precede those who have fallen asleep. <verse-number id="1 Th 4:16">16</verse-number>For the Lord himself will descend from heaven with a shout of command, with the voice of the archangel and with the trumpet of God, and the dead in Christ will rise first. <verse-number id="1 Th 4:17">17</verse-number>Then we who are alive, who remain, will be snatched away at the same time together with them in the clouds for a meeting with the Lord in the air, and thus we will be together with the Lord always. <verse-number id="1 Th 4:18">18</verse-number>Therefore comfort one another with these words. </p>
		</chapter>