<chapter id="1 Th 5">
			<pericope>The Sudden Arrival of the Day of the Lord</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Th 5:1">1</verse-number> Now concerning the times and the seasons, brothers, you have no need <supplied>of anything</supplied> to be written to you, <verse-number id="1 Th 5:2">2</verse-number>for <supplied>you</supplied> yourselves well know that the day of the Lord is coming in the <supplied>same</supplied> way as a thief in the night. <verse-number id="1 Th 5:3">3</verse-number>Whenever they say “Peace and security,” then sudden destruction will overtake them like the birth pains of <idiom-start/>a pregnant woman<idiom-end/><note>Literally “one who has in the belly”</note>, and they will not possibly escape. <verse-number id="1 Th 5:4">4</verse-number>But you, brothers, are not in the darkness, so that the day should catch you like a thief, <verse-number id="1 Th 5:5">5</verse-number>for you are all sons of light and sons of day. We are not of the night nor of darkness. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Th 5:6">6</verse-number>So then, we must not sleep like the rest, but must be on the alert and be self-controlled. <verse-number id="1 Th 5:7">7</verse-number>For those who sleep, sleep at night, and those who get drunk, are drunk at night. <verse-number id="1 Th 5:8">8</verse-number>But <supplied>because</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“are”) which is understood as causal</note> we are of the day, we must be sober, <supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“putting on”) which is understood as means</note> putting on the breastplate of faith and love and <supplied>as</supplied> a helmet the hope of salvation, <verse-number id="1 Th 5:9">9</verse-number>because God did not appoint us for wrath, but for the obtaining of salvation through our Lord Jesus Christ, <verse-number id="1 Th 5:10">10</verse-number>who died for us, so that whether we are awake or asleep, we will live at the same time with him. <verse-number id="1 Th 5:11">11</verse-number>Therefore encourage one another and build up <idiom-start/>each other<idiom-end/><note>Literally “one the one,” i.e., “one the other”</note>, just as indeed you are doing. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Final Exhortations and Benediction</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Th 5:12">12</verse-number>Now we ask you, brothers, to respect those who labor among you and rule over you in the Lord and admonish you, <verse-number id="1 Th 5:13">13</verse-number>and to esteem them beyond all measure in love, because of their work. Be at peace among yourselves. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Th 5:14">14</verse-number>And we urge you, brothers, admonish the disorderly, console the discouraged, help the sick, be patient toward all <supplied>people</supplied>. <verse-number id="1 Th 5:15">15</verse-number>See to it that no one pays back evil for evil to anyone, but always pursue good toward<note>Some manuscripts have “both toward”</note> one another and toward all <supplied>people</supplied>. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Th 5:16">16</verse-number>Rejoice always, <verse-number id="1 Th 5:17">17</verse-number>pray constantly, <verse-number id="1 Th 5:18">18</verse-number>give thanks in everything; for this <supplied>is</supplied> the will of God for you in Christ Jesus. <verse-number id="1 Th 5:19">19</verse-number>Do not quench the Spirit. <verse-number id="1 Th 5:20">20</verse-number>Do not despise prophecies, <verse-number id="1 Th 5:21">21</verse-number>but examine all <supplied>things</supplied>; hold fast to <supplied>what is</supplied> good. <verse-number id="1 Th 5:22">22</verse-number>Abstain from every form of evil. <verse-number id="1 Th 5:23">23</verse-number>Now may the God of peace himself sanctify you completely, and may your spirit and soul and body be kept complete, blameless at the coming of our Lord Jesus Christ. <verse-number id="1 Th 5:24">24</verse-number>The one who calls you <supplied>is</supplied> faithful, who also will do <supplied>this</supplied>. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Th 5:25">25</verse-number>Brothers, pray for us.<note>Some manuscripts have “pray for us also”</note> <verse-number id="1 Th 5:26">26</verse-number>Greet all the brothers with a holy kiss. <verse-number id="1 Th 5:27">27</verse-number>I adjure you by the Lord, have this letter read aloud to all the brothers. <verse-number id="1 Th 5:28">28</verse-number>The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ <supplied>be</supplied> with you. </p>
		</chapter>