<chapter id="Lk 2">
			<pericope>The Birth of Jesus Christ</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 2:1">1</verse-number> Now it happened that in those days a decree went out from Caesar<note>Or “the emperor”</note> Augustus to register all the empire. <verse-number id="Lk 2:2">2</verse-number>(This first registration took place <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Or perhaps “<supplied>before</supplied>”; here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was governor”)</note> Quirinius was governor of Syria.) <verse-number id="Lk 2:3">3</verse-number>And everyone went to be registered, each one to his own town. <verse-number id="Lk 2:4">4</verse-number>So Joseph also went up from Galilee, from the town of Nazareth, to Judea, to the city of David which is called Bethlehem, because he was of the house and family line of David, <verse-number id="Lk 2:5">5</verse-number>to be registered together with Mary, who was legally promised in marriage to him <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied in keeping with English style</note> was pregnant. <verse-number id="Lk 2:6">6</verse-number>And it happened that while they were there, <idiom-start/>the time came<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the days were completed”</note> for her to give birth. <verse-number id="Lk 2:7">7</verse-number>And she gave birth to her firstborn son, and wrapped him in strips of cloth and laid him in a manger, because there was no place for them in the inn. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Shepherds and the Angels</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 2:8">8</verse-number>And there were shepherds in the same region, living out of doors and keeping watch, guarding over their flock by night. <verse-number id="Lk 2:9">9</verse-number>And an angel of the Lord stood near them, and the glory of the Lord shone around them, and <idiom-start/>they were terribly frightened<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “they were afraid with great fear”</note> <verse-number id="Lk 2:10">10</verse-number>And the angel said to them, “Do not be afraid, for behold, I bring good news to you of great joy which will be for all the people: <verse-number id="Lk 2:11">11</verse-number>that today a Savior, who is Christ the Lord, was born for you in the city of David. <verse-number id="Lk 2:12">12</verse-number>And this will be the sign for you: you will find the baby wrapped in strips of cloth and lying in a manger.” <verse-number id="Lk 2:13">13</verse-number>And suddenly there was with the angel a multitude of the heavenly army, praising God and saying, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Lk 2:14">14</verse-number>“Glory to God in the highest, </li1>
				<li2>and on earth peace </li2>
				<li2>among people <idiom-start/>with whom he is pleased<idiom-end/>!”<note>Literally “of good pleasure”</note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 2:15">15</verse-number>And it happened that when the angels had departed from them into heaven, the shepherds began to say<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to say”)</note> to one another, “Let us go now to Bethlehem and see this thing that has happened, which the Lord has revealed to us!” <verse-number id="Lk 2:16">16</verse-number>And they went hurrying and found both Mary and Joseph, and the baby who was lying in the manger. <verse-number id="Lk 2:17">17</verse-number>And <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> saw <supplied>it</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> they made known the statement that had been told to them about this child. <verse-number id="Lk 2:18">18</verse-number>And all who heard <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> were astonished concerning what had been said to them by the shepherds. <verse-number id="Lk 2:19">19</verse-number>But Mary treasured up all these words, pondering <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> in her heart. <verse-number id="Lk 2:20">20</verse-number>And the shepherds returned, glorifying and praising God for all that they had heard and seen, just as it had been told to them. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 2:21">21</verse-number>And when eight days were completed <idiom-start/>so that he could be circumcised<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to circumcise him”</note> he was named Jesus, his name <supplied>that</supplied> <supplied>he</supplied> was called by the angel before he was conceived in the womb. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Presentation of Jesus at the Temple</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 2:22">22</verse-number>And when the days of their purification were completed according to the law of Moses, they brought him up to Jerusalem to present <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to the Lord <verse-number id="Lk 2:23">23</verse-number>(just as it is written in the law of the Lord, “Every male that opens the womb will be called holy to the Lord”)<note>An allusion to <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ex 13:2">Exod 13:2</cite>, <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ex 13:12">12</cite>, <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ex 13:15">15</cite></note> <verse-number id="Lk 2:24">24</verse-number>and to offer a sacrifice according to what was stated in the law of the Lord, “a pair of turtledoves or two young pigeons.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Le 5:11">Lev 5:11</cite>; <cite title="BibleLEB2: Le 12:8">12:8</cite></note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Prophecy of Simeon</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 2:25">25</verse-number>And behold, there was a man in Jerusalem <idiom-start/>whose name was<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to whom the name”</note> Simeon, and this man <supplied>was</supplied> righteous and devout, looking forward to the consolation of Israel, and the Holy Spirit was upon him. <verse-number id="Lk 2:26">26</verse-number>And it had been revealed to him by the Holy Spirit <supplied>that he would</supplied> not see death before he would see the Lord’s Christ.<note>Or “Messiah”</note> <verse-number id="Lk 2:27">27</verse-number>And he came in the Spirit into the temple, and when the parents brought in the child Jesus so that they could do for him according to what was customary under the law, <verse-number id="Lk 2:28">28</verse-number>he took him in <supplied>his</supplied><note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> arms and praised God and said, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Lk 2:29">29</verse-number>“Now dismiss your slave in peace, Lord, </li1>
				<li2>according to your word. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Lk 2:30">30</verse-number>For my eyes have seen your salvation </li1>
				<li2><verse-number id="Lk 2:31">31</verse-number>that you have prepared in the presence of all the peoples, </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Lk 2:32">32</verse-number>a light for revelation to the Gentiles, </li1>
				<li2>and glory to your people Israel.” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 2:33">33</verse-number>And his father and mother were astonished at what was said about him. <verse-number id="Lk 2:34">34</verse-number>And Simeon blessed them and said to his mother Mary, “Behold, this child is appointed for the fall and rise of many in Israel, and for a sign that is opposed<note>Or “rejected”</note>—<verse-number id="Lk 2:35">35</verse-number>and a sword will pierce your own soul also, so that the thoughts of many hearts will be revealed!” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Testimony of Anna</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 2:36">36</verse-number>And there was a prophetess, Anna the daughter of Phanuel of the tribe of Asher (she was advanced <idiom-start/>in years<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “with many days”</note> having lived with <supplied>her</supplied> husband seven years <idiom-start/>after her marriage<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from her virginity”</note> <verse-number id="Lk 2:37">37</verse-number>and herself <supplied>as</supplied> a widow up to eighty-four years)<note>Or “eighty-four years as a widow”</note> who did not depart from the temple with fastings and prayers, serving night and day. <verse-number id="Lk 2:38">38</verse-number>And at <supplied>that</supplied> same hour she approached <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“approached”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> began to give thanks<note>The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to give thanks”)</note> to God, and to speak about him to all those who were waiting for the redemption of Jerusalem. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 2:39">39</verse-number>And when they had completed everything according to the law of the Lord, they returned to Galilee, to their own town of Nazareth. <verse-number id="Lk 2:40">40</verse-number>And the child was growing and becoming strong, filled with wisdom, and the favor of God was upon him. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus in the Temple at Twelve Years Old</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 2:41">41</verse-number>And his parents went every year to Jerusalem for the feast of the Passover. <verse-number id="Lk 2:42">42</verse-number>And when he was twelve years <supplied>old</supplied>, they went up according to the custom of the feast. <verse-number id="Lk 2:43">43</verse-number>And <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“were completed”) which is understood as temporal</note> the days were completed, while they were returning, the boy Jesus stayed behind in Jerusalem. And his parents did not know <supplied>it</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <verse-number id="Lk 2:44">44</verse-number>but believing him to be in the group of travelers, they went a day’s journey. And they began searching for<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began searching for”)</note> him among <supplied>their</supplied><note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> relatives and <supplied>their</supplied><note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> acquaintances, <verse-number id="Lk 2:45">45</verse-number>and <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“find”) which is understood as temporal</note> did not find <supplied>him</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> they returned to Jerusalem to search for him. <verse-number id="Lk 2:46">46</verse-number>And it happened that after three days they found him in the temple <supplied>courts</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here “<supplied>courts</supplied>” is supplied to distinguish this area from the interior of the temple building itself</note> sitting in the midst of the teachers and listening to them and asking them <supplied>questions</supplied>. <verse-number id="Lk 2:47">47</verse-number>And all who heard him were amazed at his insight and <supplied>his</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*This is an understood repetition of “<supplied>his</supplied>” due to English style</note> answers. <verse-number id="Lk 2:48">48</verse-number>And <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> saw him, they were astounded and his mother said to him, “Child, why have you done this to us? Look, your father and I have been searching for you anxiously!” <verse-number id="Lk 2:49">49</verse-number>And he said to them, “<idiom-start/>Why<idiom-end/><note>Literally “what <supplied>is it</supplied> that”</note> were you searching for me? Did you not know that it was necessary <supplied>for</supplied> me to be in the <supplied>house</supplied><note>Or “things” (= business)</note> of my Father?” <verse-number id="Lk 2:50">50</verse-number>And they did not understand the statement that he spoke to them. <verse-number id="Lk 2:51">51</verse-number>And he went down with them and came to Nazareth, and was submitting to them. And his mother treasured all these things in her heart. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 2:52">52</verse-number>And Jesus was advancing in wisdom and stature and in favor with God and <supplied>with</supplied> people. </p>
		</chapter>