<chapter id="Lk 3">
			<pericope>John the Baptist Begins His Ministry</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 3:1">1</verse-number> Now in the fifteenth year of the reign of Tiberius Caesar,<note>Or “the emperor Tiberius”</note> <supplied>when</supplied> Pontius Pilate was governor of Judea, and Herod was tetrarch of Galilee, and his brother Philip was tetrarch of the region of Iturea and Trachonitis, and Lysanias was tetrarch of Abilene, <verse-number id="Lk 3:2">2</verse-number>in the time of the high priest Annas and Caiaphas, the word of God came to John the son of Zechariah in the wilderness. <verse-number id="Lk 3:3">3</verse-number>And he went into all the surrounding region of the Jordan, preaching a baptism of repentance for the forgiveness of sins, <verse-number id="Lk 3:4">4</verse-number>as it is written in the book of the words of the prophet Isaiah, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“The voice of one crying out in the wilderness, </li1>
				<li1>‘Prepare the way of the Lord, </li1>
				<li2>make his paths straight! </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Lk 3:5">5</verse-number>Every valley will be filled, </li1>
				<li2>and every mountain and hill will be leveled, </li2>
				<li1>and the crooked will become straight, </li1>
				<li2>and the rough road <supplied>will become</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>will become</supplied>” is an implied repetition of the verb earlier in the verse</note> smooth, </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Lk 3:6">6</verse-number>and all flesh will see the salvation of God.’ ”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 40:3–5">Isa 40:3–5</cite></note> </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 3:7">7</verse-number>Therefore he was saying to the crowds that came out to be baptized by him, “Offspring of vipers! Who warned you to flee from the coming wrath? <verse-number id="Lk 3:8">8</verse-number>Therefore produce fruit worthy of repentance! And do not begin to say to yourselves, ‘We have Abraham <supplied>as</supplied> father.’ For I say to you that God is able to raise up children for Abraham from these stones! <verse-number id="Lk 3:9">9</verse-number>And even now the ax is positioned at the root of the trees; therefore every tree not producing good fruit is cut down and thrown into the fire.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 3:10">10</verse-number>And the crowds were asking him, saying, “What then should we do?” <verse-number id="Lk 3:11">11</verse-number>And he answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to them, “The one who has two tunics must share with the one who does not have <supplied>one</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and the one who has food must do likewise.” <verse-number id="Lk 3:12">12</verse-number>And tax collectors also came to be baptized, and they said to him, “Teacher, what should we do?” <verse-number id="Lk 3:13">13</verse-number>And he said to them, “Collect no more than <idiom-start/>what you are ordered to<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “what is ordered to you”</note> <verse-number id="Lk 3:14">14</verse-number>And those who served in the army were also asking him, saying, “What should we also do?” And he said to them, “Extort from no one, and do not blackmail <supplied>anyone</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and be content with your pay.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 3:15">15</verse-number>And <supplied>while</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“were waiting expectantly”)</note> the people were waiting expectantly and all were pondering in their hearts concerning John, whether perhaps he might be the Christ,<note>Or “Messiah”</note> <verse-number id="Lk 3:16">16</verse-number>John answered them all, saying, “I baptize you with water, but the one who is more powerful than I <supplied>am</supplied> is coming, of whom I am not worthy to untie the strap of his sandals. He will baptize you with the Holy Spirit and fire. <verse-number id="Lk 3:17">17</verse-number>His winnowing shovel <supplied>is</supplied> in his hand, to clean out his threshing floor and to gather the wheat into his storehouse, but he will burn up the chaff with unquenchable fire.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 3:18">18</verse-number>So with many other exhortations also he proclaimed good news to the people. <verse-number id="Lk 3:19">19</verse-number>But Herod the tetrarch, who had been reproved by him concerning Herodias, his brother’s wife, and concerning all the evil deeds that Herod had done, <verse-number id="Lk 3:20">20</verse-number>added this also to them all: he also locked up John in prison. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Baptism of Jesus</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 3:21">21</verse-number>Now it happened that when all the people were baptized, Jesus also was baptized, and <supplied>while he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was praying”)</note> was praying, heaven was opened, <verse-number id="Lk 3:22">22</verse-number>and the Holy Spirit descended on him in bodily form like a dove, and a voice came from heaven, “You are my beloved Son; with you I am well pleased.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Genealogy of Jesus Christ</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 3:23">23</verse-number>And Jesus, <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“began”) which is understood as temporal</note> began <supplied>his ministry</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> was himself about thirty years <supplied>old</supplied>, being the son (as it was believed) of Joseph the <supplied>son</supplied> of Eli, <verse-number id="Lk 3:24">24</verse-number>the <supplied>son</supplied> of Matthat, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Levi, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Melchi, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Jannai, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Joseph, <verse-number id="Lk 3:25">25</verse-number>the <supplied>son</supplied> of Mattathias, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Amos, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Nahum, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Esli, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Naggai, <verse-number id="Lk 3:26">26</verse-number>the <supplied>son</supplied> of Maath, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Mattathias, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Semein, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Josech, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Joda, <verse-number id="Lk 3:27">27</verse-number>the <supplied>son</supplied> of Joanan, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Rhesa, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Zerubbabel, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Shealtiel, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Neri, <verse-number id="Lk 3:28">28</verse-number>the <supplied>son</supplied> of Melchi, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Addi, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Cosam, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Elmadam, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Er, <verse-number id="Lk 3:29">29</verse-number>the <supplied>son</supplied> of Joshua, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Eliezer, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Jorim, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Matthat, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Levi, <verse-number id="Lk 3:30">30</verse-number>the <supplied>son</supplied> of Simeon, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Judah, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Joseph, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Jonam, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Eliakim, <verse-number id="Lk 3:31">31</verse-number>the <supplied>son</supplied> of Melea, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Menna, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Mattatha, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Nathan, the <supplied>son</supplied> of David, <verse-number id="Lk 3:32">32</verse-number>the <supplied>son</supplied> of Jesse, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Obed, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Boaz, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Sala, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Nahshon, <verse-number id="Lk 3:33">33</verse-number>the <supplied>son</supplied> of Amminadab, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Admin, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Arni, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Hezron, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Perez, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Judah, <verse-number id="Lk 3:34">34</verse-number>the <supplied>son</supplied> of Jacob, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Isaac, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Abraham, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Terah, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Nahor, <verse-number id="Lk 3:35">35</verse-number>the <supplied>son</supplied> of Serug, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Reu, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Peleg, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Eber, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Shelah,<note>Greek “Sala”</note> <verse-number id="Lk 3:36">36</verse-number>the <supplied>son</supplied> of Cainan, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Arphaxad, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Shem, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Noah, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Lamech, <verse-number id="Lk 3:37">37</verse-number>the <supplied>son</supplied> of Methuselah, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Enoch, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Jared, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Mahalaleel, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Cainan, <verse-number id="Lk 3:38">38</verse-number>the <supplied>son</supplied> of Enosh, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Seth, the <supplied>son</supplied> of Adam, the <supplied>son</supplied> of God. </p>
		</chapter>