<chapter id="Lk 5">
			<pericope>Jesus Calls His First Disciples</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 5:1">1</verse-number> Now it happened that while the crowd was pressing around him and hearing the word of God, he was standing beside the lake of Gennesaret,<note>Another name for the Sea of Galilee</note> <verse-number id="Lk 5:2">2</verse-number>and he saw two boats there beside the lake, but the fishermen had gotten out of them <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“had gotten out”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> were washing their nets. <verse-number id="Lk 5:3">3</verse-number>And he got into one of the boats, which was Simon’s, <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“got”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> asked him to put out from the land a little. And he sat down <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“sat down”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> began to teach<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to teach”)</note> the crowds from the boat. <verse-number id="Lk 5:4">4</verse-number>And when he stopped speaking, he said to Simon, “Put out into the deep water and let down your nets for a catch.” <verse-number id="Lk 5:5">5</verse-number>And Simon answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “Master, <supplied>although we</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>although</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“worked hard”) which is understood as concessive</note> worked hard through the whole night, we caught nothing. But at your word I will let down the nets.” <verse-number id="Lk 5:6">6</verse-number>And <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“did”) which is understood as temporal</note> did this, they caught a very large number of fish, and their nets began to tear.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to tear”)</note> <verse-number id="Lk 5:7">7</verse-number>And they signaled to their partners in the other boat to come <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“come”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> help them, and they came and filled both the boats so that they began to sink. <verse-number id="Lk 5:8">8</verse-number>And <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> saw <supplied>it</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> Simon Peter fell down at Jesus’ knees, saying, “Depart from me, Lord, because I am <idiom-start/>a sinful man<idiom-end/>!”<note>Literally “a man, a sinner”</note> <verse-number id="Lk 5:9">9</verse-number>For amazement had seized him and all those <supplied>who were</supplied> with him at the catch of fish that they had caught, <verse-number id="Lk 5:10">10</verse-number>and so also <supplied>were</supplied> James and John, the sons of Zebedee, who were business partners with Simon. And Jesus said to Simon, “Do not be afraid! From now on you will be catching people!” <verse-number id="Lk 5:11">11</verse-number>And <supplied>after they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“brought”) which is understood as temporal</note> brought <supplied>their</supplied><note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> boats to the land, they left everything <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“left”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> followed him. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A Leper Cleansed</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 5:12">12</verse-number>And it happened that while he was in one of the towns, <idiom-start/>there was<idiom-end/><note>Literally “behold”</note> a man <idiom-start/>covered with leprosy<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “full of leprosy”</note> And <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> saw Jesus, he fell down on <supplied>his</supplied> face <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“fell down”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> begged him, saying, “Lord, if you are willing, you are able to make me clean.” <verse-number id="Lk 5:13">13</verse-number>And extending <supplied>his</supplied><note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> hand he touched him, saying, “I am willing; be clean.” And immediately the leprosy went away from him. <verse-number id="Lk 5:14">14</verse-number>And he ordered him, “Tell no one, but go <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“go”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> show yourself to the priest and bring <supplied>the offering</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> for your cleansing just as Moses commanded, for a testimony to them. <verse-number id="Lk 5:15">15</verse-number>But the report about him spread even more, and large crowds were gathering to hear <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and to be healed of their illnesses. <verse-number id="Lk 5:16">16</verse-number>But he himself was withdrawing in the wilderness and praying. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A Paralytic Healed</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 5:17">17</verse-number>And it happened that on one of the days as he was teaching, Pharisees and teachers of the law were sitting <supplied>there</supplied> who <idiom-start/>had come<idiom-end/><note>Literally “were having come”</note> from every village of Galilee and Judea and <supplied>from</supplied> Jerusalem, and the power of the Lord was <supplied>there</supplied> in order <supplied>for</supplied> him to heal. <verse-number id="Lk 5:18">18</verse-number>And behold, men <supplied>came</supplied> carrying on a stretcher a man who was paralyzed, and they were seeking to bring him in and place <supplied>him</supplied><note>Some manuscripts Some manuscripts include the pronoun “him” after “place”</note>﻿<note>Since Greek routinely omits direct objects when they are clear from context, the pronoun is not necessary here in the Greek text, but it must be supplied in the English translation</note> before him. <verse-number id="Lk 5:19">19</verse-number>And <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“find”) which is understood as temporal</note> did not find a way to bring him in because of the crowd, they went up on the roof <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> let him down through the roof tiles with the stretcher into the midst <supplied>of them</supplied>, in front of Jesus. <verse-number id="Lk 5:20">20</verse-number>And <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> saw their faith, he said, “Friend, your sins are forgiven you.” <verse-number id="Lk 5:21">21</verse-number>And the scribes and the Pharisees began to reason, saying, “Who is this man who speaks blasphemies? Who is able to forgive sins except God alone?” <verse-number id="Lk 5:22">22</verse-number>But Jesus, perceiving their thoughts, answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to them, “Why are you reasoning in your hearts? <verse-number id="Lk 5:23">23</verse-number>Which is easier to say, ‘Your sins are forgiven you,’ or to say, ‘Get up and walk?’ <verse-number id="Lk 5:24">24</verse-number>But in order that you may know that the Son of Man has authority on earth to forgive sins,” he said to the one who was paralyzed, “I say to you, ‘Get up and pick up your stretcher <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“pick up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> go to your home.’ ” <verse-number id="Lk 5:25">25</verse-number>And immediately he stood up before them, picked up what he had been lying on, <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participles (“stood up” and “picked up”) have been translated as finite verbs</note> went away to his home, glorifying God. <verse-number id="Lk 5:26">26</verse-number>And amazement seized <supplied>them</supplied> all, and they began to glorify<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to glorify”)</note> God. And they were filled with fear, saying, “We have seen wonderful things today!” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Levi Called to Follow Jesus</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 5:27">27</verse-number>And after these <supplied>things</supplied>, he went out and saw a tax collector <idiom-start/>named<idiom-end/><note>Literally “by name”</note> Levi sitting at the tax booth, and he said to him, “Follow me!” <verse-number id="Lk 5:28">28</verse-number>And leaving everything behind, he got up <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“got up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> began to follow<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to follow”)</note> him. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 5:29">29</verse-number>And Levi gave a great banquet for him in his house, and there was a large crowd of tax collectors and others who were reclining for the meal with them. <verse-number id="Lk 5:30">30</verse-number>And the Pharisees and their scribes began to complain<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to complain”)</note> to his disciples, saying, “Why do you eat and drink with the tax collectors and sinners?” <verse-number id="Lk 5:31">31</verse-number>And Jesus answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to them, “Those who are healthy do not have need of a physician, but those <idiom-start/>who are sick<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “having badly”</note> <verse-number id="Lk 5:32">32</verse-number>I have not come to call the righteous but sinners to repentance.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>On Fasting</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 5:33">33</verse-number>And they said to him, “The disciples of John fast often and make prayers—likewise also the <supplied>disciples</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The word “<supplied>disciples</supplied>” is not in the Greek text but is implied</note> of the Pharisees—but yours are eating and drinking!” <verse-number id="Lk 5:34">34</verse-number>So he<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> said<note>Some manuscripts have “So Jesus said”</note> to them, “You are not able to make the <idiom-start/>bridegroom’s attendants<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons of the bridal chamber”</note> fast as long as the bridegroom is with them, <supplied>are you</supplied>?<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here, indicated in the translation by the phrase “<supplied>are you</supplied>”</note> <verse-number id="Lk 5:35">35</verse-number>But days will come, and when the bridegroom is taken away from them, then they will fast in those days.” <verse-number id="Lk 5:36">36</verse-number>And he also told a parable to them: “No one tears a patch from a new garment <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“tears”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> puts <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> on an old garment. Otherwise, he will have torn the new also, and the old will not match the patch <supplied>that is</supplied> from the new. <verse-number id="Lk 5:37">37</verse-number>And no one pours new wine into old wineskins. Otherwise, the new wine will burst the wineskins, and it will be spilled and the wineskins will be destroyed. <verse-number id="Lk 5:38">38</verse-number>But new wine must be put into new wineskins. <verse-number id="Lk 5:39">39</verse-number>And no one <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“drinking”) which is understood as temporal</note> drinking old <supplied>wine</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The word “<supplied>wine</supplied>” is not in the Greek text but is implied</note> wants new, because he says, ‘The old is <supplied>just</supplied> fine!’ ” </p>
		</chapter>