<chapter id="Lk 6">
			<pericope>Plucking Grain on the Sabbath</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 6:1">1</verse-number> Now it happened that on a Sabbath he went through the grain fields, and his disciples were picking and eating the heads of grain, rubbing <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> in <supplied>their</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> hands. <verse-number id="Lk 6:2">2</verse-number>But some of the Pharisees said, “Why are you doing what is not permitted on the Sabbath? <verse-number id="Lk 6:3">3</verse-number>And Jesus answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to them, “Have you not read this, what David did when he and those <supplied>who were</supplied> with him were hungry—<verse-number id="Lk 6:4">4</verse-number>how he entered into the house of God and took the bread of the presentation, which it is not permitted to eat (except the priests alone), <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“took”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> ate <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and gave <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to those with him?” <verse-number id="Lk 6:5">5</verse-number>And he said to them, “The Son of Man is Lord of the Sabbath.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A Man with a Withered Hand Healed</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 6:6">6</verse-number>Now it happened that on another Sabbath he entered into the synagogue and was teaching, and a man was there, and his right hand was withered. <verse-number id="Lk 6:7">7</verse-number>So the scribes and the Pharisees were watching closely<note>Some manuscripts have “were watching him closely”</note> <supplied>to see</supplied> if he would heal on the Sabbath, in order that they could find <supplied>a reason</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to accuse him. <verse-number id="Lk 6:8">8</verse-number>But he knew their thoughts and said to the man who had the withered hand, “Get up and stand in the middle,” and he got up <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“get up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> stood there. <verse-number id="Lk 6:9">9</verse-number>And Jesus said to them, “I ask you whether it is permitted on the Sabbath to do good or to do evil, to save a life or to destroy <supplied>it</supplied>?”<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <verse-number id="Lk 6:10">10</verse-number>And <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“looking around”) which is understood as temporal</note> looking around at them all, he said to him, “Stretch out your hand,” and he did, and his hand was restored. <verse-number id="Lk 6:11">11</verse-number>But they were filled with fury, and began discussing<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began discussing”)</note> with one another what they might do to Jesus. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Selection of the Twelve Apostles</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 6:12">12</verse-number>Now it happened that in these days he went away to the mountain to pray, and was spending the whole night in prayer to God. <verse-number id="Lk 6:13">13</verse-number>And when day came, he summoned his disciples and chose from them twelve, whom he also named apostles: <verse-number id="Lk 6:14">14</verse-number>Simon (whom he also named Peter) and his brother Andrew, and James, and John, and Philip, and Bartholomew, <verse-number id="Lk 6:15">15</verse-number>and Matthew, and Thomas, and James the <supplied>son</supplied> of Alphaeus, and Simon who was called the Zealot, <verse-number id="Lk 6:16">16</verse-number>and Judas <supplied>the son</supplied> of James, and Judas Iscariot, who became a traitor. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Sermon on the Plain: The Beatitudes</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 6:17">17</verse-number>And he came down with them <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came down”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> stood on a level place, and a large crowd of his disciples and a great multitude of people from all of Judea and Jerusalem and the seacoast district of Tyre and Sidon, <verse-number id="Lk 6:18">18</verse-number>who came to hear him and to be healed of their diseases, and those who were troubled by unclean spirits were cured. <verse-number id="Lk 6:19">19</verse-number>And the whole crowd was seeking to touch him, because power was going out from him and healing <supplied>them</supplied> all. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 6:20">20</verse-number>And he lifted up his eyes to his disciples <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“lifted up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Blessed <supplied>are</supplied> the poor, </li1>
				<li2>because yours is the kingdom of God. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Lk 6:21">21</verse-number>Blessed <supplied>are</supplied> those who are hungry now, </li1>
				<li2>because you will be satisfied. </li2>
				<li1>Blessed <supplied>are</supplied> those who weep now, </li1>
				<li2>Because you will laugh. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Lk 6:22">22</verse-number>Blessed are you when people hate you, and when they exclude you and revile <supplied>you</supplied> and spurn your name as evil on account of the Son of Man. <verse-number id="Lk 6:23">23</verse-number>Rejoice in that day, and leap for joy, for behold, your reward <supplied>is</supplied> great in heaven. For their fathers used to do the same <supplied>things</supplied> to the prophets. </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Sermon on the Plain: Woes</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Lk 6:24">24</verse-number>“But woe to you who are rich, </li1>
				<li2>because you have received your comfort. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Lk 6:25">25</verse-number>Woe to you who are satisfied now, </li1>
				<li2>because you will be hungry. </li2>
				<li1>Woe, you who laugh now, </li1>
				<li2>because you will mourn and weep. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Lk 6:26">26</verse-number>Woe whenever all people speak well of you, </li1>
				<li2>for their fathers used to do the same <supplied>things</supplied> to the false prophets. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Sermon on the Plain: Love for Enemies</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 6:27">27</verse-number>“But to you who are listening I say: Love your enemies, do good to those who hate you, <verse-number id="Lk 6:28">28</verse-number>bless those who curse you, pray for those who mistreat you. <verse-number id="Lk 6:29">29</verse-number>To the one who strikes you on the cheek, offer the other also, and from the one who takes away your cloak, do not withhold your tunic also. <verse-number id="Lk 6:30">30</verse-number>Give to everyone who asks you, and from the one who takes away your things, do not ask for <supplied>them back</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <verse-number id="Lk 6:31">31</verse-number>And just as you want people <idiom-start/>to do<idiom-end/><note>Literally “would do”</note> to you, do <idiom-start/>the same<idiom-end/><note>Literally “likewise”</note> to them. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 6:32">32</verse-number>“And if you love those who love you, what kind of credit is <supplied>that</supplied> to you? For even sinners love those who love them! <verse-number id="Lk 6:33">33</verse-number>And if<note>Some manuscripts have “For even if”</note> you do good to those who do good to you, what kind of credit is <supplied>that</supplied> to you? Even the sinners do the same! <verse-number id="Lk 6:34">34</verse-number>And if you lend <supplied>to those</supplied> from whom you expect to receive <supplied>back</supplied>, what kind of credit is <supplied>that</supplied> to you? Even sinners lend to sinners, so that they may get back an equal <supplied>amount</supplied>! <verse-number id="Lk 6:35">35</verse-number>But love your enemies, and do good, and lend expecting back nothing, and your reward will be great, and you will be sons of the Most High, because he is kind to the ungrateful and wicked. <verse-number id="Lk 6:36">36</verse-number>Be merciful, just as your Father is merciful!<note>Some manuscripts have “also is merciful”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Sermon on the Plain: On Judging Others</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 6:37">37</verse-number>“And do not judge, and you will never be judged. And do not condemn, and you will never be condemned. Pardon, and you will be pardoned. <verse-number id="Lk 6:38">38</verse-number>Give, and it will be given to you, a good measure—pressed down, shaken, overflowing—they will pour out into your lap. For with the measure by which you measure out, it will be measured out to you in return.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 6:39">39</verse-number>And he also told them a parable: “Surely a blind person cannot lead the blind, <supplied>can he</supplied>?<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here, indicated in the translation by the phrase “<supplied>can he</supplied>”</note> Will they not both fall into a pit? <verse-number id="Lk 6:40">40</verse-number>A disciple is not superior to <supplied>his</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> teacher, but everyone, <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“is fully trained”) which is understood as temporal</note> is fully trained, will be like his teacher. <verse-number id="Lk 6:41">41</verse-number>And why do you see the speck <supplied>that is</supplied> in your brother’s eye, but do not notice the beam of wood <supplied>that is</supplied> in your own eye? <verse-number id="Lk 6:42">42</verse-number>How are you able to say to your brother, “Brother, allow <supplied>me</supplied> to remove the speck <supplied>that is</supplied> in your eye,” <supplied>while</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“see”) which is understood as temporal</note> you yourself do not see the beam of wood in your <supplied>own</supplied> eye? Hypocrite! First remove the beam of wood from your <supplied>own</supplied> eye, and then you will see clearly to remove the speck <supplied>that is</supplied> in your brother’s eye! </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Sermon on the Plain: Trees and Their Fruit</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 6:43">43</verse-number>“For there is no good tree that produces bad fruit, nor on the other hand a bad tree that produces good fruit, <verse-number id="Lk 6:44">44</verse-number>for each tree is known by its own fruit. For figs are not gathered from thorn plants, nor are grapes harvested from thorn bushes. <verse-number id="Lk 6:45">45</verse-number>The good person out of the good treasury of his heart brings forth good, and the evil person out of <supplied>his</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> evil <supplied>treasury</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The word “<supplied>treasury”</supplied> here is an understood repetition from earlier in the verse</note> brings forth evil. For out of the abundance of the heart his mouth speaks. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 6:46">46</verse-number>“And why do you call me ‘Lord, Lord,’ and do not do what I tell <supplied>you</supplied>?<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Sermon on the Plain: Two Houses and Two Foundations</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 6:47">47</verse-number>“Everyone who comes to me and listens to my words and does them—I will show you what he is like: <verse-number id="Lk 6:48">48</verse-number>he is like a man building a house, who dug and went down deep and laid the foundation on the rock. And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“came”)</note> a flood came, the river burst against that house and was not able to shake it, because it had been built well. <verse-number id="Lk 6:49">49</verse-number>But the one who hears <supplied>my words</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and does not do <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> is like a man who built a house on the ground without a foundation, which the river burst against, and immediately it collapsed—and the collapse of that house was great!” </p>
		</chapter>