<chapter id="Lk 7">
			<pericope>A Centurion’s Slave Healed</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 7:1">1</verse-number> After he had finished all his statements in the hearing of the people, he entered into Capernaum. <verse-number id="Lk 7:2">2</verse-number>Now a certain centurion’s slave, who was esteemed by him, <idiom-start/>was sick<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was having badly”</note> <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“was having”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> was about to die. <verse-number id="Lk 7:3">3</verse-number>So <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> heard about Jesus, he sent Jewish elders to him, asking him that he would come <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“come”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> cure his slave. <verse-number id="Lk 7:4">4</verse-number>And <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“came”) which is understood as temporal</note> came to Jesus, they began imploring<note>The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began imploring”)</note> him earnestly, saying, “He is worthy <supplied>that</supplied> you grant this for him, <verse-number id="Lk 7:5">5</verse-number>because he loves our nation and he himself built the synagogue for us.” <verse-number id="Lk 7:6">6</verse-number>So Jesus went with them. Now by this time he was not far away from the house, <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“away”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> the centurion sent friends, saying to him, “Lord, do not trouble yourself, for I am not worthy that you should come in under my roof. <verse-number id="Lk 7:7">7</verse-number>For this reason neither did I consider myself worthy to come to you. But say the word and my slave must be healed. <verse-number id="Lk 7:8">8</verse-number>For I also am a man placed under authority, who has soldiers under me, and I say to this one, ‘Go!’ and he goes, and to another one, ‘Come!’ and he comes, and to my slave, ‘Do this!’ and he does <supplied>it</supplied>.”<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 7:9">9</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> Jesus heard these <supplied>things</supplied>, he marveled at him, and turning around to the crowd that was following him, he said, “I tell you, not even in Israel have I found such great faith!” <verse-number id="Lk 7:10">10</verse-number>And <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“returned”) which is understood as temporal</note> returned to the house, those who had been sent found the slave healthy. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A Widow’s Son Raised</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 7:11">11</verse-number>And it happened that on the next <supplied>day</supplied> he went to a town called Nain, and his disciples and a large crowd went with him. <verse-number id="Lk 7:12">12</verse-number>And as he approached the gate of the town, behold, a man who had died was being carried out, his mother’s only son, and she was a widow. And a large crowd from the town was with her. <verse-number id="Lk 7:13">13</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> the Lord saw her, he had compassion for her and said to her, “Do not weep!” <verse-number id="Lk 7:14">14</verse-number>And he came up <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> touched the bier, and those who were carrying <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> stopped. And he said, “Young man, I say to you, get up!” <verse-number id="Lk 7:15">15</verse-number>And the dead man sat up and began to speak, and he gave him to his mother. <verse-number id="Lk 7:16">16</verse-number>And fear seized <supplied>them</supplied> all, and they began to glorify<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to glorify”)</note> God, saying, “A great prophet has appeared among us!” and “God has visited to help his people!” <verse-number id="Lk 7:17">17</verse-number>And this report about him went out in the whole of Judea and in all the surrounding region. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A Question from John the Baptist</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 7:18">18</verse-number>And his disciples reported to John about all these <supplied>things</supplied>. And summoning a certain two of his disciples, John <verse-number id="Lk 7:19">19</verse-number>sent <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to the Lord,<note>A number of significant manuscripts read “Jesus”</note> saying, “Are you the one who is to come, or should we look for another?” <verse-number id="Lk 7:20">20</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“came”) which is understood as temporal</note> the men came to him, they said, “John the Baptist sent us to you, saying, ‘Are you the one who is to come, or should we look for another?’ ” <verse-number id="Lk 7:21">21</verse-number>In that hour he healed many <supplied>people</supplied> of diseases and suffering and evil spirits, and he granted sight to many blind <supplied>people</supplied>. <verse-number id="Lk 7:22">22</verse-number>And he answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to them, “Go <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“go”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> tell John what you have seen and heard: the blind receive sight, the lame walk, lepers are cleansed, the deaf hear;<note>Some manuscripts have “and the deaf hear”</note> the dead are raised, the poor have good news announced to <supplied>them</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <verse-number id="Lk 7:23">23</verse-number>And whoever is not offended by me is blessed.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 7:24">24</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“had departed”)</note> the messengers of John had departed, he began to speak to the crowds concerning John: “What did you go out into the wilderness to see? A reed shaken by the wind? <verse-number id="Lk 7:25">25</verse-number>But what did you go out to see? A man dressed in soft clothing? Behold, those who are in splendid clothing and luxury are in the royal palaces. <verse-number id="Lk 7:26">26</verse-number>But what did you go out to see? A prophet? Yes, I tell you, and even more than a prophet! <verse-number id="Lk 7:27">27</verse-number>It is this man about whom it is written: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>‘Behold, I am sending my messenger before your face, </li1>
				<li1>who will prepare your way before you.’<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Mal 3:1">Mal 3:1; </cite>cf. <cite title="BibleLEB2: Mk 1:2">Mark 1:2</cite>; <cite title="BibleLEB2: Mt 11:10">Matt 11:10</cite></note> </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 7:28">28</verse-number>I tell you, there is no one greater among <supplied>those</supplied> born of women than John, but the one who is least in the kingdom of God is greater than he. <verse-number id="Lk 7:29">29</verse-number>(And all the people, <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> heard <supplied>this</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note>—even the tax collectors—affirmed the righteousness of God, <supplied>because they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had been baptized”) which is understood as causal</note> had been baptized <supplied>with</supplied> the baptism of John, <verse-number id="Lk 7:30">30</verse-number>but the Pharisees and the legal experts rejected the purpose of God for themselves, <supplied>because they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“been baptized”) which is understood as causal</note> had not been baptized by him.) </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 7:31">31</verse-number>“To what then shall I compare the people of this generation, and what are they like? <verse-number id="Lk 7:32">32</verse-number>They are like children sitting in the marketplace and calling out to one another, who say, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>‘We played the flute for you and you did not dance; </li1>
				<li1>we sang a lament and you did not weep.’ </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 7:33">33</verse-number>For John the Baptist has come not eating bread or drinking wine, and you say, ‘He has a demon!’ <verse-number id="Lk 7:34">34</verse-number>The Son of Man has come eating and drinking, and you say, ‘Behold, a man <supplied>who is</supplied> a glutton and a drunkard, a friend of tax collectors and sinners!’ <verse-number id="Lk 7:35">35</verse-number>And wisdom is vindicated by all her children.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A Sinful Woman Anoints Jesus’ Feet</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 7:36">36</verse-number>Now one of the Pharisees asked him to eat with him, and he entered into the house of the Pharisee <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“entered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> reclined at the table. <verse-number id="Lk 7:37">37</verse-number>And behold, a woman in the town who was a sinner, <supplied>when she</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“learned”) which is understood as temporal</note> learned that he was dining in the Pharisee’s house, brought an alabaster flask of perfumed oil, <verse-number id="Lk 7:38">38</verse-number>and standing behind <supplied>him</supplied> at his feet weeping, she began to wet his feet with <supplied>her</supplied> tears and was wiping <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> with the hair of her head and was kissing his feet and anointing <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> with the perfumed oil. <verse-number id="Lk 7:39">39</verse-number>Now <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> the Pharisee who invited him saw <supplied>this</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> he spoke to himself, saying, “If this man were a prophet, he would have known who and what kind of woman <supplied>this is</supplied> who is touching him, that she is a sinner.” <verse-number id="Lk 7:40">40</verse-number>And Jesus answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to him, “Simon, I have something to say to you.” And he said, “Teacher, say <supplied>it</supplied>.”<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <verse-number id="Lk 7:41">41</verse-number>“There were two debtors <supplied>who owed</supplied> a certain creditor. One owed five hundred denarii and the other fifty. <verse-number id="Lk 7:42">42</verse-number><supplied>When</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“able”)</note> they were not able to repay <supplied>him</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> he forgave <supplied>the debts</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> of both. Now which of them will love him more?” <verse-number id="Lk 7:43">43</verse-number>Simon answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “I suppose that <supplied>it is the one</supplied> to whom he forgave more.” And he said to him, “You have judged correctly.” <verse-number id="Lk 7:44">44</verse-number>And turning toward the woman, he said to Simon, “Do you see this woman? I entered into your house. You did not give me water for <supplied>my</supplied> feet, but she wet my feet with <supplied>her</supplied> tears and wiped <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> with her hair. <verse-number id="Lk 7:45">45</verse-number>You did not give me a kiss, but from the time I entered, she has not stopped kissing my feet. <verse-number id="Lk 7:46">46</verse-number>You did not anoint my head with olive oil, but she anointed my feet with perfumed oil. <verse-number id="Lk 7:47">47</verse-number><idiom-start/>For this reason<idiom-end/><note>Literally “on account of which”</note> I tell you, her sins—<supplied>which were</supplied> many—have been forgiven, for she loved much. But <supplied>the one</supplied> to whom little is forgiven loves little.” <verse-number id="Lk 7:48">48</verse-number>And he said to her, “Your sins are forgiven.” <verse-number id="Lk 7:49">49</verse-number>And those who were reclining at the table with <supplied>him</supplied> began to say among themselves, “Who is this who even forgives sins?” <verse-number id="Lk 7:50">50</verse-number>And he said to the woman, “Your faith has saved you. Go in peace.” </p>
		</chapter>