<chapter id="Lk 9">
			<pericope>The Twelve Commissioned and Sent Out</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 9:1">1</verse-number> And summoning the twelve, he gave them power and authority over all the demons and to cure diseases, <verse-number id="Lk 9:2">2</verse-number>and he sent them out to proclaim the kingdom of God and to heal the sick. <verse-number id="Lk 9:3">3</verse-number>And he said to them, “Take along nothing for the journey—neither a staff, nor a traveler’s bag, nor bread, nor money, nor to have two tunics apiece. <verse-number id="Lk 9:4">4</verse-number>And into whatever house you enter, stay there and depart from there. <verse-number id="Lk 9:5">5</verse-number>And <supplied>as for</supplied> all those who do not welcome you—<supplied>when you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“depart”) which is understood as temporal</note> depart from that town, shake off the dust from your feet for a testimony against them.” <verse-number id="Lk 9:6">6</verse-number>So they departed <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“departed”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> went throughout the villages, proclaiming the good news and healing everywhere. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Herod Perplexed About Jesus</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 9:7">7</verse-number>Now Herod the tetrarch heard about all that was happening, and he was greatly perplexed, because it was said by some that John has been raised from the dead, <verse-number id="Lk 9:8">8</verse-number>and by some that Elijah had appeared, and others that some prophet of ancient times had risen. <verse-number id="Lk 9:9">9</verse-number>And Herod said, “John I beheaded, but who is this about whom I hear such things?” And he was wanting to see him. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Feeding of Five Thousand</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 9:10">10</verse-number>And <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“returned”) which is understood as temporal</note> returned, the apostles described to him all that they had done. And he took them along <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“took … along”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> withdrew privately to a town called Bethsaida. <verse-number id="Lk 9:11">11</verse-number>But <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“found out”) which is understood as temporal</note> the crowds found out, they followed him, and welcoming them, he began to speak<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to speak”)</note> to them about the kingdom of God, and he cured those who had need of healing. <verse-number id="Lk 9:12">12</verse-number>Now the day began to be far spent, and the twelve came up <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to him, “Send away the crowd so that they can go into the surrounding villages and farms to obtain lodging and find provisions, because we are here in a desolate place. <verse-number id="Lk 9:13">13</verse-number>But he said to them, “You give them <supplied>something</supplied> to eat!” And they said, “<idiom-start/>We have no<idiom-end/><note>Literally “there is not to us”</note> more than five loaves and two fish, unless perhaps we go <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“go”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> purchase food for all these people.” <verse-number id="Lk 9:14">14</verse-number>(For there were about five thousand men.) So he said to his disciples, “Have them sit down in groups of about fifty each.” <verse-number id="Lk 9:15">15</verse-number>And they did so, and had <supplied>them</supplied> all sit down. <verse-number id="Lk 9:16">16</verse-number>And taking the five loaves and the two fish, <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied before the participle (“looking up”) in keeping with English style</note> looking up to heaven, he gave thanks and broke them and began giving<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began giving”)</note> <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to speak”)</note> to the disciples to set before the crowd. <verse-number id="Lk 9:17">17</verse-number>And <supplied>they</supplied> all ate and were satisfied, and what was left over was picked up by them—twelve baskets of broken pieces. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Peter’s Confession</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 9:18">18</verse-number>And it happened that while he was praying alone, the disciples were with him. And he asked them, saying, “Who do the crowds say <supplied>that</supplied> I am?” <verse-number id="Lk 9:19">19</verse-number>And they answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “John the Baptist, but others, Elijah, and others, that one of the ancient prophets has risen.” <verse-number id="Lk 9:20">20</verse-number>And he said to them, “But who do you say <supplied>that</supplied> I am?” And Peter answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “The Christ of God.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus Predicts His Death and Resurrection</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 9:21">21</verse-number>But he warned <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“warned”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> commanded them to tell this to no one, <verse-number id="Lk 9:22">22</verse-number>saying, “It is necessary <supplied>for</supplied> the Son of Man to suffer many <supplied>things</supplied> and to be rejected by the elders and chief priests and scribes, and to be killed, and to be raised on the third day. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Taking Up One’s Cross to Follow Jesus</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 9:23">23</verse-number>And he said to <supplied>them</supplied> all, “If anyone wants to come after me, he must deny himself and take up his cross every day and follow me. <verse-number id="Lk 9:24">24</verse-number>For whoever wants to save his life will lose it, but whoever loses his life on account of me, this person will save it. <verse-number id="Lk 9:25">25</verse-number>For what is a person benefited <supplied>if he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>if</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“gains”) which is understood as conditional</note> gains the whole world but loses or forfeits himself? <verse-number id="Lk 9:26">26</verse-number>For whoever is ashamed of me and my words, the Son of Man will be ashamed of this person when he comes in his glory and the <supplied>glory</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>glory</supplied>” is an understood repetition of the same word earlier in this verse</note> of the Father and of the holy angels. <verse-number id="Lk 9:27">27</verse-number>But I tell you truly, there are some of those standing here who will never experience death until they see the kingdom of God.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Transfiguration</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 9:28">28</verse-number>Now it happened that about eight days after these words, he took along Peter and John and James <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“took along”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> went up on the mountain to pray. <verse-number id="Lk 9:29">29</verse-number>And as he was praying, the appearance of his face became different, and his clothing <supplied>became</supplied> white, gleaming like lightning.<note>Or “became brilliant as light”; or “became dazzling white”</note> <verse-number id="Lk 9:30">30</verse-number>And behold, two men were talking with him, who were Moses and Elijah, <verse-number id="Lk 9:31">31</verse-number>who appeared in glory <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“appeared”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> were speaking <supplied>about</supplied> his departure which he was about to fulfill<note>Or “to accomplish”</note> in Jerusalem. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 9:32">32</verse-number>Now Peter and those with him were <idiom-start/>very sleepy<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “burdened with sleep”</note> but <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“became fully awake”) which is understood as temporal</note> became fully awake, they saw his glory and the two men who were standing with him. <verse-number id="Lk 9:33">33</verse-number>And it happened that as they were going away from him, Peter said to Jesus, “Master, it is good <supplied>for</supplied> us to be here. And let us make three shelters, one for you and one for Moses and one for Elijah,” not knowing what he was saying. <verse-number id="Lk 9:34">34</verse-number>And <supplied>while</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“saying”)</note> he was saying these <supplied>things</supplied>, a cloud came and overshadowed them, and they were afraid as they entered into the cloud. <verse-number id="Lk 9:35">35</verse-number>And a voice came from the cloud, saying, “This is my Son, <supplied>my</supplied> Chosen One. Listen to him!” <verse-number id="Lk 9:36">36</verse-number>And after the voice had occurred, Jesus was found alone. And they kept silent and told no one in those days anything of what they had seen. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A Demon-possessed Boy Healed</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 9:37">37</verse-number>Now it happened that on the next day, <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“had come down”)</note> they had come down from the mountain, a large crowd met him. <verse-number id="Lk 9:38">38</verse-number>And behold, a man from the crowd cried out, saying, “Teacher, I beg you to look with concern on my son, because he is my only <supplied>son</supplied>! <verse-number id="Lk 9:39">39</verse-number>And behold, a spirit seizes him and suddenly he screams, and it convulses him with foam and rarely withdraws from him, battering him severely. <verse-number id="Lk 9:40">40</verse-number>And I begged your disciples that they would expel it, and they were not able <supplied>to do so</supplied>.” <verse-number id="Lk 9:41">41</verse-number>So Jesus answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “O unbelieving and perverted generation! <idiom-start/>How long<idiom-end/><note>Literally “until when”</note> will I be with you and put up with you? Bring your son here!” <verse-number id="Lk 9:42">42</verse-number>And <supplied>while</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“approaching”)</note> he was still approaching, the demon threw him down and convulsed <supplied>him</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> But Jesus rebuked the unclean spirit and healed the boy, and gave him back to his father. <verse-number id="Lk 9:43">43</verse-number>And they were all astounded at the impressiveness of God. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus Predicts His Suffering</pericope>
			<p>But <supplied>while they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“marveling”)</note> were all marveling at all <supplied>the things</supplied> that he was doing, he said to his disciples, <verse-number id="Lk 9:44">44</verse-number>“<idiom-start/>You take these words to heart<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “you put these words into your ears”</note> for the Son of Man is about to be betrayed into the hands of men.” <verse-number id="Lk 9:45">45</verse-number>But they did not understand this statement, and it was concealed from them so that they could not understand it. And they were afraid to ask him about this statement. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Question About Who Is Greatest</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 9:46">46</verse-number>And an argument developed among them as to who of them might be greatest. <verse-number id="Lk 9:47">47</verse-number>But Jesus, <supplied>because he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“knew”) which is understood as causal</note> knew the thoughts of their hearts, took hold of a child and had him stand beside him <verse-number id="Lk 9:48">48</verse-number>and said to them, “Whoever welcomes this child in my name welcomes me, and whoever welcomes me welcomes the one who sent me. For the one who is least among you all—this one is great.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Whoever Is Not Against Us Is for Us</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 9:49">49</verse-number>And John answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “Master, we saw someone expelling demons in your name, and we tried to prevent him, because he does not follow in company with us.” <verse-number id="Lk 9:50">50</verse-number>But Jesus said to him, “Do not prevent <supplied>him</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> because whoever is not against you is for you.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus Rejected in a Samaritan Village</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 9:51">51</verse-number>Now it happened that when the days were approaching <idiom-start/>for him to be taken up<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “of his taking up”</note> he set <supplied>his</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> face to go to Jerusalem. <verse-number id="Lk 9:52">52</verse-number>And he sent messengers before <idiom-start/>him<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “his face”</note> and they went <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> entered into a village of the Samaritans in order to prepare for him. <verse-number id="Lk 9:53">53</verse-number>And they did not welcome him because <idiom-start/>he was determined to go<idiom-end/><note>Literally “his face was going”</note> to Jerusalem. <verse-number id="Lk 9:54">54</verse-number>Now <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> the disciples James and John saw <supplied>it</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> they said, “Lord, do you want us to call fire to come down from heaven and consume them?” <verse-number id="Lk 9:55">55</verse-number>But he turned around <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“turned around”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> rebuked them, <verse-number id="Lk 9:56">56</verse-number>and they proceeded to another village. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Would-be Followers</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 9:57">57</verse-number>And <supplied>as</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“were going”)</note> they were traveling on the road, someone said to him, “I will follow you wherever you go!” <verse-number id="Lk 9:58">58</verse-number>And Jesus said to him, “Foxes have dens and birds of the sky <supplied>have</supplied> nests, but the Son of Man has no place to lay <supplied>his</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> head.” <verse-number id="Lk 9:59">59</verse-number>And he said to another, “Follow me!” But he said, “Lord, first allow me to go <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“go”) has been translated as an infinitive</note> bury my father.” <verse-number id="Lk 9:60">60</verse-number>But he said to him, “Leave the dead to bury their own dead! But you go <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“go”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> proclaim the kingdom of God.” <verse-number id="Lk 9:61">61</verse-number>And another <supplied>person</supplied> also said, “I will follow you, Lord, but first allow me to say farewell to those in my house.” <verse-number id="Lk 9:62">62</verse-number>But Jesus said,<note>Some manuscripts have “said to him”</note> “No one who puts <supplied>his</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> hand on the plow and looks back is fit for the kingdom of God!” </p>
		</chapter>