<chapter id="Lk 11">
			<pericope>How to Pray</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 11:1">1</verse-number> And it happened that while he was in a certain place praying, when he stopped a certain one of his disciples said to him, “Lord, teach us to pray, just as John also taught his disciples.” <verse-number id="Lk 11:2">2</verse-number>And he said to them, “When you pray, say, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Father, </li1>
				<li1>may your name be treated as holy. </li1>
				<li1>May your kingdom come. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Lk 11:3">3</verse-number>Give us each day our daily bread. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Lk 11:4">4</verse-number>And forgive us our sins, </li1>
				<li2>for we ourselves also forgive everyone who is indebted to us. </li2>
				<li1>And do not lead us into temptation.” </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Ask, Seek, Knock</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 11:5">5</verse-number>And he said to them, “Who of you will have a friend, and will go to him at midnight and say to him, ‘Friend, lend me three loaves, <verse-number id="Lk 11:6">6</verse-number>because a friend of mine has come to me on a journey, and I do not have anything to set before him.’ <verse-number id="Lk 11:7">7</verse-number>And that one will answer from inside <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“will answer”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> say, ‘Do not cause me trouble! The door has already been shut and my children are with me in bed! I am not able to get up to give you <supplied>anything</supplied>.’<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <verse-number id="Lk 11:8">8</verse-number>I tell you, even if he does not give him <supplied>anything</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <supplied>after he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“gets up”) which is understood as temporal</note> gets up because <supplied>he</supplied> is his friend, at any rate because of his impudence<note>Or “shamelessness”; some translate as “persistence” based on the context, though this is not the normal meaning of the word</note> he will get up <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“will get up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> give him whatever he needs. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 11:9">9</verse-number>And I tell you, ask and it will be given to you; seek and you will find; knock and it will be opened for you. <verse-number id="Lk 11:10">10</verse-number>For everyone who asks receives, and the one who seeks finds, and to the one who knocks it will be opened. <verse-number id="Lk 11:11">11</verse-number>But what father from among you, <supplied>if his</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> son will ask for a fish, instead of a fish will give him a snake? <verse-number id="Lk 11:12">12</verse-number>Or also, <supplied>if</supplied> he will ask for an egg, will give him a scorpion? <verse-number id="Lk 11:13">13</verse-number>Therefore if you, <supplied>although you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>although</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“are”) which is understood as concessive</note> are evil, know how to give good gifts to your children, how much more will the Father from heaven give the Holy Spirit to those who ask him?” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A House Divided Cannot Stand</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 11:14">14</verse-number>And he was expelling a mute demon.<note>Some manuscripts have “a demon, and it was mute”</note> Now it happened that <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“came out”)</note> the demon came out, the man who had been mute spoke, and the crowds were astonished. <verse-number id="Lk 11:15">15</verse-number>But some of them said, “By Beelzebul the ruler of demons he expels demons!” <verse-number id="Lk 11:16">16</verse-number>And others, <supplied>in order to</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>in order to</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“test”) which is understood as purpose</note> test <supplied>him</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> were demanding from him a sign from heaven. <verse-number id="Lk 11:17">17</verse-number>But he, knowing their thoughts, said to them, “Every kingdom divided against itself is laid waste, and <idiom-start/>a divided household<idiom-end/><note>Literally “house against house”</note> falls. <verse-number id="Lk 11:18">18</verse-number>So if Satan also is divided against himself, how will his kingdom stand? For you say <supplied>that</supplied> I expel demons by Beelzebul. <verse-number id="Lk 11:19">19</verse-number>But if I expel demons by Beelzebul, by whom do your sons expel <supplied>them</supplied>?<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> For this <supplied>reason</supplied> they will be your judges! <verse-number id="Lk 11:20">20</verse-number>But if I expel demons by the finger of God, then the kingdom of God has come upon you! <verse-number id="Lk 11:21">21</verse-number>When a strong man, fully armed, guards his own palace, his possessions are <idiom-start/>safe<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “in peace”</note> <verse-number id="Lk 11:22">22</verse-number>But when a stronger man attacks him <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“attacks”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> conquers him, he takes away his full armor in which he trusted and distributes his plunder. <verse-number id="Lk 11:23">23</verse-number>The one who is not with me is against me, and the one who does not gather with me scatters. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>An Unclean Spirit Returns</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 11:24">24</verse-number>“Whenever an unclean spirit has gone out of a person, it travels through waterless places searching for rest, and does not find <supplied>it</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> It says,<note>Some manuscripts have “Then it says”</note> ‘I will return to my house from which I came out.’ <verse-number id="Lk 11:25">25</verse-number>And <supplied>when it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“arrives”) which is understood as temporal</note> arrives it finds <supplied>the house</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> swept and put in order. <verse-number id="Lk 11:26">26</verse-number>Then it goes and brings along seven other spirits more evil than itself, and <supplied>they</supplied> go in <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“go in”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> live there. And the last <supplied>state</supplied> of that person becomes worse than the first!” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 11:27">27</verse-number>Now it happened that as he said these <supplied>things</supplied>, a certain woman from the crowd raised <supplied>her</supplied> voice <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“raised”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to him, “Blessed <supplied>is</supplied> the womb that bore you, and <supplied>the</supplied> breasts <supplied>at</supplied> which you nursed!” <verse-number id="Lk 11:28">28</verse-number>But he said, “On the contrary, blessed <supplied>are</supplied> those who hear the word of God and follow <supplied>it</supplied>!”<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Sign of Jonah</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 11:29">29</verse-number>And <supplied>as</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“were increasing”)</note> the crowds were increasing, he began to say, “This generation is an evil generation! It demands a sign, and no sign will be given to it except the sign of Jonah! <verse-number id="Lk 11:30">30</verse-number>For just as Jonah became a sign to the Ninevites, so also the Son of Man will be to this generation. <verse-number id="Lk 11:31">31</verse-number>The queen of the south will rise up at the judgment with the people of this generation and condemn them, because she came from the ends of the earth to hear the wisdom of Solomon, and behold, <supplied>something</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “something” is supplied in the translation because the adjective is neuter gender</note> greater than Solomon <supplied>is</supplied> here! <verse-number id="Lk 11:32">32</verse-number>The people of Nineveh will stand up at the judgment with this generation and condemn it, because they repented at the proclamation of Jonah, and behold, <supplied>something</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “something” is supplied in the translation because the adjective is neuter gender</note> greater than Jonah <supplied>is</supplied> here! </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Light and Darkness</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 11:33">33</verse-number>“No one <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“lighting”) which is understood as temporal</note> lighting a lamp puts <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> in a cellar or under a bushel basket, but on a lampstand, so that those who come in can see the light. <verse-number id="Lk 11:34">34</verse-number>Your eye is the lamp of the body. When your eye is sincere, your whole body is full of light also. But when it is evil, your body <supplied>is</supplied> dark also. <verse-number id="Lk 11:35">35</verse-number>Therefore pay careful attention <supplied>that</supplied> the light in you is not darkness! <verse-number id="Lk 11:36">36</verse-number>If therefore your whole body <supplied>is</supplied> full of light, not having any part dark, it will be completely full of light, as when the lamp with <supplied>its</supplied> light gives light to you.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Pharisees and Legal Experts Denounced</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 11:37">37</verse-number>And as he was speaking, a Pharisee asked him <idiom-start/>to have a meal<idiom-end/><note>Literally “that he would have a meal”</note> with him, and he went in <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went in”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> reclined at table. <verse-number id="Lk 11:38">38</verse-number>And the Pharisee, <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> saw <supplied>it</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> was astonished that he did not first wash before the meal. <verse-number id="Lk 11:39">39</verse-number>But the Lord said to him, “Now you Pharisees cleanse the outside of the cup and of the dish, but your inside is full of greediness and wickedness. <verse-number id="Lk 11:40">40</verse-number>Fools! Did not the one who made the outside make the inside also? <verse-number id="Lk 11:41">41</verse-number>But give <supplied>as</supplied> charitable giving the things that are within, and behold, everything is clean for you. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 11:42">42</verse-number>“But woe to you, Pharisees, because you pay a tenth of mint and rue and every garden herb, and neglect justice and love for God! But it was necessary to do these <supplied>things</supplied> without neglecting those things also. <verse-number id="Lk 11:43">43</verse-number>Woe to you, Pharisees, because you love the best seat in the synagogues and the greetings in the marketplaces! <verse-number id="Lk 11:44">44</verse-number>Woe to you, because you are like unmarked graves, and the people who walk over <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> do not know <supplied>it</supplied>!<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 11:45">45</verse-number>And one of the legal experts answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to him, “Teacher, <supplied>when you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“say”) which is understood as temporal</note> say these <supplied>things</supplied>, you insult us also!” <verse-number id="Lk 11:46">46</verse-number>So he said, “Woe to you also, legal experts, because you load people <supplied>with</supplied> burdens hard to bear, and <supplied>you</supplied> yourselves do not touch the burdens with one of your fingers! <verse-number id="Lk 11:47">47</verse-number>Woe to you, because you build the tombs of the prophets, and your fathers killed them! <verse-number id="Lk 11:48">48</verse-number>As a result you are witnesses, and you approve of the deeds of your fathers, because they killed them and you build <supplied>their tombs</supplied>!<note>A large number of later manuscripts add the words “their tombs” here, with variations of wording; although the words are not likely to be original, it is necessary to supply them in keeping with English style</note> <verse-number id="Lk 11:49">49</verse-number>For this <supplied>reason</supplied> also the wisdom of God said, ‘I will send to them prophets and apostles, and <supplied>some</supplied> of them they will kill and persecute,’ <verse-number id="Lk 11:50">50</verse-number>so that the blood of all the prophets that has been shed from the foundation of the world may be required of this generation, <verse-number id="Lk 11:51">51</verse-number>from the blood of Abel to the blood of Zechariah, who perished between the altar and the temple building.<note>Literally “the house,” here a reference to the temple</note> Yes, I tell you, it will be required of this generation! <verse-number id="Lk 11:52">52</verse-number>Woe to you, legal experts, because you have taken away the key to knowledge! You did not enter yourselves, and you hindered those who were entering!” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 11:53">53</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“departed”)</note> he departed from there, the scribes and the Pharisees began to be terribly hostile, and to question him closely about many <supplied>things</supplied>, <verse-number id="Lk 11:54">54</verse-number>plotting to catch him with reference to something <idiom-start/>he might say<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “from his mouth”</note> </p>
		</chapter>