<chapter id="Lk 12">
			<pericope>Warning Against Hypocrisy</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 12:1">1</verse-number> During <idiom-start/>this time<idiom-end/><note>Literally “which time”</note> <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“had gathered together”)</note> a crowd of many thousands had gathered together, so that they were trampling one another, he began to say to his disciples first, “Beware for yourselves of the leaven of the Pharisees, which is hypocrisy. <verse-number id="Lk 12:2">2</verse-number>But nothing is concealed that will not be revealed, and secret that will not be made known. <verse-number id="Lk 12:3">3</verse-number>Therefore everything that you have said in the dark will be heard in the light, and what <idiom-start/>you have whispered<idiom-end/><note>Literally “you have spoken to the ear”</note> in the inner rooms will be proclaimed on the housetops. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Fear God Rather Than People</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 12:4">4</verse-number>“And I tell you, my friends, do not be afraid of those who kill the body, and after these <supplied>things</supplied> do not have anything more to do. <verse-number id="Lk 12:5">5</verse-number>But I will show you whom you should fear: fear the one who has authority, after the killing, to throw <supplied>you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> into hell! Yes, I tell you, fear this one! <verse-number id="Lk 12:6">6</verse-number>Are not five sparrows sold for two pennies? And not one of them is forgotten in the sight of God. <verse-number id="Lk 12:7">7</verse-number>But even the hairs of your head are all numbered! Do not be afraid; you are worth more than many sparrows. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Acknowledgement of Christ and Persecution of Disciples</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 12:8">8</verse-number>“And I tell you, everyone who acknowledges me before people, the Son of Man also will acknowledge him before the angels of God, <verse-number id="Lk 12:9">9</verse-number>but the one who denies me before people will be denied before the angels of God. <verse-number id="Lk 12:10">10</verse-number>And everyone who speaks a word against the Son of Man, it will be forgiven him, but to the one who blasphemes against the Holy Spirit, it will not be forgiven. <verse-number id="Lk 12:11">11</verse-number>But when they bring you before the synagogues and the rulers and the authorities, do not be anxious how or what you should speak in your own defense or what you should say, <verse-number id="Lk 12:12">12</verse-number>for the Holy Spirit will teach you in <supplied>that</supplied> same hour what it is necessary to say.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Parable of the Rich Landowner Who Was a Fool</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 12:13">13</verse-number>Now someone from the crowd said to him, “Teacher, tell my brother to divide the inheritance with me!” <verse-number id="Lk 12:14">14</verse-number>But he said to him, “Man, who made me a judge or an arbitrator over you?” <verse-number id="Lk 12:15">15</verse-number>And he said to them, “Watch out and guard yourselves from all greediness, because not <supplied>even</supplied> when someone has an abundance <idiom-start/>does<idiom-end/><note>Literally “is”</note> his life <supplied>consist</supplied> of his possessions.” <verse-number id="Lk 12:16">16</verse-number>And he told a parable to them, saying, “The land of a certain rich man yielded an abundant harvest. <verse-number id="Lk 12:17">17</verse-number>And he reasoned to himself, saying, ‘What should I do? For I do not have anywhere I can gather in my crops.’ <verse-number id="Lk 12:18">18</verse-number>And he said, ‘I will do this: I will tear down my barns and build larger ones, and I will gather in there all my grain and possessions. <verse-number id="Lk 12:19">19</verse-number>And I will say to my soul, “Soul, you have many possessions stored up for many years. Relax, eat, drink, celebrate!” ’ <verse-number id="Lk 12:20">20</verse-number>But God said to him, ‘Fool! This night your life<note>The same Greek word can be translated “soul” or “life” depending on the context</note> is demanded from you, and <supplied>the things</supplied> which you have prepared—whose will they be?’ <verse-number id="Lk 12:21">21</verse-number>So <supplied>is</supplied> the one who stores up treasure for himself, and who is not rich toward God!” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Anxiety</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 12:22">22</verse-number>And he said to his disciples, “For this <supplied>reason</supplied> I tell you, do not be anxious for <supplied>your</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> life, what you will eat, or for <supplied>your</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> body, what you will wear. <verse-number id="Lk 12:23">23</verse-number>For life is more than food, and the body <supplied>more than</supplied> clothing. <verse-number id="Lk 12:24">24</verse-number>Consider the ravens, that they neither sow nor reap; to them there is neither storeroom nor barn, and God feeds them. How much more are you worth than the birds? <verse-number id="Lk 12:25">25</verse-number>And which of you <supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“being anxious”) which is understood as means</note> being anxious is able to add an hour<note>Or “a cubit” (the literal meaning); most scholars understand this to refer figuratively to an “hour” of life here, though some take it as a literal measurement of height</note> to his life span? <verse-number id="Lk 12:26">26</verse-number>If then you are not even able <supplied>to do</supplied> a very little thing, why are you anxious about the rest? <verse-number id="Lk 12:27">27</verse-number>Consider the lilies, how they grow: they do not toil or spin, but I say to you, not even Solomon in all his glory was dressed like one of these. <verse-number id="Lk 12:28">28</verse-number>But if God clothes the grass in the field in this way, <supplied>although it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>although</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“is”) which is understood as concessive</note> is <supplied>here</supplied> today and tomorrow is thrown into the oven, how much more <supplied>will he do so for</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The phrase “<supplied>will he do so for</supplied>” is not in the Greek text but is implied</note> you, you of little faith? <verse-number id="Lk 12:29">29</verse-number>And you, do not consider what you will eat and what you will drink, and do not be anxious. <verse-number id="Lk 12:30">30</verse-number>For all the nations of the world seek after these <supplied>things</supplied>, and your Father knows that you need these <supplied>things</supplied>. <verse-number id="Lk 12:31">31</verse-number>But seek his kingdom and these <supplied>things</supplied> will be added to you. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 12:32">32</verse-number>“Do not be afraid, little flock, because your Father is well pleased to give you the kingdom. <verse-number id="Lk 12:33">33</verse-number>Sell your possessions and give charitable gifts. Make for yourselves money bags that do not wear out, an inexhaustible treasure in heaven<note>Or “in the heavens”</note> where thief does not approach or moth destroy. <verse-number id="Lk 12:34">34</verse-number>For where your treasure is, there your heart will be also. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>On the Alert for the Master’s Return</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 12:35">35</verse-number>“<idiom-start/>You must be prepared for action<idiom-end/><note>Literally “your loins must be girded”</note> and <supplied>your</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> lamps burning. <verse-number id="Lk 12:36">36</verse-number>And you, <supplied>be</supplied> like people who are waiting for their master when he returns from the wedding feast,<note>Or perhaps simply “feast”</note> so that <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“comes back”)</note> comes back and knocks, they can open <supplied>the door</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> for him immediately. <verse-number id="Lk 12:37">37</verse-number>Blessed <supplied>are</supplied> those slaves whom the master will find on the alert <supplied>when he</supplied> returns! Truly I say to you that he will dress himself for service and have them recline at the table and will come by <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“will come by”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> serve them. <verse-number id="Lk 12:38">38</verse-number>Even if he should come back in the second or in the third watch of the night and find <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> like this, blessed are they! <verse-number id="Lk 12:39">39</verse-number>But understand this, that if the master of the house had known what hour the thief was coming, he would not have left his house to be broken into. <verse-number id="Lk 12:40">40</verse-number>You also must be ready, because the Son of Man is coming at an hour that you do not think <supplied>he will come</supplied>.”<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The words “<supplied>he will come</supplied>” are not in the Greek text but are implied</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A Faithful Slave and an Unfaithful Slave</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 12:41">41</verse-number>And Peter said, “Lord, are you telling this parable for us, or also for everyone?” <verse-number id="Lk 12:42">42</verse-number>And the Lord said, “Who then is the faithful wise manager whom the master will put in charge over his servants to give <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <supplied>their</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> food allowance at the right time? <verse-number id="Lk 12:43">43</verse-number>Blessed <supplied>is</supplied> that slave whom his master will find so doing <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“comes back”) which is understood as temporal</note> comes back. <verse-number id="Lk 12:44">44</verse-number>Truly I say to you that he will put him in charge of all his possessions. <verse-number id="Lk 12:45">45</verse-number>But if that slave should say <idiom-start/>to himself<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “in his heart”</note> ‘My master is taking a long time to return,’ and he begins to beat the male slaves and the female slaves and to eat and drink and get drunk, <verse-number id="Lk 12:46">46</verse-number>the master of that slave will come on a day that he does not expect and at an hour that he does not know, and will cut him in two and assign his place with the unbelievers. <verse-number id="Lk 12:47">47</verse-number>And that slave who knew the will of his master and did not prepare or do according to his will <idiom-start/>will be given a severe beating<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “will be beaten much”</note> <verse-number id="Lk 12:48">48</verse-number>But the one who did not know and did <supplied>things</supplied> deserving blows <idiom-start/>will be given a light beating<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “will be beaten a few times”</note> And from everyone to whom much has been given, much will be demanded, and from him to whom they entrusted much, they will ask him <supplied>for</supplied> even more. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Not Peace, But a Sword of Divisiveness</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 12:49">49</verse-number>“I have come to bring fire on the earth, and how I wish that it had been kindled already! <verse-number id="Lk 12:50">50</verse-number>But I have a baptism to be baptized with, and how I am distressed until it is accomplished! <verse-number id="Lk 12:51">51</verse-number>Do you think that I have come to grant peace on the earth? No, I tell you, but rather division! <verse-number id="Lk 12:52">52</verse-number>For from now on there will be five in one household, divided three against two and two against three. <verse-number id="Lk 12:53">53</verse-number>They will be divided, father against son and son against father, mother against daughter and daughter against mother, mother-in-law against her daughter-in-law and daughter-in-law against mother-in-law.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Signs of the Times</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 12:54">54</verse-number>And he also said to the crowds, “When you see a cloud coming up in the west, you say at once, ‘A rainstorm is coming,’ and so it happens. <verse-number id="Lk 12:55">55</verse-number>And when <supplied>you see</supplied> the south wind blowing, you say, ‘There will be burning heat,’ and it happens. <verse-number id="Lk 12:56">56</verse-number>Hypocrites! You know how to evaluate the appearance of the earth and the sky, but how <supplied>is it</supplied> you do not know how to evaluate this present time? </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Settle Accounts Quickly</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 12:57">57</verse-number>And why do you not also judge for yourselves <supplied>what is</supplied> right? <verse-number id="Lk 12:58">58</verse-number>For as you are going with your accuser before the magistrate, make an effort to come to a settlement with him on the way, so that he will not drag you to the judge, and the judge will hand you over to the bailiff, and the bailiff will throw you into prison. <verse-number id="Lk 12:59">59</verse-number>I tell you, you will never get out of there until you have paid back even the last cent!”<note>Literally “lepton,” a small copper coin worth 1/128 of a denarius</note> </p>
		</chapter>