<chapter id="Lk 14">
			<pericope>A Man Suffering from Edema Healed</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 14:1">1</verse-number> And it happened that when he came to the house of a certain one of the leaders of the Pharisees on a Sabbath to eat <idiom-start/>a meal<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “bread”</note> they were watching him closely. <verse-number id="Lk 14:2">2</verse-number>And behold, a certain man was in front of him, suffering from edema. <verse-number id="Lk 14:3">3</verse-number>And Jesus answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to the legal experts and Pharisees, saying, “Is it permitted to heal on the Sabbath, or not?” <verse-number id="Lk 14:4">4</verse-number>But they remained silent. And he took hold of <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“took hold of”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> healed him, and sent <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> away. <verse-number id="Lk 14:5">5</verse-number>And he said to them, “Who among you, <supplied>if your</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The words “<supplied>if your</supplied>” are not in the Greek text but are implied</note> son or <supplied>your</supplied> ox falls into a well<note>Or “cistern”</note> on the day of the Sabbath, will not immediately pull him out?” <verse-number id="Lk 14:6">6</verse-number>And they were not able to make a reply to these <supplied>things</supplied>. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Parable of the Guests at the Wedding Feast</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 14:7">7</verse-number>Now he told a parable to those who had been invited <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“noticed”) which is understood as temporal</note> noticed how they were choosing for themselves the places of honor, saying to them, <verse-number id="Lk 14:8">8</verse-number>“When you are invited by someone to a wedding feast,<note>Or perhaps simply “a feast”</note> do not recline at the table in the place of honor, lest <supplied>someone</supplied> more distinguished than you has been invited by him, <verse-number id="Lk 14:9">9</verse-number>and the one who invited you <idiom-start/>both<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and him”</note> will come <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“will come”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> say to you, ‘Give the place to this person,’ and then with shame you will begin to take the last place. <verse-number id="Lk 14:10">10</verse-number>But when you are invited, go <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“go”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> recline at the table in the last place, so that when the one who invited you comes, he will say to you, ‘Friend, move up higher.’ Then it will be an honor to you in the presence of all those who are reclining at the table with you. <verse-number id="Lk 14:11">11</verse-number>For everyone who exalts himself will be humbled, and the one who humbles himself will be exalted.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Parable of the Great Banquet</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 14:12">12</verse-number>And he also said to the one who had invited him, “When you give a dinner or a banquet, do not invite your friends or your brothers or your relatives or wealthy neighbors, lest they also invite you <supplied>in return</supplied>, and repayment come to you. <verse-number id="Lk 14:13">13</verse-number>But whenever you give a banquet, invite the poor, the crippled, the lame, the blind, <verse-number id="Lk 14:14">14</verse-number>and you will be blessed, because they are not able to repay you. For it will be paid back to you at the resurrection of the righteous.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 14:15">15</verse-number>Now <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> one of those reclining at the table with <supplied>him</supplied> heard these <supplied>things</supplied>, he said to him, “Blessed <supplied>is</supplied> <idiom-start/>everyone who<idiom-end/><note>Literally “whoever”</note> will eat bread in the kingdom of God!” <verse-number id="Lk 14:16">16</verse-number>But he said to him, “A certain man was giving a large banquet and invited many. <verse-number id="Lk 14:17">17</verse-number>And he sent his slave at the hour of the banquet to say to those who have been invited, ‘Come, because now it is ready!’ <verse-number id="Lk 14:18">18</verse-number>And they all <idiom-start/>alike<idiom-end/><note>Literally “by one”</note> began to excuse themselves. The first said to him, ‘I have purchased a field, and <idiom-start/>I must<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I have necessity”</note> go out to look at it. I ask you, consider me excused.’ <verse-number id="Lk 14:19">19</verse-number>And another said, ‘I have purchased five yoke of oxen, and I am going to examine them. I ask you, consider me excused.’ <verse-number id="Lk 14:20">20</verse-number>And another said, ‘I have married a wife, and for this <supplied>reason</supplied> I am not able to come.’ <verse-number id="Lk 14:21">21</verse-number>And the slave came <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> reported these <supplied>things</supplied> to his master. Then the master of the house became angry <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“became angry”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to his slave, ‘Go out quickly into the streets and alleys of the city and bring in here the poor and crippled and blind and lame!’ <verse-number id="Lk 14:22">22</verse-number>And the slave said, ‘Sir, what you ordered has been done, and there is still room.’ <verse-number id="Lk 14:23">23</verse-number>And the master said to the slave, ‘Go out into the highways and hedges and press <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to come in, so that my house will be filled! <verse-number id="Lk 14:24">24</verse-number>For I say to you that none of those persons who were invited will taste my banquet!’ ” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Cost of Discipleship</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 14:25">25</verse-number>Now large crowds were going along with him, and he turned around <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“turned around”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to them, <verse-number id="Lk 14:26">26</verse-number>“If anyone comes to me and does not hate his own father and mother and wife and children and brothers and sisters, and furthermore, even his own life, <idiom-start/>he cannot be<idiom-end/><note>Literally “he is not able to be”</note> my disciple. <verse-number id="Lk 14:27">27</verse-number>Whoever does not carry his own cross and <idiom-start/>follow<idiom-end/><note>Literally “come after”</note> me <idiom-start/>cannot be<idiom-end/><note>Literally “is not able to be”</note> my disciple. <verse-number id="Lk 14:28">28</verse-number>For which of you, wanting to build a tower, does not first sit down <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“sit down”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> calculate the cost <supplied>to see</supplied> if he has <supplied>enough</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <idiom-start/>to complete it<idiom-end/>?<note>Literally “for completion”</note> <verse-number id="Lk 14:29">29</verse-number><idiom-start/>Otherwise<idiom-end/><note>Literally “so that lest”</note> <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“has laid”)</note> he has laid the foundation and is not able to finish <supplied>it</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> all who see <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> will begin to ridicule him, <verse-number id="Lk 14:30">30</verse-number>saying, ‘This man began to build and was not able to finish!’ <verse-number id="Lk 14:31">31</verse-number>Or what king, going out to engage another king in battle, does not sit down first <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“sit down”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> deliberate whether he is able with ten thousand to oppose the one coming against him with twenty thousand. <verse-number id="Lk 14:32">32</verse-number>But if not, <supplied>while</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“is”)</note> <supplied>the other</supplied> is still far away, he sends an ambassador <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“asks”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> asks <idiom-start/>for terms of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the things with reference to”</note> peace. <verse-number id="Lk 14:33">33</verse-number>In the <supplied>same</supplied> way, therefore, every <supplied>one</supplied> of you who does not renounce all his own possessions <idiom-start/>cannot be<idiom-end/><note>Literally “is not able to be”</note> my disciple. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 14:34">34</verse-number>“Now salt <supplied>is</supplied> good, but if salt becomes tasteless, with what will it be made salty? <verse-number id="Lk 14:35">35</verse-number>It is usable neither for the soil nor for the manure pile; they throw it out. The one who has ears to hear, let him hear!” </p>
		</chapter>