<chapter id="Lk 15">
			<pericope>The Parable of the Lost Sheep</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 15:1">1</verse-number> Now all the tax collectors and the sinners were drawing near to hear him. <verse-number id="Lk 15:2">2</verse-number>And both the Pharisees and the scribes were complaining, saying, “This man welcomes sinners and eats with them!” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 15:3">3</verse-number>So he told them this parable, saying, <verse-number id="Lk 15:4">4</verse-number>“What man of you, having a hundred sheep and losing one of them, does not leave the ninety-nine in the grassland and go after the one that was lost until he finds it? <verse-number id="Lk 15:5">5</verse-number>And <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“has found”) which is understood as temporal</note> has found <supplied>it</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> he places <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> on his shoulders, rejoicing. <verse-number id="Lk 15:6">6</verse-number>And <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“returns”) which is understood as temporal</note> returns to <supplied>his</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> home, he calls together <supplied>his</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> friends and neighbors, saying to them, ‘Rejoice with me, because I have found my sheep that was lost!’ <verse-number id="Lk 15:7">7</verse-number>I tell you that in the <supplied>same</supplied> way, there will be more joy in heaven over one sinner who repents than over ninety-nine righteous people who have no need of repentance. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Parable of the Lost Coin</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 15:8">8</verse-number>Or what woman who has ten drachmas, if she loses one drachma, does not light a lamp and sweep the house and search carefully until she finds <supplied>it</supplied>?<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <verse-number id="Lk 15:9">9</verse-number>And <supplied>when she</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“has found”) which is understood as temporal</note> has found <supplied>it</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> she calls together <supplied>her</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> friends and neighbors, saying, ‘Rejoice with me, because I have found the drachma that I had lost!’ <verse-number id="Lk 15:10">10</verse-number>In the <supplied>same</supplied> way, I tell you, there is joy in the presence of the angels of God over one sinner who repents.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Parable of the Lost Son</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 15:11">11</verse-number>And he said, “A certain man had two sons. <verse-number id="Lk 15:12">12</verse-number>And the younger of them said to <supplied>his</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> father, ‘Father, give me the share of the property that is coming to <supplied>me</supplied>.’ So he divided <supplied>his</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> assets between them. <verse-number id="Lk 15:13">13</verse-number>And after not many days, the younger son gathered everything <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“gathered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> went on a journey to a distant country, and there he squandered his wealth <supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the adverbial participle of manner (“living”)</note> living wastefully. <verse-number id="Lk 15:14">14</verse-number>And <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“had spent”)</note> he had spent everything, there was a severe famine throughout that country, and he began to be in need. <verse-number id="Lk 15:15">15</verse-number>And he went <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> hired himself out to one of the citizens of that country, and he sent him into his fields to tend pigs. <verse-number id="Lk 15:16">16</verse-number>And he was longing to fill his stomach with<note>Some manuscripts have “to stuff himself with”</note> the carob pods that the pigs were eating, and no one was giving <supplied>anything</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to him. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 15:17">17</verse-number>“But <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“came”) which is understood as temporal</note> came to himself, he said, ‘How many of my father’s hired workers have an abundance <idiom-start/>of food<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “of bread”</note> and I am dying here from hunger! <verse-number id="Lk 15:18">18</verse-number>I will set out <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“set out”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> go to my father and will say to him, ‘Father, I have sinned against heaven and <idiom-start/>in your sight<idiom-end/>!<note>Literally “in the sight of you”</note> <verse-number id="Lk 15:19">19</verse-number>I am no longer worthy to be called your son! Make me like one of your hired workers.’ <verse-number id="Lk 15:20">20</verse-number>And he set out <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“set out”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> came to his own father. But <supplied>while</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“away”)</note> he was still a long way away, his father saw him and had compassion, and ran <idiom-start/>and embraced him<idiom-end/><note>Literally “fell on his neck”</note> and kissed him. <verse-number id="Lk 15:21">21</verse-number>And <supplied>his</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> son said to him, ‘Father, I have sinned against heaven and <idiom-start/>in your sight<idiom-end/>!<note>Literally “in the sight of you”</note> I am no longer worthy to be called your son!’ <verse-number id="Lk 15:22">22</verse-number>But <supplied>his</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> father said to his slaves, ‘Quickly bring out the best robe and put <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> on him, and put a ring on his finger<note>Literally “hand,” but this is a metonymy of whole (“hand”) for part (“finger”)</note> and sandals on <supplied>his</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> feet! <verse-number id="Lk 15:23">23</verse-number>And bring the fattened calf—kill <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and let us eat <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“eat”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> celebrate, <verse-number id="Lk 15:24">24</verse-number>because this son of mine was dead, and is alive again! He was lost and is found!’ And they began to celebrate. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 15:25">25</verse-number>“Now his older son was in the field, and when he came <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> approached the house, he heard music and dancing. <verse-number id="Lk 15:26">26</verse-number>And he summoned one of the slaves <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“summoned”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> asked what these <supplied>things</supplied> meant. <verse-number id="Lk 15:27">27</verse-number>And he said to him, ‘Your brother has come, and your father has killed the fattened calf because he has gotten him back healthy.’ <verse-number id="Lk 15:28">28</verse-number>But he became angry and did not want to go in. So his father came out <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came out”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> began to implore<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to implore”)</note> him. <verse-number id="Lk 15:29">29</verse-number>But he answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to his father, ‘Behold, so many years I have served you, and have never disobeyed your command! And you never gave me a young goat so that I could celebrate with my friends! <verse-number id="Lk 15:30">30</verse-number>But when this son of yours returned—who has consumed your assets with prostitutes—you killed the fattened calf for him!’ <verse-number id="Lk 15:31">31</verse-number>But he said to him, ‘Child, you are always with me, and <idiom-start/>everything I have belongs to you<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “all my <supplied>things</supplied> are yours”</note> <verse-number id="Lk 15:32">32</verse-number>But it was necessary to celebrate and to rejoice, because this brother of yours was dead, and is alive, and was lost, and is found!’ ” </p>
		</chapter>