<chapter id="Lk 17">
			<pericope>Sin, Forgiveness, Faith, and Service</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 17:1">1</verse-number> And he said to his disciples, “It is impossible for causes for stumbling not to come, but woe <supplied>to him</supplied> through whom they come! <verse-number id="Lk 17:2">2</verse-number>It would be better for him if <idiom-start/>a millstone<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a stone belonging to a mill”</note> is placed around his neck and he is thrown into the sea than that he causes one of these little ones to sin. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 17:3">3</verse-number>“Be concerned about yourselves! If your brother sins, rebuke him, and if he repents, forgive him. <verse-number id="Lk 17:4">4</verse-number>And if he sins against you seven times in a day, and seven times he returns to you saying, ‘I repent,’ you must forgive him.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 17:5">5</verse-number>And the apostles said to the Lord, “Increase our faith!” <verse-number id="Lk 17:6">6</verse-number>So the Lord said, “If you have faith like a mustard seed, you could say to this mulberry tree, ‘Be uprooted and planted in the sea,’ and it would obey you. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 17:7">7</verse-number>“And which of you who has a slave plowing or shepherding <supplied>sheep</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> who comes in from the field will say to him, ‘Come here at once <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“come here”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> recline at the table’? <verse-number id="Lk 17:8">8</verse-number>Will he not rather say to him, ‘Prepare something that I may eat, and dress yourself to serve me while I eat and drink, and after these <supplied>things</supplied> you will eat and drink.’ <verse-number id="Lk 17:9">9</verse-number>He will not <idiom-start/>be grateful<idiom-end/><note>Literally “have gratitude”</note> to the slave because he did what was ordered, <supplied>will he</supplied>?<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here, indicated by “<supplied>will he</supplied>”</note> <verse-number id="Lk 17:10">10</verse-number>Thus you also, when you have done all the <idiom-start/>things you were ordered to do<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “things that were ordered to you”</note> say, ‘We are unworthy slaves; we have done what we were obligated to do.’ ” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Ten Lepers Cleansed</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 17:11">11</verse-number>And it happened that while traveling toward Jerusalem, he was passing through <idiom-start/>the region between<idiom-end/><note>Literally “through the midst”</note> Samaria and Galilee. <verse-number id="Lk 17:12">12</verse-number>And <supplied>as</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was entering”)</note> he was entering into a certain village, ten men met <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note>﻿<note>Some manuscripts explicitly state “him”</note>—lepers, who stood at a distance. <verse-number id="Lk 17:13">13</verse-number>And they raised <supplied>their</supplied> voices, saying, “Jesus, Master, have mercy on us!” <verse-number id="Lk 17:14">14</verse-number>And <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> saw <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> he said to them, “Go <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“go”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> show yourselves to the priests.” And it happened that as they were going, they were cleansed. <verse-number id="Lk 17:15">15</verse-number>But one of them, <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> saw that he was healed, turned back, praising God with a loud voice. <verse-number id="Lk 17:16">16</verse-number>And he fell on <supplied>his</supplied> face at his feet, giving thanks to him. And he was a Samaritan. <verse-number id="Lk 17:17">17</verse-number>So Jesus answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “Were not ten cleansed? And where <supplied>are</supplied> the nine? <verse-number id="Lk 17:18">18</verse-number>Was no one found to turn back <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“turn back”) has been translated as an infinitive</note> give praise to God except this foreigner?” <verse-number id="Lk 17:19">19</verse-number>And he said to him, “Get up <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“get up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> go your way. Your faith has saved you.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Coming of the Kingdom of God</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 17:20">20</verse-number>Now <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was asked”) which is understood as temporal</note> was asked by the Pharisees when the kingdom of God would come, he answered them and said, “The kingdom of God does not come with <idiom-start/>things that can be observed<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “observation”</note> <verse-number id="Lk 17:21">21</verse-number>nor will they say, ‘Behold, here <supplied>it is</supplied>!’ or ‘There!’ For behold, the kingdom of God is in your midst.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Coming of the Son of Man</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 17:22">22</verse-number>And he said to the disciples, “Days will come when you will desire to see one of the days of the Son of Man, and you will not see <supplied>it</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <verse-number id="Lk 17:23">23</verse-number>And they will say to you, ‘Behold, there!’ ‘Behold, here!’<note>Some manuscripts have “ ‘Behold, there!’ or ‘Behold, here!’ ”</note> Do not go out or run after <supplied>them</supplied>!<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <verse-number id="Lk 17:24">24</verse-number>For just as the lightning shines forth, flashing from <supplied>one place</supplied> under heaven to <supplied>another place</supplied> under heaven, so the Son of Man will be in his day. <verse-number id="Lk 17:25">25</verse-number>But first it is necessary <supplied>for</supplied> him to suffer many <supplied>things</supplied>, and to be rejected by this generation. <verse-number id="Lk 17:26">26</verse-number>And just as it was in the days of Noah, so also it will be in the days of the Son of Man—<verse-number id="Lk 17:27">27</verse-number>they were eating, they were drinking, they were marrying, they were being given in marriage, until the day Noah entered into the ark, and the flood came and destroyed <supplied>them</supplied> all. <verse-number id="Lk 17:28">28</verse-number>Likewise, just as it was in the days of Lot—they were eating, they were drinking, they were buying, they were selling, they were planting, they were building. <verse-number id="Lk 17:29">29</verse-number>But on the day that Lot went out from Sodom, it rained fire and sulphur from heaven and destroyed <supplied>them</supplied> all. <verse-number id="Lk 17:30">30</verse-number>It will be <idiom-start/>just the same<idiom-end/><note>Literally “according to the same”</note> on the day that the Son of Man is revealed. <verse-number id="Lk 17:31">31</verse-number>On that day, whoever is on the housetop and his goods <supplied>are</supplied> in the house must not come down to take them away. And likewise the one who <supplied>is</supplied> in the field must not turn back <verse-number id="Lk 17:32">32</verse-number>Remember Lot’s wife! <verse-number id="Lk 17:33">33</verse-number>Whoever seeks to preserve his life will lose it, but whoever loses <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> will keep it. <verse-number id="Lk 17:34">34</verse-number>I tell you that in that night there will be two in one bed; one will be taken and the other will be left. <verse-number id="Lk 17:35">35</verse-number>There will be two <supplied>women</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>women</supplied>” is supplied because the form (“two”) is feminine gender in Greek</note> grinding at the same <supplied>place</supplied>; one will be taken and the other will be left.”<note>A few manuscripts add v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Lk 17:36">36</cite> (with some variations): “There will be two in the field; one will be taken and the other will be left.”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 17:37">37</verse-number>And they answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to him, “Where, Lord?” So he said to them, “Where the dead body <supplied>is</supplied>, there also the vultures will be gathered.” </p>
		</chapter>