<chapter id="Lk 18">
			<pericope>The Parable of the Unjust Judge</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 18:1">1</verse-number> And he told them a parable to <supplied>show that</supplied> they must always pray and not be discouraged, <verse-number id="Lk 18:2">2</verse-number>saying, “There was a certain judge in a certain town who did not fear God and did not respect people. <verse-number id="Lk 18:3">3</verse-number>And there was a widow in that town, and she kept coming to him, saying, ‘Grant me justice against my adversary!’ <verse-number id="Lk 18:4">4</verse-number>And he was not willing for a time, but after these <supplied>things</supplied> he said to himself, ‘Even if I do not fear God or respect people, <verse-number id="Lk 18:5">5</verse-number>yet because this widow is causing trouble for me, I will grant her justice, so that she does not wear me down in the end <supplied>by her</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“coming back”) which is understood as means</note> coming back!’ ” <verse-number id="Lk 18:6">6</verse-number>And the Lord said, “Listen to what the unrighteous judge is saying! <verse-number id="Lk 18:7">7</verse-number>And will not God surely <idiom-start/>see to it that justice is done<idiom-end/><note>Literally “carry out the giving of justice”</note> to his chosen ones who cry out to him day and night, and will he delay toward them? <verse-number id="Lk 18:8">8</verse-number>I tell you that <idiom-start/>he will see to it that justice is done<idiom-end/><note>Literally “he will carry out the giving of justice”</note> for them soon! Nevertheless, <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“comes”) which is understood as temporal</note> the Son of Man comes, then will he find faith on earth?” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Parable of the Pharisee and the Tax Collector</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 18:9">9</verse-number>And he also told this parable to some who trusted in themselves that they were righteous, and looked down on <idiom-start/>everyone else<idiom-end/>:<note>Literally “the rest”</note> <verse-number id="Lk 18:10">10</verse-number>“Two men went up to the temple to pray, one a Pharisee and the other a tax collector. <verse-number id="Lk 18:11">11</verse-number>The Pharisee stood <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“stood”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> prayed these <supplied>things</supplied> with reference to himself: ‘God, I give thanks to you that I am not like other people—swindlers, unrighteous <supplied>people</supplied>, adulterers, or even like this tax collector! <verse-number id="Lk 18:12">12</verse-number>I fast twice a week; I give a tenth of all that I get.’ <verse-number id="Lk 18:13">13</verse-number>But the tax collector, standing far away, did not want even to raise his eyes to heaven, but was beating his breast, saying, ‘God, be merciful to me, a sinner!’ <verse-number id="Lk 18:14">14</verse-number>I tell you, this man went down to his house justified rather than that one! For everyone who exalts himself will be humbled, but the one who humbles himself will be exalted.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Little Children Brought to Jesus</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 18:15">15</verse-number>Now they were bringing even <supplied>their</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> babies to him so that he could touch them. But <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> the disciples saw <supplied>it</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> they rebuked them. <verse-number id="Lk 18:16">16</verse-number>But Jesus called them to himself, saying, “Allow the children to come to me, and do not forbid them, <idiom-start/>for to such belongs<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for of such is”</note> the kingdom of God. <verse-number id="Lk 18:17">17</verse-number>Truly I say to you, whoever does not welcome the kingdom of God like a young child will never enter into it.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A Rich Young Man</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 18:18">18</verse-number>And a certain ruler asked him, saying, “Good Teacher, <supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“doing”) which is understood as means</note> doing what will I inherit eternal life?” <verse-number id="Lk 18:19">19</verse-number>And Jesus said to him, “Why do you call me good? No one <supplied>is</supplied> good except God alone. <verse-number id="Lk 18:20">20</verse-number>You know the commandments: ‘Do not commit adultery, do not murder, do not steal, do not give false testimony, honor your father and mother.’ ”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ex 20:12–16">Exod 20:12–16</cite>; <cite title="BibleLEB2: Dt 5:16–20">Deut 5:16–20</cite></note> <verse-number id="Lk 18:21">21</verse-number>And he said, “All these I have observed from my<note>Some manuscripts omit “my”</note> youth.” <verse-number id="Lk 18:22">22</verse-number>And <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> heard <supplied>this</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> Jesus said to him, “<idiom-start/>You still lack one thing<idiom-end/>:<note>Literally “one still lacking to you”</note> Sell all that you have, and distribute <supplied>the proceeds</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to the poor—and you will have treasure in heaven—and come, follow me.” <verse-number id="Lk 18:23">23</verse-number>But <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> heard these <supplied>things</supplied> he became very sad, because he was extremely wealthy. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 18:24">24</verse-number>And Jesus took notice of him<note>Some manuscripts add “becoming very sad”</note> <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“took notice of”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “How <idiom-start/>difficult it is for<idiom-end/><note>Literally “with difficulty”</note> those who possess wealth to enter into the kingdom of God! <verse-number id="Lk 18:25">25</verse-number>For it is easier <supplied>for</supplied> a camel to go through the eye of a needle than <supplied>for</supplied> a rich person to enter into the kingdom of God. <verse-number id="Lk 18:26">26</verse-number>So those who heard <supplied>this</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> said, “And who can be saved?” <verse-number id="Lk 18:27">27</verse-number>But he said, “<supplied>What is</supplied> impossible with men is possible with God.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 18:28">28</verse-number>And Peter said, “Behold, we have left <idiom-start/>all that is ours<idiom-end/><note>Literally “our own”</note> <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“have left”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> followed you.” <verse-number id="Lk 18:29">29</verse-number>And he said to them, “Truly I say to you that there is no one who has left house or wife or brothers or parents or children on account of the kingdom of God, <verse-number id="Lk 18:30">30</verse-number>who will not receive many times more in this time and in the age to come, eternal life.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus Predicts His Death and Resurrection a Third Time</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 18:31">31</verse-number>And taking aside the twelve, he said to them, “Behold, we are going up to Jerusalem, and all the things that are written by the prophets with reference to the Son of Man will be accomplished. <verse-number id="Lk 18:32">32</verse-number>For he will be handed over to the Gentiles and will be mocked and mistreated and spit on, <verse-number id="Lk 18:33">33</verse-number>and <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“flogging”) which is understood as temporal</note> flogging <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> they will kill him, and on the third day he will rise.” <verse-number id="Lk 18:34">34</verse-number>And they understood none of these <supplied>things</supplied>, and this saying was concealed from them, and they did not comprehend the things that were said. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A Blind Man Healed at Jericho</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 18:35">35</verse-number>Now it happened that as he drew near to Jericho, a certain blind man was sitting on the side of the road begging. <verse-number id="Lk 18:36">36</verse-number>And <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> heard a crowd going by, he inquired what this meant. <verse-number id="Lk 18:37">37</verse-number>And they told him, “Jesus the Nazarene is passing by.” <verse-number id="Lk 18:38">38</verse-number>And he called out, saying, “Jesus, Son of David, have mercy on me!” <verse-number id="Lk 18:39">39</verse-number>And those who were in front rebuked him, that he should be silent, but he cried out <idiom-start/>even more loudly<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “by much more”</note> “Son of David, have mercy on me!” <verse-number id="Lk 18:40">40</verse-number>So Jesus stopped <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“stopped”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> ordered him to be brought to him. And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“approached”)</note> he approached, he asked him, <verse-number id="Lk 18:41">41</verse-number>“What do you want me to do for you?” And he said, “Lord, that I may regain <supplied>my</supplied> sight. <verse-number id="Lk 18:42">42</verse-number>And Jesus said to him, “Regain <supplied>your</supplied> sight! Your faith has saved you.” <verse-number id="Lk 18:43">43</verse-number>And immediately he regained <supplied>his</supplied> sight and began to follow<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to follow”)</note> him, glorifying God. And all the people, <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> saw <supplied>it</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> gave praise to God. </p>
		</chapter>