<chapter id="Lk 19">
			<pericope>Jesus and Zacchaeus</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 19:1">1</verse-number> And he entered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“entered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> traveled through Jericho. <verse-number id="Lk 19:2">2</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>there was<idiom-end/><note>Literally “behold”</note> a man <idiom-start/>named<idiom-end/><note>Literally “called by name”</note> Zacchaeus, and he was a chief tax collector, and he <supplied>was</supplied> rich. <verse-number id="Lk 19:3">3</verse-number>And he was seeking to see Jesus—who he was—and he was not able to as a result of the crowd, because he was short in stature. <verse-number id="Lk 19:4">4</verse-number>And he ran on ahead <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“ran on”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> climbed up into a sycamore tree so that he could see him, because he was going to go through <supplied>that way</supplied>. <verse-number id="Lk 19:5">5</verse-number>And when he came to the place, Jesus looked up <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“looked up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to him, “Zacchaeus, come down quickly, because it is necessary <supplied>for</supplied> me to stay at your house today!” <verse-number id="Lk 19:6">6</verse-number>And he came down quickly and welcomed him joyfully. <verse-number id="Lk 19:7">7</verse-number>And <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> saw <supplied>it</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> they all began to complain,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to complain”)</note> saying, “He has gone in to find lodging with a man who is a sinner!” <verse-number id="Lk 19:8">8</verse-number>And Zacchaeus stopped <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“stopped”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to the Lord, “Behold, half of my possessions, Lord, I am giving to the poor, and if I have extorted anything from anyone, I am paying <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> back four times <supplied>as much</supplied>!” <verse-number id="Lk 19:9">9</verse-number>And Jesus said to him, “Today salvation has come to this house, because he too is a son of Abraham. <verse-number id="Lk 19:10">10</verse-number>For the Son of Man came to seek and to save those who are lost.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Parable of the Ten Minas</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 19:11">11</verse-number>Now <supplied>while</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“were listening to”)</note> they were listening to these <supplied>things</supplied>, he went on <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went on”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> told a parable, because he was near Jerusalem and they thought that the kingdom of God was going to appear immediately. <verse-number id="Lk 19:12">12</verse-number>Therefore he said, “A certain nobleman traveled to a distant country to receive for himself a kingdom and to return. <verse-number id="Lk 19:13">13</verse-number>And summoning ten of his own slaves, he gave them ten minas<note>A Greek monetary unit equal to 100 drachmas</note> and said to them, ‘Do business <idiom-start/>until I come back<idiom-end/>.’<note>Literally “in which <supplied>time</supplied> I am coming back”</note> <verse-number id="Lk 19:14">14</verse-number>But his citizens hated him, and sent a delegation after him, saying, ‘We do not want this man to be king over us!’ <verse-number id="Lk 19:15">15</verse-number>And it happened that when he returned <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“receiving”) which is understood as temporal</note> receiving the kingdom, he ordered these slaves to whom he had given the money to be summoned to him, so that he could know what they had gained by trading. <verse-number id="Lk 19:16">16</verse-number>So the first arrived, saying, ‘Sir, your mina has made ten minas more!’ <verse-number id="Lk 19:17">17</verse-number>And he said to him, ‘Well done, good slave! Because you have been faithful in a very small thing, <idiom-start/>have authority<idiom-end/><note>Literally “be having authority”</note> over ten cities.’ <verse-number id="Lk 19:18">18</verse-number>And the second came, saying, ‘Sir, your mina has made five minas.’ <verse-number id="Lk 19:19">19</verse-number>So he said to this one also, ‘And you be over five cities.’ <verse-number id="Lk 19:20">20</verse-number>And another came, saying, ‘Sir, behold your mina, which I had put away for safekeeping in a piece of cloth. <verse-number id="Lk 19:21">21</verse-number>For I was afraid of you, because you are a severe man—you withdraw what you did not deposit, and you reap what you did not sow!’ <verse-number id="Lk 19:22">22</verse-number>He said to him, ‘<idiom-start/>By your own words<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from your <supplied>own</supplied> mouth”</note> I will judge you, wicked slave! You knew that I am a severe man, withdrawing what I did not deposit and reaping what I did not sow. <verse-number id="Lk 19:23">23</verse-number>And why did you not give my money to the bank, and I, <supplied>when I</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“returned”) which is understood as temporal</note> returned, would have collected it with interest?’ <verse-number id="Lk 19:24">24</verse-number>And to the bystanders he said, ‘Take away from him the mina and give <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to the one who has the ten minas!’ <verse-number id="Lk 19:25">25</verse-number>And they said to him, ‘Sir, he has ten minas.’ <verse-number id="Lk 19:26">26</verse-number>‘I tell you that to everyone who has, <supplied>more</supplied> will be given. But from the one who does not have, even what he has will be taken away. <verse-number id="Lk 19:27">27</verse-number>But these enemies of mine who did not want me to be king over them—bring <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> here and slaughter them <supplied>in</supplied> my presence!’ ” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Triumphal Entry</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 19:28">28</verse-number>And <supplied>after he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had said”) which is understood as temporal</note> had said these <supplied>things</supplied>, he traveled on ahead, going up to Jerusalem. <verse-number id="Lk 19:29">29</verse-number>And it happened that when he drew near to Bethphage and Bethany, to the hill<note>Or “mountain”</note> called <supplied>the Mount</supplied> of Olives, he sent two of the disciples, <verse-number id="Lk 19:30">30</verse-number>saying, ‘Go into the village in front of <supplied>you</supplied>, in which <supplied>as you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“enter”) which is understood as temporal</note> enter you will find a colt tied, on which <idiom-start/>no person has ever<idiom-end/><note>Literally “no one of men ever”</note> sat, and untie it <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“untie”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> bring <supplied>it</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <verse-number id="Lk 19:31">31</verse-number>And if anyone asks you, ‘Why are you untying <supplied>it</supplied>?’<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> you will say this: ‘The Lord has need of it.’ ” <verse-number id="Lk 19:32">32</verse-number>So those who were sent went <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> found <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> just as he had told them. <verse-number id="Lk 19:33">33</verse-number>And <supplied>as</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“were untying”)</note> they were untying the colt, its owners said to them, ‘Why are you untying the colt?’ <verse-number id="Lk 19:34">34</verse-number>So they said, ‘The Lord has need of it.’ <verse-number id="Lk 19:35">35</verse-number>And they brought it to Jesus, and throwing their cloaks on the colt, they put Jesus <supplied>on it</supplied>. <verse-number id="Lk 19:36">36</verse-number>And <supplied>as</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was going along”)</note> he was going along, they were spreading out their cloaks on the road. <verse-number id="Lk 19:37">37</verse-number>Now <supplied>as</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was drawing near”)</note> he was drawing near by this time to the descent from the Mount of Olives, the whole crowd of the disciples began rejoicing to praise God with a loud voice for all the miracles that they had seen, <verse-number id="Lk 19:38">38</verse-number>saying, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Blessed <supplied>is</supplied> the king, </li1>
				<li2>the one who comes in the name of the Lord!<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 118:26">Ps 118:26, </cite>with “the king” added as a clarification</note> </li2>
				<li1>Peace in heaven </li1>
				<li2>and glory in the highest!” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 19:39">39</verse-number>And some of the Pharisees from the crowd said to him, “Teacher, rebuke your disciples!” <verse-number id="Lk 19:40">40</verse-number>And he answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “I tell you that<note>Some manuscripts omit “that”</note> if these keep silent, the stones will cry out!” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus Weeps over Jerusalem</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 19:41">41</verse-number>And when he approached <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“approached”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> saw the city, he wept over it, <verse-number id="Lk 19:42">42</verse-number>saying, “If you had known on this day—even you—the things <supplied>that make</supplied> for peace! But now they are hidden from your eyes. <verse-number id="Lk 19:43">43</verse-number>For days will come upon you and your enemies will put up an embankment<note>Or “a palisade” (the term can refer to either a wooden or an earthen barricade)</note> against you, and will surround you and press you hard from all directions. <verse-number id="Lk 19:44">44</verse-number>And they will raze you to the ground, <supplied>you</supplied> and your children within you, and will not leave a stone upon a stone within you, <idiom-start/>because<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in return for which”</note> you did not recognize the time of your visitation.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Cleansing of the Temple</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 19:45">45</verse-number>And he entered into the temple <supplied>courts</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>courts</supplied>” is supplied to distinguish this area from the interior of the temple building itself</note> <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“entered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> began to drive out those who were selling, <verse-number id="Lk 19:46">46</verse-number>saying to them, “It is written, ‘And my house will be a house of prayer,’<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 56:7">Isa 56:7</cite></note> but you have made it a cave of robbers!” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 19:47">47</verse-number>And he was teaching every day in the temple <supplied>courts</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here “<supplied>courts</supplied>” is supplied to distinguish this area from the interior of the temple building itself</note> and the chief priests and the scribes and the most prominent men of the people were seeking to destroy him. <verse-number id="Lk 19:48">48</verse-number>And they did not find anything they could do, because all the people were paying close attention to <supplied>what</supplied> they were hearing from him. </p>
		</chapter>