<chapter id="Lk 20">
			<pericope>Jesus’ Authority Challenged</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 20:1">1</verse-number> And it happened that on one of the days <supplied>while</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was teaching”)</note> he was teaching the people in the temple <supplied>courts</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>courts</supplied>” is supplied to distinguish this area from the interior of the temple building itself</note> and proclaiming the gospel, the chief priests and the scribes approached together with the elders <verse-number id="Lk 20:2">2</verse-number>and said, saying to him, “Tell us, by what authority you are doing these <supplied>things</supplied>, or who is the one who gave you this authority? <verse-number id="Lk 20:3">3</verse-number>And he answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to them, “I also will ask you a question, and you tell me: <verse-number id="Lk 20:4">4</verse-number>The baptism of John—was <supplied>it</supplied> from heaven or from men? <verse-number id="Lk 20:5">5</verse-number>And they discussed <supplied>this</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> with one another, saying, “If we say ‘From heaven,’ he will say, ‘Why did you not believe him?’ <verse-number id="Lk 20:6">6</verse-number>But if we say, ‘From men,’ all the people will stone us to death, because they are convinced <supplied>that</supplied> John was a prophet.” <verse-number id="Lk 20:7">7</verse-number>And they replied <supplied>that they</supplied> did not know where <supplied>it was</supplied> from. <verse-number id="Lk 20:8">8</verse-number>And Jesus said to them, “Neither will I tell you by what authority I am doing these <supplied>things</supplied>.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Parable of the Tenant Farmers in the Vineyard</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 20:9">9</verse-number>And he began to tell the people this parable: “A man<note>Some manuscripts have “A certain man”</note> planted a vineyard, and leased it to tenant farmers, and went on a journey for a long time. <verse-number id="Lk 20:10">10</verse-number>And at the proper time he sent a slave to the tenant farmers, so that they would give him <supplied>some</supplied> of the fruit of the vineyard. But the tenant farmers sent him away empty-handed <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“beating”) which is understood as temporal</note> beating <supplied>him</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <verse-number id="Lk 20:11">11</verse-number>And he proceeded to send another slave, but they beat and dishonored that one also, <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the two previous participles (“beat” and “dishonored”) have been translated as finite verbs</note> sent <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> away empty-handed. <verse-number id="Lk 20:12">12</verse-number>And he proceeded to send a third, but they wounded <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“wounded”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> threw out this one also. <verse-number id="Lk 20:13">13</verse-number>So the owner of the vineyard said, ‘What should I do? I will send my beloved son; perhaps they will respect him.’ <verse-number id="Lk 20:14">14</verse-number>But <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> the tenant farmers saw him, they began to reason<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to reason”)</note> with one another, saying, ‘This is the heir. Let us kill him so that the inheritance will become ours!’ <verse-number id="Lk 20:15">15</verse-number>And they threw him out of the vineyard <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“threw”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> killed <supplied>him</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> What then will the owner of the vineyard do to them? <verse-number id="Lk 20:16">16</verse-number>He will come and destroy those tenant farmers and give the vineyard to others.” And <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> heard <supplied>this</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> they said, “<supplied>May this</supplied> never happen!” <verse-number id="Lk 20:17">17</verse-number>But he looked intently at them <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“looked intently at”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “What then is this that is written: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>‘The stone which the builders rejected, </li1>
				<li2>this has become <idiom-start/>the cornerstone<idiom-end/>.’<note>Literally “the head of the corner”</note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 20:18">18</verse-number>Everyone who falls on that stone will be broken to pieces, and <supplied>the one</supplied> on whom it falls—it will crush him!” <verse-number id="Lk 20:19">19</verse-number>And the scribes and the chief priests sought to lay <supplied>their</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> hands on him at <supplied>that</supplied> same hour, and they were afraid of the people, for they knew that he had told this parable with reference to them. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Paying Taxes to Caesar</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 20:20">20</verse-number>And they watched <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> closely <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“watched closely”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> sent spies who pretended they were upright, in order that they could catch him in a statement, so that they could hand him over to the authority and the jurisdiction of the governor. <verse-number id="Lk 20:21">21</verse-number>And they asked him, saying, “Teacher, we know that you speak and teach rightly, and do not <idiom-start/>show partiality<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “receive face”</note> but teach the way of God in truth. <verse-number id="Lk 20:22">22</verse-number>Is it permitted <supplied>for</supplied> us to pay taxes<note>Or “the tribute tax”</note> to Caesar or not?” <verse-number id="Lk 20:23">23</verse-number>But seeing through their craftiness, he said to them, <verse-number id="Lk 20:24">24</verse-number>“Show me a denarius! Whose image and inscription does it have?” And they answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said,<note>Some manuscripts have “And they said”</note> “Caesar’s.” <verse-number id="Lk 20:25">25</verse-number>So he said to them, “Well then, give to Caesar the things of Caesar, and to God the things of God!” <verse-number id="Lk 20:26">26</verse-number>And they were not able to catch <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note>﻿<note>Some manuscripts explicitly state “him”</note> in a statement in the sight of the people, and astonished at his answer, they became silent. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A Question About Marriage and the Resurrection</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 20:27">27</verse-number>Now some of the Sadducees—who deny <idiom-start/>that there is a resurrection<idiom-end/><note>Literally “resurrection not to exist”</note>—came up <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> asked him, <verse-number id="Lk 20:28">28</verse-number>saying, “Teacher, Moses wrote for us if someone’s brother dies having a wife, and this man is childless, that his brother should take the wife and <idiom-start/>father<idiom-end/><note>Literally “raise up”</note> descendants for his brother. <verse-number id="Lk 20:29">29</verse-number>Now there were seven brothers, and the first took a wife <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“took”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> died childless, <verse-number id="Lk 20:30">30</verse-number>and the second, <verse-number id="Lk 20:31">31</verse-number>and the third took her, and likewise also the seven did not leave children and died. <verse-number id="Lk 20:32">32</verse-number>Finally the woman also died. <verse-number id="Lk 20:33">33</verse-number>Therefore in the resurrection, the woman—whose wife will she be? For the seven had her <supplied>as</supplied> wife.” <verse-number id="Lk 20:34">34</verse-number>And Jesus said to them, “The sons of this age marry and are given in marriage, <verse-number id="Lk 20:35">35</verse-number>but those who are considered worthy to attain to that age and <supplied>to</supplied> the resurrection from the dead neither marry nor are given in marriage, <verse-number id="Lk 20:36">36</verse-number>for they are not even able to die any longer, because they are like the angels and are sons of God, <supplied>because they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“are”) which is understood as causal</note> are sons of the resurrection. <verse-number id="Lk 20:37">37</verse-number>But that the dead are raised, even Moses revealed in <supplied>the passage about</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The words “<supplied>the passage about</supplied>” are not in the Greek text but are implied; here a common form of rabbinic citation is being used to refer to an Old Testament passage</note> the bush, when he calls the Lord the God of Abraham and <supplied>the</supplied> God of Isaac and <supplied>the</supplied> God of Jacob. <verse-number id="Lk 20:38">38</verse-number>Now he is not God of the dead, but of the living, for all live to him!” <verse-number id="Lk 20:39">39</verse-number>And some of the scribes answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “Teacher, you have spoken well.” <verse-number id="Lk 20:40">40</verse-number>For they no longer dared to ask him anything. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>David’s Son and Lord</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 20:41">41</verse-number>But he said to them, “In what sense do they say <supplied>that</supplied> the Christ is David’s son? <verse-number id="Lk 20:42">42</verse-number>For David himself says in the book of Psalms, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>‘The Lord said to my Lord, </li1>
				<li2>“Sit at my right hand, </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Lk 20:43">43</verse-number>until I make your enemies </li1>
				<li2>a footstool for your feet.” ’<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 110:1">Ps 110:1</cite></note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 20:44">44</verse-number>David therefore calls him ‘Lord,’ and how is he his son?” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Warning to Beware of the Scribes</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 20:45">45</verse-number>And <supplied>while</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“were listening”)</note> all the people were listening, he said to the disciples,<note>Some manuscripts have “to his disciples”</note> <verse-number id="Lk 20:46">46</verse-number>“Beware of the scribes, who like walking around in long robes and who love greetings in the marketplaces and the best seats in the synagogues and the places of honor at banquets, <verse-number id="Lk 20:47">47</verse-number>who devour the houses of widows and pray lengthy <supplied>prayers</supplied> for the sake of appearance. These will receive more severe condemnation!” </p>
		</chapter>