<chapter id="Lk 21">
			<pericope>A Poor Widow’s Offering</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 21:1">1</verse-number> And he looked up <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“looked up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> saw the rich putting their gifts into the contribution box, <verse-number id="Lk 21:2">2</verse-number>and he saw a certain poor widow putting in there two small copper coins.<note>This coin was the <i>lepton</i>, worth 1/128 of a denarius</note> <verse-number id="Lk 21:3">3</verse-number>And he said, “Truly I say to you that this poor widow put in more than all <supplied>of them</supplied>. <verse-number id="Lk 21:4">4</verse-number>For these all put <supplied>gifts</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> into the offering out of their abundance, but this <supplied>woman</supplied> out of her poverty put in all the means of subsistence that she had.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Destruction of the Temple Predicted</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 21:5">5</verse-number>And <supplied>while</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“were speaking”)</note> some were speaking about the temple, that it was adorned with precious stones and votive offerings, he said, <verse-number id="Lk 21:6">6</verse-number>“<supplied>As for</supplied> these <supplied>things</supplied> that you see—days will come in which not <supplied>one</supplied> stone will be left on <supplied>another</supplied> stone that will not be thrown down!” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Signs of the End of the Age</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 21:7">7</verse-number>And they asked him, saying, “Teacher, when therefore will these <supplied>things</supplied> happen, and what <supplied>will be</supplied> the sign when these <supplied>things</supplied> are about to take place?” <verse-number id="Lk 21:8">8</verse-number>And he said, Watch out that you are not deceived! For many will come in my name, saying, ‘I am <supplied>he</supplied>,’ and ‘The time is near!’ Do not go after them! <verse-number id="Lk 21:9">9</verse-number>And when you hear about wars and insurrections, do not be terrified, for these <supplied>things</supplied> must happen first, but the end <supplied>will</supplied> not <supplied>be</supplied> at once.” <verse-number id="Lk 21:10">10</verse-number>Then he said to them, “nation will rise up against nation and kingdom against kingdom. <verse-number id="Lk 21:11">11</verse-number>There will be great earthquakes and famines and plagues in <supplied>various</supplied> places. There will be terrible sights and great signs from heaven. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Persecution of Disciples Predicted</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 21:12">12</verse-number>“But before all these <supplied>things</supplied>, they will lay their hands on you and will persecute <supplied>you</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> handing <supplied>you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> over to the synagogues and prisons. You will be brought before<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the participle (“be brought before”) is translated as a finite verb because of English style</note> kings and governors because of my name. <verse-number id="Lk 21:13">13</verse-number>This will turn out to you for a <supplied>time of</supplied> witness. <verse-number id="Lk 21:14">14</verse-number><idiom-start/>Therefore make up your minds<idiom-end/><note>Literally “therefore place in your hearts”</note> not to prepare in advance to speak in your own defense, <verse-number id="Lk 21:15">15</verse-number>for I will give you a mouth and wisdom that all your opponents will not be able to resist or contradict. <verse-number id="Lk 21:16">16</verse-number>And you will be handed over even by parents and brothers and relatives and friends, and they will put to death <supplied>some</supplied> of you. <verse-number id="Lk 21:17">17</verse-number>And you will be hated by all because of my name. <verse-number id="Lk 21:18">18</verse-number>Even a hair of your head will never perish! <verse-number id="Lk 21:19">19</verse-number>By your patient endurance you will gain your lives. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Desolation of Jerusalem</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 21:20">20</verse-number>“But when you see Jerusalem surrounded by armies, then know that its desolation has come near. <verse-number id="Lk 21:21">21</verse-number>Then those in Judea must flee to the mountains, and those <idiom-start/>inside it<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the midst of it”</note> must depart, and those in the fields must not enter into it, <verse-number id="Lk 21:22">22</verse-number>because these are days of vengeance, <supplied>so that</supplied> all the things that are written can be fulfilled. <verse-number id="Lk 21:23">23</verse-number>Woe to those <idiom-start/>who are pregnant<idiom-end/><note>Literally “who have in the womb”</note> and to those who are nursing <supplied>their babies</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The words “<supplied>their babies</supplied>” are not in the Greek text but are supplied as a necessary clarification</note> in those days! For there will be great distress on the earth and wrath against this people, <verse-number id="Lk 21:24">24</verse-number>and they will fall by the edge of the sword, and will be led captive into all the nations,<note>The same Greek word, occurring three times in this verse, can be translated “nations” or “Gentiles” depending on the context</note> and Jerusalem will be trampled down by the Gentiles until the times of the Gentiles are fulfilled. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Arrival of the Son of Man</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 21:25">25</verse-number>“And there will be signs in the sun and moon and stars, and on the earth distress of nations in perplexity from the noise of the sea and <supplied>its</supplied> surging, <verse-number id="Lk 21:26">26</verse-number>people fainting from fear and expectation of what is coming on the inhabited earth, for the powers of the heavens will be shaken.<note>An allusion to <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 34:4">Isa 34:4</cite></note> <verse-number id="Lk 21:27">27</verse-number>And then they will see the Son of Man arriving in a cloud<note>An allusion to <cite title="BibleLEB2: Da 7:13">Dan 7:13</cite></note> with power and great glory. <verse-number id="Lk 21:28">28</verse-number>But <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“begin”)</note> these <supplied>things</supplied> begin to happen, stand up straight and raise your heads, because your redemption is drawing near!” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Parable of the Fig Tree</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 21:29">29</verse-number>And he told them a parable: “Look at the fig tree and all the trees. <verse-number id="Lk 21:30">30</verse-number>When they put out <supplied>foliage</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> now you see for yourselves <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“see”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> know that by this time the summer is near. <verse-number id="Lk 21:31">31</verse-number>So also you, when you see these <supplied>things</supplied> happening, know<note>Or “you know”</note> that the kingdom of God is near. <verse-number id="Lk 21:32">32</verse-number>Truly I say to you that this generation will never pass away until all <supplied>things</supplied> take place! <verse-number id="Lk 21:33">33</verse-number>Heaven and earth will pass away, but my words will never pass away. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Be Alert</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 21:34">34</verse-number>“But take care for yourselves, lest your hearts are weighed down with dissipation and drunkenness and the worries of daily life, and that day come upon you suddenly <verse-number id="Lk 21:35">35</verse-number>like a trap. For it will come upon all who reside on the face of the whole earth. <verse-number id="Lk 21:36">36</verse-number>But be alert at all times, praying that you may have strength to escape all these <supplied>things</supplied> <supplied>that</supplied> are going to happen, and to stand before the Son of Man.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 21:37">37</verse-number>So <supplied>throughout</supplied> the days he was teaching in the temple <supplied>courts</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here “<supplied>courts</supplied>” is supplied to distinguish this area from the interior of the temple building itself</note> and <supplied>throughout</supplied> the nights he was going out <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“was going out”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> spending the night on the hill that is called <supplied>the Mount</supplied> of Olives. <verse-number id="Lk 21:38">38</verse-number>And all the people were getting up very early in the morning <supplied>to come</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The words “<supplied>to come</supplied>” are not in the Greek text but are implied</note> to him in the temple <supplied>courts</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>courts</supplied>” is supplied to distinguish this area from the interior of the temple building itself</note> to listen to him. </p>
		</chapter>