<chapter id="Lk 23">
			<pericope>Jesus Brought Before Pilate</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 23:1">1</verse-number> And the whole assembly of them rose up <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“rose up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> brought him before Pilate. <verse-number id="Lk 23:2">2</verse-number>And they began to accuse him, saying, “We have found this man misleading our nation and forbidding <supplied>us</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to pay taxes to Caesar, and saying <supplied>he</supplied> himself is Christ, a king!” <verse-number id="Lk 23:3">3</verse-number>And Pilate asked him, saying, “Are you the king of the Jews?” And he answered him <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “You say <supplied>so</supplied>.” <verse-number id="Lk 23:4">4</verse-number>So Pilate said to the chief priests and the crowds, “I find no basis for an accusation against this man.” <verse-number id="Lk 23:5">5</verse-number>But they insisted, saying, “He incites the people, teaching throughout the whole of Judea and beginning from Galilee as far as here.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus Brought Before Herod</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 23:6">6</verse-number>Now <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> Pilate heard <supplied>this</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> he asked if the man was a Galilean. <verse-number id="Lk 23:7">7</verse-number>And <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“found out”) which is understood as temporal</note> found out that he was from the jurisdiction of Herod, he sent him over to Herod, who was also in Jerusalem in those days. <verse-number id="Lk 23:8">8</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> Herod saw Jesus, he was very glad, for he had been wanting to see him for a long time, because he had heard about him and was hoping to see some miracle performed by him. <verse-number id="Lk 23:9">9</verse-number>So he questioned him <idiom-start/>at considerable length<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “with many words”</note> but he answered nothing to him. <verse-number id="Lk 23:10">10</verse-number>And the chief priests and the scribes were standing there vehemently accusing him. <verse-number id="Lk 23:11">11</verse-number>And Herod with his soldiers also treated him with contempt, and <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“mocking”) which is understood as temporal</note> mocking <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied to connect the two participles (“mocking” and “dressing”) in keeping with English style</note> dressing <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <supplied>in</supplied> glistening clothing, he sent him back to Pilate. <verse-number id="Lk 23:12">12</verse-number>And both Herod and Pilate became friends with one another on <supplied>that</supplied> same day, <idiom-start/>for they had previously been enemies of one another<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “for they had previously existed being at enmity with each other”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Pilate Releases Barabbas</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 23:13">13</verse-number>So Pilate called together the chief priests and the rulers and the people <verse-number id="Lk 23:14">14</verse-number><supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the participle in the previous verse (“called together”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to them, “You brought me this man as one who was misleading the people, and behold, <supplied>when I</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“examined”) which is understood as temporal</note> examined <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> before you, I found nothing in this man as basis for the accusation which <idiom-start/>you are making<idiom-end/><note>Literally “you are accusing”</note> against him. <verse-number id="Lk 23:15">15</verse-number>But neither <supplied>did</supplied> Herod, because he sent him back to us. And behold, nothing deserving death <idiom-start/>has been done<idiom-end/><note>Literally “is having been done”</note> by him. <verse-number id="Lk 23:16">16</verse-number>Therefore I will punish him <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“punish”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> release <supplied>him</supplied>.”<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <note>Many of the most important Greek manuscripts lack v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Lk 23:17">17</cite>, “Now he was obligated to release for them at the feast one person.”</note> <verse-number id="Lk 23:18">18</verse-number>But they all cried out in unison, saying, “Take this man away, and release for us Barabbas!” <verse-number id="Lk 23:19">19</verse-number>(who had been thrown in prison because of a certain insurrection that had taken place in the city, and <supplied>for</supplied> murder). <verse-number id="Lk 23:20">20</verse-number>And Pilate, wanting to release Jesus, addressed <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note>﻿<note>Some manuscripts explicitly state “them”</note> again, <verse-number id="Lk 23:21">21</verse-number>but they kept crying out, saying, “Crucify! Crucify him!” <verse-number id="Lk 23:22">22</verse-number>So he said to them a third <supplied>time</supplied>, “Why? What wrong has this man done? I found no basis for an accusation <idiom-start/>deserving death<idiom-end/><note>Literally “of death”</note> in him. Therefore I will punish him <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“punish”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> release <supplied>him</supplied>.”<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <verse-number id="Lk 23:23">23</verse-number>But they were urgent, demanding with loud cries <supplied>that</supplied> he be crucified. And their cries prevailed. <verse-number id="Lk 23:24">24</verse-number>And Pilate decided <supplied>that</supplied> their demand should be granted. <verse-number id="Lk 23:25">25</verse-number>And he released the one who had been thrown into prison because of insurrection and murder, whom they were asking for, but Jesus he handed over to their will. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus Is Crucified</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 23:26">26</verse-number>And as they led him away, they seized Simon, a certain <supplied>man</supplied> of Cyrene, who was coming from the country, <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“seized”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> placed the cross on him, to carry <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> behind Jesus. <verse-number id="Lk 23:27">27</verse-number>And a great crowd of the people were following him, and of women who were mourning and lamenting him. <verse-number id="Lk 23:28">28</verse-number>But turning to them, Jesus said, “Daughters of Jerusalem, do not weep for me, but weep for yourselves and for your children! <verse-number id="Lk 23:29">29</verse-number>For behold, days are coming in which they will say, ‘Blessed <supplied>are</supplied> the barren, and the wombs that did not give birth, and <supplied>the</supplied> breasts that did not nurse!’ <verse-number id="Lk 23:30">30</verse-number>Then they will begin to say to the mountains, ‘Fall on us!’ and to the hills, ‘Cover us!’ <verse-number id="Lk 23:31">31</verse-number>For if they do these <supplied>things</supplied> <idiom-start/>when the wood is green<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “in the green wood”</note> what will happen <idiom-start/>when it is dry<idiom-end/>?”<note>Literally “in the dry”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 23:32">32</verse-number>And two other criminals were also led away to be executed with him. <verse-number id="Lk 23:33">33</verse-number>And when they came to the place that is called “The Skull,” there they crucified him, and the criminals, the one on <supplied>his</supplied> right and the other on <supplied>his</supplied> left. <verse-number id="Lk 23:34">34</verse-number>〚But Jesus said, “Father, forgive them, for they do not know what they are doing.”〛<note>Many important manuscripts lack v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Lk 23:34a">34a</cite>, “But Jesus said, ‘Father, forgive them, for they do not know what they are doing.’ ”</note> And they cast lots to divide his clothes. <verse-number id="Lk 23:35">35</verse-number>And the people stood there watching, but the rulers also ridiculed <supplied>him</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> saying, “He saved others; let him save himself, if this <supplied>man</supplied> is the Christ<note>Or “Messiah”</note> of God, the Chosen One!” <verse-number id="Lk 23:36">36</verse-number>And the soldiers also mocked him, coming up <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied to connect the two participles (“coming up” and “offering”) in keeping with English style</note> offering him sour wine <verse-number id="Lk 23:37">37</verse-number>and saying, “If you are the king of the Jews, save yourself!” <verse-number id="Lk 23:38">38</verse-number>And there was also an inscription over him, “This <supplied>is</supplied> the king of the Jews.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 23:39">39</verse-number>And one of the criminals who were hanged there reviled him, saying, “Are you not the Christ? Save yourself—and us!” <verse-number id="Lk 23:40">40</verse-number>But the other answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied to connect the two participles (“answered” and “rebuked”) in keeping with English style</note> rebuked him, saying, “Do you not even fear God, because you are undergoing the same condemnation? <verse-number id="Lk 23:41">41</verse-number>And we indeed justly, for we are receiving <idiom-start/>what we deserve<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<supplied>things</supplied> worthy”</note> <supplied>for</supplied> what we have done. But this man has done nothing wrong!” <verse-number id="Lk 23:42">42</verse-number>And he said, “Jesus, remember me when you come into your kingdom!” <verse-number id="Lk 23:43">43</verse-number>And he said to him, “Truly I say to you, today you will be with me in paradise.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus Dies on the Cross</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 23:44">44</verse-number>And by this time it was about the sixth hour, and darkness came over the whole land until the ninth hour <verse-number id="Lk 23:45">45</verse-number><supplied>because</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“failed”) which is understood as causal</note> <supplied>the light</supplied> of the sun failed. And the curtain of the temple was torn apart <supplied>down</supplied> the middle. <verse-number id="Lk 23:46">46</verse-number>And Jesus, calling out with a loud voice, said, “Father, into your hands I entrust my spirit!”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 31:5">Ps 31:5</cite></note> And <supplied>after he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“said”) which is understood as temporal</note> said this, he expired. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 23:47">47</verse-number>Now <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> the centurion saw what had happened, he began to praise<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to praise”)</note> God, saying, “Certainly this man was righteous!” <verse-number id="Lk 23:48">48</verse-number>And all the crowds that had come together for this spectacle, <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> saw the things that had happened, returned <supplied>home</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The word “<supplied>home</supplied>” is not in the Greek text, but is implied</note> beating <supplied>their</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> breasts. <verse-number id="Lk 23:49">49</verse-number>And all his acquaintances, and the women who had followed him from Galilee who saw these <supplied>things</supplied>, stood at a distance. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus Is Buried</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 23:50">50</verse-number>And behold, a man <idiom-start/>named<idiom-end/><note>Literally “by name”</note> Joseph, who was a member of the council,<note>Or “a member of the Sanhedrin”</note> a good<note>Some manuscripts have “and a good”</note> and righteous man <verse-number id="Lk 23:51">51</verse-number>(this man was not consenting to their plan and deed), from Arimathea, <idiom-start/>a Judean town<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “a town of the Jews”</note> who was looking forward to the kingdom of God. <verse-number id="Lk 23:52">52</verse-number>This man approached Pilate <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“approached”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> asked for the body of Jesus. <verse-number id="Lk 23:53">53</verse-number>And he took <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> down <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“wrapped”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> wrapped it in a linen cloth and placed him in a tomb cut into the rock where no one had ever been placed. <verse-number id="Lk 23:54">54</verse-number>And it was the day of preparation, and the Sabbath was drawing near. <verse-number id="Lk 23:55">55</verse-number>And the women who had been accompanying him from Galilee followed <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“followed”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> saw the tomb and how his body was placed. <verse-number id="Lk 23:56">56</verse-number>And they returned <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“returned”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> prepared fragrant spices and perfumes, and on the Sabbath they rested according to the commandment. </p>
		</chapter>