<chapter id="Lk 24">
			<pericope>Jesus Is Raised</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 24:1">1</verse-number> Now on the first <supplied>day</supplied> of the week, at very early dawn, they came back to the tomb bringing the fragrant spices which they had prepared. <verse-number id="Lk 24:2">2</verse-number>And they found the stone had been rolled away from the tomb, <verse-number id="Lk 24:3">3</verse-number>but <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“went in”) which is understood as temporal</note> went in, they did not find the body.<note>Some manuscripts add “of the Lord Jesus”</note> <verse-number id="Lk 24:4">4</verse-number>And it happened that while they were perplexed about this, behold, two men in gleaming clothing stood near them. <verse-number id="Lk 24:5">5</verse-number>And <supplied>as</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participles (“were” and “bowed”)</note> they were terrified and bowed their faces to the ground, they said to them, “Why are you looking for the living among the dead? <verse-number id="Lk 24:6">6</verse-number>He is not here, but has been raised! Remember how he spoke to you <supplied>while he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was”) which is understood as temporal</note> was still in Galilee, <verse-number id="Lk 24:7">7</verse-number>saying that the Son of Man must be delivered into the hands of men <supplied>who are</supplied> sinners, and be crucified, and on the third day rise?” <verse-number id="Lk 24:8">8</verse-number>And they remembered his words, <verse-number id="Lk 24:9">9</verse-number>and <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“returned”) which is understood as temporal</note> returned from the tomb, they reported all these <supplied>things</supplied> to the eleven and to all the rest. <verse-number id="Lk 24:10">10</verse-number>Now Mary Magdalene and Joanna and Mary the <supplied>mother</supplied> of James and the others with them were telling these <supplied>things</supplied> to the apostles. <verse-number id="Lk 24:11">11</verse-number>And these words appeared to them as nonsense, and they refused to believe them. <verse-number id="Lk 24:12">12</verse-number>But Peter got up <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“got up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> ran to the tomb, and bending over to look, he saw only the <supplied>strips of</supplied> linen cloth, and he went away to his home<note>Or “wondering to himself,” if the prepositional phrase modifies the following participle</note> wondering what had happened. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus Encountered on the Road to Emmaus</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 24:13">13</verse-number>And behold, on <supplied>that</supplied> same day, two of them were traveling to a village <idiom-start/>named<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to which the name”</note> Emmaus <supplied>that was</supplied> sixty stadia<note>A “stade” or “stadium” (plur. “stadia”) is about 607 ft (187 m)</note> distant from Jerusalem, <verse-number id="Lk 24:14">14</verse-number>and they were conversing with one another about all these <supplied>things</supplied> that had happened. <verse-number id="Lk 24:15">15</verse-number>And it happened that while they were conversing, and discussing, Jesus himself also approached <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“approached”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> began to go along with<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to go along with”)</note> them, <verse-number id="Lk 24:16">16</verse-number>but their eyes were prevented from recognizing him. <verse-number id="Lk 24:17">17</verse-number>And he said to them, “What <supplied>are</supplied> these matters that you are discussing with one another <supplied>as you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“walking along”) which is understood as temporal</note> are walking along?” And they stood still, looking sad. <verse-number id="Lk 24:18">18</verse-number>And one <supplied>of them</supplied>, <idiom-start/>named<idiom-end/><note>Literally “by name”</note> Cleopas, answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to him, “<supplied>Are</supplied> you the only one living near Jerusalem and not knowing the things that have happened in it in these days?” <verse-number id="Lk 24:19">19</verse-number>And he said to them, “What <supplied>things</supplied>?” So they said to him, “The things concerning Jesus the Nazarene, a man who was a prophet, powerful in deed and word before God and all the people, <verse-number id="Lk 24:20">20</verse-number>and how our chief priests and rulers handed him over to a sentence of death, and crucified him. <verse-number id="Lk 24:21">21</verse-number>But we were hoping that he was the one who was going to redeem Israel. But in addition to all these <supplied>things</supplied>, this <supplied>is</supplied> the third day <idiom-start/>since<idiom-end/><note>Literally “he spends from which”</note> these <supplied>things</supplied> took place. <verse-number id="Lk 24:22">22</verse-number>But also some women from among us astonished us, who were at the tomb early in the morning, <verse-number id="Lk 24:23">23</verse-number>and <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“find”) which is understood as temporal</note> did not find his body, they came back saying <supplied>they</supplied> had seen even a vision of angels, who said <supplied>that</supplied> he was alive! <verse-number id="Lk 24:24">24</verse-number>And some of those with us went out to the tomb and found <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> like this, just as the women had also said, but him they did not see.” <verse-number id="Lk 24:25">25</verse-number>And he said to them, “O foolish and slow in heart to believe in all that the prophets have spoken! <verse-number id="Lk 24:26">26</verse-number>Was it not necessary <supplied>that</supplied> the Christ suffer these <supplied>things</supplied> and enter into his glory?” <verse-number id="Lk 24:27">27</verse-number>And beginning from Moses and from all the prophets, he interpreted to them the things concerning himself in all the scriptures. <verse-number id="Lk 24:28">28</verse-number>And they drew near to the village where they were going, and he acted as though he was going farther. <verse-number id="Lk 24:29">29</verse-number>And they urged him strongly, saying, “Stay with us, because it is <supplied>getting</supplied> toward evening, and by this time the day is far spent.” And he went in to stay with them. <verse-number id="Lk 24:30">30</verse-number>And it happened that when he reclined at the table with them, he took the bread <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“took”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> gave thanks, and <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“breaking”) which is understood as temporal</note> breaking <supplied>it</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> he gave <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to them. <verse-number id="Lk 24:31">31</verse-number>And their eyes were opened, and they recognized him, and he became invisible to them. <verse-number id="Lk 24:32">32</verse-number>And they said to one another, “Were not our hearts burning within us while he was speaking with us on the road, while he was explaining the scriptures to us?” <verse-number id="Lk 24:33">33</verse-number>And they got up <supplied>that</supplied> same hour <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“got up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> returned to Jerusalem and found the eleven and those with them assembled, <verse-number id="Lk 24:34">34</verse-number>saying, “The Lord has really been raised, and has appeared to Simon!” <verse-number id="Lk 24:35">35</verse-number>And they began describing<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began describing”)</note> <idiom-start/>what happened<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the things”</note> on the road, and how he was recognized by them in the breaking of the bread. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus Appears to His Disciples</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 24:36">36</verse-number>And <supplied>while</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“were saying”)</note> they were saying these <supplied>things</supplied>, he himself stood there among them.<note>Some manuscripts add “and said to them, ‘Peace to you!’ ”</note> <verse-number id="Lk 24:37">37</verse-number>But they were startled and became terrified, <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the two previous participles (“startled” and “terrified”) have been translated as finite verbs</note> thought <supplied>they</supplied> had seen a ghost. <verse-number id="Lk 24:38">38</verse-number>And he said to them, “Why are you frightened? And for what <supplied>reason</supplied> do doubts arise in your hearts? <verse-number id="Lk 24:39">39</verse-number>Look at my hands and my feet, that I am I myself! Touch me and see, because a ghost does not have flesh and bones, as <idiom-start/>you see that I have<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “you see me having”</note> <verse-number id="Lk 24:40">40</verse-number>And <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had said”) which is understood as temporal</note> had said this, he showed them <supplied>his</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> hands and <supplied>his</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> feet. <verse-number id="Lk 24:41">41</verse-number>And <supplied>while</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“disbelieving”)</note> they were still disbelieving because of joy and were marveling, he said to them, “Do you have anything <idiom-start/>to eat<idiom-end/><note>Literally “eatable”</note> here?” <verse-number id="Lk 24:42">42</verse-number>So they gave him a piece of broiled fish, <verse-number id="Lk 24:43">43</verse-number>and he took <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“took”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> ate <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> in front of them. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus Commissions His Disciples</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 24:44">44</verse-number>And he said to them, “These <supplied>are</supplied> my words that I spoke to you <supplied>while I</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was”) which is understood as temporal</note> was still with you, that everything that is written about me in the law of Moses and the prophets and psalms must be fulfilled.” <verse-number id="Lk 24:45">45</verse-number>Then he opened their minds to understand the scriptures, <verse-number id="Lk 24:46">46</verse-number>and said to them, “Thus it is written <supplied>that</supplied> the Christ would suffer and would rise from the dead on the third day, <verse-number id="Lk 24:47">47</verse-number>and repentance and the forgiveness<note>Some manuscripts have “repentance for the forgiveness”</note> of sins would be proclaimed in his name to all the nations,<note>The same Greek word can be translated “nations” or “Gentiles” depending on the context</note> beginning from Jerusalem. <verse-number id="Lk 24:48">48</verse-number>You are witnesses of these <supplied>things</supplied>. <verse-number id="Lk 24:49">49</verse-number>And behold, I am sending out<note>Some manuscripts have “am sending”</note> what was promised by my Father upon you, but you stay in the city until you are clothed with power from on high.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Ascension</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Lk 24:50">50</verse-number>And he led them out as far as Bethany, and lifting up his hands, he blessed them. <verse-number id="Lk 24:51">51</verse-number>And it happened that while he was blessing them, he parted from them and was taken up into heaven. <verse-number id="Lk 24:52">52</verse-number>And they worshiped him <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“worshiped”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> returned to Jerusalem with great joy. <verse-number id="Lk 24:53">53</verse-number>And they were <idiom-start/>continually<idiom-end/><note>Literally “through everything”</note> in the temple <supplied>courts</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>courts</supplied>” is supplied to distinguish this area from the interior of the temple building itself</note> praising God. </p>
		</chapter>