<chapter id="Ezr 2">
			<pericope>The List of Returned Exiles</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ezr 2:1">1</verse-number>Now these were the people<note>Or “sons”</note> of the province who came up from the captivity of the exile whom Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon carried captive to Babylonia. They returned to Jerusalem and Judah, each to his <supplied>own</supplied> city. <verse-number id="Ezr 2:2">2</verse-number>They came with Zerubbabel, Jeshua, Nehemiah, Seraiah, Reelaiah, Mordecai, Bilshan, Mispar, Bigvai, Rehum, and Baanah. </p>
			<p>The number of the men of the people of Israel: <verse-number id="Ezr 2:3">3</verse-number>the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Parosh, two thousand one hundred and seventy-two; <verse-number id="Ezr 2:4">4</verse-number>the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Shephatiah, three hundred and seventy-two; <verse-number id="Ezr 2:5">5</verse-number>the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Arah, seven hundred and seventy-five; <verse-number id="Ezr 2:6">6</verse-number>the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Pahath-moab, <supplied>particularly</supplied> the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Jeshua and Joab, two thousand eight hundred and twelve; <verse-number id="Ezr 2:7">7</verse-number>the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Elam, one thousand two hundred and fifty-four; <verse-number id="Ezr 2:8">8</verse-number>the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Zattu, nine hundred and forty-five; <verse-number id="Ezr 2:9">9</verse-number>the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Zaccai, seven hundred and sixty; <verse-number id="Ezr 2:10">10</verse-number>the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Bani, six hundred and forty-two; <verse-number id="Ezr 2:11">11</verse-number>the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Bebai, six hundred and twenty-three; <verse-number id="Ezr 2:12">12</verse-number>the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Azgad, one thousand two hundred and twenty-two; <verse-number id="Ezr 2:13">13</verse-number>the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Adonikam, six hundred and sixty-six; <verse-number id="Ezr 2:14">14</verse-number>the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Bigvai, two thousand fifty-six; <verse-number id="Ezr 2:15">15</verse-number>the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Adin, four hundred and fifty-four; <verse-number id="Ezr 2:16">16</verse-number>the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Ater, <supplied>particularly</supplied> of Hezekiah, ninety-eight; <verse-number id="Ezr 2:17">17</verse-number>the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Bezai, three hundred and twenty-three; <verse-number id="Ezr 2:18">18</verse-number>the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Jorah, one hundred and twelve; <verse-number id="Ezr 2:19">19</verse-number>the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Hashum, two hundred and twenty-three; <verse-number id="Ezr 2:20">20</verse-number>the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Gibbar, ninety-five; <verse-number id="Ezr 2:21">21</verse-number>the people<note>Or “sons”</note> of Bethlehem, one hundred and twenty-three; <verse-number id="Ezr 2:22">22</verse-number>the men of Netophah, fifty-six; <verse-number id="Ezr 2:23">23</verse-number>the men of Anathoth, one hundred and twenty-eight; <verse-number id="Ezr 2:24">24</verse-number>the people<note>Or “sons”</note> of Azmaveth, forty-two; <verse-number id="Ezr 2:25">25</verse-number>the people<note>Or “sons”</note> of Kiriath Αrim, Kephirah, and Beeroth, seven hundred and forty-three; <verse-number id="Ezr 2:26">26</verse-number>the people<note>Or “sons”</note> of Ramah and Geba, six hundred and twenty-one; <verse-number id="Ezr 2:27">27</verse-number>the men of Micmash, one hundred and twenty-two; <verse-number id="Ezr 2:28">28</verse-number>the men of Bethel and Ai, two hundred and twenty-three; <verse-number id="Ezr 2:29">29</verse-number>the people<note>Or “sons”</note> of Nebo, fifty-two; <verse-number id="Ezr 2:30">30</verse-number>the people<note>Or “sons”</note> of Magbish, one hundred and fifty-six; <verse-number id="Ezr 2:31">31</verse-number>the people<note>Or “sons”</note> of the other Elam, one thousand two hundred and fifty-four; <verse-number id="Ezr 2:32">32</verse-number>the people<note>Or “sons”</note> of Harim, three hundred and twenty; <verse-number id="Ezr 2:33">33</verse-number>the people<note>Or “sons”</note> of Lod, Hadid, and Ono, seven hundred and twenty-five; <verse-number id="Ezr 2:34">34</verse-number>the people<note>Or “sons”</note> of Jericho, three hundred and forty-five; <verse-number id="Ezr 2:35">35</verse-number>the people<note>Or “sons”</note> of Senaah, three thousand six hundred and thirty. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ezr 2:36">36</verse-number>The priests: the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Jedaiah, of the house of Jeshua, nine hundred and seventy-three; <verse-number id="Ezr 2:37">37</verse-number>the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Immer, one thousand fifty-two; <verse-number id="Ezr 2:38">38</verse-number>the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Pashhur, one thousand two hundred and forty-seven; <verse-number id="Ezr 2:39">39</verse-number>the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Harim, one thousand seventeen. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ezr 2:40">40</verse-number>The Levites: the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Jeshua and Kadmiel, of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Hodaviah, seventy-four. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ezr 2:41">41</verse-number>The singers: the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Asaph, one hundred and twenty-eight. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ezr 2:42">42</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of the gatekeepers: the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Shallum, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Ater, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Talmon, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Akkub, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Hatita, and the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Shobai; in total one hundred and thirty-nine. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ezr 2:43">43</verse-number>The temple servants: the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Ziha, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Hasupha, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Tabbaoth, <verse-number id="Ezr 2:44">44</verse-number>the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Keros, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Siaha, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Padon, <verse-number id="Ezr 2:45">45</verse-number>the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Lebanah, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Hagabah, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Akkub, <verse-number id="Ezr 2:46">46</verse-number>the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Hagab, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Shamlai, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Hanan, <verse-number id="Ezr 2:47">47</verse-number>the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Giddel, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Gahar, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Reaiah, <verse-number id="Ezr 2:48">48</verse-number>the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Rezin, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Nekoda, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Gazzam, <verse-number id="Ezr 2:49">49</verse-number>the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Uzza, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Paseah, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Besai, <verse-number id="Ezr 2:50">50</verse-number>the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Asnah, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Meunim, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Nephisim, <verse-number id="Ezr 2:51">51</verse-number>the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Bakbuk, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Hakupha, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Harhur, <verse-number id="Ezr 2:52">52</verse-number>the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Bazluth, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Mehida, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Harsha, <verse-number id="Ezr 2:53">53</verse-number>the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Barkos, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Sisera, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Temah, <verse-number id="Ezr 2:54">54</verse-number>the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Neziah, and the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Hatipha. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ezr 2:55">55</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Solomon’s servants: the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Sotai, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Hassophereth, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Peruda, <verse-number id="Ezr 2:56">56</verse-number>the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Jaalah, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Darkon, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Giddel, <verse-number id="Ezr 2:57">57</verse-number>the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Shephatiah, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Hattil, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Pochereth-hazzebaim, and the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Ami. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ezr 2:58">58</verse-number>All the temple servants and the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Solomon’s servants were three hundred and ninety-two. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ezr 2:59">59</verse-number>Now these were the ones who came up from Tel-melah, Tel-harsha, Cherub, Addan, and Immer, but they were not able to prove their fathers’ household and their descent, if they were from Israel: <verse-number id="Ezr 2:60">60</verse-number>the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Delaiah, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Tobiah, and the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Nekoda, six hundred and fifty-two. <verse-number id="Ezr 2:61">61</verse-number>And from the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of the priests: the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Habaiah, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Hakkoz, and the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Barzillai (who took a wife from the daughters of Barzillai the Gileadite, and was called by their name). <verse-number id="Ezr 2:62">62</verse-number>These sought their record in the genealogy <supplied>records</supplied>, but they were not found, and <idiom-start/>were excluded from the priesthood as unclean<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “they were unclean from the priesthood”</note> <verse-number id="Ezr 2:63">63</verse-number>The governor said to them that they could not eat from the holy food of the sanctuary<note>Or “most holy things”</note> until there was present a priest for the Urim and Thummim. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ezr 2:64">64</verse-number>The whole assembly together was forty-two thousand three hundred and sixty, <verse-number id="Ezr 2:65">65</verse-number>apart from their male and female servants, of whom were seven thousand three hundred and thirty-seven; and they had two hundred male and female singers. <verse-number id="Ezr 2:66">66</verse-number>Their horses <supplied>numbered</supplied> seven hundred and thirty-six, their mules <supplied>numbered</supplied> two hundred and forty-five, <verse-number id="Ezr 2:67">67</verse-number>their camels <supplied>numbered</supplied> four hundred and thirty-five, their donkeys <supplied>numbered</supplied> six thousand seven hundred and twenty. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Gifts Given for Temple Work</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ezr 2:68">68</verse-number>When <supplied>some</supplied> of the heads of <idiom-start/>families<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the fathers”</note> came to the house of Yahweh that <supplied>is</supplied> in Jerusalem, they gave freewill offerings for the house of God to erect it on its place. <verse-number id="Ezr 2:69">69</verse-number>According to their ability they gave to the treasury room for the work sixty-one thousand darics of gold, five thousand minas of silver, and one hundred priestly tunics. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ezr 2:70">70</verse-number>The priests, the Levites, and some of the people lived <supplied>in Jerusalem</supplied>, and the singers, the gatekeepers, and the temple servants <supplied>lived</supplied> in their cities, and all Israel in their cities. </p>
		</chapter>