<chapter id="Ac 1">
			<pericope>The Preface</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 1:1">1</verse-number> I produced the former account, O Theophilus, about all <idiom-start/>that<idiom-end/><note>Literally “of what”</note> Jesus began to do and to teach, <verse-number id="Ac 1:2">2</verse-number>until the day he was taken up, <supplied>after he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had given orders”) which is understood as temporal</note> had given orders through the Holy Spirit to the apostles whom he had chosen, <verse-number id="Ac 1:3">3</verse-number>to whom he also presented himself alive after he suffered, with many convincing proofs, appearing to them over a period of forty days and speaking the things about the kingdom of God. <verse-number id="Ac 1:4">4</verse-number>And <supplied>while he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was with”) which is understood as temporal</note> was with<note>Or “was assembling with,” or “was sharing a meal with”</note> <supplied>them</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> he commanded them, “Do not depart from Jerusalem, but wait for what was promised by the Father, which you heard about from me. <verse-number id="Ac 1:5">5</verse-number>For John baptized with water, but you will be baptized with the Holy Spirit <idiom-start/>not many days from now<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “not many days after these”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Ascension</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 1:6">6</verse-number>So <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had come together”) which is understood as temporal</note> they had come together, they began asking<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began asking”)</note> him, saying, “Lord, <supplied>is it</supplied> at this time you are restoring the kingdom to Israel?” <verse-number id="Ac 1:7">7</verse-number>But he said to them, “It is not for you to know <supplied>the</supplied> times or seasons that the Father has set by his own authority. <verse-number id="Ac 1:8">8</verse-number>But you will receive power <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“has come”)</note> the Holy Spirit has come upon you, and you will be my witnesses in Jerusalem, and in all Judea and Samaria, and to the farthest part of the earth.” <verse-number id="Ac 1:9">9</verse-number>And <supplied>after he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had said”) which is understood as temporal</note> had said these <supplied>things</supplied>, <supplied>while</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“were watching”)</note> they were watching, he was taken up, and a cloud received him from their sight. <verse-number id="Ac 1:10">10</verse-number>And as they were staring into the sky <supplied>while</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was departing”)</note> he was departing, behold, two men in white clothing stood by them <verse-number id="Ac 1:11">11</verse-number>who also said, “Men <idiom-start/>of Galilee<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “Galileans”</note> why do you stand there looking<note>Some manuscripts have “gazing”</note> into the sky? This Jesus who was taken up from you into heaven like this will come back in the same way you saw him departing into heaven!” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Matthias Chosen to Replace Judas</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 1:12">12</verse-number>Then they returned to Jerusalem from the mountain that is called Olive Grove<note>This is a variation of the name “Mount of Olives”</note> which is near Jerusalem, <idiom-start/>a Sabbath day’s journey away<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “having a journey of a Sabbath”</note> <verse-number id="Ac 1:13">13</verse-number>And when they had entered, they went up to the upstairs room where they were staying—Peter and John and James and Andrew, Philip and Thomas, Bartholomew and Matthew, James <supplied>son</supplied> of Alphaeus and Simon the Zealot and Judas <supplied>son</supplied> of James. <verse-number id="Ac 1:14">14</verse-number>All these were busily engaged with one mind in prayer, together with the women and Mary the mother of Jesus and with<note>Some manuscripts omit “with”</note> his brothers. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 1:15">15</verse-number>And in those days Peter stood up in the midst of the brothers (and it was a crowd of persons of about one hundred twenty at the same <supplied>place</supplied>) <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“stood up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, <verse-number id="Ac 1:16">16</verse-number>“Men <supplied>and</supplied> brothers, it was necessary <supplied>that</supplied> the scripture be fulfilled, which the Holy Spirit proclaimed beforehand through the mouth of David concerning Judas, who became a guide to those who arrested Jesus, <verse-number id="Ac 1:17">17</verse-number>because he was counted among us and received a share in this ministry.” <verse-number id="Ac 1:18">18</verse-number>(Now this man acquired a field for the wages of <supplied>his</supplied> wickedness, and falling headlong, he burst open in the middle and all his intestines spilled out. <verse-number id="Ac 1:19">19</verse-number>And it became known to all who live in Jerusalem, so that that field was called in their own language<note>That is, Aramaic</note> “Akeldama,” that is, “Field of Blood.”) <verse-number id="Ac 1:20">20</verse-number>“For it is written in the book of Psalms, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>‘Let his residence become deserted, </li1>
				<li2>and let there be no one to live in it,’<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 69:25">Ps 69:25</cite></note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p>and, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>‘Let another person take his position.’<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 109:8">Ps 109:8</cite></note> </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 1:21">21</verse-number>Therefore it is necessary for <supplied>one</supplied> of the men who have accompanied us during all the time <supplied>in</supplied> which the Lord Jesus went in and went out among us, <verse-number id="Ac 1:22">22</verse-number>beginning from the baptism of John until the day <supplied>on</supplied> which he was taken up from us—one of these <supplied>men</supplied> must become a witness of his resurrection together with us.” <verse-number id="Ac 1:23">23</verse-number>And they proposed two <supplied>men</supplied>, Joseph called Barsabbas (who was called Justus) and Matthias. <verse-number id="Ac 1:24">24</verse-number>And they prayed <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“prayed”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “You, Lord, who know the hearts of all, show clearly which one of these two you have chosen <verse-number id="Ac 1:25">25</verse-number>to take the place in this ministry and apostleship from which Judas turned aside to depart to his own place.” <verse-number id="Ac 1:26">26</verse-number>And they cast lots for them, and the lot fell on Matthias, and he was added <supplied>to serve</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The words “<supplied>to serve</supplied>” are not in the Greek text, but are implied</note> with the eleven apostles. </p>
		</chapter>