<chapter id="Ac 2">
			<pericope>Pentecost and the Coming of the Holy Spirit</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 2:1">1</verse-number> And when the day of Pentecost had come, they were all together in the same <supplied>place</supplied>. <verse-number id="Ac 2:2">2</verse-number>And suddenly a sound like a violent rushing wind came from heaven and filled the whole house where they were sitting. <verse-number id="Ac 2:3">3</verse-number>And divided<note>Or perhaps “distributed”</note> tongues like fire appeared to them and rested on each one of them. <verse-number id="Ac 2:4">4</verse-number>And they were all filled with the Holy Spirit and began to speak in other languages<note>Or “tongues”</note> as the Spirit gave them <supplied>ability</supplied> to speak out. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 2:5">5</verse-number>Now there were Jews residing in Jerusalem, devout men from every nation under heaven. <verse-number id="Ac 2:6">6</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“happened”)</note> this sound occurred, the crowd gathered and was in confusion, because each one was hearing them speaking in his own language. <verse-number id="Ac 2:7">7</verse-number>And they were astounded and astonished, saying, “Behold, are not all these who are speaking Galileans? <verse-number id="Ac 2:8">8</verse-number>And how do we hear, each one <supplied>of us</supplied>, in <idiom-start/>our own native language<idiom-end/>?<note>Literally “our own language in which we were born”</note> <verse-number id="Ac 2:9">9</verse-number>Parthians and Medes and Elamites and those residing <supplied>in</supplied> Mesopotamia, Judea and Cappadocia, Pontus and Asia,<note>A reference to the Roman province of Asia (modern Asia Minor)</note> <verse-number id="Ac 2:10">10</verse-number>Phrygia and Pamphylia, Egypt and the parts of Libya toward Cyrene, and the Romans who were in town, <verse-number id="Ac 2:11">11</verse-number>both Jews and proselytes, Cretans and Arabs—we hear them speaking in our <supplied>own</supplied> languages the great deeds of God!” <verse-number id="Ac 2:12">12</verse-number>And all were amazed and greatly perplexed, saying <idiom-start/>to one another<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “one to the other”</note> “<idiom-start/>What can this mean?<idiom-end/>”<note>Literally “what does this want to be”</note> <verse-number id="Ac 2:13">13</verse-number>But others jeered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“jeered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “They are full of sweet new wine!” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Peter’s Sermon on the Day of Pentecost</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 2:14">14</verse-number>But Peter, standing with the eleven, raised his voice and declared to them, “Judean men, and all those who live <supplied>in</supplied> Jerusalem, let this be known to you, and pay attention to my words! <verse-number id="Ac 2:15">15</verse-number>For these <supplied>men</supplied> are not drunk, as you assume, because it is the third hour of the day. <verse-number id="Ac 2:16">16</verse-number>But this is what was spoken through the prophet Joel: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ac 2:17">17</verse-number>‘And it will be in the last days,’ God says, </li1>
				<li2>‘I will pour out my Spirit on all flesh, </li2>
				<li3>and your sons and your daughters will prophesy, </li3>
				<li3>and your young men will see visions, </li3>
				<li3>and your old men will dream dreams. </li3>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ac 2:18">18</verse-number>And even on my male slaves and on my female slaves </li1>
				<li2>I will pour out my Spirit in those days, and they will prophesy. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ac 2:19">19</verse-number>And I will cause wonders in the heaven<note>Or “sky”</note> above </li1>
				<li2>and signs on the earth below, </li2>
				<li2>blood and fire and vapor of smoke. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ac 2:20">20</verse-number>The sun will be changed to darkness </li1>
				<li2>and the moon to blood, </li2>
				<li2>before the great and glorious day of the Lord comes. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ac 2:21">21</verse-number>And it will be <supplied>that</supplied> everyone who calls upon the name of the Lord will be saved.’<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Joe 2:28–32">Joel 2:28–32</cite></note> </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 2:22">22</verse-number>“Israelite men, listen to these words! Jesus the Nazarene, a man attested to you by God with deeds of power and wonders and signs that God did through him in your midst, just as <supplied>you</supplied> yourselves know—<verse-number id="Ac 2:23">23</verse-number>this man, delivered up by the determined plan and foreknowledge of God, you executed <supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“nailing to”) which is understood as means</note> nailing to <supplied>a cross</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The words “<supplied>a cross</supplied>” are not in the Greek text but are implied by the nature of the verb</note> through the hand of lawless men. <verse-number id="Ac 2:24">24</verse-number>God raised <idiom-start/>him<idiom-end/><note>Literally “whom”; it is necessary to specify “him” in the translation to avoid confusion with the “lawless men” in the previous verse</note> up, having brought to an end the pains of death, because it was not possible <supplied>for</supplied> him to be held by it. <verse-number id="Ac 2:25">25</verse-number>For David says with reference to him, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>‘I saw the Lord before me <idiom-start/>continually<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “through everything”</note> </li1>
				<li2>for he is at my right hand so that I will not be shaken. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ac 2:26">26</verse-number>For this <supplied>reason</supplied> my heart was glad </li1>
				<li2>and my tongue rejoiced greatly, </li2>
				<li2>furthermore also my flesh will live in hope, </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ac 2:27">27</verse-number>because you will not abandon my soul in Hades, </li1>
				<li2>nor will you permit your Holy One to experience decay. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ac 2:28">28</verse-number>You have made known to me the paths of life; </li1>
				<li2>you will fill me with gladness with your presence.’<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 16:8–11">Ps 16:8–11</cite></note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 2:29">29</verse-number>“Men <supplied>and</supplied> brothers, it is possible to speak with confidence to you about the patriarch David, that he both died and was buried, and his tomb is with us until this day. <verse-number id="Ac 2:30">30</verse-number>Therefore, <supplied>because he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was”) which is understood as causal</note> was a prophet and knew that God had sworn to him with an oath to seat <idiom-start/>one of his descendants<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from the fruit of his loins”</note> on his throne, <verse-number id="Ac 2:31">31</verse-number><supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“having foreseen”) which is understood as means</note> having foreseen <supplied>this</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> he spoke about the resurrection of the Christ,<note>Or “Messiah”</note> that neither was he abandoned in Hades nor did his flesh experience decay. <verse-number id="Ac 2:32">32</verse-number>This Jesus God raised up, of which<note>Or “of whom,” referring to Jesus</note> we all are witnesses. <verse-number id="Ac 2:33">33</verse-number>Therefore, having been exalted to the right hand of God and having received the promise of the Holy Spirit from the Father, he has poured out this that you see and hear.<note>Some manuscripts have “both see and hear”</note> <verse-number id="Ac 2:34">34</verse-number>For David did not ascend into heaven, but he himself says, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>‘The Lord said to my Lord, </li1>
				<li1>“Sit at my right hand, </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ac 2:35">35</verse-number>until I make your enemies a footstool for your feet.” ’<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 110:1">Ps 110:1</cite></note> </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 2:36">36</verse-number>Therefore let all the house of Israel know beyond a doubt, that God has made him both Lord and Christ—this Jesus whom you crucified!” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Response to Peter’s Sermon</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 2:37">37</verse-number>Now <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> heard <supplied>this</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> they were pierced to the heart and said to Peter and the other apostles, “What should we do, men <supplied>and</supplied> brothers?” <verse-number id="Ac 2:38">38</verse-number>And Peter <supplied>said</supplied><note>Some manuscripts explicitly add “said”</note> to them, “Repent and be baptized, each one of you, in the name of Jesus Christ for the forgiveness of your sins, and you will receive the gift of the Holy Spirit. <verse-number id="Ac 2:39">39</verse-number>For the promise is for you and for your children, and for all those <supplied>who are</supplied> far away, as many as the Lord our God calls to himself.” <verse-number id="Ac 2:40">40</verse-number>And with many other words he solemnly urged and exhorted them, saying, “Be saved from this crooked generation!” <verse-number id="Ac 2:41">41</verse-number>So those who accepted his message were baptized, and on that day about three thousand souls were added. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Fellowship of the First Believers</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 2:42">42</verse-number>And they were devoting themselves to the teaching of the apostles and to fellowship, to the breaking of bread and to prayers. <verse-number id="Ac 2:43">43</verse-number>And fear came on every soul, and many wonders and signs were being performed by the apostles. <verse-number id="Ac 2:44">44</verse-number>And all who believed were in the same <supplied>place</supplied>, and had everything in common. <verse-number id="Ac 2:45">45</verse-number>And they began selling<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began selling”)</note> <supplied>their</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> possessions and property, and distributing these <supplied>things</supplied> to all, to the degree that anyone had need. <verse-number id="Ac 2:46">46</verse-number>And every day, devoting themselves <supplied>to meeting</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The words “<supplied>to meeting</supplied>” are not in the Greek text but are implied</note> with one purpose in the temple <supplied>courts</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>courts</supplied>” is supplied to distinguish this area from the interior of the temple building itself</note> and breaking bread from house <supplied>to house</supplied>, they were eating <supplied>their</supplied> food with joy and simplicity of heart, <verse-number id="Ac 2:47">47</verse-number>praising God and having favor with all the people. And the Lord was adding every day to the total <supplied>of</supplied> those who were being saved. </p>
		</chapter>