<chapter id="Ac 4">
			<pericope>Peter and John Arrested</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 4:1">1</verse-number> And <supplied>while</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“were speaking”)</note> they were speaking to the people, the priests and the captain of the temple and the Sadducees approached them, <verse-number id="Ac 4:2">2</verse-number>greatly annoyed because they were teaching the people and proclaiming in Jesus the resurrection from the dead. <verse-number id="Ac 4:3">3</verse-number>And they laid hands on them and put <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> in custody until the next day, because it was already evening. <verse-number id="Ac 4:4">4</verse-number>But many of those who listened to the message believed, and the number of the men was approximately five thousand. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Peter and John on Trial Before the Sanhedrin</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 4:5">5</verse-number>And it happened that on the next day, their rulers and elders and scribes came together in Jerusalem, <verse-number id="Ac 4:6">6</verse-number>and Annas the high priest, and Caiaphas and John and Alexander, and all those who were from the high priest’s family. <verse-number id="Ac 4:7">7</verse-number>And they made them stand in <supplied>their</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> midst <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“stand”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> began to ask,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to ask”)</note> “By what power or by what name did you do this?” <verse-number id="Ac 4:8">8</verse-number>Then Peter, filled with the Holy Spirit, said to them, “Rulers of the people and elders, <verse-number id="Ac 4:9">9</verse-number>if we are being examined today concerning a good deed <supplied>done to</supplied> a sick man—by what <supplied>means</supplied><note>Or “through whom”</note> this man was healed—<verse-number id="Ac 4:10">10</verse-number>let it be known to all of you and to all the people of Israel that by the name of Jesus Christ the Nazarene, whom you crucified, whom God raised from the dead—by him this man stands before you healthy! <verse-number id="Ac 4:11">11</verse-number>This one<note>“This one” refers to Jesus</note> is the stone that was rejected by you, the builders, that has become <idiom-start/>the cornerstone<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the head of the corner”; this verse is an allusion to <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 118:22">Ps 118:22</cite></note> <verse-number id="Ac 4:12">12</verse-number>And there is salvation in no one else, for there is no other name under heaven that is given among people by which we must be saved.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 4:13">13</verse-number>Now <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> saw the boldness of Peter and John, and understood that they were uneducated and untrained men, they were astonished, and recognized them, that they had been with Jesus. <verse-number id="Ac 4:14">14</verse-number>And <supplied>because they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as causal</note> saw the man who had been healed standing there with them, they had nothing to say in return. <verse-number id="Ac 4:15">15</verse-number>But <supplied>after they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had ordered”) which is understood as temporal</note> had ordered them to go outside the Sanhedrin,<note>Or “council”</note> they began to confer<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to confer”)</note> with one another, <verse-number id="Ac 4:16">16</verse-number>saying, “What should we do with these men? For that a remarkable sign has taken place through them <supplied>is</supplied> evident to all those who live <supplied>in</supplied> Jerusalem, and we are not able to deny <supplied>it</supplied>!<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <verse-number id="Ac 4:17">17</verse-number>But in order that it may not spread much <supplied>further</supplied> among the people, let us warn them to speak no more in this name <idiom-start/>to anyone at all<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “to no man”</note> <verse-number id="Ac 4:18">18</verse-number>And they called them <supplied>back</supplied> <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“called”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> commanded <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> not to speak or to teach at all in the name of Jesus. <verse-number id="Ac 4:19">19</verse-number>But Peter and John answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to them, “Whether it is right in the sight of God to listen to you rather than God, you decide! <verse-number id="Ac 4:20">20</verse-number>For we are not able to refrain from speaking about <supplied>the things</supplied> that we have seen and heard.” <verse-number id="Ac 4:21">21</verse-number>So <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“threatening … further”) which is understood as temporal</note> threatening <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> further, they released them, finding no way to punish them on account of the people, because they were all praising God for what had happened. <verse-number id="Ac 4:22">22</verse-number>For the man on whom this sign of healing had been performed was more <supplied>than</supplied> forty years <supplied>old</supplied>. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Believers Pray for Continued Bold Witness</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 4:23">23</verse-number>And <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“were released”) which is understood as temporal</note> were released, they went to their own <supplied>people</supplied> and reported all that the chief priests and the elders had said to them. <verse-number id="Ac 4:24">24</verse-number>And <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> heard <supplied>it</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> they lifted <supplied>their</supplied> voices with one mind to God and said, “Master, you <supplied>are</supplied> the one who made the heaven and the earth and the sea and all the things in them, <verse-number id="Ac 4:25">25</verse-number>the one who said by the Holy Spirit through the mouth of our father David, your servant, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>‘Why do the nations<note>Or “Gentiles”; the same Greek word can be translated “nations” or “Gentiles” depending on the context</note> rage, </li1>
				<li2>and the peoples conspire in vain? </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ac 4:26">26</verse-number>The kings of the earth stood opposed, </li1>
				<li2>and the rulers assembled together at the same <supplied>place</supplied>, </li2>
				<li1>against the Lord and against his Christ.’<note>Or “Messiah”; this is a quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 2:1–2">Ps 2:1–2</cite></note> </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 4:27">27</verse-number>For in truth both Herod and Pontius Pilate, together with the Gentiles and the peoples of Israel, assembled together in this city against your holy servant Jesus whom you anointed, <verse-number id="Ac 4:28">28</verse-number>to do all that your hand and plan<note>Some manuscripts have “and your plan”</note> had predestined to take place. <verse-number id="Ac 4:29">29</verse-number>And now, Lord, concern yourself with their threats and grant your slaves to speak your message with all boldness, <verse-number id="Ac 4:30">30</verse-number><supplied>as</supplied> you extend your hand to heal and signs and wonders are performed through the name of your holy servant Jesus.” <verse-number id="Ac 4:31">31</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“had prayed”)</note> they had prayed, the place in which they were gathered was shaken, and they were all filled with the Holy Spirit and began to speak<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to speak”)</note> the word<note>Or “message”</note> of God with boldness. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Believers Share All Things in Common</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 4:32">32</verse-number>Now the group of those who believed were one heart and soul, and no one said anything of what belonged to him was his own, but all <supplied>things</supplied> were theirs in common. <verse-number id="Ac 4:33">33</verse-number>And with great power the apostles were giving testimony <supplied>to</supplied> the resurrection of the Lord Jesus, and great grace was on them all. <verse-number id="Ac 4:34">34</verse-number>For there was not even anyone needy among them, because all those who were owners of plots of land or houses were selling <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“were selling”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> bringing the proceeds of the things that were sold <verse-number id="Ac 4:35">35</verse-number>and placing <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> at the feet of the apostles. And it was being distributed to each as anyone had need. <verse-number id="Ac 4:36">36</verse-number>So Joseph, who was called Barnabas by the apostles (which is translated “son of encouragement”), a Levite of Cyprus by nationality, <verse-number id="Ac 4:37">37</verse-number>sold a field<note>Or “a farm”</note> that belonged to him <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“sold”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> brought the money and placed <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> at the feet of the apostles. </p>
		</chapter>