<chapter id="Ac 5">
			<pericope>Ananias and Sapphira Lie to the Holy Spirit</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 5:1">1</verse-number> Now a certain man <idiom-start/>named<idiom-end/><note>Literally “by name”</note> Ananias, together with his wife Sapphira, sold a piece of property, <verse-number id="Ac 5:2">2</verse-number>and he kept back for himself <supplied>some</supplied> of the proceeds, and <supplied>his</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> wife was aware of <supplied>it</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the participle “was aware of” in this genitive absolute construction has been translated as a finite verb in keeping with English style</note> And he brought a certain part <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“brought”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> placed <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> at the feet of the apostles. <verse-number id="Ac 5:3">3</verse-number>But Peter said, “Ananias, for what <supplied>reason</supplied> has Satan filled your heart, <supplied>that</supplied> you lied to the Holy Spirit and kept back for yourself <supplied>some</supplied> of the proceeds of the piece of land? <verse-number id="Ac 5:4">4</verse-number><supplied>When it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“remained”) which is understood as temporal</note> remained to you, did it not remain <supplied>yours</supplied>? And <supplied>when it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was sold”) which is understood as temporal</note> was sold, was it at your disposal? How <supplied>is it</supplied> that you have contrived this deed in your heart? You have not lied to people, but to God!” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 5:5">5</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> Ananias heard these words, he fell down <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“fell down”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> died. And great fear came on all those who heard about <supplied>it</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <verse-number id="Ac 5:6">6</verse-number>So the young men stood up, wrapped him up, and carried <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> out <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“carried … out”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> buried <supplied>him</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <verse-number id="Ac 5:7">7</verse-number>And it happened that <supplied>there was</supplied> an interval of about three hours, and his wife came in, not knowing what had happened. <verse-number id="Ac 5:8">8</verse-number>And Peter said to her, “Tell me whether you <supplied>both</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>both</supplied>” reflects the second person plural verb, which refers to both Ananias and Sapphira</note> were paid this much <supplied>for</supplied> the piece of land.” And she said, “Yes, this much.” <verse-number id="Ac 5:9">9</verse-number>So Peter <supplied>said</supplied> to her, “How <supplied>is it</supplied> that it was agreed by you <supplied>two</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>two</supplied>” is supplied in the translation to indicate that the pronoun (“you”) is plural in the Greek text</note> to test the Spirit of the Lord? Behold, the feet of those who buried your husband <supplied>are</supplied> at the door, and they will carry you out!” <verse-number id="Ac 5:10">10</verse-number>And immediately she fell down at his feet and died. So <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“came in”) which is understood as temporal</note> the young men came in, they found her dead, and carried <supplied>her</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> out <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“carried … out”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> buried <supplied>her</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> with her husband. <verse-number id="Ac 5:11">11</verse-number>And great fear came on the whole church and on all who heard about these <supplied>things</supplied>. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Many Signs and Wonders Are Performed by the Apostles</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 5:12">12</verse-number>Now many signs and wonders were being performed among the people through the hands of the apostles. And they were all together<note>Or perhaps “by common consent”</note> in Solomon’s Portico. <verse-number id="Ac 5:13">13</verse-number>And none of the rest dared to join them, but the people spoke highly of them. <verse-number id="Ac 5:14">14</verse-number>And even more believers in the Lord<note>Or “even more believers were being added to the Lord”</note> were being added, large numbers of both men and women, <verse-number id="Ac 5:15">15</verse-number>so that they even carried out the sick into the streets and put <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> on cots and mats<note>Or “mattresses”</note> so that <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“came by”)</note> Peter came by, at least <supplied>his</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> shadow would fall on some of them. <verse-number id="Ac 5:16">16</verse-number>And the people of the towns around Jerusalem also came together, bringing the sick and those tormented by unclean spirits, who were all being healed. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Apostles Arrested and Imprisoned</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 5:17">17</verse-number>Now the high priest rose up and all those <supplied>who were</supplied> with him (that is, the party of the Sadducees), <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“rose up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> they were filled with jealousy. <verse-number id="Ac 5:18">18</verse-number>And they laid hands on the apostles and put them in the public prison. <verse-number id="Ac 5:19">19</verse-number>But during the night an angel of the Lord opened the doors of the prison and led them <supplied>out</supplied> <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the two previous participles (“opened” and “led”) have been translated as finite verbs</note> said, <verse-number id="Ac 5:20">20</verse-number>“Go and stand in the temple <supplied>courts</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>courts</supplied>” is supplied to distinguish this area from the interior of the temple building itself</note> <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“stand”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> proclaim to the people all the words of this life.” <verse-number id="Ac 5:21">21</verse-number>And <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> heard <supplied>this</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> they entered at daybreak into the temple <supplied>courts</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>courts</supplied>” is supplied to distinguish this area from the interior of the temple building itself</note> and began teaching.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began teaching”)</note> </p>
			<p>Now <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“arrived”) which is understood as temporal</note> the high priest and those with him arrived, they summoned the Sanhedrin—even the whole council of elders of the sons of Israel—and sent to the prison to have them brought. <verse-number id="Ac 5:22">22</verse-number>But the officers who came<note>Or “<supplied>when they</supplied> came”</note> did not find them in the prison, and they returned <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“returned”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> reported, <verse-number id="Ac 5:23">23</verse-number>saying, “We found the prison locked with all security and the guards standing at the doors, but <supplied>when we</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“opened”) which is understood as temporal</note> opened <supplied>them</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> we found no one inside!” <verse-number id="Ac 5:24">24</verse-number>Now when both the captain of the temple and the chief priests heard these words, they were greatly perplexed concerning them, <supplied>as to</supplied> what this might be. <verse-number id="Ac 5:25">25</verse-number>But someone came <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> reported to them, “Behold, the men whom you put in prison are standing in the temple <supplied>courts</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>courts</supplied>” is supplied to distinguish this area from the interior of the temple building itself</note> and teaching the people!” <verse-number id="Ac 5:26">26</verse-number>Then the captain went with the officers <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> brought them, not with force (for they were afraid of the people, lest they be stoned <supplied>by them</supplied>).<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The words “<supplied>by them</supplied>” are not in the Greek text but are implied</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Apostles on Trial Before the Sanhedrin</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 5:27">27</verse-number>And <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had brought”) which is understood as temporal</note> had brought them, they made <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> stand in the Sanhedrin,<note>Or “council”</note> and the high priest put a question to them, <verse-number id="Ac 5:28">28</verse-number>saying, “<idiom-start/>We strictly commanded<idiom-end/><note>Literally “we commanded with a commandment”</note> you<note>Some manuscripts have “Did we not strictly command you”</note> not to teach in this name? And behold, you have filled Jerusalem with your teaching! And you are intending to bring upon us the blood of this man!” <verse-number id="Ac 5:29">29</verse-number>But Peter and the apostles answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “It is necessary to obey God rather than men! <verse-number id="Ac 5:30">30</verse-number>The God of our fathers raised up Jesus, whom you killed <supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“hanging”) which is understood as means</note> hanging <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> on a tree. <verse-number id="Ac 5:31">31</verse-number>This one God has exalted to his right hand <supplied>as</supplied> Leader and Savior to grant repentance to Israel and forgiveness of sins. <verse-number id="Ac 5:32">32</verse-number>And we are witnesses of these things, and <supplied>so is</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The words “<supplied>so is</supplied>” are not in the Greek text but are implied</note> the Holy Spirit whom God has given to those who obey him.” <verse-number id="Ac 5:33">33</verse-number>Now <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> they heard <supplied>this</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> they were infuriated, and were wanting to execute them. <verse-number id="Ac 5:34">34</verse-number>But a certain man stood up in the Sanhedrin,<note>Or “council”</note> a Pharisee <idiom-start/>named<idiom-end/><note>Literally “by name”</note> Gamaliel, a teacher of the law respected by all the people, <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“stood up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> gave orders to put the men outside for a short time. <verse-number id="Ac 5:35">35</verse-number>And he said to them, “Men <supplied>and</supplied> Israelites, take care for yourselves what you are about to do to these men! <verse-number id="Ac 5:36">36</verse-number>For before these days, Theudas rose up saying he was somebody. A number of men, about four hundred, joined <idiom-start/>him<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to whom”</note> <idiom-start/>He<idiom-end/><note>Literally “who”</note> was executed, and all who followed him were dispersed and came to nothing. <verse-number id="Ac 5:37">37</verse-number>After this man, Judas the Galilean rose up in the days of the census and <idiom-start/>caused people to follow him in revolt<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “caused people to revolt after him”</note> And that one perished, and all who followed him were scattered. <verse-number id="Ac 5:38">38</verse-number>And now I tell you, keep away from these men, and leave them alone, because if this plan or this matter is from people, it will be overthrown.<note>Or “it will fail”</note> <verse-number id="Ac 5:39">39</verse-number>But if it is from God, you will not be able to overthrow them, lest you even be found fighting against God.” So they were persuaded by him. <verse-number id="Ac 5:40">40</verse-number>And they summoned the apostles, beat <supplied>them</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> commanded <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> not to speak in the name of Jesus, and released <supplied>them</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <verse-number id="Ac 5:41">41</verse-number>So they went out from the presence of the Sanhedrin<note>Or “council”</note> rejoicing, because they had been considered worthy to be dishonored for the sake of the name. <verse-number id="Ac 5:42">42</verse-number>Every day, both in the temple <supplied>courts</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>courts</supplied>” is supplied to distinguish this area from the interior of the temple building itself</note> and from house <supplied>to house</supplied>, they did not stop teaching and proclaiming the good news <supplied>that</supplied> the Christ<note>Or “Messiah”</note> <supplied>was</supplied> Jesus. </p>
		</chapter>