<chapter id="Ac 7">
			<pericope>Stephen’s Defense</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 7:1">1</verse-number> And the high priest said, “Is it so concerning these <supplied>things</supplied>?” <verse-number id="Ac 7:2">2</verse-number>So he said, “Men—brothers and fathers—listen: The God of glory appeared to our father Abraham <supplied>while he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was”) which is understood as temporal</note> was in Mesopotamia, before he settled in Haran, <verse-number id="Ac 7:3">3</verse-number>and said to him, ‘Go out from your land and from your relatives and come to the land that I will show you.’ <verse-number id="Ac 7:4">4</verse-number>Then he went out from the land of the Chaldeans <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went out”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> settled in Haran. And from there, after his father died, he caused him to move to this land in which you now live. <verse-number id="Ac 7:5">5</verse-number>And he did not give him an inheritance in it—not even a footstep<note>Literally “a step of a foot”</note>—and he promised to give <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to him for his possession, and to his descendants after him, <idiom-start/>although he did not have<idiom-end/><note>Literally “not being to him”</note><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>although</supplied>” is supplied in the translation as a component of the participle (“was”) which is understood as concessive</note> a child. <verse-number id="Ac 7:6">6</verse-number>But God spoke like this: ‘His descendants will be foreigners in a foreign land, and they will enslave them and mistreat <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> four hundred years, <verse-number id="Ac 7:7">7</verse-number>and the nation <idiom-start/>that<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to which”</note> they will serve as slaves, I will judge,’ God said, ‘and after these <supplied>things</supplied> they will come out<note>Verses <cite title="BibleLEB2:Ac 7:6–7">6–7</cite> are a quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ge 15:13–14">Gen 15:13–14</cite></note> and will worship me in this place.’<note>The final phrase is an allusion to <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ex 3:12">Exod 3:12</cite></note> <verse-number id="Ac 7:8">8</verse-number>And he gave him the covenant of circumcision, and so he became the father of Isaac and circumcised him on the eighth day, and Isaac <supplied>did so with</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the words “<supplied>did so with</supplied>” are not in the Greek text but are implied; in view of the “covenant of circumcision” mentioned earlier in the verse, it is probable that circumcision and not just fatherhood is involved</note> Jacob, and Jacob <supplied>did so with</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the words “<supplied>did so with</supplied>” are not in the Greek text but are implied; see the note on the same phrase earlier in this verse</note> the twelve patriarchs. <verse-number id="Ac 7:9">9</verse-number>And the patriarchs, <supplied>because they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“were jealous of”) which is understood as causal</note> were jealous of Joseph, sold <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> into Egypt. And God was with him, <verse-number id="Ac 7:10">10</verse-number>and rescued him from all his afflictions and granted him favor and wisdom in the sight of Pharaoh king of Egypt. And he appointed him ruler over Egypt and all<note>Some manuscripts have “over all”</note> his household. <verse-number id="Ac 7:11">11</verse-number>And a famine came over all Egypt and Canaan and great affliction, and our fathers could not find food. <verse-number id="Ac 7:12">12</verse-number>So <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> Jacob heard <supplied>there</supplied> was grain in Egypt, he sent out our fathers first. <verse-number id="Ac 7:13">13</verse-number>And on the second <supplied>visit</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The word “<supplied>visit</supplied>” is not in the Greek text but is implied</note> Joseph was made known to his brothers, and the family of Joseph became known to Pharaoh. <verse-number id="Ac 7:14">14</verse-number>So Joseph sent <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“sent”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> summoned his father Jacob and all <supplied>his</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> relatives, seventy-five persons in <supplied>all</supplied>. <verse-number id="Ac 7:15">15</verse-number>And Jacob went down to Egypt and died, he and our fathers. <verse-number id="Ac 7:16">16</verse-number>And they were brought back to Shechem and buried in the tomb that Abraham had bought for a sum of silver from the sons of Hamor in Shechem. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 7:17">17</verse-number>“But as the time of the promise that God had made to Abraham was drawing near, the people increased and multiplied in Egypt <verse-number id="Ac 7:18">18</verse-number>until another king arose over Egypt who did not know Joseph. <verse-number id="Ac 7:19">19</verse-number>This man deceitfully took advantage of our<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> people <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“deceitfully took advantage of”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> mistreated our ancestors, <idiom-start/>causing them to abandon their infants<idiom-end/><note>Literally “making their infants be abandoned”</note> so that they would not be kept alive. <verse-number id="Ac 7:20">20</verse-number>At this time Moses was born, and he was beautiful to God. <idiom-start/>He<idiom-end/><note>Literally “who”</note> was brought up <supplied>for</supplied> three months in <supplied>his</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> father’s house, <verse-number id="Ac 7:21">21</verse-number>and <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was abandoned”)</note> he was abandoned, the daughter of Pharaoh took him <supplied>up</supplied> and brought him <supplied>up</supplied> <idiom-start/>as her own son<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “for a son to herself”</note> <verse-number id="Ac 7:22">22</verse-number>And Moses was educated in all the wisdom of the Egyptians, and was powerful in his words and deeds. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 7:23">23</verse-number>“But when <idiom-start/>he was forty years old<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “a period of time of forty years was fulfilled for him”</note> it entered in his heart to visit his brothers, the sons of Israel. <verse-number id="Ac 7:24">24</verse-number>And <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> saw one of them being unjustly harmed, he defended <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and <idiom-start/>avenged<idiom-end/><note>Literally “produced vengeance <supplied>for</supplied>”</note> the one who had been oppressed <supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“striking down”) which is understood as means</note> striking down the Egyptian. <verse-number id="Ac 7:25">25</verse-number>And he thought his<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> brothers would understand that God was granting deliverance to them by his hand, but they did not understand. <verse-number id="Ac 7:26">26</verse-number>And on the following day, he made an appearance to them <supplied>while they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“were fighting”) which is understood as temporal</note> were fighting and was attempting to reconcile<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the imperfect verb has been translated as conative (“was attempting to reconcile”)</note> them in peace, saying, ‘Men <supplied>and</supplied> brothers, why are you doing wrong to one another?’ <verse-number id="Ac 7:27">27</verse-number>But the one who was doing wrong to <supplied>his</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> neighbor pushed him aside, saying, ‘Who appointed you a ruler and a judge over us? <verse-number id="Ac 7:28">28</verse-number>You do not want to do away with me <idiom-start/>the same way<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the manner in which”</note> you did away with the Egyptian yesterday, <supplied>do you</supplied>?’<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ex 2:14">Exod 2:14; </cite>the negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here, indicated by “<supplied>do you</supplied>”</note> <verse-number id="Ac 7:29">29</verse-number>And at this statement, Moses fled and became a foreigner in the land of Midian, where he became the father of two sons. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 7:30">30</verse-number>“And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“had been completed”)</note> forty years had been completed, an angel appeared to him in the desert of Mount Sinai in the flame of a burning bush. <verse-number id="Ac 7:31">31</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> Moses saw <supplied>it</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> he was astonished at the sight, and <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“approached”)</note> he approached to look at <supplied>it</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> the voice of the Lord came: <verse-number id="Ac 7:32">32</verse-number>‘I <supplied>am</supplied> the God of your fathers, the God of Abraham and of Isaac and of Jacob!’<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ex 3:6">Exod 3:6</cite></note> So Moses began trembling <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“began”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> did not dare to look at <supplied>it</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <verse-number id="Ac 7:33">33</verse-number>And the Lord said to him, ‘Untie the sandals from your feet, for the place on which you are standing is holy ground. <verse-number id="Ac 7:34">34</verse-number><idiom-start/>I have certainly seen<idiom-end/><note>Literally “seeing I have seen”</note> the mistreatment of my people <supplied>who are</supplied> in Egypt and have heard their groaning, and I have come down to deliver them. And now come, I will send you to Egypt.’<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ex 3:5">Exod 3:5</cite>, <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ex 3:7–8">7–8</cite>, <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ex 3:10">10</cite></note> <verse-number id="Ac 7:35">35</verse-number>This Moses whom they had repudiated, saying, ‘Who appointed you a ruler and a judge?’<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ex 2:14">Exod 2:14 </cite>(see v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Ac 7:27">27</cite> above)</note>—this man God sent <supplied>as</supplied> both ruler and redeemer with <idiom-start/>the help<idiom-end/><note>Literally “hand”</note> of the angel who appeared to him in the bush. <verse-number id="Ac 7:36">36</verse-number>This man led them out, performing wonders and signs in the land of Egypt and at the Red Sea and in the wilderness <supplied>for</supplied> forty years. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 7:37">37</verse-number>“This is the Moses who said to the sons of Israel, ‘God will raise up for you a prophet like me from among your brothers.’<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Dt 18:15">Deut 18:15</cite></note> <verse-number id="Ac 7:38">38</verse-number>This is the one who was in the congregation in the wilderness with the angel who spoke to him at Mount Sinai, and who <supplied>with</supplied> our fathers received living oracles to give to us, <verse-number id="Ac 7:39">39</verse-number>to whom our fathers were not willing to become obedient, but rejected <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and turned <supplied>back</supplied> in their hearts to Egypt, <verse-number id="Ac 7:40">40</verse-number>saying to Aaron, ‘Make us gods who will go on before us! For this Moses, who led us out from the land of Egypt—we do not know what has happened to him!’<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ex 32:1">Exod 32:1</cite>, <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ex 32:23">23</cite></note> <verse-number id="Ac 7:41">41</verse-number>And they manufactured a calf in those days, and offered up a sacrifice to the idol, and began rejoicing<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began rejoicing”)</note> in the works of their hands. <verse-number id="Ac 7:42">42</verse-number>But God turned away and gave them over to worship the host of heaven, just as it is written in the book of the prophets: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>‘You did not bring offerings and sacrifices to me </li1>
				<li2><supplied>for</supplied> forty years in the wilderness, <supplied>did you</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here, indicated by “<supplied>did you</supplied>”</note> house of Israel? </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ac 7:43">43</verse-number>And you took along the tabernacle<note>Or “tent”</note> of Moloch </li1>
				<li2>and the star of the god<note>Some manuscripts have “of your god”</note> Rephan, </li2>
				<li1>the images that you made, to worship them, </li1>
				<li2>and I will deport you beyond Babylon!’<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Am 5:25–27">Amos 5:25–27</cite></note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 7:44">44</verse-number>The tabernacle of the testimony <idiom-start/>belonged<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was”</note> to our fathers in the wilderness, just as the one who spoke to Moses directed <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to make it according to the design that he had seen, <verse-number id="Ac 7:45">45</verse-number>and which, <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“receiving”) which is understood as temporal</note> receiving <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> in turn, our fathers brought in with Joshua <idiom-start/>when they dispossessed the<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the possession of the”</note> nations that God drove out from the presence of our fathers, until the days of David, <verse-number id="Ac 7:46">46</verse-number>who found favor in the sight of God and asked to find a habitation for the God of Jacob.<note>Some manuscripts have “for the house of Jacob”</note> <verse-number id="Ac 7:47">47</verse-number>But Solomon built a house for him. <verse-number id="Ac 7:48">48</verse-number>But the Most High does not live in <supplied>houses</supplied><note>Or “temples made by human hands”; either word (“houses” or “temples”) is understood here</note> made by human hands, just as the prophet says, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ac 7:49">49</verse-number>‘Heaven <supplied>is</supplied> my throne </li1>
				<li2>and earth <supplied>is</supplied> the footstool for my feet. </li2>
				<li1>What kind of house will you build for me, says the Lord, </li1>
				<li2>or what <supplied>is the</supplied> place of my rest? </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ac 7:50">50</verse-number>Did not my hand make all these <supplied>things</supplied>?’<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 66:1–2">Isa 66:1–2</cite></note> </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 7:51">51</verse-number>“<supplied>You</supplied> stiff-necked <supplied>people</supplied> and uncircumcised in hearts and in <supplied>your</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> ears! You constantly resist the Holy Spirit! As your fathers <supplied>did</supplied>, <supplied>so</supplied> also <supplied>do</supplied> you! <verse-number id="Ac 7:52">52</verse-number>Which of the prophets did your fathers not persecute? And they killed those who announced beforehand about the coming of the Righteous One, whose betrayers and murderers you have now become, <verse-number id="Ac 7:53">53</verse-number><supplied>you</supplied> who received the law by directions of angels and have not observed <supplied>it</supplied>!” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Stephen’s Martyrdom</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 7:54">54</verse-number>Now <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> heard these <supplied>things</supplied>, they were infuriated in their hearts and gnashed <supplied>their</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> teeth at him. <verse-number id="Ac 7:55">55</verse-number>But he, being full of the Holy Spirit, looked intently into heaven <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“looked intently”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> saw the glory of God, and Jesus standing at the right hand of God. <verse-number id="Ac 7:56">56</verse-number>And he said, “Behold, I see the heavens opened and the Son of Man standing at the right hand of God!” <verse-number id="Ac 7:57">57</verse-number>But crying out with a loud voice, they stopped their ears and rushed at him with one purpose. <verse-number id="Ac 7:58">58</verse-number>And <supplied>after they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had driven”) which is understood as temporal</note> had driven <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> out of the city, they began to stone<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began stoning”)</note> <supplied>him</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and the witnesses laid aside their cloaks at the feet of a young man named Saul. <verse-number id="Ac 7:59">59</verse-number>And they kept on stoning Stephen <supplied>as he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was calling out”) which is understood as temporal</note> was calling out and saying, “Lord Jesus, receive my spirit!” <verse-number id="Ac 7:60">60</verse-number>And falling to <supplied>his</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> knees, he cried out with a loud voice, “Lord, do not hold this sin against them!” And <supplied>after he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“said”) which is understood as temporal</note> said this, he fell asleep.<note>Or “he passed away”</note> </p>
		</chapter>