<chapter id="Ac 9">
			<pericope>Saul’s Conversion on the Damascus Road</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 9:1">1</verse-number> But Saul, still breathing threats and murder against the disciples of the Lord, went to the high priest <verse-number id="Ac 9:2">2</verse-number><supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the participle in the previous verse (“went to”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> asked for letters from him to the synagogues in Damascus, so that if he found any who were of the Way, both men and women, he could bring <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> tied up<note>Or figuratively “bring <supplied>them</supplied> under arrest”</note> to Jerusalem. <verse-number id="Ac 9:3">3</verse-number>Now as <supplied>he</supplied> proceeded, it happened that <supplied>when</supplied> he approached Damascus, suddenly a light from heaven flashed around him. <verse-number id="Ac 9:4">4</verse-number>And falling to the ground, he heard a voice saying to him, “Saul, Saul, why are you persecuting me?” <verse-number id="Ac 9:5">5</verse-number>So he said, “Who are you, Lord?” And he <supplied>said</supplied>, “I am Jesus, whom you are persecuting! <verse-number id="Ac 9:6">6</verse-number>But get up and enter into the city, and it will be told to you <idiom-start/>what you must do<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “what thing it is necessary <supplied>that</supplied> you do”</note> <verse-number id="Ac 9:7">7</verse-number>(Now the men who were traveling together with him stood speechless, <supplied>because they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as causal</note> heard the voice but saw no one.) <verse-number id="Ac 9:8">8</verse-number>So Saul got up from the ground, but <supplied>although</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>although</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the genitive absolute participle (“were open”) which is understood as concessive</note> his eyes were open he could see nothing. And leading him by the hand, they brought <supplied>him</supplied> into Damascus. <verse-number id="Ac 9:9">9</verse-number>And he was <idiom-start/>unable to see<idiom-end/><note>Literally “not seeing”</note> <supplied>for</supplied> three days, and he did not eat or drink. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Ananias Sent to Saul</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 9:10">10</verse-number>Now there was a certain disciple in Damascus <idiom-start/>named<idiom-end/><note>Literally “by name”</note> Ananias, and the Lord said to him in a vision, “Ananias!” And he said, “Behold, <supplied>here</supplied> I <supplied>am</supplied>, Lord!” <verse-number id="Ac 9:11">11</verse-number>And the Lord <supplied>said</supplied> to him, “Get up, go to the street called ‘Straight’ and in the house of Judas look for <idiom-start/>a man named Saul from Tarsus<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “Saul by name of Tarsus”</note> For behold, he is praying, <verse-number id="Ac 9:12">12</verse-number>and he has seen in a vision a man <idiom-start/>named<idiom-end/><note>Literally “by name”</note> Ananias coming in and placing hands<note>Some manuscripts have “placing his hands”</note> on him so that he may regain <supplied>his</supplied> sight.” <verse-number id="Ac 9:13">13</verse-number>But Ananias replied, “Lord, I have heard from many <supplied>people</supplied> about this man, how much harm he has done to your saints in Jerusalem, <verse-number id="Ac 9:14">14</verse-number>and here he has authority from the chief priests to tie up<note>Or figuratively “to arrest” or “to imprison”</note> all who call upon your name!” <verse-number id="Ac 9:15">15</verse-number>But the Lord said to him, “Go, because this man is my chosen instrument to carry my name before Gentiles<note>The same Greek word can be translated “nations” or “Gentiles” depending on the context</note> and kings and the sons of Israel. <verse-number id="Ac 9:16">16</verse-number>For I will show him how much he must suffer for the sake of my name.” <verse-number id="Ac 9:17">17</verse-number>So Ananias departed and entered into the house, and placing <supplied>his</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> hands on him, he said, “Brother Saul, the Lord Jesus, who appeared to you on the road by which you came, has sent me so that you may regain <supplied>your</supplied> sight and be filled with the Holy Spirit.” <verse-number id="Ac 9:18">18</verse-number>And immediately <supplied>something</supplied> like scales fell from his eyes and he regained <supplied>his</supplied> sight and got up <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“got up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> was baptized, <verse-number id="Ac 9:19">19</verse-number>and <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“taking”) which is understood as temporal</note> taking food, he regained his strength. And he was with the disciples in Damascus several days. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Saul Proclaims Christ in Damascus</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 9:20">20</verse-number>And immediately he began proclaiming<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began proclaiming”)</note> Jesus in the synagogues: “This one is the Son of God!” <verse-number id="Ac 9:21">21</verse-number>And all who heard <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> were amazed, and were saying, “Is this not the one who was wreaking havoc in Jerusalem <supplied>on</supplied> those who call upon this name, and had come here for this <supplied>reason</supplied>, that he could bring them tied up<note>Or figuratively “bring them under arrest”</note> to the chief priests?” <verse-number id="Ac 9:22">22</verse-number>But Saul was increasing in strength even more, and was confounding the Jews who lived in Damascus <supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“proving”) which is understood as means</note> proving that this one is the Christ.<note>Or “Messiah”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 9:23">23</verse-number>And when many days had elapsed, the Jews plotted to do away with him. <verse-number id="Ac 9:24">24</verse-number>But their plot became known to Saul, and they were also watching the gates both day and night so that they could do away with him. <verse-number id="Ac 9:25">25</verse-number>But his disciples took <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> at night <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“took”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> let him down through the wall <supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“lowering”) which is understood as means</note> lowering <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> in a basket. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Saul in Jerusalem</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 9:26">26</verse-number>And <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“arrived”) which is understood as temporal</note> arrived in Jerusalem, he was attempting to associate with the disciples, and they were all afraid of him, <supplied>because they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“believe”) which is understood as causal</note> did not believe that he was a disciple. <verse-number id="Ac 9:27">27</verse-number>But Barnabas took him <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“took”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> brought <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to the apostles and related to them how he had seen the Lord on the road and that he had spoken to him, and how in Damascus he had spoken boldly in the name of Jesus. <verse-number id="Ac 9:28">28</verse-number>And he was going in and going out among them in Jerusalem, speaking boldly in the name of the Lord. <verse-number id="Ac 9:29">29</verse-number>And he was speaking and debating with the <idiom-start/>Greek-speaking Jews<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “Hellenists”</note> but they were trying to do away with him. <verse-number id="Ac 9:30">30</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“found out”) which is understood as temporal</note> the brothers found out, they brought him down to Caesarea and sent him away to Tarsus. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 9:31">31</verse-number>Then the church throughout all of Judea and Galilee and Samaria had peace, being strengthened. And living in the fear of the Lord and the encouragement of the Holy Spirit, it was increasing <supplied>in numbers</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The words “<supplied>in numbers</supplied>” are not in the Greek text but are implied</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Aeneas Healed</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 9:32">32</verse-number>Now it happened that <supplied>as</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was traveling”) which is understood as temporal</note> Peter was traveling through all <supplied>the places</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The words “<supplied>the places</supplied>” are not in the Greek text but are implied</note> <supplied>he</supplied> also came down to the saints who lived <supplied>in</supplied> Lydda. <verse-number id="Ac 9:33">33</verse-number>And he found there a certain man <idiom-start/>named<idiom-end/><note>Literally “by name”</note> Aeneas who was paralyzed, who had been lying on a mat<note>Or “mattress”</note> for eight years. <verse-number id="Ac 9:34">34</verse-number>And Peter said to him, “Aeneas, Jesus Christ heals you! Get up and make your bed yourself!” And immediately he got up. <verse-number id="Ac 9:35">35</verse-number>And all those who lived <supplied>in</supplied> Lydda and Sharon saw him, who <supplied>all</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>all</supplied>” is supplied to indicate the relative pronoun is plural</note> indeed turned to the Lord. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Dorcas Raised</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 9:36">36</verse-number>Now in Joppa there was a certain female disciple <idiom-start/>named<idiom-end/><note>Literally “by name”</note> Tabitha (which translated means “Dorcas”).<note>“Dorcas” is the Greek translation of the Aramaic name “Tabitha” which means “deer” or “gazelle”</note> She was full of good deeds and charitable giving which she was constantly doing.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the imperfect verb is translated as a customary imperfect (“was constantly doing”)</note> <verse-number id="Ac 9:37">37</verse-number>Now it happened that in those days <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“becoming sick”) which is understood as temporal</note> becoming sick, she died. And <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“washing”) which is understood as temporal</note> washing <supplied>her</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> they placed her in an upstairs room. <verse-number id="Ac 9:38">38</verse-number>And <supplied>because</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was”) which is understood as causal</note> Lydda was near Joppa, the disciples, <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> heard that Peter was in <idiom-start/>Lydda<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “in it”</note> sent two men to him, urging, “Do not delay to come to us!” <verse-number id="Ac 9:39">39</verse-number>So Peter got up <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“got up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> accompanied them. <supplied>When he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“arrived”) which is understood as temporal</note> arrived, they brought <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> up to the upstairs room, and all the widows came to him, weeping and showing <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> tunics and <supplied>other</supplied> clothing that Dorcas used to make <supplied>while she</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was”) which is understood as temporal</note> was with them. <verse-number id="Ac 9:40">40</verse-number>But Peter sent <supplied>them</supplied> all outside, and, falling to <supplied>his</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> knees, he prayed. And turning toward the body, he said, “Tabitha, get up!” And she opened her eyes, and <supplied>when she</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> saw Peter, she sat up. <verse-number id="Ac 9:41">41</verse-number>And he gave her <supplied>his</supplied> hand <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“gave”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> raised her up. And he called the saints and the widows <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“called”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> presented her alive. <verse-number id="Ac 9:42">42</verse-number>And it became known throughout all Joppa, and many believed in the Lord. <verse-number id="Ac 9:43">43</verse-number>And it happened that <supplied>he</supplied> stayed many days in Joppa with a certain Simon, a tanner.<note>Or “with a certain Simon Berseus”; most modern English versions treat the word as Simon’s profession (“Simon the tanner”), but the word may actually be a surname (“Simon Berseus” or “Simon Tanner”)</note> </p>
		</chapter>