<chapter id="Ac 11">
			<pericope>Peter’s Explanation to the Church in Jerusalem</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 11:1">1</verse-number> Now the apostles and the brothers who were throughout Judea heard that the Gentiles also had accepted the word<note>Or “message”</note> of God. <verse-number id="Ac 11:2">2</verse-number>So when Peter went up to Jerusalem, those of the circumcision took issue with him, <verse-number id="Ac 11:3">3</verse-number>saying, “You went to men <idiom-start/>who were uncircumcised<idiom-end/><note>Literally “who had uncircumcision</note> and ate with them!” <verse-number id="Ac 11:4">4</verse-number>But Peter began <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“began”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> explained <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to them in an orderly sequence, saying, <verse-number id="Ac 11:5">5</verse-number>“I was in the city of Joppa praying, and in a trance I saw a vision—an object something like a large sheet coming down, being let down from heaven by its four corners, and it came to me. <verse-number id="Ac 11:6">6</verse-number><supplied>As I</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“looked intently”) which is understood as temporal</note> looked intently into it, I was considering <supplied>it</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and I saw the four-footed animals of the earth and the wild animals and the reptiles and the birds of the sky. <verse-number id="Ac 11:7">7</verse-number>And I also heard a voice saying to me, ‘Get up, Peter, slaughter and eat!’ <verse-number id="Ac 11:8">8</verse-number>But I said, ‘Certainly not, Lord! For nothing common or unclean has ever entered into my mouth!’ <verse-number id="Ac 11:9">9</verse-number>But the voice replied from heaven for the second time, ‘<supplied>The things</supplied> which God has made clean, you must not consider unclean!’ <verse-number id="Ac 11:10">10</verse-number>And this happened three times, and everything was pulled up into heaven again. <verse-number id="Ac 11:11">11</verse-number>And behold, at once three men who had been sent to me from Caesarea approached the house in which we were <supplied>staying</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the word “staying” is not in the Greek text but is implied</note> <verse-number id="Ac 11:12">12</verse-number>And the Spirit told me to accompany them, not hesitating <supplied>at all</supplied>. So these six brothers also went with me, and we entered into the man’s house. <verse-number id="Ac 11:13">13</verse-number>And he reported to us how he had seen the angel standing in his house and saying, ‘Send to Joppa and summon Simon, who is also called Peter, <verse-number id="Ac 11:14">14</verse-number>who will speak words to you by which you will be saved, you and all your household.’ <verse-number id="Ac 11:15">15</verse-number>And <supplied>as</supplied> I was beginning to speak, the Holy Spirit fell on them, just as also on us at the beginning. <verse-number id="Ac 11:16">16</verse-number>And I remembered the word of the Lord, how he said, ‘John baptized with water, but you will be baptized with the Holy Spirit.’<note>An allusion to <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ac 1:5">Acts 1:5</cite></note> <verse-number id="Ac 11:17">17</verse-number>Therefore if God gave them the same gift as also to us <supplied>when we</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“believed”) which is understood as temporal</note> believed in the Lord Jesus Christ, who was I <supplied>to be</supplied> able to hinder God?” <verse-number id="Ac 11:18">18</verse-number>And <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> heard these <supplied>things</supplied>, they became silent<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the aorist verb is translated as ingressive (“became silent”)</note> and praised God, saying, “Then God has granted the repentance <supplied>leading</supplied> to life to the Gentiles also!” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Developments in the Church in Antioch</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 11:19">19</verse-number>Now those who had been scattered because of the persecution that took place over Stephen traveled as far as Phoenicia and Cyprus and Antioch, proclaiming the message to no one except Jews alone. <verse-number id="Ac 11:20">20</verse-number>But some of them were men from Cyprus and Cyrene, who, <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“came”) which is understood as temporal</note> came to Antioch, began to speak<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to speak”)</note> to the Hellenists<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here this term could refer to (1) Greek-speaking Jews or (2) Greek-speaking non-Jews (i.e., Gentiles)</note> also, proclaiming the good news about the Lord Jesus. <verse-number id="Ac 11:21">21</verse-number>And the hand of the Lord was with them, and a large number who believed turned to the Lord. <verse-number id="Ac 11:22">22</verse-number><idiom-start/>And the report came to the attention<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and the report was heard in the ears”</note> of the church that was in Jerusalem about them, and they sent out Barnabas as far as<note>Some manuscripts have “to go as far as”</note> Antioch, <verse-number id="Ac 11:23">23</verse-number>who, <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“arrived”) which is understood as temporal</note> arrived and saw the grace of God, rejoiced and encouraged <supplied>them</supplied> all to remain true to the Lord with <idiom-start/>devoted hearts<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “purpose of heart”</note> <verse-number id="Ac 11:24">24</verse-number>because he was a good man and full of the Holy Spirit and of faith. And a large number were added<note>Or “were brought”</note> to the Lord. <verse-number id="Ac 11:25">25</verse-number>So he departed for Tarsus to look for Saul. <verse-number id="Ac 11:26">26</verse-number>And <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“found”) which is understood as temporal</note> found <supplied>him</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> he brought <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to Antioch. And it happened to them also <supplied>that they</supplied> met together <supplied>for</supplied> a whole year with the church and taught a large number <supplied>of people</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The words “<supplied>of people</supplied>” are not in the Greek text but are implied</note> And in Antioch the disciples were first called Christians. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 11:27">27</verse-number>Now in those days prophets came down from Jerusalem to Antioch. <verse-number id="Ac 11:28">28</verse-number>And one of them <idiom-start/>named<idiom-end/><note>Literally “by name”</note> Agabus stood up <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“stood up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> indicated by the Spirit <supplied>that</supplied> a great famine was about to come over the whole inhabited earth (which took place in the time of Claudius). <verse-number id="Ac 11:29">29</verse-number>So from the disciples, <idiom-start/>according to their ability to give<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to the degree that anyone was prospering”</note> each one of them determined to send <supplied>financial aid</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> for support to the brothers who lived in Judea, <verse-number id="Ac 11:30">30</verse-number>which they also did, sending <supplied>the aid</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to the elders by the hand of Barnabas and Saul. </p>
		</chapter>