<chapter id="Ac 12">
			<pericope>Herod Kills James and Imprisons Peter</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 12:1">1</verse-number> Now at that time, Herod the king laid hands on some of those from the church to harm <supplied>them</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <verse-number id="Ac 12:2">2</verse-number>So he executed James the brother of John with a sword. <verse-number id="Ac 12:3">3</verse-number>And <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> saw that it was pleasing to the Jews, he proceeded to arrest Peter also. (<idiom-start/>Now this was during the feast<idiom-end/><note>Literally “now these were the days”</note> of Unleavened Bread.) <verse-number id="Ac 12:4">4</verse-number><supplied>After he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had arrested”) which is understood as temporal</note> had arrested <idiom-start/>him<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “whom”</note> he also put <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> in prison, handing <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> over to four squads of soldiers to guard him, intending to bring him <idiom-start/>out for public trial<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the people”</note> after the Passover. <verse-number id="Ac 12:5">5</verse-number>Thus Peter was kept in the prison, but prayer was fervently being made to God by the church for him. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Peter Rescued by an Angel</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 12:6">6</verse-number>Now when Herod was about to bring him <supplied>out</supplied>, on that <supplied>very</supplied> night Peter was sleeping between two soldiers, bound with two chains, and guards before the door were watching the prison. <verse-number id="Ac 12:7">7</verse-number>And behold, an angel of the Lord stood near <supplied>him</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and a light shone in the prison cell. And striking Peter’s side, he woke him up, saying, “Get up <idiom-start/>quickly<idiom-end/>!”<note>Literally “with quickness”</note> And his chains fell off of <supplied>his</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> hands. <verse-number id="Ac 12:8">8</verse-number>And the angel said to him, “Gird yourself and put on your sandals!” And he did so. And he said to him, “Wrap your cloak around you and follow me!” <verse-number id="Ac 12:9">9</verse-number>And he went out <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went out”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> was following <supplied>him</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> And he did not know that what was being done by the angel was real, but was thinking <supplied>he</supplied> was seeing a vision. <verse-number id="Ac 12:10">10</verse-number>And <supplied>after they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had passed”) which is understood as temporal</note> had passed the first and second guard, they came to the iron gate that leads to the city, which opened for them by itself, and they went out <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went out”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> went forward <supplied>along</supplied> one narrow street, and at once the angel departed from him. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 12:11">11</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“came”) which is understood as temporal</note> Peter came to himself, he said, “Now I know truly that the Lord has sent out his angel and rescued me from the hand of Herod and all <idiom-start/>that the Jewish people expected<idiom-end/>!”<note>Literally “the expectation of the people of the Jews”</note> <verse-number id="Ac 12:12">12</verse-number>And <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“realized”) which is understood as temporal</note> realized <supplied>this</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> he went to the house of Mary, the mother of John (who is also called Mark), where many <supplied>people</supplied> were gathered together and were praying. <verse-number id="Ac 12:13">13</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“knocked”)</note> he knocked at the door of the gateway, a female slave <idiom-start/>named<idiom-end/><note>Literally “by name”</note> Rhoda came up to answer. <verse-number id="Ac 12:14">14</verse-number>And recognizing Peter’s voice, because of <supplied>her</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> joy she did not open the gate, but ran in <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“ran in”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> announced <supplied>that</supplied> Peter was standing at the gate. <verse-number id="Ac 12:15">15</verse-number>But they said to her, “You are out of your mind!” But she kept insisting<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*This imperfect verb is translated as an iterative imperfect (“kept insisting”)</note> it was so. And they kept saying,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*This imperfect verb is translated as an iterative imperfect (“kept saying”)</note> “It is his angel!” <verse-number id="Ac 12:16">16</verse-number>But Peter was continuing to knock, and <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“opened”) which is understood as temporal</note> opened <supplied>the door</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> they saw him and were astonished. <verse-number id="Ac 12:17">17</verse-number>But motioning to them with <supplied>his</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> hand to be silent, he related to them how the Lord had brought him out of the prison. And he said, “Report these <supplied>things</supplied> to James and to the brothers,” and he departed <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“departed”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> went to another place. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 12:18">18</verse-number>Now <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“came”)</note> day came, there was not a little commotion among the soldiers <supplied>as to</supplied> what then had become of Peter. <verse-number id="Ac 12:19">19</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had searched for”) which is understood as temporal</note> Herod had searched for him and did not find <supplied>him</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> he questioned the guards <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“questioned”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> ordered <supplied>that they</supplied> be led away to execution. And he came down from Judea to Caesarea <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came down”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> stayed <supplied>there</supplied>. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Herod’s Gruesome Death</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 12:20">20</verse-number>Now he was very angry with the Tyrians and Sidonians. So they came to him with one purpose, and <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“persuading”) which is understood as temporal</note> persuading Blastus, <idiom-start/>the king’s chamberlain<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the <supplied>one</supplied> over the bedroom of the king”</note> they asked for peace, because their country was supported with food from the king’s country. <verse-number id="Ac 12:21">21</verse-number>So on an appointed day Herod, <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“putting on”) which is understood as temporal</note> putting on royal clothing and sitting down on the judgment seat, began to deliver a public address to them. <verse-number id="Ac 12:22">22</verse-number>But the people began to call out loudly,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to call out loudly”)</note> “The voice of a god and not of a man!” <verse-number id="Ac 12:23">23</verse-number>And immediately an angel of the Lord struck him down <idiom-start/>because<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in return for which”</note> he did not give the glory to God. And he was eaten by worms <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“was”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> died. <verse-number id="Ac 12:24">24</verse-number>But the word of God kept on increasing<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*This imperfect verb has been translated as customary (“kept on increasing”)</note> and multiplying. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 12:25">25</verse-number>So Barnabas and Saul returned to<note>Some manuscripts read “from”</note> Jerusalem <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had completed”) which is understood as temporal</note> had completed <supplied>their</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> service, having taken along with <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> John (who is also called Mark). </p>
		</chapter>