<chapter id="Ac 13">
			<pericope>Barnabas and Saul Sent Out from Antioch</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 13:1">1</verse-number> Now there were prophets and teachers in Antioch in the church that was there: Barnabas, and Simeon (who was called Niger), and Lucius the Cyrenian, and Manaen (a close friend of Herod the tetrarch), and Saul. <verse-number id="Ac 13:2">2</verse-number>And <supplied>while</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“were serving”)</note> they were serving the Lord and fasting, the Holy Spirit said, “Set apart now for me Barnabas and Saul for the work to which I have called them.” <verse-number id="Ac 13:3">3</verse-number>Then, <supplied>after they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had fasted”) which is understood as temporal</note> had fasted and prayed and placed <supplied>their</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> hands on them, they sent <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> away. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Confronting a Magician on Cyprus</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 13:4">4</verse-number>Therefore, sent out by the Holy Spirit, they came down to Seleucia, and from there they sailed away to Cyprus. <verse-number id="Ac 13:5">5</verse-number>And <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“came”) which is understood as temporal</note> came to Salamis, they began to proclaim the word of God in the synagogues of the Jews. And they also had John <supplied>as</supplied> assistant. <verse-number id="Ac 13:6">6</verse-number>And <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had crossed over”) which is understood as temporal</note> had crossed over the whole island as far as Paphos, they found a certain man, a magician, a Jewish false prophet whose name <supplied>was</supplied> Bar-Jesus,<verse-number id="Ac 13:7">7</verse-number>who was with the proconsul Sergius Paulus, an intelligent man. This man summoned Barnabas and Saul <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“summoned”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> wished to hear the word of God. <verse-number id="Ac 13:8">8</verse-number>But Elymas the magician (for his name is translated in this way) opposed them, attempting to turn the proconsul away from the faith. <verse-number id="Ac 13:9">9</verse-number>But Saul (also called Paul), filled with the Holy Spirit, looked intently at him <verse-number id="Ac 13:10">10</verse-number><supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the participle in the previous verse (“looked intently at”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “O <supplied>you who are</supplied> full of all deceit and of all unscrupulousness, <supplied>you</supplied> son of the devil, <supplied>you</supplied> enemy of all righteousness! Will you not stop making crooked the straight paths of the Lord! <verse-number id="Ac 13:11">11</verse-number>And now behold, the hand of the Lord <supplied>is</supplied> against you, and you will be blind, not seeing the sun <idiom-start/>for a while<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “until the time”</note> And immediately mist and darkness fell over him, and he was going around looking for <supplied>people</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*In Greek the direct object (“people”) is understood and must be supplied in the English translation; since the following noun is plural, “people” rather than “someone” is used here</note> to lead <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> by the hand. <verse-number id="Ac 13:12">12</verse-number>Then <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> the proconsul saw what had happened, he believed, <supplied>because he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was astounded”) which is understood as causal</note> was astounded at the teaching about<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “about” reflects an objective genitive (“the Lord” is the object of the teaching)</note> the Lord. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Preaching in the Synagogue at Pisidian Antioch</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 13:13">13</verse-number>Now <idiom-start/>Paul and his companions<idiom-end/><note>Literally “those around Paul”</note> put out to sea from Paphos <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“put out to sea”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> came to Perga in Pamphylia, but John departed from them <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“departed”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> returned to Jerusalem. <verse-number id="Ac 13:14">14</verse-number>And they went on from Perga <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went on”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> arrived at Pisidian Antioch. And they entered into the synagogue on the day of the Sabbath <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“entered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> sat down. <verse-number id="Ac 13:15">15</verse-number>So after the reading from the law and the prophets, the rulers of the synagogue sent <supplied>word</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to them, saying, “Men <supplied>and</supplied> brothers, if there is any message of exhortation by you for the people, say <supplied>it</supplied>.”<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 13:16">16</verse-number>So Paul stood up,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the participle (“stood up”) is translated as a finite verb because of English style</note> and motioning with <supplied>his</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> hand, he said, “Israelite men, and those who fear God, listen! <verse-number id="Ac 13:17">17</verse-number>The God of this people Israel chose our fathers and exalted the people during <supplied>their</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> stay in the land of Egypt, and with uplifted arm he led them out of it. <verse-number id="Ac 13:18">18</verse-number>And for a period of time <supplied>of</supplied> about forty years, he put up with them in the wilderness. <verse-number id="Ac 13:19">19</verse-number>And <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“destroying”) which is understood as temporal</note> destroying seven nations in the land of Canaan, he gave their land <supplied>to his people</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The words “<supplied>to his people</supplied>” are supplied as a clarification of who received the land</note> as an inheritance. <verse-number id="Ac 13:20">20</verse-number><supplied>This took</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The words “<supplied>This took</supplied>” are not in the Greek text but are supplied in keeping with English style</note> about four hundred and fifty years. And after these <supplied>things</supplied>, he gave <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the indirect object “<supplied>them</supplied>” is not in the Greek text but is implied</note> judges until Samuel the prophet. <verse-number id="Ac 13:21">21</verse-number>And then they asked for a king, and God gave them Saul son of Kish, a man from the tribe of Benjamin, <supplied>for</supplied> forty years. <verse-number id="Ac 13:22">22</verse-number>And <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“removing”) which is understood as temporal</note> removing him, he raised up David for their king, about whom he also said, testifying, ‘I have found David the <supplied>son</supplied> of Jesse <supplied>to be</supplied> a man in accordance with my heart, who will carry out all my will.’<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: 1 Sa 13:14">1 Sam 13:14</cite></note> <verse-number id="Ac 13:23">23</verse-number>From the descendants of this man, according to <supplied>his</supplied> promise, God brought to Israel a Savior, Jesus. <verse-number id="Ac 13:24">24</verse-number>Before <idiom-start/>his coming<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the presence of his coming”</note> John had publicly proclaimed<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the participle (“had publicly proclaimed”) has been translated as a finite verb in keeping with English style</note> a baptism of repentance to all the people of Israel. <verse-number id="Ac 13:25">25</verse-number>But while John was completing <supplied>his</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> mission, he said, ‘What do you suppose me to be? I am not <supplied>he</supplied>! But behold, one is coming after me of whom I am not worthy to untie the sandals of <supplied>his</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> feet!’ </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 13:26">26</verse-number>“Men <supplied>and</supplied> brothers, sons of the family of Abraham and those among you who fear God—to us the message of this salvation has been sent! <verse-number id="Ac 13:27">27</verse-number>For those who live in Jerusalem and their rulers, <supplied>because they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“did not recognize”) which is understood as causal</note> did not recognize this one, and the voices of the prophets that are read on every Sabbath, fulfilled <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“condemning”) which is understood as means</note> condemning <supplied>him</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <verse-number id="Ac 13:28">28</verse-number>And <supplied>although they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>although</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the genitive absolute participle (“found”) which is understood as concessive</note> found no charge <supplied>worthy</supplied> of death, they asked Pilate <supplied>that</supplied> he be executed. <verse-number id="Ac 13:29">29</verse-number>And when they had carried out all the things that were written about him, they took <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> down from the tree <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“took … down”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> placed <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> in a tomb. <verse-number id="Ac 13:30">30</verse-number>But God raised him from the dead, <verse-number id="Ac 13:31">31</verse-number>who appeared for many days to those who had come up with him from Galilee to Jerusalem—who are now his witnesses to the people. <verse-number id="Ac 13:32">32</verse-number>And we proclaim the good news to you: that the promise that was made to the fathers, <verse-number id="Ac 13:33">33</verse-number>this <supplied>promise</supplied><note>It is necessary to repeat the word “<supplied>promise</supplied>” from the previous verse for clarity here</note> God has fulfilled to our children<note>Some manuscripts have “to us their children”</note> <supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“raising”) which is understood as means</note> raising Jesus, as it is also written in the second psalm, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>‘You are my Son; </li1>
				<li2>today I have fathered you.’<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 2:7">Ps 2:7</cite></note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 13:34">34</verse-number>But that he has raised him from the dead, no more going to return to decay, he has spoken in this way: ‘I will give you the reliable divine decrees of David.’<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 55:3">Isa 55:3</cite></note> <verse-number id="Ac 13:35">35</verse-number>Therefore he also says in another <supplied>psalm</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The word “<supplied>psalm</supplied>” is not in the Greek text but is implied</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>‘You will not permit your Holy One to experience decay.’<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 16:10">Ps 16:10</cite></note> </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 13:36">36</verse-number>For David, <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“serving”) which is understood as temporal</note> serving the purpose of God in his own generation, fell asleep and <idiom-start/>was buried with<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was gathered to”</note> his fathers, and experienced decay. <verse-number id="Ac 13:37">37</verse-number>But he whom God raised up did not experience decay. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 13:38">38</verse-number>“Therefore let it be known to you, men <supplied>and</supplied> brothers, that through this one forgiveness of sins is proclaimed to you, and from all <supplied>the things</supplied> from which you were not able to be justified by the law of Moses, <verse-number id="Ac 13:39">39</verse-number>by this one everyone who believes is justified! <verse-number id="Ac 13:40">40</verse-number>Watch out, therefore, lest what is stated by the prophets come upon <supplied>you</supplied>:<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ac 13:41">41</verse-number>‘Look, you scoffers, </li1>
				<li2>and be astonished and perish! </li2>
				<li2>For I am doing a work in your days, </li2>
				<li2>a work that you would never believe </li2>
				<li3><supplied>even</supplied> if someone were to tell <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to you.’ ”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Hab 1:5">Hab 1:5</cite></note> </li3>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Response to the Message in Pisidian Antioch</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 13:42">42</verse-number>And <supplied>as</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“were going out”)</note> they were going out, they began urging<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began urging”)</note> <supplied>that</supplied> these things be spoken about to them on the next Sabbath. <verse-number id="Ac 13:43">43</verse-number>And <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“had broken up”)</note> the synagogue had broken up, many of the Jews and the devout<note>Or “God-fearing”</note> proselytes followed Paul and Barnabas, who were speaking to them <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“were speaking to”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> were persuading them to continue in the grace of God. <verse-number id="Ac 13:44">44</verse-number>And on the coming Sabbath, nearly the whole city came together to hear the word of the Lord. <verse-number id="Ac 13:45">45</verse-number>But <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> the Jews saw the crowds, they were filled with jealousy, and began contradicting what was being said by Paul <supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“reviling”) which is understood as means</note> reviling <supplied>him</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <verse-number id="Ac 13:46">46</verse-number>Both Paul and Barnabas spoke boldly <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“spoke boldly”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “It was necessary <supplied>that</supplied> the word of God be spoken first to you, since you reject it and do not consider yourselves worthy of eternal life! Behold, we are turning to the Gentiles! <verse-number id="Ac 13:47">47</verse-number>For so the Lord has commanded us: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>‘I have appointed you <idiom-start/>to be<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for”</note> a light for the Gentiles, </li1>
				<li2><idiom-start/>that you would bring<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<supplied>that</supplied> you would bring”</note> salvation to the end of the earth.’<note>An allusion to <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 42:6">Isa 42:6</cite>; <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 49:6">49:6</cite></note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 13:48">48</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> the Gentiles heard <supplied>this</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> they began to rejoice<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to rejoice”)</note> and to glorify the word of the Lord. And all those who were designated for eternal life believed. <verse-number id="Ac 13:49">49</verse-number>So the word of the Lord was carried through the whole region. <verse-number id="Ac 13:50">50</verse-number>But the Jews incited the devout women of high social standing and the most prominent men of the city, and stirred up persecution against Paul and Barnabas and threw them out of their district. <verse-number id="Ac 13:51">51</verse-number>So <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“shaking off”) which is understood as temporal</note> shaking off the dust from <supplied>their</supplied> feet against them, they went to Iconium. <verse-number id="Ac 13:52">52</verse-number>And the disciples were filled with joy and with the Holy Spirit. </p>
		</chapter>