<chapter id="Ac 14">
			<pericope>Preaching in Iconium</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 14:1">1</verse-number> Now it happened that in Iconium they entered <idiom-start/>together<idiom-end/><note>Literally “according to the same”</note> into the synagogue of the Jews and spoke in such a way that a large number of both Jews and Greeks believed. <verse-number id="Ac 14:2">2</verse-number>But the Jews who were disobedient stirred up and <idiom-start/>poisoned the minds<idiom-end/><note>Literally “embittered the souls”</note> of the Gentiles against the brothers. <verse-number id="Ac 14:3">3</verse-number>So they stayed <supplied>there</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> for a considerable time, speaking boldly for the Lord, who testified to the message of his grace, granting signs and wonders to be performed through their hands. <verse-number id="Ac 14:4">4</verse-number>But the population of the city was divided, and <idiom-start/>some<idiom-end/><note>Literally “those on the one hand”</note> were with the Jews <idiom-start/>and some<idiom-end/><note>Literally “those on the other hand”</note> with the apostles. <verse-number id="Ac 14:5">5</verse-number>So when an inclination took place <supplied>on the part</supplied> of both the Gentiles and the Jews, together with their rulers, to mistreat <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and to stone them, <verse-number id="Ac 14:6">6</verse-number>they became aware of <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“became aware of”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> fled to the Lycaonian cities—Lystra and Derbe and the surrounding region. <verse-number id="Ac 14:7">7</verse-number>And there they were continuing to proclaim the good news. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Mistaken for Gods in Lystra</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 14:8">8</verse-number>And in Lystra a certain man was sitting powerless in his feet, lame from <idiom-start/>birth<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “his mother’s womb”</note> who had never walked. <verse-number id="Ac 14:9">9</verse-number>This man listened <supplied>while</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was speaking”)</note> Paul was speaking. <idiom-start/>Paul<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “who”</note> looking intently at him and seeing that he had faith to be healed, <verse-number id="Ac 14:10">10</verse-number>said with a loud voice, “Stand upright on your feet!” And he leaped up and began walking.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began walking”)</note> <verse-number id="Ac 14:11">11</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> the crowds saw what Paul had done, they raised their voices in the Lycaonian language, saying, “The gods have become like men <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“have become like”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> have come down to us!” <verse-number id="Ac 14:12">12</verse-number>And they began calling<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began calling”)</note> Barnabas Zeus and Paul Hermes, because he was the <idiom-start/>principal speaker<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “leader of the message”</note> <verse-number id="Ac 14:13">13</verse-number>And the priest of the <supplied>temple</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The word “<supplied>temple</supplied>” is not in the Greek text but is implied</note> of Zeus that was just outside the city brought bulls and garlands to the gates <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“brought”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> was wanting to offer sacrifice, along with the crowds. <verse-number id="Ac 14:14">14</verse-number>But <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard about”) which is understood as temporal</note> the apostles Barnabas and Paul heard about <supplied>it</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> they tore their clothing <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“tore”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> rushed out into the crowd, shouting <verse-number id="Ac 14:15">15</verse-number>and saying, “Men, why are you doing these <supplied>things</supplied>? We also are men with the same nature as you, proclaiming the good news <supplied>that</supplied> you should turn from these worthless things to the living God, who made the heaven and the earth and the sea and all the things <supplied>that are</supplied> in them—<verse-number id="Ac 14:16">16</verse-number>who in generations that are past permitted all the nations<note>Or “Gentiles”; the same Greek word can be translated “nations” or “Gentiles” depending on the context</note> to go their <supplied>own</supplied> ways. <verse-number id="Ac 14:17">17</verse-number>And yet he did not leave himself without witness <supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“doing good”) which is understood as means</note> doing good, giving you rain from heaven and fruitful seasons, satisfying <supplied>you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> with food and your hearts with gladness.” <verse-number id="Ac 14:18">18</verse-number>And <supplied>although</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>although</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“said”) which is understood as concessive</note> they said these <supplied>things</supplied>, <supplied>only</supplied> with difficulty did they dissuade the crowds from offering sacrifice to them. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 14:19">19</verse-number>But Jews arrived from Antioch and Iconium, and <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had won over”) which is understood as temporal</note> had won over the crowds and stoned Paul, they dragged <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> outside the city, thinking he was dead. <verse-number id="Ac 14:20">20</verse-number>But <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“surrounded”)</note> the disciples surrounded him, he got up <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“got up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> went into the city. And on the next day he departed with Barnabas for Derbe. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Paul and Barnabas Return to Antioch in Syria</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 14:21">21</verse-number>And <supplied>after they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had proclaimed the good news”) which is understood as temporal</note> had proclaimed the good news in that city and made many disciples, they returned to Lystra and to Iconium and to Antioch, <verse-number id="Ac 14:22">22</verse-number>strengthening the souls of the disciples, encouraging <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to continue in the faith and <supplied>saying</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The word “<supplied>saying</supplied>” is not in the Greek text but is implied</note> “Through many persecutions<note>Or “afflictions”</note> it is necessary <supplied>for</supplied> us to enter into the kingdom of God.” <verse-number id="Ac 14:23">23</verse-number>And <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had appointed”) which is understood as temporal</note> had appointed elders for them in every church, <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“praying”) which is understood as temporal</note> praying with fasting, they entrusted them to the Lord, in whom they had believed. <verse-number id="Ac 14:24">24</verse-number>And they passed through Pisidia <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“passed through”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> came to Pamphylia. <verse-number id="Ac 14:25">25</verse-number>And <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“proclaimed”) which is understood as temporal</note> they proclaimed the message in Perga, they went down to Attalia, <verse-number id="Ac 14:26">26</verse-number>and from there they sailed away to Antioch where they had been commended to the grace of God for the work that they had completed. <verse-number id="Ac 14:27">27</verse-number>And <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“arrived”) which is understood as temporal</note> arrived and called the church together, they reported all that God had done with them, and that he had opened a door of faith for the Gentiles.<note>Or “nations”; the same Greek word can be translated “nations” or “Gentiles” depending on the context</note> <verse-number id="Ac 14:28">28</verse-number>And they stayed no little time with the disciples. </p>
		</chapter>