<chapter id="Ac 15">
			<pericope>The Jerusalem Council</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 15:1">1</verse-number> And some men came down from Judea <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came down”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> began teaching<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began teaching”)</note> the brothers, “Unless you are circumcised according to the custom <supplied>prescribed</supplied> by Moses, you cannot be saved.” <verse-number id="Ac 15:2">2</verse-number>And <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was”)</note> there was no little strife and debate by Paul and Barnabas against them, they appointed Paul and Barnabas and some others from among them to go up to the apostles and elders in Jerusalem concerning this issue. <verse-number id="Ac 15:3">3</verse-number>So they were sent on their way by the church, <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“were sent on their way”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> passed through both Phoenicia and Samaria, telling in detail the conversion of the Gentiles and bringing great joy to all the brothers. <verse-number id="Ac 15:4">4</verse-number>And <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“arrived”) which is understood as temporal</note> arrived in Jerusalem, they were received by the church and the apostles and the elders, and reported all that God had done with them. <verse-number id="Ac 15:5">5</verse-number>But some of those who had believed from the party of the Pharisees stood up, saying, “It is necessary to circumcise them and to command <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to observe the law of Moses!” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 15:6">6</verse-number>Both the apostles and the elders assembled to deliberate concerning this matter. <verse-number id="Ac 15:7">7</verse-number>And <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was”)</note> there was much debate, Peter stood up <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“stood up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to them, “Men <supplied>and</supplied> brothers, you know that in the early days<note>Or “from ancient days”</note> God chose among you through my mouth <supplied>that</supplied> the Gentiles should hear the message of the gospel and believe. <verse-number id="Ac 15:8">8</verse-number>And God, who knows the heart, testified to them <supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“giving”) which is understood as means</note> giving <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> the Holy Spirit, just as he also <supplied>did</supplied> to us. <verse-number id="Ac 15:9">9</verse-number>And he made no distinction between us and them, cleansing their hearts by faith. <verse-number id="Ac 15:10">10</verse-number>So now why are you putting God to the test <supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the infinitive (“placing”) which is understood as means</note> placing on the neck of the disciples a yoke that neither our fathers nor we have been able to bear? <verse-number id="Ac 15:11">11</verse-number>But we believe <supplied>we</supplied> will be saved through the grace of the Lord Jesus in <idiom-start/>the same<idiom-end/><note>Literally “which”</note> way those also <supplied>are</supplied>.” <verse-number id="Ac 15:12">12</verse-number>And the whole group became silent and listened to Barnabas and Paul describing all the signs and wonders God had done among the Gentiles through them. <verse-number id="Ac 15:13">13</verse-number>And after they had stopped speaking, James answered, saying, “Men <supplied>and</supplied> brothers, listen to me! <verse-number id="Ac 15:14">14</verse-number>Simeon has described how God first concerned himself to take from among the Gentiles a people for his name. <verse-number id="Ac 15:15">15</verse-number>And with this the words of the prophets agree, just as it is written: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ac 15:16">16</verse-number>‘After these <supplied>things</supplied> I will return </li1>
				<li2>and build up again the tent of David that has fallen, </li2>
				<li2>and the <supplied>parts</supplied> of it that had been torn down I will build up again </li2>
				<li2>and will restore it, </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ac 15:17">17</verse-number>so that the rest of humanity may seek the Lord, </li1>
				<li2>even all the Gentiles<note>The same Greek word can be translated “nations” or “Gentiles” depending on the context</note> <idiom-start/>who are called by my name<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “on whom my name has been called on them”</note> </li2>
				<li2>says the Lord,<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Am 9:11–12">Amos 9:11–12</cite></note> who makes these <supplied>things</supplied> <verse-number id="Ac 15:18">18</verse-number>known from of old.’<note>The last phrase of v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Ac 15:17">17</cite> and all of v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Ac 15:18">18</cite> is an allusion to <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 45:21">Isa 45:21</cite></note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 15:19">19</verse-number>Therefore I conclude we should not cause difficulty for those from among the Gentiles who turn to God, <verse-number id="Ac 15:20">20</verse-number>but we should write a letter to them to abstain from the pollution of idols and from sexual immorality and from what has been strangled and from blood. <verse-number id="Ac 15:21">21</verse-number>For Moses has those who proclaim him in every city from ancient generations, <supplied>because he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“is read aloud”) which is understood as causal</note> is read aloud in the synagogues on every Sabbath.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Letter from the Council</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 15:22">22</verse-number>Then it seemed best to the apostles and the elders, together with the whole church, to send men chosen from among them to Antioch with Paul and Barnabas—Judas who was called Barsabbas and Silas, men <supplied>who were</supplied> leaders among the brothers—<verse-number id="Ac 15:23">23</verse-number>writing <supplied>this letter</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <idiom-start/>to be delivered by them<idiom-end/>:<note>Literally “by their hand”</note> </p>
			<p>The apostles and the elders, brothers. </p>
			<p>To the brothers <supplied>who are</supplied> from among the Gentiles in Antioch and Syria and Cilicia. </p>
			<p/>
			<block>
				<p>Greetings! </p>
				<p><verse-number id="Ac 15:24">24</verse-number>Because we have heard that some have gone out from among us—to whom we gave no orders—<supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“have gone out”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> have thrown you into confusion by words upsetting your <idiom-start/>minds<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “souls”</note> <verse-number id="Ac 15:25">25</verse-number>it seemed best to us, <idiom-start/>having reached a unanimous decision<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “having become of one mind”</note> <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied in keeping with English style</note> having chosen men, to send <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to you together with our dear friends Barnabas and Paul, <verse-number id="Ac 15:26">26</verse-number>men who have risked their lives on behalf of the name of our Lord Jesus Christ. <verse-number id="Ac 15:27">27</verse-number>Therefore we have sent Judas and Silas, and they will report the same <supplied>things</supplied> by word of mouth. <verse-number id="Ac 15:28">28</verse-number>For it seemed best to the Holy Spirit and to us to place on you no greater burden except these necessary things: <verse-number id="Ac 15:29">29</verse-number><supplied>that you</supplied> abstain from food sacrificed to idols, and from blood, and from what has been strangled, and from sexual immorality. <supplied>If you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>if</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“keep”) which is understood as conditional</note> keep yourselves from <idiom-start/>these things<idiom-end/><note>Literally “which things”</note> you will do well. </p>
				<p>Farewell. </p>
			</block>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Letter Is Delivered to Antioch</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 15:30">30</verse-number>So <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“were sent off”) which is understood as temporal</note> they were sent off, they came down to Antioch, and <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“calling together”) which is understood as temporal</note> calling together the community, they delivered the letter. <verse-number id="Ac 15:31">31</verse-number>And <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“read … aloud”) which is understood as temporal</note> read <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> aloud, they rejoiced at the encouragement. <verse-number id="Ac 15:32">32</verse-number>Both Judas and Silas, who were also prophets themselves, encouraged and strengthened the brothers by a long message. <verse-number id="Ac 15:33">33</verse-number>And <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“spending”) which is understood as temporal</note> spending <supplied>some</supplied> time, they were sent away in peace from the brothers to those who had sent them.<note>A few later manuscripts add v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Ac 15:34">34</cite>, “But Silas decided to stay there.”</note> <verse-number id="Ac 15:35">35</verse-number>But Paul and Barnabas remained in Antioch teaching and proclaiming the word of the Lord with many others also. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Paul and Barnabas Disagree and Part Company</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 15:36">36</verse-number>And after some days, Paul said to Barnabas, “Come then,<supplied>let us</supplied> return <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“return”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> visit the brothers in every town in which we proclaimed the word of the Lord, <supplied>to see</supplied> how they are <supplied>doing</supplied>.” <verse-number id="Ac 15:37">37</verse-number>Now Barnabas wanted to take John who was called Mark along also, <verse-number id="Ac 15:38">38</verse-number>but Paul held the opinion they should not take this one along, who departed from them in Pamphylia and did not accompany them in the work. <verse-number id="Ac 15:39">39</verse-number>And a sharp disagreement took place, so that they separated from one another. And Barnabas took along Mark <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“took along”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> sailed away to Cyprus, <verse-number id="Ac 15:40">40</verse-number>but Paul chose Silas <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“chose”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> departed, <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“being commended”) which is understood as temporal</note> being commended to the grace of the Lord by the brothers. <verse-number id="Ac 15:41">41</verse-number>And he traveled through Syria and Cilicia, strengthening the churches. </p>
		</chapter>