<chapter id="Ac 18">
			<pericope>Paul, Silas, and Timothy in Corinth</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 18:1">1</verse-number> After these <supplied>things</supplied> he departed from Athens <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“departed”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> went to Corinth. <verse-number id="Ac 18:2">2</verse-number>And he found a certain Jew <idiom-start/>named<idiom-end/><note>Literally “by name”</note> Aquila, <idiom-start/>a native<idiom-end/><note>Literally “by nationality”</note> of Pontus who had arrived recently from Italy <idiom-start/>along with<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and”</note> Priscilla his wife, because Claudius had ordered all the Jews to depart from Rome, <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“found”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> he went to them. <verse-number id="Ac 18:3">3</verse-number>And because <supplied>he</supplied> was practicing the same trade, he stayed with them and worked, for they were tentmakers by trade. <verse-number id="Ac 18:4">4</verse-number>And he argued in the synagogue every Sabbath, attempting to persuade<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the imperfect verb has been translated as conative (“attempting to persuade”)</note> both Jews and Greeks. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 18:5">5</verse-number>Now when both Silas and Timothy came down from Macedonia, Paul began to be occupied with<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to be occupied with”)</note> the message, solemnly testifying to the Jews <supplied>that</supplied> the Christ<note>Or “Messiah”</note> was Jesus. <verse-number id="Ac 18:6">6</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“resisted”)</note> they resisted and reviled <supplied>him</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> he shook out <supplied>his</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> clothes <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“shook out”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to them, “Your blood <supplied>be</supplied> on your <supplied>own</supplied> heads! I <supplied>am</supplied> guiltless! From now on I will go to the Gentiles!” <verse-number id="Ac 18:7">7</verse-number>And leaving there, he entered into the house of someone <idiom-start/>named<idiom-end/><note>Literally “by name”</note> Titius Justus, a worshiper<note>Or “a God-fearer”</note> of God whose house was next door to the synagogue. <verse-number id="Ac 18:8">8</verse-number>And Crispus, the ruler of the synagogue, believed in the Lord together with his whole household. And many of the Corinthians, <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard about”) which is understood as temporal</note> heard about <supplied>it</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> believed and were baptized. <verse-number id="Ac 18:9">9</verse-number>And the Lord said to Paul by a vision in the night, “Do not be afraid, but speak and do not keep silent, <verse-number id="Ac 18:10">10</verse-number>because I am with you and no one will attack you to harm you, because many people are mine in this city.” <verse-number id="Ac 18:11">11</verse-number>So he stayed a year and six months, teaching the word of God among them. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Paul Accused Before the Proconsul Gallio</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 18:12">12</verse-number>Now <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was”)</note> Gallio was proconsul of Achaia, the Jews rose up with one purpose against Paul and brought him before the judgment seat, <verse-number id="Ac 18:13">13</verse-number>saying, “This man is persuading people to worship God contrary to the law!” <verse-number id="Ac 18:14">14</verse-number>But <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was about”)</note> Paul was about to open <supplied>his</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> mouth, Gallio said to the Jews, “If it was some crime or wicked villainy, O Jews, <idiom-start/>I would have been justified in accepting<idiom-end/><note>Literally “with respect to a motive I would have accepted”</note> your complaint. <verse-number id="Ac 18:15">15</verse-number>But if it is questions concerning a word and names and <idiom-start/>your own law<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the according to you law”</note> see to <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> yourselves! I do not wish to be a judge of these <supplied>things</supplied>.” <verse-number id="Ac 18:16">16</verse-number>And he drove them away from the judgment seat. <verse-number id="Ac 18:17">17</verse-number>So they all seized Sosthenes, the ruler of the synagogue, <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“seized”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> began beating<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began beating”)</note> <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> in front of the judgment seat. And none of these <supplied>things</supplied> was a concern to Gallio. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Paul Returns to Antioch in Syria</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 18:18">18</verse-number>So Paul, <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“remaining”) which is understood as temporal</note> remaining many days longer, said farewell to the brothers <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“said farewell”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> sailed away to Syria, and with him Priscilla and Aquila. He shaved <supplied>his</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> head at Cenchrea, because he had <supplied>taken</supplied> a vow.<verse-number id="Ac 18:19">19</verse-number>So they arrived at Ephesus, and those he left behind there, but he himself entered into the synagogue <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“entered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> discussed with the Jews. <verse-number id="Ac 18:20">20</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“asked”)</note> they asked <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to stay for a longer time, he did not give his consent, <verse-number id="Ac 18:21">21</verse-number>but saying farewell and telling <supplied>them</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> “I will return to you again <supplied>if</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “if” is supplied as a component of the conditional adverbial participle (“wills”)</note> God wills,” he set sail from Ephesus. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 18:22">22</verse-number>And <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“arrived”) which is understood as temporal</note> arrived at Caesarea, he went up and greeted the church, <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the two previous participles (“went up” and “greeted”) have been translated as finite verbs</note> went down to Antioch. <verse-number id="Ac 18:23">23</verse-number>And <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“spending”) which is understood as temporal</note> spending some time <supplied>there</supplied>, he departed, traveling through one <supplied>place</supplied> after another <supplied>in</supplied> the Galatian region and Phrygia, strengthening all the disciples. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Early Ministry of Apollos</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 18:24">24</verse-number>Now a certain Jew <idiom-start/>named<idiom-end/><note>Literally “by name”</note> Apollos, <idiom-start/>a native<idiom-end/><note>Literally “by nationality”</note> Alexandrian, arrived in Ephesus—an eloquent man who was well-versed in the scriptures. <verse-number id="Ac 18:25">25</verse-number>This man had been instructed <supplied>in</supplied> the way of the Lord, and being enthusiastic in spirit, he was speaking and teaching accurately the <supplied>things</supplied> about Jesus, <supplied>although he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>although</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“knew”) which is understood as concessive</note> knew only the baptism of John. <verse-number id="Ac 18:26">26</verse-number>And he began to speak boldly in the synagogue, but <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> Priscilla and Aquila heard him, they took him aside and explained the way of God to him more accurately. <verse-number id="Ac 18:27">27</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“wanted”)</note> he wanted to cross over to Achaia, the brothers encouraged <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“encouraged”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> wrote to the disciples to welcome him. <supplied>When he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“arrived”) which is understood as temporal</note> arrived, <idiom-start/>he<idiom-end/><note>Literally “who”</note> assisted greatly those who had believed through grace. <verse-number id="Ac 18:28">28</verse-number>For he was vigorously refuting the Jews in public, demonstrating through the scriptures <supplied>that</supplied> the Christ<note>Or “Messiah”</note> was Jesus. </p>
		</chapter>