<chapter id="Ac 19">
			<pericope>Paul Finds Disciples of John the Baptist in Ephesus</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 19:1">1</verse-number> And it happened that <supplied>while</supplied> Apollos was in Corinth, Paul traveled through the inland regions <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“traveled through”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> came<note>Some manuscripts have “<supplied>and</supplied> came down”</note> to Ephesus and found some disciples. <verse-number id="Ac 19:2">2</verse-number>And he said to them, “Did you receive the Holy Spirit <supplied>when you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“believed”) which is understood as temporal</note> believed?” And they <supplied>said</supplied> to him, “But we have not even heard that there is a Holy Spirit!” <verse-number id="Ac 19:3">3</verse-number>And he said, “Into what then were you baptized?” And they said, “Into the baptism of John.” <verse-number id="Ac 19:4">4</verse-number>And Paul said, “John baptized <supplied>with</supplied> a baptism of repentance, telling the people that they should believe in the one who was to come after him—that is, in Jesus.” <verse-number id="Ac 19:5">5</verse-number>And <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> heard <supplied>this</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> they were baptized in the name of the Lord Jesus. <verse-number id="Ac 19:6">6</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“laid”)</note> Paul laid hands<note>Some manuscripts have “placed his hands”</note> on them, the Holy Spirit came upon them and they began to speak<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to speak”)</note> in tongues and to prophesy. <verse-number id="Ac 19:7">7</verse-number>(Now the total <supplied>number</supplied> <supplied>of</supplied> men was about twelve.) </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 19:8">8</verse-number>So he entered into the synagogue <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“entered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> was speaking boldly for three months, discussing and attempting to convince<note>The present tense participle has been translated as a conative present (“attempting to convince”)</note> <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> concerning<note>Some manuscripts have “<supplied>of</supplied> the things concerning”</note> the kingdom of God. <verse-number id="Ac 19:9">9</verse-number>But when some became hardened and were disobedient, reviling the Way before the congregation, he departed from them <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“departed”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> took away the disciples, leading discussions every day in the lecture hall of Tyrannus. <verse-number id="Ac 19:10">10</verse-number>And this took place for two years, so that all who lived in Asia<note>A reference to the Roman province of Asia (modern Asia Minor)</note> heard the word of the Lord, both Jews and Greeks. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Would-be Exorcists</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 19:11">11</verse-number>And God was performing <idiom-start/>extraordinary<idiom-end/><note>Literally “not the ordinary”</note> miracles by the hands of Paul, <verse-number id="Ac 19:12">12</verse-number>so that even handkerchiefs or work aprons <idiom-start/>that had touched his skin<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from his skin”</note> were carried away to those who were sick, and <supplied>their</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> diseases left them and the evil spirits came out <supplied>of them</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The words “<supplied>of them</supplied>” are not in the Greek text but are implied</note> <verse-number id="Ac 19:13">13</verse-number>But some itinerant Jewish exorcists also attempted to pronounce the name of the Lord Jesus over those who had evil spirits, saying, “I adjure you by Jesus whom Paul preaches!” <verse-number id="Ac 19:14">14</verse-number>(Now seven sons of a certain Sceva, a Jewish chief priest, were doing this.) <verse-number id="Ac 19:15">15</verse-number>But the evil spirit answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to them, “Jesus I know, and Paul I am acquainted with, but who are you?” <verse-number id="Ac 19:16">16</verse-number>And the man <idiom-start/>who had the evil spirit<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in whom the evil spirit was”</note> leaped on them, subdued all of them, <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “and” is supplied because the two previous participles (“leaped” and “subdued”) have been translated as finite verbs</note> prevailed against them, so that they ran away from that house naked and wounded. <verse-number id="Ac 19:17">17</verse-number>And this became known to all who lived in Ephesus, both Jews and Greeks, and fear fell upon them all, and the name of the Lord Jesus was exalted. <verse-number id="Ac 19:18">18</verse-number>And many of those who had believed came, confessing and disclosing their practices, <verse-number id="Ac 19:19">19</verse-number>and many of those who practiced magic brought together <supplied>their</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> books <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“brought together”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> burned <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> up in the sight of everyone. And they counted up their value and found <supplied>it was</supplied> <idiom-start/>fifty thousand silver coins<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “five ten thousands of silver coins”</note> <verse-number id="Ac 19:20">20</verse-number>In this way the word of the Lord was growing in power and was prevailing. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A Major Riot in Ephesus</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 19:21">21</verse-number>Now when these <supplied>things</supplied> were completed, Paul resolved in the Spirit to go to Jerusalem, passing through Macedonia and Achaia, saying, “After I have been there, it is necessary <supplied>for</supplied> me to see Rome also.” <verse-number id="Ac 19:22">22</verse-number>So <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“sending”) which is understood as temporal</note> sending two of those who were assisting him, Timothy and Erastus, to Macedonia, he himself stayed <supplied>some</supplied> time in Asia.<note>A reference to the Roman province of Asia (modern Asia Minor)</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 19:23">23</verse-number>Now there happened at that time no little disturbance concerning the Way. <verse-number id="Ac 19:24">24</verse-number>For someone <idiom-start/>named<idiom-end/><note>Literally “by name”</note> Demetrius, a silversmith who made silver replicas of the temple of Artemis, was bringing no little business to the craftsmen. <verse-number id="Ac 19:25">25</verse-number><idiom-start/>These<idiom-end/><note>Literally “whom”</note> he gathered together, and the workers occupied with such things, <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“gathered together”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “Men, you know that from this business <idiom-start/>we get our prosperity<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “prosperity is to us”</note> <verse-number id="Ac 19:26">26</verse-number>and you see and hear that not only in Ephesus but in almost all of Asia<note>A reference to the Roman province of Asia (modern Asia Minor)</note> this man Paul has persuaded <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“has persuaded”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> turned away a large crowd <supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saying”) which is understood as means</note> saying that the <supplied>gods</supplied> made by hands are not gods. <verse-number id="Ac 19:27">27</verse-number>So not only is there a danger this line of business of ours <supplied>will</supplied> come into disrepute, but also the temple of the great goddess Artemis <supplied>will</supplied> be regarded as nothing—and <supplied>she</supplied> is about to be brought down even from her grandeur, <supplied>she</supplied> whom the whole <supplied>of</supplied> Asia<note>A reference to the Roman province of Asia (modern Asia Minor)</note> and the <supplied>entire</supplied> world worship!” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 19:28">28</verse-number>And <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> heard <supplied>this</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and became full of rage, they began to shout,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to shout”)</note> saying, “Great <supplied>is</supplied> Artemis of the Ephesians!” <verse-number id="Ac 19:29">29</verse-number>And the city was filled with the tumult, and with one purpose they rushed into the theater, seizing Gaius and Aristarchus, Macedonians <supplied>who were</supplied> traveling companions of Paul. <verse-number id="Ac 19:30">30</verse-number>But <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“wanted”)</note> Paul wanted to enter into the popular assembly, the disciples would not let him. <verse-number id="Ac 19:31">31</verse-number>And even some of the Asiarchs<note>Or “provincial authorities”</note> who were his friends sent <supplied>word</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to him <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“sent”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> were urging <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> not to risk himself <supplied>by going</supplied> into the theater. <verse-number id="Ac 19:32">32</verse-number>So some were shouting <supplied>one thing</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <supplied>and</supplied> some another, for the assembly was in confusion, and the majority did not know <idiom-start/>why<idiom-end/><note>Literally “on account of what”</note> they had assembled. <verse-number id="Ac 19:33">33</verse-number>And <supplied>some</supplied> of the crowd advised<note>Or “concluded <supplied>it was about</supplied>”</note> Alexander, <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“put … forward”)</note> the Jews put him forward. But Alexander, motioning <supplied>with his</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> hand, was wanting to defend himself to the popular assembly. <verse-number id="Ac 19:34">34</verse-number>But <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“recognized”) which is understood as temporal</note> recognized that he was a Jew, they were shouting with one voice from all <supplied>of them</supplied> for about two hours, “Great <supplied>is</supplied> Artemis of the Ephesians!” <verse-number id="Ac 19:35">35</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had quieted”) which is understood as temporal</note> the city secretary had quieted the crowd, he said, “Ephesian men, for who is there among men who does not know the Ephesian city is honorary temple keeper of the great Artemis and of <supplied>her</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> image fallen from heaven? <verse-number id="Ac 19:36">36</verse-number>Therefore <supplied>because</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the causal genitive absolute participle (“are”)</note> these <supplied>things</supplied> are undeniable, it is necessary <supplied>that</supplied> you be quiet and do nothing rash! <verse-number id="Ac 19:37">37</verse-number>For you have brought these men <supplied>here</supplied> <supplied>who are</supplied> neither temple robbers nor blasphemers of our goddess. <verse-number id="Ac 19:38">38</verse-number>If then Demetrius and the craftsmen <supplied>who are</supplied> with him have a complaint against anyone, the court days are observed and there are proconsuls—let them bring charges against one another! <verse-number id="Ac 19:39">39</verse-number>But if you desire anything further, it will be settled in the lawful assembly. <verse-number id="Ac 19:40">40</verse-number>For indeed we are in danger of being accused of rioting concerning today, <supplied>since there</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>since</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the causal genitive absolute participle (“is”)</note> is no cause in relation to which we will be able to give an account concerning this disorderly gathering!” And <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had said”) which is understood as temporal</note> had said these <supplied>things</supplied>, he dismissed the assembly.<note>Verse <cite title="BibleLEB2:Ac 19:41">41</cite> in the English Bible is included as part of v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Ac 19:40">40</cite> in the standard editions of the Greek text</note> </p>
		</chapter>