<chapter id="Ac 20">
			<pericope>Paul Travels Through Macedonia and Greece</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 20:1">1</verse-number> Now after the turmoil had ceased, Paul summoned<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the participle (“summoned”) has been translated as a finite verb in keeping with English style</note> the disciples, and <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“encouraging”) which is understood as temporal</note> encouraging <supplied>them</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> he said farewell <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“departed”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> departed to travel to Macedonia. <verse-number id="Ac 20:2">2</verse-number>And <supplied>after he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had gone through”) which is understood as temporal</note> had gone through those regions and encouraged them <idiom-start/>at length<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “with many a word”</note> he came to Greece <verse-number id="Ac 20:3">3</verse-number>and stayed<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the participle (“stayed”) has been translated as a finite verb in keeping with English style</note> three months. <supplied>Because</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the causal genitive absolute participle (“was made”)</note> a plot was made against him by the Jews <supplied>as he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was about to”) which is understood as temporal</note> was about to set sail for Syria, he came to a decision to return through Macedonia. <verse-number id="Ac 20:4">4</verse-number>And Sopater <supplied>son</supplied> of Pyrrhus from Berea, and Aristarchus and Secundus from Thessalonica, and Gaius from Derbe, and Timothy, and Tychicus and Trophimus from Asia, were accompanying him. <verse-number id="Ac 20:5">5</verse-number>And these had gone on ahead <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“had gone on ahead”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> were waiting for us in Troas. <verse-number id="Ac 20:6">6</verse-number>And we sailed away from Philippi after the days of Unleavened Bread and came to them at Troas within five days, where we stayed seven days. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Eutychus Falls from a Window</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 20:7">7</verse-number>And on the first <supplied>day</supplied> of the week, <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“had assembled”)</note> we had assembled to break bread, Paul began conversing<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began conversing”)</note> with them, <supplied>because he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was going to”) which is understood as causal</note> was going to leave on the next day, and he extended <supplied>his</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> message until midnight. <verse-number id="Ac 20:8">8</verse-number>Now there were quite a few lamps in the upstairs room where we were gathered. <verse-number id="Ac 20:9">9</verse-number>And a certain young man <idiom-start/>named<idiom-end/><note>Literally “by name”</note> Eutychus who was sitting in the window was sinking into a deep sleep <supplied>while</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was conversing”)</note> Paul was conversing at length. Being overcome by sleep, he fell down from the third story and was picked up dead. <verse-number id="Ac 20:10">10</verse-number>But Paul went down <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went down”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> threw himself on him, and putting his arms around <supplied>him</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> said, “Do not be distressed, for his life is in him.” <verse-number id="Ac 20:11">11</verse-number>So he went up and broke bread,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*This participle and the previous one (“went up”) have been translated as finite verbs in keeping with English style</note> and <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had eaten”) which is understood as temporal</note> had eaten and talked for a long <supplied>time</supplied>, until dawn, then he departed. <verse-number id="Ac 20:12">12</verse-number>And they led the youth away alive, and <idiom-start/>were greatly<idiom-end/><note>Literally “were not moderately”</note> comforted. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Voyage to Miletus</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 20:13">13</verse-number>But we went on ahead to the ship <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went on ahead”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> put out to sea for Assos, intending to take Paul on board there. For having made arrangements in this way, he himself was intending to travel by land. <verse-number id="Ac 20:14">14</verse-number>And when he met us at Assos, we took him on board <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“took … on board”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> went to Mitylene. <verse-number id="Ac 20:15">15</verse-number>And we sailed from there on the next <supplied>day</supplied>, <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“sailed”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> arrived opposite Chios. And on the next <supplied>day</supplied> we approached Samos, and on the following <supplied>day</supplied> we came to Miletus. <verse-number id="Ac 20:16">16</verse-number>For Paul had decided to sail past Ephesus so that he would not be <supplied>having</supplied> to spend time in Asia.<note>A reference to the Roman province of Asia (modern Asia Minor)</note> For he was hurrying if it could be possible for him to be in Jerusalem on the day of Pentecost. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Paul’s Farewell to the Ephesian Elders</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 20:17">17</verse-number>And from Miletus he sent <supplied>word</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to Ephesus <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“sent”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> summoned the elders of the church. <verse-number id="Ac 20:18">18</verse-number>And when they came to him, he said to them, “You know from the first day on which I set foot in Asia<note>A reference to the Roman province of Asia (modern Asia Minor)</note> how I was the whole time with you—<verse-number id="Ac 20:19">19</verse-number>serving the Lord with all humility and with tears, and with the trials that happened to me through the plots of the Jews—<verse-number id="Ac 20:20">20</verse-number>how I did not shrink from proclaiming to you anything that would be profitable, and <supplied>from</supplied> teaching you in public and from house <supplied>to house</supplied>, <verse-number id="Ac 20:21">21</verse-number>testifying both to Jews and to Greeks with respect to repentance toward God and faith in our Lord Jesus. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 20:22">22</verse-number>“And now behold, bound by the Spirit I am traveling to Jerusalem, not knowing the things that will happen to me <idiom-start/>there<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “in it”</note> <verse-number id="Ac 20:23">23</verse-number>except that the Holy Spirit testifies to me in town <supplied>after town</supplied>, saying that bonds and persecutions await me. <verse-number id="Ac 20:24">24</verse-number>But I consider <supplied>my</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> life <supplied>as</supplied> worth <idiom-start/>nothing<idiom-end/><note>Or “not a single word”; literally “not any thing”</note> to myself, in order to finish my mission and the ministry that I received from the Lord Jesus, to testify <supplied>to</supplied> the gospel of the grace of God. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 20:25">25</verse-number>“And now behold, I know that all <supplied>of</supplied> you, among whom I went about proclaiming the kingdom, will see my face no more. <verse-number id="Ac 20:26">26</verse-number>Therefore I testify to you on this very day that I am guiltless of the blood of all <supplied>of you</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The words “<supplied>of you</supplied>” are not in the Greek text but are implied</note> <verse-number id="Ac 20:27">27</verse-number>for I did not shrink from proclaiming to you the whole purpose of God. <verse-number id="Ac 20:28">28</verse-number>Be on guard for yourselves and for all the flock among which the Holy Spirit has appointed you <supplied>as</supplied> overseers, to shepherd the church of God which he obtained through the blood of his own <supplied>Son</supplied>.<note>Or “through his own blood”; the Greek construction can be taken either way, with “Son” implied if the meaning is “through the blood of his own”</note> <verse-number id="Ac 20:29">29</verse-number>I know that after my departure fierce wolves will come in among you, not sparing the flock. <verse-number id="Ac 20:30">30</verse-number>And from among you yourselves men will arise, speaking <idiom-start/>perversions of the truth<idiom-end/><note>Literally “crooked things”</note> in order to draw away the disciples after them. <verse-number id="Ac 20:31">31</verse-number>Therefore be on the alert, remembering that night and day <supplied>for</supplied> three years I did not stop warning each one <supplied>of you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The words “<supplied>of you</supplied>” are not in the Greek text but are implied</note> with tears. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 20:32">32</verse-number>“And now I entrust you to God and to the message of his grace, which is able to build <supplied>you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> up and to give <supplied>you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> the inheritance among all those who are sanctified. <verse-number id="Ac 20:33">33</verse-number>I have desired no one’s silver or gold or clothing! <verse-number id="Ac 20:34">34</verse-number>You yourselves know that these hands served <supplied>to meet</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The words “<supplied>to meet</supplied>” are not in the Greek text but are supplied for clarity</note> my needs and <supplied>the needs of</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The words “<supplied>the needs of</supplied>” are supplied in keeping with English style to maintain the parallelism with the earlier phrase “my needs”</note> those who were with me. <verse-number id="Ac 20:35">35</verse-number>I have shown you <supplied>with respect to</supplied> all <supplied>things</supplied> that <supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“working hard”) which is understood as means</note> working hard in this way it is necessary to help those who are in need, and to remember the words of the Lord Jesus that he himself said, “It is more blessed to give than to receive.”<note>Perhaps an allusion to <cite title="BibleLEB2: Mt 10:8">Matt 10:8; </cite>these exact words are not found in the NT gospels</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 20:36">36</verse-number>And <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had said”) which is understood as temporal</note> had said these <supplied>things</supplied>, he fell to his knees <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“fell to”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> prayed with them all. <verse-number id="Ac 20:37">37</verse-number>And there was considerable weeping by all, and <idiom-start/>hugging<idiom-end/><note>Literally “falling on the neck of”</note> Paul, they kissed him, <verse-number id="Ac 20:38">38</verse-number>especially distressed at the statement that he had said, that they were going to see his face no more. And they accompanied him to the ship. </p>
		</chapter>