<chapter id="Ac 21">
			<pericope>Paul Travels on to Jerusalem</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 21:1">1</verse-number> And it happened that after we tore ourselves away<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the participle (“tore ourselves away”) has been translated as a finite verb in keeping with English style</note> from them, we put out to sea, <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous infinitive (“put out to sea”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> running a straight course we came to Cos and on the next <supplied>day</supplied> to Rhodes, and from there to Patara. <verse-number id="Ac 21:2">2</verse-number>And finding a ship that was crossing over to Phoenicia, we went aboard <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went aboard”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> put out to sea. <verse-number id="Ac 21:3">3</verse-number>And <supplied>after we</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“sighted”) which is understood as temporal</note> sighted Cyprus and left it behind <idiom-start/>on the port side<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “left”</note> we sailed to Syria and arrived at Tyre, because the ship was to unload <supplied>its</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> cargo there. <verse-number id="Ac 21:4">4</verse-number>And we stayed there seven days <supplied>after we</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“found”) which is understood as temporal</note> found the disciples, who kept telling Paul through the Spirit not to set foot in Jerusalem. <verse-number id="Ac 21:5">5</verse-number>And it happened that when our days were over, we departed <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“departed”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> went on our way, <supplied>while</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“accompanied”)</note> all <supplied>of them</supplied> accompanied us, together with <supplied>their</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The word “<supplied>their</supplied>” is not in the Greek text but is implied</note> wives and children, as far as outside the city. And <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“falling to”) which is understood as temporal</note> falling to our knees on the beach <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “and” is supplied to join this and the previous participle (“falling to”) in keeping with English style</note> praying, <verse-number id="Ac 21:6">6</verse-number>we said farewell to one another and embarked in the ship, and they returned to their own <supplied>homes</supplied>. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 21:7">7</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had completed”) which is understood as temporal</note> we had completed the voyage from Tyre, we arrived at Ptolemais. And <supplied>after we</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“greeted”) which is understood as temporal</note> greeted the brothers, we stayed one day with them. <verse-number id="Ac 21:8">8</verse-number>And on the next day we departed <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “and” is supplied to join this and the previous participle (“departed”) in keeping with English style</note> came to Caesarea, and entered into the house of Philip the evangelist, who was <supplied>one</supplied> of the seven, <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “and” is supplied to join this and the previous participle (“was”) in keeping with English style</note> stayed with him. <verse-number id="Ac 21:9">9</verse-number>(<idiom-start/>Now this man had<idiom-end/><note>Literally “now to this man were”</note> four virgin daughters who prophesied.) </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 21:10">10</verse-number>And <supplied>while we</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“were staying”)</note> were staying <supplied>there</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> many days, a certain prophet <idiom-start/>named<idiom-end/><note>Literally “by name”</note> Agabus came down from Judea. <verse-number id="Ac 21:11">11</verse-number>And he came to us and took Paul’s belt. Tying up his own feet and hands, he said, “This is what the Holy Spirit says: ‘In this way the Jews in Jerusalem will tie up the man whose belt this is, and will deliver <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> into the hands of the Gentiles.’ ” <verse-number id="Ac 21:12">12</verse-number>And when we heard these <supplied>things</supplied>, both we and the local residents urged him not to go up to Jerusalem. <verse-number id="Ac 21:13">13</verse-number>Then Paul replied, “What are you doing weeping and breaking my heart? For I am ready not only to be tied up, but even to die in Jerusalem for the name of the Lord Jesus!” <verse-number id="Ac 21:14">14</verse-number>And <supplied>because</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the causal genitive absolute participle (“be persuaded”)</note> he would not be persuaded, we remained silent, saying, “The will of the Lord be done.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 21:15">15</verse-number>So after these days we got ready <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“got ready”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> went up to Jerusalem. <verse-number id="Ac 21:16">16</verse-number>And <supplied>some</supplied> of the disciples from Caesarea also traveled together with us, bringing <supplied>us</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to a certain Mnason of Cyprus, a disciple of long standing,<note>Or perhaps “one of the original disciples”</note> with whom we were to be entertained as guests. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Paul Visits the Leaders of the Jerusalem Church</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 21:17">17</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“came”)</note> we came to Jerusalem, the brothers welcomed us gladly. <verse-number id="Ac 21:18">18</verse-number>And on the next <supplied>day</supplied> Paul went in with us to James, and all the elders were present. <verse-number id="Ac 21:19">19</verse-number>And <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“greeting”) which is understood as temporal</note> greeting them, he began to relate<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to relate”)</note> <idiom-start/>one after the other<idiom-end/><note>Literally “with respect to each one”</note> <supplied>the things</supplied> which God had done among the Gentiles through his ministry. <verse-number id="Ac 21:20">20</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> they heard <supplied>this</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> they began to glorify<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to glorify”)</note> God. And they said to him, “You see, brother, how many ten thousands there are among the Jews who have believed, and they are all zealous adherents of the law. <verse-number id="Ac 21:21">21</verse-number>And they have been informed about you that you are teaching all the Jews <supplied>who are</supplied> among the Gentiles <supplied>the</supplied> abandonment of Moses, telling them not to circumcise <supplied>their</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> children or to live according to <supplied>our</supplied><note>Literally “according to the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> customs. <verse-number id="Ac 21:22">22</verse-number>What then <idiom-start/>is to be done<idiom-end/>?<note>Literally “is it”</note> Doubtless they will all hear that you have come! <verse-number id="Ac 21:23">23</verse-number>Therefore do this that we tell you: <idiom-start/>we have<idiom-end/><note>Literally “there are to us”</note> four men who have <supplied>taken</supplied> a vow upon themselves.<note>Some manuscripts have “on themselves”</note> <verse-number id="Ac 21:24">24</verse-number>Take these <supplied>men</supplied> <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“take”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> purify yourself along with them and <idiom-start/>pay their expenses<idiom-end/><note>Literally “spend on them”</note> so that they can shave <supplied>their</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> heads, and everyone will know that <supplied>the things</supplied> which they had been informed about you are nothing, but you yourself also agree with observing the law. <verse-number id="Ac 21:25">25</verse-number>But concerning the Gentiles who have believed, we have written a letter <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“deciding”) which is understood as temporal</note> deciding they should avoid food sacrificed to idols and blood and <supplied>what has been</supplied> strangled and sexual immorality.” <verse-number id="Ac 21:26">26</verse-number>Then Paul took along the men on the next day, <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” has been supplied in keeping with English style</note> <supplied>after he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had purified”) which is understood as temporal</note> had purified himself together with them, he entered into the temple <supplied>courts</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here “<supplied>courts</supplied>” is supplied to distinguish this area from the interior of the temple building itself</note> announcing the completion of the days of purification until <idiom-start/>the time<idiom-end/><note>Literally “which <supplied>time</supplied>”</note> the offering would be presented on behalf of each one of them. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Paul Arrested in the Temple Courts</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 21:27">27</verse-number>But when the seven days were about to be completed, the Jews from Asia<note>A reference to the Roman province of Asia (modern Asia Minor)</note> who had seen him in the temple <supplied>courts</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>courts</supplied>” is supplied to distinguish this area from the interior of the temple building itself</note> stirred up the whole crowd and laid hands on him, <verse-number id="Ac 21:28">28</verse-number>shouting, “Israelite men, help! This is the man who is teaching everyone everywhere against the people and the law and this place! And furthermore he also brought Greeks into the temple, and has defiled this holy place!” <verse-number id="Ac 21:29">29</verse-number>(For they had previously seen Trophimus the Ephesian in the city with him, whom they thought that Paul had brought into the temple.) <verse-number id="Ac 21:30">30</verse-number>And the whole city was stirred up, and the people came running together, and they seized Paul <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“seized”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> dragged him outside of the temple <supplied>courts</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here “<supplied>courts</supplied>” is supplied to distinguish this area from the interior of the temple building itself</note> and immediately the doors were shut. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 21:31">31</verse-number>And <supplied>as they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“were seeking”)</note> were seeking to kill him, a report came up to the military tribune of the cohort that all Jerusalem was in confusion. <verse-number id="Ac 21:32">32</verse-number><idiom-start/>He<idiom-end/><note>Literally “who”</note> immediately took along soldiers and centurions <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“took along”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> ran down to them. And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> they saw the military tribune and the soldiers, they stopped beating Paul. <verse-number id="Ac 21:33">33</verse-number>Then the military tribune came up <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> arrested him and ordered <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to be bound with two chains, and inquired who he was and what it was that he had done. <verse-number id="Ac 21:34">34</verse-number>But some in the crowd were shouting one thing <supplied>and</supplied> others <supplied>another</supplied>, and <supplied>because</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the causal genitive absolute participle (“able”)</note> he was not able to find out the truth on account of the commotion, he gave orders to bring him into the barracks.<note>Or “headquarters”</note> <verse-number id="Ac 21:35">35</verse-number>And when he came to the steps, it happened that he had to be carried by the soldiers on account of the violence of the crowd, <verse-number id="Ac 21:36">36</verse-number>for the crowd of people was following <supplied>them</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> shouting, “Away with him!” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Paul Permitted to Address the Crowd</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 21:37">37</verse-number>And <supplied>as he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was about to”) which is understood as temporal</note> was about to be brought into the barracks,<note>Or “headquarters”</note> Paul said to the military tribune, “Is it permitted for me to say something to you?” And he said, “Do you know Greek? <verse-number id="Ac 21:38">38</verse-number>Then you are not the Egyptian who before these days raised a revolt and led out into the wilderness the four thousand men of the Assassins?”<note>Also known as the “Sicarii” from the Latin word “sicarius” = dagger, after the short dagger used to assassinate political opponents</note> <verse-number id="Ac 21:39">39</verse-number>But Paul said, “I am a Jewish man from Tarsus in Cilicia, a citizen of no unimportant city. Now I ask you, allow me to speak to the people.” <verse-number id="Ac 21:40">40</verse-number>So <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“permitted”)</note> he permitted <supplied>him</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> Paul, standing there on the steps, motioned with <supplied>his</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> hand to the people. And <supplied>when there</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was”)</note> was a great silence, he addressed <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> in the Aramaic language, saying, </p>
		</chapter>