<chapter id="Ac 24">
			<pericope>Paul Before Felix at Caesarea Maritima</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 24:1">1</verse-number> And after five days the high priest Ananias came down with some elders and an attorney, a certain Tertullus, all of whom brought charges against Paul to the governor. <verse-number id="Ac 24:2">2</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“had been summoned”)</note> he had been summoned, Tertullus began to accuse <supplied>him</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> saying, “We have experienced<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here this participle (“have experienced”) and the following participle (“are taking place”) have been translated as finite verbs in keeping with English style</note> much<note>Or “many <supplied>years</supplied>,” with “years” understood</note> peace through you, and reforms are taking place in this nation through your foresight. <verse-number id="Ac 24:3">3</verse-number>Both in every <supplied>way</supplied> and everywhere we acknowledge <supplied>this</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> most excellent Felix, with all gratitude. <verse-number id="Ac 24:4">4</verse-number>But so that I may not impose on you for longer, I implore you to hear us briefly with your <supplied>customary</supplied> graciousness. <verse-number id="Ac 24:5">5</verse-number>For we have found<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here this participle (“found”) has been translated as a finite verb in keeping with English style</note> this man <supplied>to be</supplied> a public menace and one who causes riots among all the Jews throughout the Roman Empire<note>Literally “the inhabited earth,” but here this is probably rhetorical hyperbole for the Roman Empire, especially since Felix, the Roman governor, is being addressed</note> and a ringleader of the sect of the Nazarenes, <verse-number id="Ac 24:6">6</verse-number>who even attempted to desecrate the temple, and we arrested <idiom-start/>him<note>Literally “whom”</note>﻿<idiom-end/>.<note>Some later manuscripts include the following additional material between v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Ac 24:6">6</cite> and v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Ac 24:8">8</cite>: “and we wanted to judge him according to our law, (24:7) but Lysius the military tribune came and took him from our hands with much violence, (24:8) ordering his accusers to come before you.”</note> <verse-number id="Ac 24:8">8</verse-number><supplied>When</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“examine”) which is understood as temporal</note> you yourself examine <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> you will be able to find out from <idiom-start/>him<idiom-end/><note>Literally “whom”</note> about all these <supplied>things</supplied> of which we are accusing him.” <verse-number id="Ac 24:9">9</verse-number>And the Jews also joined in the attack, asserting these <supplied>things</supplied> were so. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 24:10">10</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“gestured”)</note> the governor gestured for him to speak, Paul replied, “<supplied>Because I</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“know”) which is understood as causal</note> know you have been a judge over this nation for many years, I defend myself cheerfully <supplied>with respect to</supplied> the things concerning myself. <verse-number id="Ac 24:11">11</verse-number>You can ascertain that <idiom-start/>it has not been more than<idiom-end/><note>Literally “there are not to me more than”</note> twelve days <idiom-start/>since<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from which <supplied>time</supplied>”</note> I went up to Jerusalem to worship. <verse-number id="Ac 24:12">12</verse-number>And neither did they find me arguing with anyone or making a crowd develop in the temple <supplied>courts</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>courts</supplied>” is supplied to distinguish this area from the interior of the temple building itself</note> nor in the synagogues nor throughout the city. <verse-number id="Ac 24:13">13</verse-number>Nor can they prove <supplied>the things</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to you concerning which they are now accusing me. <verse-number id="Ac 24:14">14</verse-number>But I do confess this to you, that according to the Way (which they call a sect), so I worship the God of our fathers, believing all things <supplied>that are</supplied> in accordance with the law and that are written in the prophets, <verse-number id="Ac 24:15">15</verse-number>having a hope in God which these <supplied>men</supplied> also themselves await: <supplied>that</supplied> there is going to be a resurrection of both the righteous and the unrighteous. <verse-number id="Ac 24:16">16</verse-number><idiom-start/>For this reason<idiom-end/><note>Literally “by this”</note> also <supplied>I</supplied> myself <idiom-start/>always<idiom-end/><note>Literally “through everything”</note> do my best to have a clear conscience toward God and people. <verse-number id="Ac 24:17">17</verse-number>So after many years, I came to practice charitable giving and offerings to my people,<note>Or “nation”</note> <verse-number id="Ac 24:18">18</verse-number>in which they found me purified in the temple <supplied>courts</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here “<supplied>courts</supplied>” is supplied to distinguish this area from the interior of the temple building itself</note> not with a crowd or with a disturbance. <verse-number id="Ac 24:19">19</verse-number>But <supplied>there are</supplied> some Jews from Asia<note>A reference to the Roman province of Asia (modern Asia Minor)</note> who ought to be present before you and bring charges against <supplied>me</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> if they have anything against me, <verse-number id="Ac 24:20">20</verse-number>or these <supplied>men</supplied> themselves should say what crime they found <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“stood”)</note> I stood before the Sanhedrin,<note>Or “council”</note> <verse-number id="Ac 24:21">21</verse-number>other than concerning this one declaration that I shouted <supplied>while</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“standing there”) which is understood as temporal</note> standing there before them: ‘I am being judged before you today concerning the resurrection of the dead!’ ” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Paul Held Awaiting Trial</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 24:22">22</verse-number>But Felix, <supplied>because he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“understood”) which is understood as causal</note> understood the <supplied>facts</supplied> concerning the Way more accurately, put them off, saying, “When Lysias the military tribune comes down, I will decide <idiom-start/>your case<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “the <supplied>case</supplied> with respect to you”</note> <verse-number id="Ac 24:23">23</verse-number><supplied>He</supplied> ordered<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here this participle (“ordered”) has been translated as a finite verb in keeping with English style</note> the centurion <supplied>for</supplied> him to be guarded and to have some freedom, and in no way to prevent any of his own <supplied>people</supplied><note>This could refer to either friends or relatives</note> <supplied>from</supplied> serving him. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 24:24">24</verse-number>And after some days, <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“arrived”) which is understood as temporal</note> Felix arrived with his wife Drusilla, who was Jewish, he sent for Paul and listened to him concerning faith in Christ Jesus. <verse-number id="Ac 24:25">25</verse-number>And <supplied>while</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was discussing”)</note> he was discussing about righteousness and self control and the judgment that is to come, Felix became afraid <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“became”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> replied, “Go away for the present, and <supplied>when I</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“have”) which is understood as temporal</note> have an opportunity, I will summon you.” <verse-number id="Ac 24:26">26</verse-number>At the same time he was also hoping that money would be given to him by Paul. For this reason also he sent for him as often as possible <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“sent for”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> talked with him. <verse-number id="Ac 24:27">27</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“had passed”)</note> two years had passed, Felix received as successor Porcius Festus. And <supplied>because he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“wanted”) which is understood as causal</note> wanted to do a favor for the Jews, Felix left Paul behind <idiom-start/>as a prisoner<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “bound”</note> </p>
		</chapter>