<chapter id="Ac 25">
			<pericope>Paul Appeals to Caesar</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 25:1">1</verse-number> Now <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“set foot in”) which is understood as temporal</note> Festus set foot in the province, after three days he went up to Jerusalem from Caesarea. <verse-number id="Ac 25:2">2</verse-number>And the chief priests and the most prominent men of the Jews brought charges against Paul to him, and were urging him, <verse-number id="Ac 25:3">3</verse-number>asking for a favor against him, that he summon him to Jerusalem, <supplied>because they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“were preparing ”) which is understood as causal</note> were preparing an ambush to do away with him along the way. <verse-number id="Ac 25:4">4</verse-number>Then Festus replied <supplied>that</supplied> Paul was being kept at Caesarea, and <supplied>he</supplied> himself was about to go <supplied>there</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> in a short time. <verse-number id="Ac 25:5">5</verse-number>So he said, “Let those among you <supplied>who are</supplied> prominent go down with <supplied>me</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“go down with”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> if there is any wrong in the man, let them bring charges against him.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 25:6">6</verse-number>And <supplied>after he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had stayed”) which is understood as temporal</note> had stayed among them not more than eight or ten days, he went down to Caesarea. On the next day he sat down on the judgment seat <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“sat down”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> gave orders <supplied>for</supplied> Paul to be brought. <verse-number id="Ac 25:7">7</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“arrived”)</note> he arrived, the Jews who had come down from Jerusalem stood around him, bringing many and serious charges that they were not able to prove, <verse-number id="Ac 25:8">8</verse-number><supplied>while</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“said in his defense”)</note> Paul said in his defense, “Neither against the law of the Jews nor against the temple nor against Caesar have I sinned with reference to anything!” <verse-number id="Ac 25:9">9</verse-number>But Festus, <supplied>because he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“wanted”) which is understood as causal</note> wanted to do a favor for the Jews, answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to Paul, “Are you willing to go up to Jerusalem to be tried before me there concerning these <supplied>things</supplied>?” <verse-number id="Ac 25:10">10</verse-number>But Paul said, “I am standing before the judgment seat of Caesar, where it is necessary <supplied>for</supplied> me to be judged. I have done no wrong to the Jews, as you also know very well. <verse-number id="Ac 25:11">11</verse-number>If then I am doing wrong<note>Or “I am in the wrong”</note> and have done anything deserving death, I am not trying to avoid<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the present tense has been translated as conative (“trying to avoid”)</note> dying. But if there is nothing <supplied>true</supplied> of <supplied>the things</supplied> which these <supplied>people</supplied> are accusing me, no one can give me up to them. I appeal to Caesar!” <verse-number id="Ac 25:12">12</verse-number>Then Festus, <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“discussing”) which is understood as temporal</note> discussing <supplied>this</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> with <supplied>his</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> council, replied, “You have appealed to Caesar—to Caesar you will go!” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Festus Asks King Agrippa for Advice</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 25:13">13</verse-number>Now <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“had passed”)</note> some days had passed, King Agrippa and Bernice arrived at Caesarea to welcome Festus. <verse-number id="Ac 25:14">14</verse-number>And while they were staying there many days, Festus laid out the <supplied>case</supplied> against Paul to the king, saying, “There is a certain man left behind by Felix <supplied>as</supplied> a prisoner, <verse-number id="Ac 25:15">15</verse-number>concerning whom <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was”)</note> I was in Jerusalem the chief priests and the elders of the Jews presented evidence, asking for a sentence of condemnation against him. <verse-number id="Ac 25:16">16</verse-number>To <idiom-start/>them<idiom-end/><note>Literally “whom”</note> I replied that it was not the custom of the Romans to give up any man before the one who had been accused met <supplied>his</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> accusers face to <supplied>face</supplied> and received an opportunity for a defense concerning the accusation. <verse-number id="Ac 25:17">17</verse-number>Therefore, <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“had assembled”)</note> they had assembled here, <supplied>I</supplied> made<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here this participle (“made”) has been translated as a finite verb in keeping with English style</note> no delay; on the next <supplied>day</supplied> I sat down on the judgment seat <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “and” is supplied because the two previous participles (“made” and “sat down”) have been translated as finite verbs</note> gave orders <supplied>for</supplied> the man to be brought. <verse-number id="Ac 25:18">18</verse-number><supplied>When they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“stood up”) which is understood as temporal</note> stood up, <supplied>his</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> accusers began bringing<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began bringing”)</note> no charge concerning <idiom-start/>him<idiom-end/><note>Literally “whom”</note> of the evil deeds that I was suspecting, <verse-number id="Ac 25:19">19</verse-number>but they had some issues with him concerning their own religion, and concerning a certain Jesus, who was dead, whom Paul claimed to be alive. <verse-number id="Ac 25:20">20</verse-number>And <supplied>because</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was at a loss”) which is understood as causal</note> I was at a loss with regard to the investigation concerning these <supplied>things</supplied>, I asked if he was willing to go to Jerusalem and to be judged there concerning these <supplied>things</supplied>. <verse-number id="Ac 25:21">21</verse-number>But <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“appealed”)</note> Paul appealed <supplied>that</supplied> he be kept under guard for the decision of His Majesty the Emperor, I gave orders <supplied>for</supplied> him to be kept under guard until I could send him to Caesar.” <verse-number id="Ac 25:22">22</verse-number>So Agrippa <supplied>said</supplied> to Festus, “I want to hear the man myself also.” “Tomorrow,” he said, “you will hear him.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 25:23">23</verse-number>So on the next day, Agrippa and Bernice came with great pageantry and entered into the audience hall, along with military tribunes and the most prominent men of the city. And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“gave the order”)</note> Festus gave the order, Paul was brought in. <verse-number id="Ac 25:24">24</verse-number>And Festus said, “King Agrippa and all who are present with us, you see this man about whom the whole population of the Jews appealed to me, both in Jerusalem and here, shouting <supplied>that</supplied> he must not live any longer. <verse-number id="Ac 25:25">25</verse-number>But I understood <supplied>that</supplied> he had done nothing deserving death himself, and <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“appealed to”)</note> this man appealed to His Majesty the Emperor, I decided to send <supplied>him</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <verse-number id="Ac 25:26">26</verse-number>I do not have anything definite to write to <supplied>my</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> lord about <idiom-start/>him<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “whom”</note> Therefore I have brought him before you <supplied>all</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>all</supplied>” is supplied in the translation to indicate that the pronoun (“you”) is plural</note>—and especially before you, King Agrippa—so that <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“has taken place”)</note> this preliminary hearing has taken place, I may have something to write. <verse-number id="Ac 25:27">27</verse-number>For it seems unreasonable to me to send a prisoner and not to indicate the charges against him.” </p>
		</chapter>