<chapter id="Ac 26">
			<pericope>Paul Makes His Defense Before King Agrippa</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 26:1">1</verse-number> So Agrippa said to Paul, “It is permitted for you to speak for yourself.” Then Paul extended <supplied>his</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> hand <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“extended”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> began to defend himself:<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to defend himself”)</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 26:2">2</verse-number>“Concerning all <supplied>the things</supplied> of which I am accused by the Jews, King Agrippa, I consider myself fortunate <supplied>that</supplied> before you I am about to defend myself today, <verse-number id="Ac 26:3">3</verse-number><supplied>because</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“are”) which is understood as causal</note> you are especially acquainted with both all the customs and controversial questions with respect to the Jews. Therefore I beg <supplied>you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to listen to me with patience. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 26:4">4</verse-number>“Now all the Jews know my manner of life from <supplied>my</supplied> youth, that had taken place from the beginning among my <supplied>own</supplied> people<note>Or “nation”</note> and in Jerusalem, <verse-number id="Ac 26:5">5</verse-number>having known me for a long time, if they are willing to testify, that in accordance with the strictest party of our religion I lived <supplied>as</supplied> a Pharisee. <verse-number id="Ac 26:6">6</verse-number>And now I stand here on trial on the basis of hope in the promise made by God to our fathers, <verse-number id="Ac 26:7">7</verse-number>to which our twelve tribes hope to attain as <supplied>they</supplied> earnestly serve <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> night and day. Concerning this hope I am being accused by the Jews, O king! <verse-number id="Ac 26:8">8</verse-number>Why is it thought incredible by you <supplied>people</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “people” is supplied in the translation to indicate that the pronoun (“you”) is plural</note> that God raises the dead? <verse-number id="Ac 26:9">9</verse-number>Indeed, I myself thought it was necessary to do many <supplied>things</supplied> opposed to the name of Jesus the Nazarene, <verse-number id="Ac 26:10">10</verse-number>which I also did in Jerusalem, and not only did I lock up many of the saints in prison, having received authority from the chief priests, but also <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“were being executed”)</note> they were being executed, I cast <supplied>my</supplied> vote<note>Literally “voting pebble,” but here “vote” rather than “voting pebble” is used in the translation to avoid the idea that this small stone was actually thrown at the accused (it was used as a method of voting)</note> against <supplied>them</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <verse-number id="Ac 26:11">11</verse-number>And throughout all the synagogues I punished them often <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“punished”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> tried to force<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The imperfect tense has been translated as conative here (“tried to force”)</note> <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to blaspheme, and <supplied>because I</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was enraged”) which is understood as causal</note> was enraged at them beyond measure, I was pursuing <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> even as far as to foreign cities. <verse-number id="Ac 26:12">12</verse-number>In <idiom-start/>this activity<idiom-end/><note>Literally “which”</note> I was traveling to Damascus with the authority and full power of the chief priests. <verse-number id="Ac 26:13">13</verse-number>In the middle of the day along the road, O king, I saw a light from heaven, more than the brightness of the sun, shining around me and those who were traveling with me. <verse-number id="Ac 26:14">14</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“had … fallen”)</note> we had all fallen to the ground, I heard a voice saying to me in the Aramaic language, ‘Saul, Saul, why are you persecuting me? <supplied>It is</supplied> hard for you to kick against the goads!’ <verse-number id="Ac 26:15">15</verse-number>So I said, ‘Who are you, Lord?’ And the Lord said, ‘I am Jesus whom you are persecuting. <verse-number id="Ac 26:16">16</verse-number>But get up and stand on your feet, because for this <supplied>reason</supplied> I have appeared to you, to appoint you a servant and witness both <supplied>to the things</supplied> in which you saw me and <supplied>to the things</supplied> in which I will appear to you, <verse-number id="Ac 26:17">17</verse-number>rescuing you from the people and from the Gentiles to whom I am sending you, <verse-number id="Ac 26:18">18</verse-number>to open their eyes <supplied>so that they</supplied> may turn from darkness to light and from the power of Satan to God, <supplied>so that</supplied> they may receive forgiveness of sins and a share among those who are sanctified by faith in me.’ </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 26:19">19</verse-number>“Therefore, O King Agrippa, I was not disobedient to the heavenly vision, <verse-number id="Ac 26:20">20</verse-number>but to those in Damascus first, and in Jerusalem and all the region of Judea and to the Gentiles, I proclaimed <supplied>that they should</supplied> repent and turn to God, doing deeds worthy of repentance. <verse-number id="Ac 26:21">21</verse-number>On account of these <supplied>things</supplied> the Jews seized me in<note>Some manuscripts have “while I was in”</note> the temple <supplied>courts</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>courts</supplied>” is supplied to distinguish this area from the interior of the temple building itself</note> <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“seized”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> were attempting to kill <supplied>me</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <verse-number id="Ac 26:22">22</verse-number>Therefore I have experienced help from God until this day, <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“have experienced”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> I stand here testifying to both small and great, saying nothing except what both the prophets and Moses have said were going to happen, <verse-number id="Ac 26:23">23</verse-number>that the Christ<note>Or “Messiah”</note> was to suffer <supplied>and</supplied> that <supplied>as</supplied> the first of the resurrection from the dead, he was going to proclaim light both to the people and to the Gentiles.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 26:24">24</verse-number>And <supplied>as</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was saying … in his defense”)</note> he was saying these things in his defense, Festus said with a loud voice, “You are out of your mind, Paul! <supplied>Your</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> great learning <idiom-start/>is driving<idiom-end/><note>Literally “is turning”</note> you <idiom-start/>insane<idiom-end/>!”<note>Literally “to madness”</note> <verse-number id="Ac 26:25">25</verse-number>But Paul said, “I am not out of my mind, most excellent Festus, but am speaking words of truth and rationality. <verse-number id="Ac 26:26">26</verse-number>For the king knows about these <supplied>things</supplied>, to whom also I am speaking freely, for I am not convinced <supplied>that</supplied> these <supplied>things</supplied> in any way have escaped<note>Some manuscripts have “that any of these <supplied>things</supplied> in any way has escaped”</note> his notice, because this <idiom-start/>was<idiom-end/><note>Literally “is”</note> not <idiom-start/>done<idiom-end/><note>Literally “having been done”</note> in a corner. <verse-number id="Ac 26:27">27</verse-number>Do you believe the prophets, King Agrippa? I know that you believe.” <verse-number id="Ac 26:28">28</verse-number>But Agrippa <supplied>said</supplied> to Paul, “In a short time are you persuading me to become a Christian?”<note>Or “In a short time you are persuading me to become a Christian”</note> <verse-number id="Ac 26:29">29</verse-number>And Paul <supplied>replied</supplied>, “I pray to God, whether in a short time or in a long time, not only you but also all those who are listening to me today may become such <supplied>people</supplied> as I also am, except for these bonds!” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 26:30">30</verse-number>Both the king and the governor got up, and Bernice and those who were sitting with them. <verse-number id="Ac 26:31">31</verse-number>And <supplied>as they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“were going out”)</note> were going out, they were talking to one another, saying, “This man is not doing anything deserving death or imprisonment.” <verse-number id="Ac 26:32">32</verse-number>And Agrippa said to Festus, “This man could have been released if he had not appealed to Caesar.” </p>
		</chapter>