<chapter id="Ac 27">
			<pericope>Paul and His Associates Sail for Rome</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 27:1">1</verse-number> And when it was decided <supplied>that</supplied> we would sail away to Italy, they handed over Paul and some other prisoners to a centurion <idiom-start/>named<idiom-end/><note>Literally “by name”</note> Julius of the Augustan<note>The meaning and significance of the title “Augustan” is highly debated, as is the precise identification of this military unit; it may be an honorary unit designation given to auxiliary or provincial troops</note> Cohort. <verse-number id="Ac 27:2">2</verse-number>And we went aboard a ship from Adramyttium that was about to sail to the places along the <supplied>coast</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The word “<supplied>coast</supplied>” is not in the Greek text but is implied</note> of Asia<note>A reference to the Roman province of Asia (modern Asia Minor)</note> <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went aboard”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> put out to sea. Aristarchus, a Macedonian from Thessalonica, was with us. <verse-number id="Ac 27:3">3</verse-number>And on the next <supplied>day</supplied>, we put in at Sidon. And Julius, treating Paul kindly, allowed <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to go to <supplied>his</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> friends <idiom-start/>to be cared for<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to experience care”</note> <verse-number id="Ac 27:4">4</verse-number>And from there we put out to sea <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“put out to sea”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> sailed under the lee of Cyprus, because the winds were against <supplied>us</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <verse-number id="Ac 27:5">5</verse-number>And <supplied>after we</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had sailed across”) which is understood as temporal</note> had sailed across the open sea along Cilicia and Pamphylia, we put in at Myra in Lycia. <verse-number id="Ac 27:6">6</verse-number>And there the centurion found an Alexandrian ship sailing for Italy <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“found”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> put us <idiom-start/>on board<idiom-end/><note>Literally “into”</note> it. <verse-number id="Ac 27:7">7</verse-number>And sailing slowly, in many days and with difficulty we came<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here this participle (“came”) has been translated as a finite verb in keeping with English style</note> to Cnidus. <supplied>Because</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the causal genitive absolute participle (“permit … to go further”)</note> the wind did not permit us to go further, we sailed under the lee of Crete off Salmone. <verse-number id="Ac 27:8">8</verse-number>And sailing along its coast with difficulty, we came to a certain place called Fair Havens, near which was the town <supplied>of</supplied> Lasea. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 27:9">9</verse-number>And <supplied>because</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the causal genitive absolute participle (“had passed”)</note> considerable time had passed and the voyage was now dangerous because even the Fast<note>A reference to the Jewish Day of Atonement (Yom Kippur) which occurs in mid-autumn</note> was already over, Paul strongly recommended, <verse-number id="Ac 27:10">10</verse-number>saying to them, “Men, I perceive that the voyage is going <idiom-start/>to end<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to be”</note> with disaster and great loss, not only of the cargo and the ship, but also of our lives!” <verse-number id="Ac 27:11">11</verse-number>But the centurion was convinced even more by the shipmaster and the shipowner than by what was said by Paul. <verse-number id="Ac 27:12">12</verse-number>And <supplied>because</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the causal genitive absolute participle (“was”)</note> the harbor was unsuitable for spending the winter in, the majority decided on a plan to put out to sea from there, if somehow they could arrive at Phoenix, a harbor of Crete facing toward the southwest and toward the northwest, to spend the winter <supplied>there</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A Violent Storm at Sea</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 27:13">13</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“began to blow gently”)</note> a southwest wind began to blow gently, <supplied>because they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“thought”) which is understood as causal</note> thought <supplied>they</supplied> could accomplish their purpose, they weighed anchor <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“weighed anchor”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> sailed close along Crete. <verse-number id="Ac 27:14">14</verse-number>But not long afterward a wind like a hurricane, called the northeaster,<note>Literally “Euraquilo,” a violent northern wind</note> rushed down from it.<note>That is, from the island of Crete</note> <verse-number id="Ac 27:15">15</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was caught”)</note> the ship was caught and <supplied>was</supplied> not able to head into the wind, we gave way <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“gave way”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> were driven <supplied>along</supplied>. <verse-number id="Ac 27:16">16</verse-number>And running under the lee of a certain small island called Cauda, we were able with difficulty to get the ship’s boat under control. <verse-number id="Ac 27:17">17</verse-number><supplied>After</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“hoisting”) which is understood as temporal</note> hoisting <idiom-start/>it up<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “which”</note> they made use of supports to undergird the ship. And <supplied>because they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“were afraid”) which is understood as causal</note> were afraid lest they run aground on the Syrtis, they lowered the sea anchor <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“lowered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> thus were driven <supplied>along</supplied>. <verse-number id="Ac 27:18">18</verse-number>And <supplied>because</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the causal genitive absolute participle (“battered by the storm”)</note> we were violently battered by the storm, on the next <supplied>day</supplied> <idiom-start/>they began<idiom-end/><note>Literally “they began to carry out”</note> jettisoning <supplied>the cargo</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <verse-number id="Ac 27:19">19</verse-number>and on the third <supplied>day</supplied> they threw overboard the gear of the ship with their own hands. <verse-number id="Ac 27:20">20</verse-number>But <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“appeared”)</note> neither sun nor stars appeared for many days, and <supplied>with</supplied> not a little bad weather confronting <supplied>us</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> finally all hope was abandoned <supplied>that</supplied> we would be saved. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 27:21">21</verse-number>And <supplied>because</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the causal genitive absolute participle (“were experiencing”)</note> many were experiencing lack of appetite, at that time Paul stood up in their midst <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“stood up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “Men, <supplied>you</supplied> ought to have followed my <supplied>advice</supplied> not to put out to sea from Crete, and <supplied>thus</supplied> avoided this damage and loss! <verse-number id="Ac 27:22">22</verse-number>And now I urge you to cheer up, for there will be no loss of life from among you, but only of the ship. <verse-number id="Ac 27:23">23</verse-number>For this night an angel of the God whose I am and whom I serve came to me, <verse-number id="Ac 27:24">24</verse-number>saying, ‘Do not be afraid, Paul! It is necessary <supplied>for</supplied> you to stand before Caesar, and behold, God has graciously granted you all who are sailing with you.’ <verse-number id="Ac 27:25">25</verse-number>Therefore keep up your courage, men, for I believe God that it will be like this—according to <idiom-start/>the<idiom-end/><note>Literally “which”</note> way it was told to me. <verse-number id="Ac 27:26">26</verse-number>But it is necessary <supplied>that</supplied> we run aground on some island.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 27:27">27</verse-number>And when the fourteenth night had come, <supplied>as</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“were being driven”)</note> we were being driven in the Adriatic Sea about the middle of the night, the sailors suspected <idiom-start/>they were approaching some land<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “some land was approaching them”</note> <verse-number id="Ac 27:28">28</verse-number>And taking soundings, they found twenty fathoms. So going on a little <supplied>further</supplied> and taking soundings again, they found fifteen fathoms. <verse-number id="Ac 27:29">29</verse-number>And <supplied>because they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“were afraid”) which is understood as causal</note> were afraid lest somewhere we run aground against rough places, they threw down four anchors from the stern <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“threw down”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> prayed for day to come. <verse-number id="Ac 27:30">30</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“were seeking”)</note> the sailors were seeking to escape from the ship and were lowering the ship’s boat into the sea, pretending as if they were going to lay out anchors from the bow, <verse-number id="Ac 27:31">31</verse-number>Paul said to the centurion and the soldiers, “Unless these <supplied>men</supplied> remain with the ship, you cannot be saved!” <verse-number id="Ac 27:32">32</verse-number>Then the soldiers cut away the ropes of the ship’s boat and let it fall away.<note>Or “let it drift away”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 27:33">33</verse-number>And until the day was about to come, Paul was urging <supplied>them</supplied> all to take <supplied>some</supplied> food, saying, “Today <supplied>is the</supplied> fourteenth day you have waited <supplied>anxiously</supplied>, <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“have waited”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> you have continued without eating, having taken nothing. <verse-number id="Ac 27:34">34</verse-number>Therefore I urge you to take <supplied>some</supplied> food, for this is necessary for your preservation. For not a hair from your head will be lost.” <verse-number id="Ac 27:35">35</verse-number>And <supplied>after he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“said”) which is understood as temporal</note> said these <supplied>things</supplied> and took bread, he gave thanks to God in front of <supplied>them</supplied> all, and <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“breaking”) which is understood as temporal</note> breaking <supplied>it</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> he began to eat. <verse-number id="Ac 27:36">36</verse-number>So they all were<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here this participle (“were”) has been translated as a finite verb in keeping with English style</note> encouraged and partook of food themselves. <verse-number id="Ac 27:37">37</verse-number>(Now we were <supplied>in</supplied> all two hundred seventy six persons on the ship.) <verse-number id="Ac 27:38">38</verse-number>And <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had eaten their fill”) which is understood as temporal</note> had eaten their fill of food, they lightened the ship <supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“throwing”) which is understood as means</note> throwing the wheat<note>Or “grain”</note> into the sea. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Shipwreck</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 27:39">39</verse-number>Now when day came, they did not recognize the land, but they noticed a certain bay having a beach, onto which they decided to run the ship ashore if they could. <verse-number id="Ac 27:40">40</verse-number>And slipping the anchors, they left <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> in the sea, at the same time loosening the ropes<note>Or “bands” (referring to the linkage that tied the steering oars together)</note> of the steering oars. And hoisting the foresail to the <supplied>wind</supplied> that was blowing, they held course for the beach. <verse-number id="Ac 27:41">41</verse-number>But falling into a place of crosscurrents,<note>Or “a reef”; literally “a place of two seas,” an expression of uncertain meaning but most likely a nautical technical term for some adverse sea condition</note> they ran the ship aground. And the bow stuck fast <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“stuck fast”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> stayed immovable, but the stern was being broken up by the violence.<note>Some manuscripts have “the violence of the waves”</note> <verse-number id="Ac 27:42">42</verse-number>Now the plan of the soldiers was that they would kill the prisoners lest any escape <supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“swimming away”) which is understood as means</note> swimming away, <verse-number id="Ac 27:43">43</verse-number>but the centurion, <supplied>because he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“wanted”) which is understood as causal</note> wanted to save Paul, prevented them <idiom-start/>from doing what they intended<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “of the intention”</note> and gave orders <supplied>that</supplied> those who were able to swim should jump in first to get to the land, <verse-number id="Ac 27:44">44</verse-number>and <supplied>then</supplied> the rest, <supplied>some</supplied> of whom <supplied>floated</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The word “<supplied>floated</supplied>” is not in the Greek text, but is supplied in the translation for clarity</note> on planks and <supplied>some</supplied> of whom on anything <supplied>that was</supplied> from the ship. And in this way all were brought safely to the land. </p>
		</chapter>