<chapter id="Ac 28">
			<pericope>Paul on Malta</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 28:1">1</verse-number> And <supplied>after we</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“were brought safely through”) which is understood as temporal</note> were brought safely through, then we found out that the island was called Malta. <verse-number id="Ac 28:2">2</verse-number>And the local inhabitants showed <idiom-start/>extraordinary<idiom-end/><note>Literally “not the ordinary”</note> kindness to us, for they lit a fire <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“lit”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> welcomed us all, because of the rain that had begun and because of the cold. <verse-number id="Ac 28:3">3</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“had gathered”)</note> Paul had gathered a large number of sticks and was placing <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> on the fire, a viper came out because of the heat <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came out”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> fastened itself on his hand. <verse-number id="Ac 28:4">4</verse-number>And when the local people saw the creature hanging from his hand, they began saying<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began saying”)</note> to one another, “Doubtless this man is a murderer whom, <supplied>although he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>although</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was rescued”) which is understood as concessive</note> was rescued from the sea, Justice<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here personified as a goddess</note> has not permitted to live!” <verse-number id="Ac 28:5">5</verse-number>He, in turn, shook off the creature into the fire <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“shook off”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> suffered no harm. <verse-number id="Ac 28:6">6</verse-number>But they were expecting <supplied>that</supplied> he was going to swell up<note>Or “to burn with fever” (either meaning is possible here)</note> or suddenly to fall down dead. So <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“had waited”)</note> they had waited for a long <supplied>time</supplied> and saw nothing unusual happen to him, they changed their minds <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“changed their minds”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> began saying<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began saying”)</note> <supplied>that</supplied> he was a god. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 28:7">7</verse-number>Now in the <supplied>regions</supplied> around that place were fields belonging to the chief official of the island, <idiom-start/>named<idiom-end/><note>Literally “by name”</note> Publius, who welcomed us <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“welcomed”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> entertained <supplied>us</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> hospitably <supplied>for</supplied> three days. <verse-number id="Ac 28:8">8</verse-number>And it happened that the father of Publius was lying down, afflicted with fever and dysentery. Paul went<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here this participle (“went”) has been translated as a finite verb in keeping with English style</note> to <idiom-start/>him<idiom-end/><note>Literally “whom”</note> and <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“praying”) which is understood as temporal</note> praying, he placed <supplied>his</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> hands on him <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“placed”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> healed him. <verse-number id="Ac 28:9">9</verse-number>And <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“had taken place”)</note> this had taken place, the rest of those on the island who had diseases were coming and being healed also. <verse-number id="Ac 28:10">10</verse-number>They also honored us with many honors, and <supplied>when we</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“putting out to sea”) which is understood as temporal</note> were putting out to sea, they gave <supplied>us</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> the <supplied>things</supplied> <idiom-start/>we needed<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “for the needs”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Paul Arrives in Rome at Last</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 28:11">11</verse-number>Now after three months we put out to sea in a ship that had wintered at the island, an Alexandrian <supplied>one</supplied> <idiom-start/>with the twin gods Castor and Pollux as its insignia<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “marked with the Dioscuri” (a joint name for the twin gods Castor and Pollux)</note> <verse-number id="Ac 28:12">12</verse-number>And putting in at Syracuse, we stayed <supplied>there</supplied> three days. <verse-number id="Ac 28:13">13</verse-number>From there we got underway<note>Or “we sailed along” (with “the coast” understood); the exact meaning of the text as it stands is disputed and various additional terms have to be supplied in any case</note> <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“got underway”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> arrived at Rhegium, and after one day a south wind came up <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> on the second day we came to Puteoli, <verse-number id="Ac 28:14">14</verse-number>where we found brothers, <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“found”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> were implored to stay with them seven days. And in this way we came to Rome. <verse-number id="Ac 28:15">15</verse-number>And from there the brothers, <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> heard the <supplied>news</supplied> about us, came to meet us as far as the Forum of Appius and Three Taverns. <supplied>When he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> saw them, Paul gave thanks to God <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“gave thanks”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> took courage. <verse-number id="Ac 28:16">16</verse-number>And when we entered into Rome, Paul was allowed to stay by himself with the soldier who was guarding him. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Paul and the Jewish Community in Rome</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 28:17">17</verse-number>Now it happened that after three days, he called together those who were the most prominent of the Jews. And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“had assembled”)</note> they had assembled, he said to them, “Men <supplied>and</supplied> brothers, <supplied>although</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>although</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had done”) which is understood as concessive</note> I had done nothing against <supplied>our</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> people or the customs of our fathers, from Jerusalem I was delivered <supplied>as</supplied> a prisoner into the hands of the Romans, <verse-number id="Ac 28:18">18</verse-number>who, <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had examined”) which is understood as temporal</note> had examined me, were wanting to release <supplied>me</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> because there was no basis for an accusation <supplied>worthy</supplied> of death with me. <verse-number id="Ac 28:19">19</verse-number>But <supplied>because</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the causal genitive absolute participle (“objected”)</note> the Jews objected, I was forced to appeal to Caesar (not as <supplied>if I</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>if</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had”) which is understood as concessive</note> had any <supplied>charge</supplied> to bring against my <supplied>own</supplied> people).<note>Or “nation”</note> <verse-number id="Ac 28:20">20</verse-number>Therefore for this reason I have requested to see you and to speak with <supplied>you</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> for because of the hope of Israel I am wearing this chain!” <verse-number id="Ac 28:21">21</verse-number>And they said to him, “We have received no letters about you from Judea, nor has any of the brothers come <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“come”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> reported or spoken anything evil about you. <verse-number id="Ac 28:22">22</verse-number>But we would like to hear from you what you think, for concerning this sect it is known to us that it is spoken against everywhere.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 28:23">23</verse-number>And <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had set”) which is understood as temporal</note> had set a day with him, many more came to him at his lodging place, to whom he was explaining from early in the morning until evening, testifying about the kingdom of God and attempting to convince<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the present tense has been translated as conative (“attempting to convince”)</note> them about Jesus from both the law of Moses and the prophets. <verse-number id="Ac 28:24">24</verse-number>And <supplied>some</supplied> were convinced <supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“what was said”) which is understood as means</note> what was said, but <supplied>others</supplied> refused to believe. <verse-number id="Ac 28:25">25</verse-number>So being in disagreement with one another, they began to leave <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“made”)</note> Paul made one statement: “The Holy Spirit spoke rightly through the prophet Isaiah to your fathers, <verse-number id="Ac 28:26">26</verse-number>saying, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>‘Go to this people and say, </li1>
				<li2>“<idiom-start/>You will keep on hearing<idiom-end/><note>Literally “hearing you will hear”</note> and will never understand, </li2>
				<li1>and <idiom-start/>you will keep on seeing<idiom-end/><note>Literally “seeing you will see”</note> and will never perceive. </li1>
				<li2><verse-number id="Ac 28:27">27</verse-number>For the heart of this people has become dull, </li2>
				<li1>and with <supplied>their</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> ears they hear with difficulty, </li1>
				<li2>and they have shut their eyes, </li2>
				<li1>lest they see with <supplied>their</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> eyes, </li1>
				<li2>and hear with <supplied>their</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> ears, </li2>
				<li2>and understand with <supplied>their</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> heart, </li2>
				<li1>and turn, and I would heal them.” ’<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 6:9–10">Isa 6:9–10</cite></note> </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 28:28">28</verse-number>Therefore let it be known to you that this salvation of God has been sent to the Gentiles. They also will listen!”<note>Some later manuscripts include v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Ac 28:29">29</cite>: “And when he had said these things, the Jews departed, having a great dispute among themselves.”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ac 28:30">30</verse-number>So he stayed two whole years in his own rented house, and welcomed all who came to him, <verse-number id="Ac 28:31">31</verse-number>proclaiming the kingdom of God and teaching the <supplied>things</supplied> concerning the Lord Jesus Christ with all boldness, without hindrance. </p>
		</chapter>