<chapter id="Mt 1">
			<pericope>The Genealogy of Jesus Christ</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 1:1">1</verse-number> The book of the genealogy of Jesus Christ, the son of David, the son of Abraham. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 1:2">2</verse-number>Abraham became the father of Isaac, and Isaac became the father of Jacob, and Jacob became the father of Judah and his brothers, <verse-number id="Mt 1:3">3</verse-number>and Judah became the father of Perez and Zerah by Tamar, and Perez became the father of Hezron, and Hezron became the father of Aram,<note>Although the Greek text reads “Aram,” many English versions substitute the Old Testament form of the name, “Ram” (cf. <cite title="BibleLEB2: 1 Ch 2:9">1 Chr 2:9</cite>; <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ru 4:19">Ruth 4:19</cite>), here and in the following verse</note> <verse-number id="Mt 1:4">4</verse-number>and Aram became the father of Amminadab, and Amminadab became the father of Nahshon, and Nahshon became the father of Salmon, <verse-number id="Mt 1:5">5</verse-number>and Salmon became the father of Boaz by Rahab, and Boaz became the father of Obed by Ruth, and Obed became the father of Jesse, <verse-number id="Mt 1:6">6</verse-number>and Jesse became the father of David the king. </p>
			<p>And David became the father of Solomon by the <supplied>wife</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The word “wife” is not in the Greek text, but is implied idiomatically</note> of Uriah, <verse-number id="Mt 1:7">7</verse-number>and Solomon became the father of Rehoboam, and Rehoboam became the father of Abijah, and Abijah became the father of Asa,<note>Greek “Asaph,” alternately spelled “Asa” in many English versions here and in the following verse (cf. <cite title="BibleLEB2: 1 Ch 3:10">1 Chr 3:10</cite>)</note> <verse-number id="Mt 1:8">8</verse-number>and Asa became the father of Jehoshaphat,<note>Greek “Josaphat”; alternately spelled “Jehoshaphat” in many English versions</note> and Jehoshaphat became the father of Joram, and Joram became the father of Uzziah, <verse-number id="Mt 1:9">9</verse-number>and Uzziah became the father of Jotham, and Jotham became the father of Ahaz, and Ahaz became the father of Hezekiah, <verse-number id="Mt 1:10">10</verse-number>and Hezekiah became the father of Manasseh, and Manasseh became the father of Amon,<note>The earliest and best Greek manuscripts read “Amos,” but many English versions use the Old Testament form of the name here, “Amon” (cf. <cite title="BibleLEB2: 2 Ki 21:18">2 Kgs 21:18</cite>)</note> and Amon became the father of Josiah, <verse-number id="Mt 1:11">11</verse-number>and Josiah became the father of Jechoniah and his brothers, at the time of the deportation to Babylon. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 1:12">12</verse-number>And after the deportation to Babylon, Jechoniah became the father of Shealtiel,<note>Greek “Salathiel,” but many English versions use the Old Testament form of the name here, “Shealtiel” (cf. <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ezr 3:2">Ezra 3:2</cite>)</note> and Shealtiel became the father of Zerubbabel, <verse-number id="Mt 1:13">13</verse-number>and Zerubbabel became the father of Abiud, and Abiud became the father of Eliakim, and Eliakim became the father of Azor, <verse-number id="Mt 1:14">14</verse-number>and Azor became the father of Zadok, and Zadok became the father of Achim, and Achim became the father of Eliud, <verse-number id="Mt 1:15">15</verse-number>and Eliud became the father of Eleazar, and Eleazar became the father of Matthan, and Matthan became the father of Jacob, <verse-number id="Mt 1:16">16</verse-number>and Jacob became the father of Joseph, the husband of Mary by whom<note>The Greek relative pronoun is feminine gender and thus refers only to Mary, not Joseph</note> was born Jesus, who is called Christ. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 1:17">17</verse-number>Therefore all the generations from Abraham to David <supplied>are</supplied> fourteen generations, and from David to the deportation to Babylon <supplied>are</supplied> fourteen generations, and from the deportation to Babylon to the Christ <supplied>are</supplied> fourteen generations. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Birth of Jesus Christ</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 1:18">18</verse-number>Now the birth of Jesus Christ occurred in this way. His mother Mary had been betrothed to Joseph, <supplied>but</supplied> before they came together, she was found <idiom-start/>to be pregnant<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to have in the womb”</note> by the Holy Spirit. <verse-number id="Mt 1:19">19</verse-number>So Joseph her husband, being righteous and not wanting to disgrace her, intended to divorce her secretly. <verse-number id="Mt 1:20">20</verse-number>But <supplied>as</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“considering”)</note> he was considering these things, behold, an angel of the Lord appeared to him in a dream, saying, “Joseph, son of David, do not be afraid to take Mary <supplied>as</supplied> your wife, for what has been conceived in her is from the Holy Spirit. <verse-number id="Mt 1:21">21</verse-number>And she will give birth to a son, and you will call his name ‘Jesus,’ because he will save his people from their sins.” <verse-number id="Mt 1:22">22</verse-number>Now all this happened in order that what was spoken by the Lord through the prophet would be fulfilled, saying, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Mt 1:23">23</verse-number>“Behold, the virgin <idiom-start/>will become pregnant<idiom-end/><note>Literally “will have in the womb”</note> and will give birth to a son, </li1>
				<li1>and they will call his name Emmanuel,”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 7:14">Isa 7:14</cite></note> </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p>which is translated, “God with us.”<note>An allusion to <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 8:8">Isa 8:8</cite>, <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 8:10">10 </cite>in the Greek OT (LXX)</note> <verse-number id="Mt 1:24">24</verse-number>And Joseph, <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “when” is supplied as a component of the participle (“woke up”) which is understood as temporal</note> woke up from sleep, did as the angel of the Lord commanded him, and he took his wife <verse-number id="Mt 1:25">25</verse-number>and <idiom-start/>did not have sexual relations with<idiom-end/><note>Literally “did not know”</note> her until she gave birth to a son. And he called his name Jesus. </p>
		</chapter>