<chapter id="Mt 2">
			<pericope>Wise Men Visit Jesus</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 2:1">1</verse-number> Now <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was born”)</note> Jesus was born in Bethlehem of Judea in the days of Herod the king, behold, wise men from the east came to Jerusalem, <verse-number id="Mt 2:2">2</verse-number>saying, “Where is the one who has been born king of the Jews? For we have seen his star at its rising<note>Or, “when it rose”; traditionally rendered “in the east” by many English versions</note> and have come to worship him.” <verse-number id="Mt 2:3">3</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> King Herod heard <supplied>it</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> he was troubled, and all Jerusalem with him, <verse-number id="Mt 2:4">4</verse-number>and <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“calling together”) which is understood as temporal</note> calling together all the chief priests and scribes of the people, he inquired from them where the Christ was to be born. <verse-number id="Mt 2:5">5</verse-number>So they said to him, “In Bethlehem of Judea, for thus it is written by the prophet, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Mt 2:6">6</verse-number>‘And you, Bethlehem, land of Judah, </li1>
				<li2>are by no means least among the rulers of Judah, </li2>
				<li1>for from you will go out a ruler </li1>
				<li2>who will shepherd my people Israel.’ ”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Mic 5:2">Mic 5:2</cite></note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 2:7">7</verse-number>Then Herod secretly summoned the wise men <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“summoned”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> determined precisely from them the time <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“appeared”)</note> the star appeared. <verse-number id="Mt 2:8">8</verse-number>And he sent them to Bethlehem <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“sent”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “Go, inquire carefully concerning the child, and when you have found <supplied>him</supplied>, report to me so that I also may come <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“may come”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> worship him.” <verse-number id="Mt 2:9">9</verse-number><supplied>After</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“listened to”) which is understood as temporal</note> they listened to the king, they went out, and behold, the star which they had seen at its rising<note>Or, “when it rose”; traditionally rendered “in the east” by many English versions</note> led them until it came <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> stood above <supplied>the place</supplied> where the child was. <verse-number id="Mt 2:10">10</verse-number>Now <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> saw the star, they rejoiced <supplied>with</supplied> very great joy. <verse-number id="Mt 2:11">11</verse-number>And <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“came”) which is understood as temporal</note> came into the house, they saw the child with Mary his mother, and they fell down <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“fell down”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> worshiped him. And opening their treasure boxes, they offered him gifts of gold and frankincense and myrrh. <verse-number id="Mt 2:12">12</verse-number>And being warned in a dream not to return to Herod, they went back to their <supplied>own</supplied> country by another route. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Joseph, Mary, and Jesus Escape to Egypt</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 2:13">13</verse-number>Now <supplied>after</supplied> they had gone away, behold, an angel of the Lord appeared in a dream to Joseph, saying, “Get up, take the child and his mother and flee to Egypt, and stay there until I tell you. For Herod is about to seek the child to destroy him.” <verse-number id="Mt 2:14">14</verse-number>So he got up <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“got up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> took the child and his mother during the night and went away to Egypt. <verse-number id="Mt 2:15">15</verse-number>And he was there until the death of Herod, in order that what was said by the Lord through the prophet would be fulfilled, saying, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Out of Egypt I called my son.” </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Herod Has Innocent Children Murdered</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 2:16">16</verse-number>Then Herod, <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> saw that he had been deceived by the wise men, became very angry, and he sent <supplied>soldiers</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“sent”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> executed all the children in Bethlehem and in all the region <supplied>around</supplied> it from <supplied>the age of</supplied> two years old and under, according to the time which he had determined precisely from the wise men. <verse-number id="Mt 2:17">17</verse-number>Then what was spoken by the prophet Jeremiah was fulfilled, saying, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Mt 2:18">18</verse-number>“A voice was heard in Ramah, </li1>
				<li2>weeping and great mourning, </li2>
				<li1>Rachel weeping <supplied>for</supplied> her children, </li1>
				<li2>and she did not want to be comforted, </li2>
				<li1>because <idiom-start/>they exist no longer<idiom-end/><note>Literally “they are not”</note>.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Je 31:15">Jer 31:15</cite></note> </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Joseph, Mary, and Jesus Return to Nazareth</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 2:19">19</verse-number>Now <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“had died”)</note> Herod had died, behold, an angel of the Lord appeared in a dream to Joseph in Egypt, <verse-number id="Mt 2:20">20</verse-number>saying, “Get up, take the child and his mother and go to the land of Israel, for those who were seeking the life of the child are dead.” <verse-number id="Mt 2:21">21</verse-number>So he got up <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“got up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> took the child and his mother and <idiom-start/>entered<idiom-end/><note>Literally “entered into”</note> the land of Israel. <verse-number id="Mt 2:22">22</verse-number>But <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> heard that Archelaus was reigning over Judea in place of his father Herod, he was afraid to go there, and being warned in a dream, he took refuge in the regions of Galilee. <verse-number id="Mt 2:23">23</verse-number>And he came <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> lived in a town called Nazareth, in order that what was said by the prophets would be fulfilled:<note>Literally “that”; the conjunction could be understood (1) to introduce a direct quotation, serving a function similar to modern English quotation marks, and thus not translated; or (2) to introduce an indirect quotation, in which case it could be translated “that he would be called a Nazarene”</note> “He will be called a Nazarene.” </p>
		</chapter>