<chapter id="Mt 3">
			<pericope>John the Baptist Begins His Ministry</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 3:1">1</verse-number> Now in those days John the Baptist came preaching in the Judean wilderness <verse-number id="Mt 3:2">2</verse-number>and saying, “Repent, for the kingdom of heaven has come near!” <verse-number id="Mt 3:3">3</verse-number>For this is the one who was spoken about by the prophet Isaiah, saying, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“The voice of one crying out in the wilderness, </li1>
				<li1>‘Prepare the way of the Lord, </li1>
				<li2>make his paths straight.’ ”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 40:3">Isa 40:3</cite></note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 3:4">4</verse-number>Now John himself had his clothing made from camel’s hair and a belt made of leather around his waist, and his food was locusts and wild honey. <verse-number id="Mt 3:5">5</verse-number>Then Jerusalem and all Judea and all the district around the Jordan were going out to him, <verse-number id="Mt 3:6">6</verse-number>and they were being baptized by him in the Jordan River <supplied>as they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“confessed”) which is understood as temporal</note> confessed their sins. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 3:7">7</verse-number>But <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> saw many of the Pharisees and Sadducees coming to his baptism, he said to them, “Offspring of vipers! Who warned you to flee from the coming wrath? <verse-number id="Mt 3:8">8</verse-number>Therefore produce fruit worthy of repentance! <verse-number id="Mt 3:9">9</verse-number>And do not think to say to yourselves, ‘We have Abraham <supplied>as</supplied> father.’ For I say to you that God is able to raise up children for Abraham from these stones! <verse-number id="Mt 3:10">10</verse-number>Already now the ax is positioned at the root of the trees; therefore every tree not producing good fruit is cut down and thrown into the fire. <verse-number id="Mt 3:11">11</verse-number>I baptize you with water for repentance, but the one who comes after me is more powerful than I <supplied>am</supplied>, whose sandals I am not worthy to carry. He will baptize you with the Holy Spirit and fire. <verse-number id="Mt 3:12">12</verse-number>His winnowing shovel <supplied>is</supplied> in his hand, and he will clean out his threshing floor and will gather his wheat into the storehouse, but he will burn up the chaff with unquenchable fire.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Baptism of Jesus</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 3:13">13</verse-number>Then Jesus came from Galilee to the Jordan to John in order to be baptized by him. <verse-number id="Mt 3:14">14</verse-number>But John tried to prevent<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The imperfect verb is understood as conative (“tried to”)</note> him, saying, “<idiom-start/>I need<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I have need”</note> to be baptized by you, and do you come to me?” <verse-number id="Mt 3:15">15</verse-number>But Jesus answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to him, “Permit <supplied>it</supplied> now, for in this way it is right for us to fulfill all righteousness.” Then he permitted him. <verse-number id="Mt 3:16">16</verse-number>Now <supplied>after he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was baptized”) which is understood as temporal</note> was baptized, Jesus immediately went up from the water, and behold, the heavens opened<note>Some manuscripts have “opened to him”</note> and he saw the Spirit of God descending like a dove coming<note>Some manuscripts have “and coming”</note> upon him. <verse-number id="Mt 3:17">17</verse-number>And behold, <supplied>there was</supplied><note>The words “<supplied>there was</supplied>” are not in the Greek text, but are supplied to make a complete sentence in English</note> a voice from heaven saying, “This is my beloved Son, with whom I am well pleased.” </p>
		</chapter>