<chapter id="Mt 4">
			<pericope>The Temptation of Jesus</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 4:1">1</verse-number> Then Jesus was led up into the wilderness by the Spirit to be tempted by the devil, <verse-number id="Mt 4:2">2</verse-number>and <supplied>after he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had fasted”) which is understood as temporal</note> had fasted forty days and forty nights, then he was hungry. <verse-number id="Mt 4:3">3</verse-number>And the tempter approached <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“approached”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to him, “If you are the Son of God, order that these stones become bread.” <verse-number id="Mt 4:4">4</verse-number>But he answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “It is written, ‘Man will not live on bread alone, but on every word that comes out of the mouth of God.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Dt 8:3">Deut 8:3</cite></note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 4:5">5</verse-number>Then the devil took him to the holy city<note>That is, Jerusalem</note> and placed him on the highest point of the temple <verse-number id="Mt 4:6">6</verse-number>and said to him, “If you are the Son of God, throw yourself down! For it is written, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>‘He will command his angels concerning you,’<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 91:11">Ps 91:11</cite></note> </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p>and </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>‘On <supplied>their</supplied> hands they will lift you up, </li1>
				<li1>lest you strike your foot against a stone.’ ”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 91:12">Ps 91:12</cite></note> </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 4:7">7</verse-number>Jesus said to him, “On the other hand it is written, ‘You are not to put the Lord your God to the test.’ ”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Dt 6:16">Deut 6:16</cite></note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 4:8">8</verse-number>Again the devil took him to a very high mountain and showed him all the kingdoms of the world and their glory, <verse-number id="Mt 4:9">9</verse-number>and he said to him, “I will give to you all these things, if you will fall down <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“will fall down”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> worship me.” <verse-number id="Mt 4:10">10</verse-number>Then Jesus said to him, “Go away, Satan, for it is written, ‘You shall worship the Lord your God and serve only him.’ ”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Dt 6:13">Deut 6:13</cite></note> <verse-number id="Mt 4:11">11</verse-number>Then the devil left him, and behold, angels came and began ministering to him. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Public Ministry in Galilee</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 4:12">12</verse-number>Now <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> heard that John <idiom-start/>had been arrested<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “had been handed over”</note> he withdrew into Galilee. <verse-number id="Mt 4:13">13</verse-number>And leaving Nazareth, he went <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> lived in Capernaum by the sea, in the region of Zebulun and Naphtali, <verse-number id="Mt 4:14">14</verse-number>in order that what was spoken by the prophet Isaiah would be fulfilled, who said, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Mt 4:15">15</verse-number>“Land of Zebulun and land of Naphtali, </li1>
				<li1><idiom-start/>toward the sea<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the way of the sea”</note> on the other side of the Jordan, </li1>
				<li2>Galilee of the Gentiles<note>Or “nations”; the same Greek word can be translated “nations” or “Gentiles” depending on the context</note>— </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Mt 4:16">16</verse-number>the people who sit in darkness </li1>
				<li2>have seen a great light, </li2>
				<li1>and the ones who sit in the land and shadow of death, </li1>
				<li2>a light has dawned on them.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 9:1">Isa 9:1</cite></note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 4:17">17</verse-number>From that time <supplied>on</supplied>, Jesus began to preach and to say, “Repent, because the kingdom of heaven is near.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus Calls His First Disciples</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 4:18">18</verse-number>Now <supplied>as he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was walking”) which is understood as temporal</note> was walking beside the Sea of Galilee, he saw two brothers, Simon called Peter and his brother Andrew, throwing a casting net into the sea (for they were fishermen). <verse-number id="Mt 4:19">19</verse-number>And he said to them, “<idiom-start/>Follow me<idiom-end/><note>Literally “come behind me”</note> and I will make you fishers of people.” <verse-number id="Mt 4:20">20</verse-number>And immediately they left their nets <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“left”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> followed him. <verse-number id="Mt 4:21">21</verse-number>And going on from there, he saw two other brothers, James the <supplied>son</supplied> of Zebedee and his brother John, in the boat with their father Zebedee, mending their nets, and he called them. <verse-number id="Mt 4:22">22</verse-number>And immediately they left the boat and their father <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“left”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> followed him. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Teaching, Preaching, and Healing throughout Galilee</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 4:23">23</verse-number>And he went around through all of Galilee, teaching in their synagogues and proclaiming the good news of the kingdom and healing every disease and every sickness among the people. <verse-number id="Mt 4:24">24</verse-number>And a report about him went out <idiom-start/>throughout<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the whole of”</note> Syria, and they brought to him all those <idiom-start/>who were sick<idiom-end/><note>Literally “having badly”</note> with various diseases and afflicted by torments, demon-possessed<note>Some manuscripts have “and demon-possessed”</note> and epileptics and paralytics, and he healed them. <verse-number id="Mt 4:25">25</verse-number>And large crowds followed him from Galilee, Decapolis, Jerusalem, Judea, and from the other side of the Jordan. </p>
		</chapter>