<chapter id="Mt 7">
			<pericope>The Sermon on the Mount: On Judging Others</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 7:1">1</verse-number> “Do not judge, so that you will not be judged. <verse-number id="Mt 7:2">2</verse-number>For by what judgment you judge, you will be judged, and by what measure you measure out, it will be measured out to you. <verse-number id="Mt 7:3">3</verse-number>And why do you see the speck <supplied>that is</supplied> in your brother’s eye, but do not notice the beam of wood in your <supplied>own</supplied> eye? <verse-number id="Mt 7:4">4</verse-number>Or how will you say to your brother, ‘Allow <supplied>me</supplied> to remove the speck from your eye,’ and behold, the beam of wood <supplied>is</supplied> in your <supplied>own</supplied> eye? <verse-number id="Mt 7:5">5</verse-number>Hypocrite! First remove the beam of wood from your <supplied>own</supplied> eye and then you will see clearly to remove the speck from your brother’s eye! </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 7:6">6</verse-number>“Do not give what is holy to dogs, or throw your pearls in front of pigs, lest they trample them with their feet, and turn around <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“turn around”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> tear you to pieces. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Sermon on the Mount: Ask, Seek, Knock</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 7:7">7</verse-number>“Ask and it will be given to you; seek and you will find; knock and it will be opened for you. <verse-number id="Mt 7:8">8</verse-number>For everyone who asks receives, and the one who seeks finds, and to the one who knocks it will be opened. <verse-number id="Mt 7:9">9</verse-number>Or what man is <supplied>there</supplied> among you, <supplied>if</supplied> his son will ask him <supplied>for</supplied> bread, will give him a stone? <verse-number id="Mt 7:10">10</verse-number>Or also <supplied>if</supplied> he will ask for a fish, will give him a snake? <verse-number id="Mt 7:11">11</verse-number>Therefore if you, <supplied>although you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>although</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“are”) which is understood as concessive</note> are evil, know how to give good gifts to your children, how much more will your Father who is in heaven give good things to those who ask him? <verse-number id="Mt 7:12">12</verse-number>Therefore <supplied>in</supplied> all <supplied>things</supplied>, whatever you want that people should do to you, thus also you do to them. For this is the law and the prophets. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Sermon on the Mount: The Narrow Gate</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 7:13">13</verse-number>“Enter through the narrow gate, because broad <supplied>is</supplied> the gate and spacious <supplied>is</supplied> the road that leads to destruction, and there are many who enter through it, <verse-number id="Mt 7:14">14</verse-number>because narrow<note>Some manuscripts have “how narrow”</note> <supplied>is</supplied> the gate and constricted <supplied>is</supplied> the road that leads to life, and there are few who find it! </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Sermon on the Mount: Recognizing False Prophets</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 7:15">15</verse-number>“Beware of false prophets who come to you in sheep’s clothing, but inside are ravenous wolves. <verse-number id="Mt 7:16">16</verse-number>You will recognize them by their fruits: they do not gather grapes from thorn bushes or figs from thistles, <supplied>do they</supplied>?<note>The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here, indicated by “<supplied>do they</supplied>”</note> <verse-number id="Mt 7:17">17</verse-number>In the <supplied>same</supplied> way, every good tree produces good fruit, but a bad tree produces bad fruit. <verse-number id="Mt 7:18">18</verse-number>A good tree is not able to produce bad fruit, nor a bad tree to produce good fruit. <verse-number id="Mt 7:19">19</verse-number>Every tree that does not produce good fruit is cut down and thrown into the fire. <verse-number id="Mt 7:20">20</verse-number>As a result, you will recognize them by their fruits. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Sermon on the Mount: False Followers</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 7:21">21</verse-number>“Not everyone who says to me, ‘Lord, Lord,’ will enter into the kingdom of heaven, but the one who does the will of my Father who is in heaven. <verse-number id="Mt 7:22">22</verse-number>On that day many will say to me, ‘Lord, Lord, did we not prophesy in your name, and expel demons in your name, and perform many miracles in your name?’ <verse-number id="Mt 7:23">23</verse-number>And then <idiom-start/>I will say to them plainly<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “I will declare to them”</note> ‘I never knew you. Depart from me, you who practice lawlessness!’ </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Sermon on the Mount: Two Houses and Two Foundations</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 7:24">24</verse-number>“Therefore everyone who hears these words of mine and does them will be like a wise man who built his house on the rock. <verse-number id="Mt 7:25">25</verse-number>And the rain came down and the rivers came and the winds blew and beat against that house, and it did not collapse, because its foundation was laid on the rock. <verse-number id="Mt 7:26">26</verse-number>And everyone who hears these words of mine and does not do them will be like a foolish man who built his house on the sand. <verse-number id="Mt 7:27">27</verse-number>And the rain came down and the rivers came and the winds blew and beat against that house, and it collapsed, and its fall was great.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Sermon on the Mount: Response</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 7:28">28</verse-number>And it happened when Jesus finished these words the crowds were amazed at his teaching, <verse-number id="Mt 7:29">29</verse-number>because he was teaching them like one who had authority, and not like their scribes. </p>
		</chapter>