<chapter id="Mt 8">
			<pericope>A Leper Cleansed</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 8:1">1</verse-number> And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“came down”)</note> he came down from the mountain, large crowds followed him. <verse-number id="Mt 8:2">2</verse-number>And behold, a leper approached <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“approached”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> worshiped him, saying, “Lord, if you are willing, you are able to make me clean.” <verse-number id="Mt 8:3">3</verse-number>And extending his hand he touched him, saying, “I am willing, be clean.” And immediately his leprosy was cleansed. <verse-number id="Mt 8:4">4</verse-number>And Jesus said to him, “See that you tell no one, but go, show yourself to the priest and offer the gift that Moses commanded, for a testimony to them.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A Centurion’s Slave Healed</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 8:5">5</verse-number>Now <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“entered”)</note> he entered Capernaum, a centurion approached him, appealing to him <verse-number id="Mt 8:6">6</verse-number>and saying, “Lord, my slave<note>Traditionally “servant”; the Greek term here is one often used of a slave who was regarded with some degree of affection, possibly a personal servant (the parallel passage in <cite title="BibleLEB2: Lk 7:7">Luke 7:7 </cite>uses the more common term for slave)</note> is lying paralyzed in my<note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> house, terribly tormented!” <verse-number id="Mt 8:7">7</verse-number>And he said to him, “I will come <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“come”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> heal him.” <verse-number id="Mt 8:8">8</verse-number>And the centurion answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “Lord, I am not worthy that you should come in under my roof. But only say the word and my slave will be healed. <verse-number id="Mt 8:9">9</verse-number>For I also am a man under authority who has soldiers under me, and I say to this one, ‘Go!’ and he goes, and to another one, ‘Come!’ and he comes, and to my slave, ‘Do this!’ and he does <supplied>it</supplied><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation (see the parallel in <cite title="BibleLEB2: Lk 7:8">Luke 7:8</cite>).</note>.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 8:10">10</verse-number>Now <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> Jesus heard <supplied>this</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> he was astonished, and said to those who were following <supplied>him</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> “Truly I say to you, I have found such great faith with no one in Israel. <verse-number id="Mt 8:11">11</verse-number>But I say to you that many will come from east and west and <idiom-start/>be seated at the banquet<idiom-end/><note>Literally “recline at table”</note> with Abraham and Isaac and Jacob in the kingdom of heaven. <verse-number id="Mt 8:12">12</verse-number>But the sons of the kingdom will be thrown out into the outer darkness. In that place there will be weeping and gnashing of teeth!” <verse-number id="Mt 8:13">13</verse-number>And Jesus said to the centurion, “Go, as you have believed it will be done for you.” And the slave<note>Many later manuscripts have “his slave”</note> was healed at that hour. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Many at Capernaum Are Healed</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 8:14">14</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“came”) which is understood as temporal</note> Jesus came into Peter’s house, he saw his mother-in-law lying down and suffering with a fever. <verse-number id="Mt 8:15">15</verse-number>And he touched her hand and the fever left her, and she got up and began to serve him. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 8:16">16</verse-number>Now <supplied>when it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was”)</note> was evening, they brought to him many who were demon-possessed, and he expelled the spirits with a word. And he healed all <idiom-start/>those who were sick<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “those who were having badly”</note> <verse-number id="Mt 8:17">17</verse-number>in order that what was spoken through the prophet Isaiah would be fulfilled, who said, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“He himself took away our sicknesses, </li1>
				<li1>and carried away our diseases.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 53:4">Isa 53:4</cite></note> </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Would-be Followers</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 8:18">18</verse-number>Now <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> Jesus saw many crowds<note>Some manuscripts have “a crowd”</note> around him, he gave orders to depart to the other side.<note>That is, the other side of the Sea of Galilee</note> <verse-number id="Mt 8:19">19</verse-number>And a scribe approached <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“approached”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to him, “Teacher, I will follow you wherever you go!” <verse-number id="Mt 8:20">20</verse-number>And Jesus said to him, “Foxes have dens and birds of the sky <supplied>have</supplied> nests, but the Son of Man has no place to lay his head.” <verse-number id="Mt 8:21">21</verse-number>And another of the disciples<note>Some manuscripts have “of his disciples”</note> said to him, “Lord, allow me first to go and bury my father.” <verse-number id="Mt 8:22">22</verse-number>But Jesus said to him, “Follow me, and leave the dead to bury their own dead!” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Calming of a Storm</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 8:23">23</verse-number>And <supplied>as</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“got”) which is understood as temporal</note> he got into the boat, his disciples followed him. <verse-number id="Mt 8:24">24</verse-number>And behold, a great storm arose on the sea, so that the boat was being inundated by the waves, but he himself was asleep. <verse-number id="Mt 8:25">25</verse-number>And they came <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> woke him, saying, “Lord, save <supplied>us</supplied>!<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> We are perishing!” <verse-number id="Mt 8:26">26</verse-number>And he said to them, “Why are you fearful, <supplied>you</supplied> of little faith?” Then he got up <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“got up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> rebuked the winds and the sea and there was a great calm. <verse-number id="Mt 8:27">27</verse-number>And the men were astonished, saying, “What sort of <supplied>man</supplied> is this, that even the winds and the sea obey him?” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Demon-possessed Gadarenes Healed</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 8:28">28</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“came”)</note> he came to the other side,<note>That is, the other side of the Sea of Galilee</note> to the region of the Gadarenes,<note>Many manuscripts read “Gergesenes”; others read “Gerasenes” (see <cite title="BibleLEB2: Lk 8:26">Luke 8:26</cite>)</note> two demon-possessed men coming from among the tombs met him, very violent, so that no one was able to pass by along that road. <verse-number id="Mt 8:29">29</verse-number>And behold, they cried out, saying, “<idiom-start/>What do you have to do with us<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “what to us and to you”</note> Son of God? Have you come here to torment us before the time?”<note>That is, before the appointed time of judgment</note> <verse-number id="Mt 8:30">30</verse-number>Now a long way from them a large herd of pigs was feeding. <verse-number id="Mt 8:31">31</verse-number>So the demons implored him, saying, “If you are going to expel us, send us into the herd of pigs.” <verse-number id="Mt 8:32">32</verse-number>And he said to them, “Go!” So they departed <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“departed”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> went into the pigs, and behold, the whole herd rushed headlong down the steep slope into the sea and drowned in the water. <verse-number id="Mt 8:33">33</verse-number>Now the herdsmen fled and went into the town <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> reported everything, including the things concerning the demon-possessed men. <verse-number id="Mt 8:34">34</verse-number>And behold, the whole town came out to meet Jesus, and <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> saw him, they implored <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> that he would depart from their region. </p>
		</chapter>