<chapter id="Mt 9">
			<pericope>A Paralytic Healed</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 9:1">1</verse-number> And getting into a boat, he crossed over and came to his own town.<note>A reference to Capernaum</note> <verse-number id="Mt 9:2">2</verse-number>And behold, they brought to him a paralytic lying on a stretcher, and <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> Jesus saw their faith, he said to the paralytic, “Have courage, child, your sins are forgiven.” <verse-number id="Mt 9:3">3</verse-number>And behold, some of the scribes said to themselves, “This man is blaspheming!” <verse-number id="Mt 9:4">4</verse-number>And knowing<note>Some manuscripts have “perceiving”</note> their thoughts, Jesus said, “Why do you think evil in your hearts? <verse-number id="Mt 9:5">5</verse-number>For which is easier to say, ‘Your sins are forgiven,’ or to say, ‘Get up and walk’? <verse-number id="Mt 9:6">6</verse-number>But in order that you may know that the Son of Man has authority on earth to forgive sins,” then he said to the paralytic, “Get up, pick up your stretcher and go to your home.” <verse-number id="Mt 9:7">7</verse-number>And he got up <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“got up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> went to his home. <verse-number id="Mt 9:8">8</verse-number>But <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> the crowds saw <supplied>this</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> they were afraid and glorified God who had given such authority to men. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Matthew Called to Follow Jesus</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 9:9">9</verse-number>And <supplied>as</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> Jesus was going away from there, he saw a man called Matthew sitting at the tax booth and said to him, “Follow me!” And he stood up <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“stood up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> followed him. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 9:10">10</verse-number>And it happened <supplied>as</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was dining”)</note> he <idiom-start/>was dining<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was reclining at table”</note> in the house, behold, many tax collectors and sinners were coming <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“were coming”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> <idiom-start/>dining<idiom-end/><note>Literally “reclining at table”</note> with Jesus and his disciples. <verse-number id="Mt 9:11">11</verse-number>And <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> saw <supplied>it</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> the Pharisees began to say to his disciples, “Why does your teacher eat with tax collectors and sinners?” <verse-number id="Mt 9:12">12</verse-number>And <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> heard <supplied>it</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> he said, “Those who are healthy do not have need of a physician, but those <idiom-start/>who are sick<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “having badly”</note> <verse-number id="Mt 9:13">13</verse-number>But go <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“go”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> learn what it means, “I want mercy and not sacrifice.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ho 6:6">Hos 6:6 </cite>(see also <cite title="BibleLEB2: Mt 12:7">Matt 12:7</cite>)</note> For I did not come to call the righteous, but sinners.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>On Fasting</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 9:14">14</verse-number>Then the disciples of John<note>That is, John the Baptist</note> approached him, saying, “Why do we and the Pharisees fast often, but your disciples do not fast?” <verse-number id="Mt 9:15">15</verse-number>And Jesus said to them, “<idiom-start/>The bridegroom’s attendants<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the sons of the bridal chamber”</note> are not able to mourn as long as the bridegroom is with them. But days are coming when the bridegroom is taken away from them, and then they will fast. <verse-number id="Mt 9:16">16</verse-number>But no one puts a patch of unshrunken cloth on an old garment, for its patch pulls away from the garment, and the tear becomes worse. <verse-number id="Mt 9:17">17</verse-number>Nor do they put new wine into old wineskins. <idiom-start/>Otherwise<idiom-end/><note>Literally “but if not”</note> the wineskins burst and the wine is spilled, and the wineskins are destroyed. But they put new wine into new wineskins and both are preserved.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A Woman Healed and a Daughter Raised</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 9:18">18</verse-number><supplied>As</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was saying”)</note> he was saying these <supplied>things</supplied> to them, behold, one of the rulers came <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> knelt down before him, saying, “My daughter has just now died, but come, place your hand on her and she will live!” <verse-number id="Mt 9:19">19</verse-number>And Jesus and his disciples got up <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“got up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> followed him. <verse-number id="Mt 9:20">20</verse-number>And behold, a woman who had been suffering with a hemorrhage twelve years approached from behind <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“approached”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> touched the edge<note>Or “tassel”</note> of his cloak, <verse-number id="Mt 9:21">21</verse-number>for she said to herself, “If only I touch his cloak I will be healed.” <verse-number id="Mt 9:22">22</verse-number>But Jesus, turning around and seeing her, said, “Have courage, daughter! Your faith has healed you.” And the woman was healed from that hour. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 9:23">23</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“came”) which is understood as temporal</note> Jesus came into the ruler’s house and saw the flute players and the disorderly crowd, <verse-number id="Mt 9:24">24</verse-number>he said, “Go away, because the girl is not dead, but is sleeping.” And they ridiculed him. <verse-number id="Mt 9:25">25</verse-number>But when the crowd had been sent out, he entered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“entered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> took her hand, and the girl got up. <verse-number id="Mt 9:26">26</verse-number>And this report went out into that whole region. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Two Blind Men Healed</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 9:27">27</verse-number>And <supplied>as</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“going away”) which is understood as temporal</note> Jesus was going away from there, two blind men followed him, crying out and saying, “Have mercy on us, Son of David!” <verse-number id="Mt 9:28">28</verse-number>And <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“came”) which is understood as temporal</note> came into the house, the blind men approached him, and Jesus said to them, “Do you believe that I am able to do this?” They said to him, “Yes, Lord.” <verse-number id="Mt 9:29">29</verse-number>Then he touched their eyes, saying, “According to your faith let it be done for you.” <verse-number id="Mt 9:30">30</verse-number>And their eyes were opened, and Jesus sternly warned them, saying, “See <supplied>that</supplied> no one finds out.” <verse-number id="Mt 9:31">31</verse-number>But they went out <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went out”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> spread the report about him in that whole region. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A Demon Expelled</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 9:32">32</verse-number>Now <supplied>as</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“were going away”)</note> they were going away, behold, they brought to him a demon-possessed man <supplied>who was</supplied> unable to speak. <verse-number id="Mt 9:33">33</verse-number>And <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“had been expelled”)</note> the demon had been expelled, the one who had been mute spoke, and the crowds were astonished, saying, “<idiom-start/>This has never been seen before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “never has it been seen thus”</note> in Israel!” <verse-number id="Mt 9:34">34</verse-number>But the Pharisees were saying,<note>Or “began to say”</note> “By the ruler of demons he expels the demons!” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A Plentiful Harvest But Few Workers</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 9:35">35</verse-number>And Jesus was going around all the towns and the villages, teaching in their synagogues and proclaiming the good news of the kingdom and healing every<note>Or “every kind of”</note> disease and every<note>Or “every kind of”</note> sickness. <verse-number id="Mt 9:36">36</verse-number>And <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> saw the crowds, he had compassion for them, because they were weary and dejected, like sheep that did not have a shepherd. <verse-number id="Mt 9:37">37</verse-number>Then he said to his disciples, “The harvest <supplied>is</supplied> plentiful, but the workers <supplied>are</supplied> few. <verse-number id="Mt 9:38">38</verse-number>Therefore ask the Lord of the harvest that he send out workers into his harvest.” </p>
		</chapter>