<chapter id="Mt 10">
			<pericope>The Twelve Commissioned and Sent Out</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 10:1">1</verse-number> And summoning his twelve disciples, he gave them authority over unclean spirits, so that they could expel <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and could heal every<note>Or “every kind of”</note> disease and every<note>Or “every kind of”</note> sickness. <verse-number id="Mt 10:2">2</verse-number>Now these are the names of the twelve apostles: first Simon who is called Peter, and Andrew his brother, James<note>Some manuscripts have “and James”</note> the <supplied>son</supplied> of Zebedee, and John his brother, <verse-number id="Mt 10:3">3</verse-number>Philip, and Bartholomew, Thomas, and Matthew the tax collector, James the <supplied>son</supplied> of Alphaeus, and Thaddaeus, <verse-number id="Mt 10:4">4</verse-number>Simon the Zealot,<note>Literally “the Cananean,” but according to BDAG 507 s.v., this term has no relation at all to the geographical terms for Cana or Canaan, but is derived from the Aramaic term for “enthusiast, zealot” (see <cite title="BibleLEB2: Lk 6:15">Luke 6:15</cite>; <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ac 1:13">Acts 1:13</cite>)</note> and Judas Iscariot—the one who also betrayed him. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 10:5">5</verse-number>Jesus sent out these twelve, instructing them saying, “Do not go on the road to the Gentiles, and do not enter into a city of the Samaritans, <verse-number id="Mt 10:6">6</verse-number>but go instead to the lost sheep of the house of Israel. <verse-number id="Mt 10:7">7</verse-number>And <supplied>as you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“are going”) which is understood as temporal</note> are going, preach, saying, ‘The kingdom of heaven has come near!’ <verse-number id="Mt 10:8">8</verse-number>Heal those who are sick, raise the dead, cleanse lepers, expel demons. Freely you have received; freely give. <verse-number id="Mt 10:9">9</verse-number>Do not procure gold or silver or copper for your belts. <verse-number id="Mt 10:10">10</verse-number>Do not <supplied>take</supplied> a traveler’s bag for the road, or two tunics, or sandals, or a staff, for the worker <supplied>is</supplied> deserving of his provisions. <verse-number id="Mt 10:11">11</verse-number>And into whatever town or village you enter, inquire who in it is worthy, and stay <supplied>there</supplied> until you depart. <verse-number id="Mt 10:12">12</verse-number>And <supplied>when you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“enter”) which is understood as temporal</note> enter into the house, greet it. <verse-number id="Mt 10:13">13</verse-number>And if the house is worthy, let your peace come upon it, but if it is not worthy, let your peace return to you. <verse-number id="Mt 10:14">14</verse-number>And whoever does not welcome you or listen to your words, shake off the dust from your feet <supplied>as you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“are going”) which is understood as temporal</note> are going out of that house or <supplied>that</supplied><note>A repetition of “that” is supplied in English; the single Greek term is understood to modify both “house” and “town”</note> town. <verse-number id="Mt 10:15">15</verse-number>Truly I say to you, it will be more bearable for the region of Sodom and Gomorrah on the day of judgment than for that town! </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Persecution of Disciples Predicted</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 10:16">16</verse-number>“Behold, I am sending you out like sheep in the midst of wolves. Therefore be wise as serpents and innocent as doves. <verse-number id="Mt 10:17">17</verse-number>But beware of people, because they will hand you over to councils, and they will flog you in their synagogues. <verse-number id="Mt 10:18">18</verse-number>And you will be brought before both governors and kings because of me, for a witness to them and to the Gentiles. <verse-number id="Mt 10:19">19</verse-number>But whenever they hand you over, do not be anxious how <supplied>to speak</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>to speak</supplied>” has been supplied for stylistic reasons, since “how to speak” is more natural in English than “how to say”; in Greek the same verb works with both expressions (“how or what you should say”) and also occurs again at the end of the verse</note> or what you should say, for what you should say will be given to you at that hour. <verse-number id="Mt 10:20">20</verse-number>For you are not the ones who are speaking, but the Spirit of your Father <supplied>who is</supplied> speaking through you. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 10:21">21</verse-number>“And brother will hand over brother to death, and a father <supplied>his</supplied> children, and children will rise up against parents and have them put to death, <verse-number id="Mt 10:22">22</verse-number>and you will be hated by everyone because of my name. But the one who endures to the end—this one will be saved. <verse-number id="Mt 10:23">23</verse-number>And whenever they persecute you in this town, flee to another, for truly I say to you, you will never finish <supplied>going through</supplied> the towns of Israel until the Son of Man comes. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 10:24">24</verse-number>“A disciple is not superior to his teacher, nor a slave superior to his master. <verse-number id="Mt 10:25">25</verse-number><supplied>It is</supplied> enough for the disciple that he become like his teacher, and the slave like his master. If they have called the master of the house Beelzebul, how much more the members of his household? </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Fear God Rather Than People</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 10:26">26</verse-number>“Therefore do not be afraid of them, because nothing is hidden that will not be revealed, and nothing secret that will not become known. <verse-number id="Mt 10:27">27</verse-number>What I say to you in the dark, tell in the light, and what you hear in your ear, proclaim on the housetops. <verse-number id="Mt 10:28">28</verse-number>And do not be afraid of those who kill the body but are not able to kill the soul, but instead be afraid of the one who is able to destroy both soul and body in hell. <verse-number id="Mt 10:29">29</verse-number>Are not two sparrows sold for a penny?<note>Literally, “an assarion,” a Roman coin worth about 1/16 of a denarius</note> And one of them will not fall to the ground <idiom-start/>without the knowledge and consent<idiom-end/><note>Literally “without”; the phrase “the knowledge and consent” is implied when this term is used of God</note> of your Father. <verse-number id="Mt 10:30">30</verse-number>And even the hairs of your head are all numbered! <verse-number id="Mt 10:31">31</verse-number>Therefore do not be afraid; you are worth more than many sparrows. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 10:32">32</verse-number>“Therefore everyone who acknowledges me before people, I also will acknowledge him before my Father <supplied>who is</supplied> in heaven. <verse-number id="Mt 10:33">33</verse-number>But whoever denies me before people, I also will deny him before my Father <supplied>who is</supplied> in heaven. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Not Peace, But a Sword of Divisiveness</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 10:34">34</verse-number>“Do not think that I have come to bring peace on the earth! I have not come to bring peace, but a sword. <verse-number id="Mt 10:35">35</verse-number>For I have come to turn a man against his father, and a daughter against her mother, and a daughter-in-law against her mother-in-law. <verse-number id="Mt 10:36">36</verse-number>And the enemies of a man <supplied>will be</supplied> the members of his household.<note>An allusion to <cite title="BibleLEB2: Mic 7:6">Mic 7:6</cite></note> <verse-number id="Mt 10:37">37</verse-number>The one who loves father or mother more than me is not worthy of me, and the one who loves son or daughter more than me is not worthy of me. <verse-number id="Mt 10:38">38</verse-number>And whoever does not take up his cross and follow me is not worthy of me. <verse-number id="Mt 10:39">39</verse-number>The one who finds his life will lose it, and the one who loses his life because of me will find it. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>On Rewards</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 10:40">40</verse-number>“The one who receives you receives me, and the one who receives me receives the one who sent me. <verse-number id="Mt 10:41">41</verse-number>The one who receives a prophet in the name of a prophet will receive a prophet’s reward, and the one who receives a righteous person in the name of a righteous person will receive a righteous person’s reward. <verse-number id="Mt 10:42">42</verse-number>And whoever gives one of these little ones only a cup of cold water to drink in the name of a disciple, truly I say to you, he will never lose his reward.” </p>
		</chapter>