<chapter id="Mt 12">
			<pericope>Plucking Grain on the Sabbath</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 12:1">1</verse-number> At that time Jesus went through the grain fields on the Sabbath. And his disciples were hungry, and they began to pluck off heads of grain and eat <supplied>them</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <verse-number id="Mt 12:2">2</verse-number>But <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> the Pharisees saw <supplied>it</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> they said to him, “Behold, your disciples are doing what it is not permitted to do on the Sabbath!” <verse-number id="Mt 12:3">3</verse-number>So he said to them, “Have you not read what David did when he was hungry, and those with him, <verse-number id="Mt 12:4">4</verse-number>how he entered into the house of God and ate the bread of the presentation, which it was not permitted for him or for those with him to eat, but only for the priests? <verse-number id="Mt 12:5">5</verse-number>Or have you not read in the law that on the Sabbath the priests in the temple violate the sanctity of the Sabbath and are guiltless? <verse-number id="Mt 12:6">6</verse-number>But I tell you that <supplied>something</supplied> greater than the temple is here! <verse-number id="Mt 12:7">7</verse-number>And if you had known what <idiom-start/>it means<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “it is”</note> ‘I want mercy and not sacrifice,’ you would not have condemned the guiltless. <verse-number id="Mt 12:8">8</verse-number>For the Son of Man is lord of the Sabbath.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A Man with a Withered Hand Healed</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 12:9">9</verse-number>And going on from there he came into their synagogue. <verse-number id="Mt 12:10">10</verse-number>And behold, <supplied>there was</supplied> a man who had a withered hand, and they asked him, saying, “Is it permitted to heal on the Sabbath?” in order that they could accuse him. <verse-number id="Mt 12:11">11</verse-number>But he said to them, “What man will there be among you who will have one sheep and if this one fell into a pit on the Sabbath, will not take hold of it and lift <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> out? <verse-number id="Mt 12:12">12</verse-number>Then to what degree <supplied>is</supplied> a man worth more than a sheep? So then, it is permitted to do good on the Sabbath.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 12:13">13</verse-number>Then he said to the man, “Stretch out your hand,” and he stretched <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> out, and it was restored <supplied>as</supplied> healthy as the other <supplied>one</supplied>. <verse-number id="Mt 12:14">14</verse-number>But the Pharisees went out <idiom-start/>and plotted<idiom-end/><note>Literally “taking counsel”</note> against him in order that they could destroy him. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>God’s Chosen Servant</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 12:15">15</verse-number>Now Jesus, <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“learned”) which is understood as temporal</note> learned of <supplied>it</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> withdrew from there, and many<note>Some manuscripts have “many crowds”</note> followed him, and he healed them all. <verse-number id="Mt 12:16">16</verse-number>And he warned them that they should not <idiom-start/>reveal his identity<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “make him known”</note> <verse-number id="Mt 12:17">17</verse-number>in order that what was spoken through the prophet Isaiah would be fulfilled, who said, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Mt 12:18">18</verse-number>“Behold my servant whom I have chosen, </li1>
				<li2>my beloved in whom my soul is well pleased. </li2>
				<li1>I will put my Spirit on him, </li1>
				<li2>and he will proclaim justice to the Gentiles. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Mt 12:19">19</verse-number>He will not quarrel or cry out, </li1>
				<li2>nor will anyone hear his voice in the streets. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Mt 12:20">20</verse-number>A crushed reed he will not break, </li1>
				<li2>and a smoldering wick he will not extinguish, </li2>
				<li1>until he brings justice to victory. </li1>
				<li2><verse-number id="Mt 12:21">21</verse-number>And in his name the Gentiles<note>Or “the nations”; the same Greek word (in the plural) can be translated as “nations,” “Gentiles,” or “pagans”</note> will hope.<note>Verses <cite title="BibleLEB2:Mt 12:18–21">18–21</cite> are a quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 42:1–4">Isa 42:1–4</cite></note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A House Divided Cannot Stand</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 12:22">22</verse-number>Then a demon-possessed man <supplied>who was</supplied> blind and mute was brought to him. And he healed him so that the <supplied>man who was</supplied> mute could speak and see. <verse-number id="Mt 12:23">23</verse-number>And all the crowds were amazed and began saying, “Perhaps this one is the Son of David!” <verse-number id="Mt 12:24">24</verse-number>But the Pharisees, <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> heard <supplied>it</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> said, “This man does not expel demons except by Beelzebul the ruler of demons!” <verse-number id="Mt 12:25">25</verse-number>But knowing their thoughts, he said to them, “Every kingdom divided against itself is laid waste, and every city or household divided against itself will not stand. <verse-number id="Mt 12:26">26</verse-number>And if Satan expels Satan, he is divided against himself. How then will his kingdom stand? <verse-number id="Mt 12:27">27</verse-number>And if I expel demons by Beelzebul, by whom do your sons expel <supplied>them</supplied>?<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> For this <supplied>reason</supplied> they will be your judges! <verse-number id="Mt 12:28">28</verse-number>But if I expel demons by the Spirit of God, then the kingdom of God has come upon you! <verse-number id="Mt 12:29">29</verse-number>Or how can someone enter into the house of a strong <supplied>man</supplied> and steal his property, unless he first ties up the strong <supplied>man</supplied>? And then he can thoroughly plunder his house. <verse-number id="Mt 12:30">30</verse-number>The one who is not with me is against me, and the one who does not gather with me scatters. <verse-number id="Mt 12:31">31</verse-number>For this <supplied>reason</supplied> I tell you, every sin and blasphemy will be forgiven people, but the blasphemy against the Spirit will not be forgiven! <verse-number id="Mt 12:32">32</verse-number>And whoever speaks a word against the Son of Man, it will be forgiven him. But whoever speaks against the Holy Spirit, it will not be forgiven him either in this age or in the coming one! </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Good Trees and Good Fruit or Bad Trees and Bad Fruit</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 12:33">33</verse-number>“Either make the tree good and its fruit <supplied>is</supplied> good, or make the tree bad and its fruit <supplied>is</supplied> bad, for the tree is known by its fruit. <verse-number id="Mt 12:34">34</verse-number>Offspring of vipers! How are you able to say good things <supplied>when you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“are”) which is understood as temporal</note> are evil? For from the abundance of the heart the mouth speaks. <verse-number id="Mt 12:35">35</verse-number>The good person from his<note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> good treasury brings out good <supplied>things</supplied>, and the evil person from his<note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> evil treasury brings out evil <supplied>things</supplied>. <verse-number id="Mt 12:36">36</verse-number>But I tell you that every worthless word that they speak, people will give an account for it on the day of judgment! <verse-number id="Mt 12:37">37</verse-number>For by your words you will be vindicated, and by your words you will be condemned.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Sign of Jonah</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 12:38">38</verse-number>Then some of the scribes and Pharisees answered him saying, “Teacher, we want to see a sign from you!” <verse-number id="Mt 12:39">39</verse-number>But he answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to them, “An evil and adulterous generation desires a sign, and no sign will be given to it except the sign of the prophet Jonah! <verse-number id="Mt 12:40">40</verse-number>For just as Jonah was in the belly of the huge fish three days and three nights, so the Son of Man will be in the heart of the earth three days and three nights. <verse-number id="Mt 12:41">41</verse-number>The people of Nineveh will stand up at the judgment with this generation and condemn it, because they repented at the proclamation of Jonah, and behold, <supplied>something</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “something” is supplied in the translation because the adjective is neuter gender</note> greater than Jonah <supplied>is</supplied> here! <verse-number id="Mt 12:42">42</verse-number>The queen of the south will rise up at the judgment with this generation and condemn it, because she came from the ends of the earth to hear the wisdom of Solomon, and behold, <supplied>something</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “something” is supplied in the translation because the adjective is neuter gender</note> greater than Solomon <supplied>is</supplied> here! </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>An Unclean Spirit Returns</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 12:43">43</verse-number>“Now whenever an unclean spirit has gone out of a person, it travels through waterless places searching for rest, and does not find <supplied>it</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <verse-number id="Mt 12:44">44</verse-number>Then it says, ‘I will return to my house from which I came out.’ And <supplied>when it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“arrives”) which is understood as temporal</note> arrives it finds <supplied>the house</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> unoccupied and swept and put in order. <verse-number id="Mt 12:45">45</verse-number>Then it goes and brings along with itself seven other spirits more evil than itself, and <supplied>they</supplied> go in <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“go in”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> live there. And the last <supplied>state</supplied> of that person becomes worse than the first. So it will be for this evil generation also!” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus’ Mother and Brothers</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 12:46">46</verse-number>And<note>Some manuscripts omit “And”</note> <supplied>while</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“speaking”)</note> he was still speaking to the crowds, behold, his mother and brothers were standing there outside, desiring to speak to him. <verse-number id="Mt 12:47">47</verse-number>And someone told him, “Behold, your mother and your brothers are standing there outside desiring to speak to you.” <verse-number id="Mt 12:48">48</verse-number>But he answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to the one who told him, “Who is my mother, and who are my brothers?” <verse-number id="Mt 12:49">49</verse-number>And stretching out his hand toward his disciples, he said, “Behold my mother and my brothers! <verse-number id="Mt 12:50">50</verse-number>For whoever does the will of my Father <supplied>who is</supplied> in heaven, he is my brother and sister and mother.” </p>
		</chapter>