<chapter id="Mt 13">
			<pericope>The Parable of the Sower</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 13:1">1</verse-number> On that day Jesus went out of the house <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went out”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> was sitting by the sea.<note>That is, the Sea of Galilee</note> <verse-number id="Mt 13:2">2</verse-number>And large crowds gathered close around him, so that he got into a boat to sit down, and all the crowd was standing on the shore. <verse-number id="Mt 13:3">3</verse-number>And he spoke many <supplied>things</supplied> to them in parables, saying, “Behold, the sower went out to sow, <verse-number id="Mt 13:4">4</verse-number>and while he was sowing, <idiom-start/>some seed<idiom-end/><note>Literally “some of which”</note> fell on the side of the path, and the birds came <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> devoured it. <verse-number id="Mt 13:5">5</verse-number>And other <supplied>seed</supplied> fell on the rocky ground, where it did not have much soil, and it sprang up at once because it did not have <supplied>any</supplied> depth of soil. <verse-number id="Mt 13:6">6</verse-number>But <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“rose”)</note> the sun rose it was scorched, and because it did not have <supplied>enough</supplied> root, it withered. <verse-number id="Mt 13:7">7</verse-number>And other <supplied>seed</supplied> fell among the thorn plants, and the thorn plants came up and choked it. <verse-number id="Mt 13:8">8</verse-number>But other <supplied>seed</supplied> fell on the good soil and produced grain,<note>Literally “fruit,” describing here the grain harvested from the healthy plants; in contemporary English this would more naturally be expressed by terms like “grain” or “crop”</note> this one a hundred <supplied>times as much</supplied> and this one sixty and this one thirty. <verse-number id="Mt 13:9">9</verse-number>The one who has ears, let him hear!” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Reason for the Parables</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 13:10">10</verse-number>And the disciples came up <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to him, “<idiom-start/>Why<idiom-end/><note>Literally “because of what”</note> do you speak to them in parables?” <verse-number id="Mt 13:11">11</verse-number>And he answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to them, “To you it has been granted to know the mysteries of the kingdom of heaven, but to those <supplied>people</supplied> it has not been granted. <verse-number id="Mt 13:12">12</verse-number>For whoever has, to him <supplied>more</supplied> will be given, and he will have an abundance. But whoever does not have, even what he has will be taken away from him. <verse-number id="Mt 13:13">13</verse-number>For this <supplied>reason</supplied> I speak to them in parables, because seeing they do not see, and hearing they do not hear, nor do they understand, <verse-number id="Mt 13:14">14</verse-number>and with reference to them the prophecy of Isaiah is fulfilled that says, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“<idiom-start/>You will listen carefully<idiom-end/><note>Literally “with hearing you will hear”</note> and will never understand, </li1>
				<li2>and <idiom-start/>you will look closely<idiom-end/><note>Literally “seeing you will see”</note> and will never perceive. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Mt 13:15">15</verse-number>For the heart of this people has become dull, </li1>
				<li2>and with their ears they hear with difficulty, </li2>
				<li2>and they have shut their eyes, </li2>
				<li1>so that they would not see with their eyes </li1>
				<li2>and hear with their ears </li2>
				<li2>and understand with their heart </li2>
				<li2>and turn, and I would heal them.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 6:9–10">Isa 6:9–10</cite></note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 13:16">16</verse-number>But your eyes <supplied>are</supplied> blessed because they see, and your ears because they hear. <verse-number id="Mt 13:17">17</verse-number>For truly I say to you that many prophets and righteous <supplied>people</supplied> longed to see what you see, and did not see <supplied>it</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and to hear what you hear, and did not hear <supplied>it</supplied>!<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Parable of the Sower Interpreted</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 13:18">18</verse-number>“You, therefore, listen to the parable of the sower: <verse-number id="Mt 13:19">19</verse-number><supplied>When</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“hears”)</note> anyone hears the word about the kingdom and does not understand <supplied>it</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> the evil one comes and snatches away what was sown in his heart. This is what was sown on the side of the path. <verse-number id="Mt 13:20">20</verse-number>And what was sown on the rocky ground—this is the one who hears the word and immediately receives it with joy. <verse-number id="Mt 13:21">21</verse-number>But he does not have a root in himself, but <idiom-start/>lasts only a little while<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “is temporary”</note> and <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“happens”)</note> affliction or persecution happens because of the word, immediately he falls away. <verse-number id="Mt 13:22">22</verse-number>And what was sown into the thorn plants—this is the one who hears the word, and the anxiety of this world<note>Some manuscripts have “of the world”</note> and the deceitfulness of wealth choke the word and it becomes unproductive. <verse-number id="Mt 13:23">23</verse-number>But what was sown on the good soil—this is the one who hears the word and understands <supplied>it</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> who indeed bears fruit and produces, this one a hundred <supplied>times as much</supplied>, and this one sixty, and this one thirty.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Parable of the Weeds Among the Wheat</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 13:24">24</verse-number>He put before them another parable, saying, “The kingdom of heaven may be compared to a man who sowed good seed in his field. <verse-number id="Mt 13:25">25</verse-number>But while his<note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> people were sleeping, his enemy came and sowed darnel<note>A weed that looks similar to wheat but has poisonous seeds</note> in the midst of the wheat and went away. <verse-number id="Mt 13:26">26</verse-number>So when the <idiom-start/>wheat<idiom-end/><note>Literally “grass,” “hay,” but in this context referring to the good plants as opposed to the weeds</note> sprouted and yielded grain, then the darnel appeared also. <verse-number id="Mt 13:27">27</verse-number>So the slaves of the master of the house came <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to him, ‘Master, did you not sow good seed in your field? How then does it have darnel?’ <verse-number id="Mt 13:28">28</verse-number>And he said to them, ‘An enemy has done this!’ So the slaves said to him, ‘Then do you want us to go <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“go”) has been translated as an English infinitive</note> gather them?’ <verse-number id="Mt 13:29">29</verse-number>But he said, “No, lest <supplied>when you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“gather”) which is understood as temporal</note> gather the darnel you uproot the wheat together with it. <verse-number id="Mt 13:30">30</verse-number>Let both grow together until the harvest, and at the season of the harvest I will tell the reapers, “First gather the darnel and tie it into bundles to burn them, but gather the wheat into my storehouse.” ’ ” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Parable of the Mustard Seed</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 13:31">31</verse-number>He put before them another parable, saying, “The kingdom of heaven is like a mustard seed that a man took <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“took”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> sowed in his field. <verse-number id="Mt 13:32">32</verse-number><idiom-start/>It<idiom-end/><note>Literally “which,” but a new sentence is started here in the English translation</note> is the smallest of all the seeds, but when it is grown it is larger than the garden herbs and becomes a tree, so that the birds of the sky come and nest in its branches.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Parable of the Yeast</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 13:33">33</verse-number>He told them another parable: “The kingdom of heaven is like yeast that a woman took <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“took”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> put into three measures of wheat flour until the whole <supplied>batch</supplied> was leavened.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Parables Fulfill Prophecy</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 13:34">34</verse-number>Jesus spoke all these <supplied>things</supplied> to the crowds in parables, and he was saying nothing to them without a parable, <verse-number id="Mt 13:35">35</verse-number>in order that what was spoken through the prophet would be fulfilled, who said, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“I will open my mouth in parables; </li1>
				<li2>I will proclaim what has been hidden since the creation.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 78:2">Ps 78:2</cite></note><note>Some manuscripts have “since the creation of the world”</note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Parable of the Weeds Interpreted</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 13:36">36</verse-number>Then he left the crowds <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“left”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> came into the house, and his disciples came to him saying, “Explain the parable of the darnel in the field to us.” <verse-number id="Mt 13:37">37</verse-number>So he answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “The one who sows the good seed is the Son of Man, <verse-number id="Mt 13:38">38</verse-number>and the field is the world. And the good seed—these are the sons of the kingdom, but the darnel are the sons of the evil one. <verse-number id="Mt 13:39">39</verse-number>And the enemy who sowed them is the devil, and the harvest is the end of the age, and the reapers are angels. <verse-number id="Mt 13:40">40</verse-number>Thus just as the darnel is gathered and burned<note>Some manuscripts have “burned up”</note> with fire, so it will be at the end of the age. <verse-number id="Mt 13:41">41</verse-number>The Son of Man will send out his angels and they will gather out of his kingdom all the causes of sin and those who do lawless deeds, <verse-number id="Mt 13:42">42</verse-number>and throw them into the fiery furnace.<note>An allusion to <cite title="BibleLEB2: Da 3:6">Dan 3:6</cite></note> In that place there will be weeping and gnashing of teeth! <verse-number id="Mt 13:43">43</verse-number>Then the righteous will shine like the sun in the kingdom of their Father.<note>An allusion to <cite title="BibleLEB2: Da 12:3">Dan 12:3</cite></note> The one who has ears, let him hear! </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Parable of the Treasure Hidden in a Field</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 13:44">44</verse-number>“The kingdom of heaven is like treasure hidden in a field, that a man found <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“found”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> concealed, and in his joy he goes and sells everything that he has and buys that field. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Parable of the Valuable Pearl</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 13:45">45</verse-number>“Again, the kingdom of heaven is like a merchant searching for fine pearls. <verse-number id="Mt 13:46">46</verse-number>And <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“found”) which is understood as temporal</note> found one very valuable pearl, he went <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> sold everything that he possessed and purchased it. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Parable of the Dragnet</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 13:47">47</verse-number>“Again, the kingdom of heaven is like a dragnet that was thrown into the sea and gathered <supplied>fish</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> of every kind, <verse-number id="Mt 13:48">48</verse-number>which when it was filled they pulled to shore and sat down <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“sat down”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> collected the good <supplied>fish</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the word “<supplied>fish</supplied>” is not in the Greek text but is implied</note> into containers, but the bad they threw out. <verse-number id="Mt 13:49">49</verse-number>Thus it will be at the end of the age. The angels will go out and separate the evil from among the righteous <verse-number id="Mt 13:50">50</verse-number>and throw them into the fiery furnace.<note>An allusion to <cite title="BibleLEB2: Da 3:6">Dan 3:6</cite></note> In that place there will be weeping and gnashing of teeth! </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 13:51">51</verse-number>“Have you understood all these <supplied>things</supplied>?” They said to him, “Yes.” <verse-number id="Mt 13:52">52</verse-number>And he said to them, “For this <supplied>reason</supplied> every scribe who has been trained for the kingdom of heaven is like the master of the house who brings out of his storeroom new <supplied>things</supplied> and old <supplied>things</supplied>.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Rejected at Nazareth</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 13:53">53</verse-number>And it happened that when Jesus had finished these parables he went away from there. <verse-number id="Mt 13:54">54</verse-number>And he came to his hometown <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> began to teach<note>The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to teach”)</note> them in their synagogue, so that they were amazed and said, “From where did this man <supplied>get</supplied> this wisdom and these miracles? <verse-number id="Mt 13:55">55</verse-number>Is not this one the son of the carpenter? Is not his mother called Mary and his brothers James and Joseph and Simon and Judas? <verse-number id="Mt 13:56">56</verse-number>And are not all his sisters with us? From where then did this man <supplied>get</supplied> all these <supplied>things</supplied>?” <verse-number id="Mt 13:57">57</verse-number>And they were offended by him. But Jesus said to them, “A prophet is not without honor except in his <supplied>own</supplied> hometown and in his <supplied>own</supplied> household.” <verse-number id="Mt 13:58">58</verse-number>And he did not perform many miracles in that place because of their unbelief. </p>
		</chapter>