<chapter id="Mt 15">
			<pericope>Human Traditions and God’s Commandments</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 15:1">1</verse-number> Then Pharisees and scribes came to Jesus from Jerusalem, saying, <verse-number id="Mt 15:2">2</verse-number>“Why do your disciples break the tradition of the elders? For they do not wash their hands when they eat <idiom-start/>a meal<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “bread”</note> <verse-number id="Mt 15:3">3</verse-number>So he answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to them, “Why do you also break the commandment of God because of your tradition? <verse-number id="Mt 15:4">4</verse-number>For God said, ‘Honor your<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> father and your<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> mother,’<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ex 20:12">Exod 20:12</cite>; <cite title="BibleLEB2: Dt 5:16">Deut 5:16</cite></note> and ‘The one who speaks evil of father or mother <idiom-start/>must certainly die<idiom-end/><note>Literally “let him die the death”</note>.’<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ex 21:17">Exod 21:17</cite>; <cite title="BibleLEB2: Le 20:9">Lev 20:9</cite></note> <verse-number id="Mt 15:5">5</verse-number>But you say, ‘Whoever says to his<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> father or his<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> mother, “Whatever <idiom-start/>benefit you would have received<idiom-end/><note>Literally “you would have been benefited”</note> from me <supplied>is</supplied> a gift <supplied>to God</supplied>,” <verse-number id="Mt 15:6">6</verse-number>need not honor his father,’<note>Most later manuscripts add “or his mother”</note> and you make void the word of God for the sake of your tradition. <verse-number id="Mt 15:7">7</verse-number>Hypocrites! Isaiah correctly prophesied about you saying, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Mt 15:8">8</verse-number>‘This people honors me with their<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> lips, </li1>
				<li2>but their heart is far, far away from me, </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Mt 15:9">9</verse-number>and they worship me in vain, </li1>
				<li2>teaching <supplied>as</supplied> doctrines the commandments of men.’ ”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 29:13">Isa 29:13</cite></note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Defilement from Within</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 15:10">10</verse-number>And summoning the crowd, he said to them, “Hear and understand: <verse-number id="Mt 15:11">11</verse-number>It is not what goes into the mouth that defiles a person, but what comes out of the mouth—this defiles a person.” <verse-number id="Mt 15:12">12</verse-number>Then the disciples came <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to him, “Do you know that the Pharisees were offended <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> heard this saying?” <verse-number id="Mt 15:13">13</verse-number>And he answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “Every plant that my heavenly Father did not plant will be uprooted. <verse-number id="Mt 15:14">14</verse-number>Let<note>Or “Depart from”</note> them! They are blind guides of the blind. And if the blind guide the blind, both will fall into a pit.” <verse-number id="Mt 15:15">15</verse-number>But Peter answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to him, “Explain this parable to us.” <verse-number id="Mt 15:16">16</verse-number>But he said, “Are you also still without understanding? <verse-number id="Mt 15:17">17</verse-number>Do you not understand that everything that enters into the mouth goes into the stomach and is evacuated into the latrine? <verse-number id="Mt 15:18">18</verse-number>But the things that come out of the mouth come from the heart, and these defile the person. <verse-number id="Mt 15:19">19</verse-number>For from the heart come evil plans, murder, adultery, sexual immorality, theft, false witness, abusive speech. <verse-number id="Mt 15:20">20</verse-number>These are the things that defile a person. But eating with unwashed hands does not defile a person!” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A Canaanite Woman’s Great Faith</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 15:21">21</verse-number>And departing from there, Jesus went away to the region of Tyre and Sidon. <verse-number id="Mt 15:22">22</verse-number>And behold, a Canaanite woman from that district came <supplied>and</supplied> cried out, saying, “Have mercy on me, Lord, Son of David! My daughter <supplied>is</supplied> severely possessed by a demon!” <verse-number id="Mt 15:23">23</verse-number>But he did not answer her a word. And his disciples came up <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> asked him, saying, “Send her away, because she is crying out after us!” <verse-number id="Mt 15:24">24</verse-number>But he answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “I was not sent except to the lost sheep of the house of Israel.” <verse-number id="Mt 15:25">25</verse-number>But she came <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> knelt down before him, saying, “Lord, help me!” <verse-number id="Mt 15:26">26</verse-number>And he answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “It is not right to take the children’s bread and throw <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to the dogs!” <verse-number id="Mt 15:27">27</verse-number>So she said, “Yes, Lord, for even the dogs eat the crumbs that fall from their master’s table.” <verse-number id="Mt 15:28">28</verse-number>Then Jesus answered <supplied>and</supplied> said to her, “O woman, your faith <supplied>is</supplied> great! Let it be done for you as you want.” And her daughter was healed from that hour. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Many Others Healed in Galilee</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 15:29">29</verse-number>And departing from there, Jesus went along the Sea of Galilee, and he went up on the mountain <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> was sitting there. <verse-number id="Mt 15:30">30</verse-number>And large crowds came to him, having with them <supplied>the</supplied> mute, blind, lame, crippled,<note>Some manuscripts have “<supplied>the</supplied> lame, blind, crippled, mute”</note> and many others, and they put them down at his feet, and he healed them. <verse-number id="Mt 15:31">31</verse-number>So then the crowd was astonished <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> saw the mute speaking, the crippled healthy, and the lame walking, and the blind seeing, and they praised the God of Israel. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Feeding of Four Thousand</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 15:32">32</verse-number>And Jesus summoned his disciples <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“summoned”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “I have compassion on the crowd, because they have remained with me three days already and do not have anything to eat, and I do not want to send them away hungry lest they give out on the way.” <verse-number id="Mt 15:33">33</verse-number>And the disciples said to him, “Where in <supplied>this</supplied> desolate place <idiom-start/>can we get<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for us”</note> so much bread that such a great crowd could be satisfied?” <verse-number id="Mt 15:34">34</verse-number>And Jesus said to them, “How many loaves do you have?” So they said, “Seven, and a few little fish.” <verse-number id="Mt 15:35">35</verse-number>And commanding the crowd to recline for a meal on the ground, <verse-number id="Mt 15:36">36</verse-number>he took the seven loaves and the fish and <supplied>after he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had given thanks”) which is understood as temporal</note> had given thanks, he broke <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and began giving<note>The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began giving”)</note> <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to the disciples, and the disciples <supplied>gave them</supplied> to the crowds. <verse-number id="Mt 15:37">37</verse-number>And they all ate and were satisfied, and they picked up what was left over of the broken pieces, seven baskets full. <verse-number id="Mt 15:38">38</verse-number>Now those who ate were four thousand men, in addition to women and children. <verse-number id="Mt 15:39">39</verse-number>And <supplied>after he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had given thanks”) which is understood as temporal</note> sent away the crowds, he got into the boat and went to the region of Magadan. </p>
		</chapter>