<chapter id="Mt 16">
			<pericope>The Signs of the Times</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 16:1">1</verse-number> And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“came”) which is understood as temporal</note> the Pharisees and Sadducees came to test <supplied>him</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> they asked him to show them a sign from heaven. <verse-number id="Mt 16:2">2</verse-number>So he answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to them, “<supplied>When</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“comes”)</note> evening comes you say, ‘<supplied>It will be</supplied> fair weather because the sky is red,’ <verse-number id="Mt 16:3">3</verse-number>and early in the morning, ‘Today <supplied>it will be</supplied> stormy weather, because the sky is red <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied in the translation because of English style</note> darkening.’ You know how to evaluate correctly the appearance of the sky, but you are not able <supplied>to evaluate</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>to evaluate</supplied>” is an implied repetition of the verb earlier in the verse</note> the signs of the times. <verse-number id="Mt 16:4">4</verse-number>An evil and adulterous generation seeks for a sign, and a sign will not be given to it except the sign of Jonah!” And he left them <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“left”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> went away. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Beware the Leaven of the Pharisees and Sadducees</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 16:5">5</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“arrived”) which is understood as temporal</note> the disciples arrived at the other side,<note>That is, the other side of the Sea of Galilee</note> they had forgotten to take bread. <verse-number id="Mt 16:6">6</verse-number>And Jesus said to them, “Watch out for and beware of the leaven of the Pharisees and Sadducees!” <verse-number id="Mt 16:7">7</verse-number>So they were discussing <supplied>this</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> among themselves, saying, “<supplied>It is</supplied> because we did not take bread.” <verse-number id="Mt 16:8">8</verse-number>But knowing <supplied>this</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> Jesus said, “Why are you discussing among yourselves that you did not take bread,<note>Some manuscripts have “you do not have bread”</note> <supplied>you</supplied> of little faith? <verse-number id="Mt 16:9">9</verse-number>Do you not yet understand or do you not remember the five loaves for the five thousand, and how many baskets you took up? <verse-number id="Mt 16:10">10</verse-number>Or the seven loaves for the four thousand and how many baskets you took up? <verse-number id="Mt 16:11">11</verse-number>How do you not understand that I did not speak to you about bread? But beware of the leaven of the Pharisees and Sadducees!” <verse-number id="Mt 16:12">12</verse-number>Then they understood that he did not say to beware of the leaven of bread, but of the teaching of the Pharisees and Sadducees. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Peter’s Confession at Caesarea Philippi</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 16:13">13</verse-number>Now <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“came”) which is understood as temporal</note> Jesus came to the region of Caesarea <idiom-start/>Philippi<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “of Philip”</note> he began asking<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began asking”)</note> his disciples, saying, “Who do people say <supplied>that</supplied> the Son of Man is?” <verse-number id="Mt 16:14">14</verse-number>And they said, <idiom-start/>Some<idiom-end/><note>Literally “those on the one hand”</note> <supplied>say</supplied> John the Baptist, but others Elijah, and others Jeremiah or one of the prophets.” <verse-number id="Mt 16:15">15</verse-number>He said to them, “But who do you say <supplied>that</supplied> I am?” <verse-number id="Mt 16:16">16</verse-number>And Simon Peter answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “You are the Christ, the Son of the living God!” <verse-number id="Mt 16:17">17</verse-number>And Jesus answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to him, “Blessed are you, Simon son of Jonah, because flesh and blood did not reveal <supplied>this</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to you, but my Father <supplied>who is</supplied> in heaven. <verse-number id="Mt 16:18">18</verse-number>And I also say to you that you are Peter, and on this rock I will build my church, and the gates of Hades will not overpower it! <verse-number id="Mt 16:19">19</verse-number>I will give you the keys of the kingdom of heaven, and whatever you bind on earth will be bound<note>Or “will have been bound”</note> in heaven, and whatever you release on earth will be released<note>Or “will have been released”</note> in heaven.” <verse-number id="Mt 16:20">20</verse-number>Then he commanded the disciples that they should tell no one that he was the Christ. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus Predicts His Death and Resurrection</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 16:21">21</verse-number>From that time <supplied>on</supplied> Jesus began to show his disciples that he must go to Jerusalem and suffer many <supplied>things</supplied> from the elders and chief priests and scribes, and be killed, and be raised on the third day. <verse-number id="Mt 16:22">22</verse-number>And Peter took him aside <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“took … aside”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> began to rebuke him, saying, <idiom-start/>God forbid<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “merciful to you”</note> Lord! This will never happen to you!” <verse-number id="Mt 16:23">23</verse-number>But he turned around <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“turned around”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to Peter, “Get behind me, Satan! You are a cause for stumbling to me, because you are not intent on the things of God, but the things of people!” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Taking Up One’s Cross to Follow Jesus</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 16:24">24</verse-number>Then Jesus said to his disciples, “If anyone wants to come after me, let him deny himself and take up his cross and follow me. <verse-number id="Mt 16:25">25</verse-number>For whoever wants to save his life will lose it, but whoever loses his life on account of me will find it. <verse-number id="Mt 16:26">26</verse-number>For what will a person be benefited if he gains the whole world but forfeits his life? Or what will a person give in exchange for his life? <verse-number id="Mt 16:27">27</verse-number>For the Son of Man is going to come in the glory of his Father with his angels, and at that time he will reward each one according to <idiom-start/>what he has done<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “his activity”</note> <verse-number id="Mt 16:28">28</verse-number>Truly I say to you, that there are some of those standing here who will never experience death until they see the Son of Man coming in his kingdom.” </p>
		</chapter>