<chapter id="Mt 17">
			<pericope>The Transfiguration</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 17:1">1</verse-number> And after six days Jesus took along Peter and James and John his brother, and led them up on a high mountain by themselves. <verse-number id="Mt 17:2">2</verse-number>And he was transfigured before them, and his face shone like the sun, and his clothing became bright as the light. <verse-number id="Mt 17:3">3</verse-number>And behold, Moses and Elijah appeared to them, talking with him. <verse-number id="Mt 17:4">4</verse-number>So Peter answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to Jesus, “Lord, it is good <supplied>that</supplied> we are here! If you want, I will make here three shelters, one for you and one for Moses and one for Elijah.” <verse-number id="Mt 17:5">5</verse-number><supplied>While</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“speaking”)</note> he was still speaking, behold, a bright cloud overshadowed them, and behold, a voice from the cloud said, “This is my beloved Son, with whom I am well pleased. Listen to him!” <verse-number id="Mt 17:6">6</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> the disciples heard <supplied>this</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> they fell down on their faces and were extremely frightened. <verse-number id="Mt 17:7">7</verse-number>And Jesus came and touched them <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“touched”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “Get up and do not be afraid.” <verse-number id="Mt 17:8">8</verse-number>And <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“lifted up”) which is understood as temporal</note> lifted up their eyes they saw no one except him—Jesus alone. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 17:9">9</verse-number>And <supplied>as</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“were coming down”)</note> they were coming down from the mountain, Jesus commanded them saying, “Tell no one the vision until the Son of Man is raised from the dead.” <verse-number id="Mt 17:10">10</verse-number>And the disciples asked him, saying, “Then why do the scribes say that Elijah must come first?” <verse-number id="Mt 17:11">11</verse-number>And he answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “Elijah indeed is coming, and will restore all <supplied>things</supplied>. <verse-number id="Mt 17:12">12</verse-number>But I say to you that Elijah has already come, and they did not recognize him, but did with him whatever they wanted. In the <supplied>same</supplied> way also the Son of Man is going to suffer <supplied>at</supplied> their hands.” <verse-number id="Mt 17:13">13</verse-number>Then the disciples understood that he had spoken to them about John the Baptist. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A Demon-possessed Boy Healed</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 17:14">14</verse-number>And <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“came”)</note> came to the crowd, a man approached him, kneeling down before him <verse-number id="Mt 17:15">15</verse-number>and saying, “Lord, have mercy on my son, because he has seizures and suffers severely, for often he falls into the fire and often into the water. <verse-number id="Mt 17:16">16</verse-number>And I brought him to your disciples, and they were not able to heal him.” <verse-number id="Mt 17:17">17</verse-number>And Jesus answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “O unbelieving and perverse generation! <idiom-start/>How long<idiom-end/><note>Literally “until when”</note> will I be with you? <idiom-start/>How long<idiom-end/><note>Literally “until when”</note> must I put up with you? Bring him here to me!” <verse-number id="Mt 17:18">18</verse-number>And Jesus rebuked him, and the demon came out of him and the boy was healed from that hour. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 17:19">19</verse-number>Then the disciples approached Jesus privately <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“approached”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, <idiom-start/>Why<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for what”</note> were we not able to expel it?” <verse-number id="Mt 17:20">20</verse-number>And he said to them, “Because of your little faith. For truly I say to you, if you have faith like a mustard seed, you will say to this mountain, ‘Move from here <supplied>to</supplied> there,’ and it will move, and nothing will be impossible for you.”<note>Most later Greek manuscripts add v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Mt 17:21">21</cite>, “But this kind does not go out except by prayer and fasting.”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus Predicts His Death and Resurrection a Second Time</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 17:22">22</verse-number>Now <supplied>as</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“were gathering”)</note> they were gathering in Galilee, Jesus said to them, “The Son of Man is going to be betrayed into the hands of men,<note>Or possibly “of people,” in a generic sense, although the reference here may be to the specific group responsible for Jesus’ arrest, where it is unlikely women were present</note> <verse-number id="Mt 17:23">23</verse-number>and they will kill him, and on the third day he will be raised.” And they were extremely distressed. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Paying the Double Drachma Temple Tax</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 17:24">24</verse-number>Now <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“arrived”)</note> they arrived in Capernaum, the ones who collected the double drachma <supplied>tax</supplied><note>This refers to the half-shekel annual tax paid by Jewish males to support the temple; over time the name of the coin commonly used to pay the tax came to be used for the tax itself</note> came up to Peter and said, “Does your teacher not pay the double drachma <supplied>tax</supplied>?” <verse-number id="Mt 17:25">25</verse-number>He said, “Yes.” And <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“came”) which is understood as temporal</note> came into the house, Jesus spoke to him first, saying, “What do you think, Simon? From whom do the kings of the earth collect tolls or taxes—from their own sons, or from foreigners?” <verse-number id="Mt 17:26">26</verse-number>And <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“said”) which is understood as temporal</note> said, “From foreigners,” Jesus said to him, “Then the sons are free. <verse-number id="Mt 17:27">27</verse-number>But so that we do not give offense to them, go out to the sea, cast <supplied>a line with</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The words “<supplied>a line with</supplied>” are not in the Greek text but are implied</note> a hook, and take the first fish that comes up. And <supplied>when you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“open”) which is understood as temporal</note> open its mouth, you will find a four-drachma coin. Take that <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“take”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> give <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to them for me and you.” </p>
		</chapter>