<chapter id="Mt 18">
			<pericope>The Question About Who Is Greatest</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 18:1">1</verse-number> At that time the disciples came up to Jesus, saying, “Who then is the greatest in the kingdom of heaven?” <verse-number id="Mt 18:2">2</verse-number>And calling a child <supplied>to himself</supplied>, he had him stand in their midst <verse-number id="Mt 18:3">3</verse-number>and said, “Truly I say to you, unless you turn around and become like young children, you will never enter into the kingdom of heaven! <verse-number id="Mt 18:4">4</verse-number>Therefore whoever humbles himself like this child, this person is the greatest in the kingdom of heaven, <verse-number id="Mt 18:5">5</verse-number>and whoever welcomes one child such as this in my name welcomes me. <verse-number id="Mt 18:6">6</verse-number>But whoever causes one of these little ones who believe in me to sin, it would be better for him that <idiom-start/>a large millstone<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a millstone of a donkey”</note> be hung on<note>Some manuscripts have “around”</note> his neck and he be drowned in the depths of the sea. <verse-number id="Mt 18:7">7</verse-number>Woe to the world because of causes for stumbling, for <supplied>it is</supplied> a necessity <supplied>that</supplied> causes for stumbling come; nevertheless, woe to the person through whom the cause for stumbling comes. <verse-number id="Mt 18:8">8</verse-number>And if your hand or your foot causes you to sin, cut it off and throw <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> from you! It is better for you to enter into life crippled or lame than, having two hands or two feet, to be thrown into the eternal fire! <verse-number id="Mt 18:9">9</verse-number>And if your eye causes you to sin, tear it out and throw <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> from you! It is better for you to enter into life one-eyed than, having two eyes, to be thrown into fiery hell! </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Parable of the Lost Sheep</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 18:10">10</verse-number>“See to it that you do not despise one of these little ones, for I tell you that their angels in heaven constantly see the face of my Father <supplied>who is</supplied> in heaven.<note>Many later Greek manuscripts include vs. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Mt 18:11">11</cite>, “For the Son of Man came to save those who are lost.”</note> <verse-number id="Mt 18:12">12</verse-number>What do you think? If <idiom-start/>a certain man has<idiom-end/><note>Literally “there are to a certain man”</note> a hundred sheep, and one of them wanders away, will he not leave the ninety-nine on the hills and go <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“go”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> look for the one that wandered away? <verse-number id="Mt 18:13">13</verse-number>And if he happens to find it, truly I say to you that he rejoices over it more than over the ninety-nine that did not wander away. <verse-number id="Mt 18:14">14</verse-number>In the <supplied>same</supplied> way it is not the will <idiom-start/>of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the presence of”</note> your Father <supplied>who is</supplied> in heaven that one of these little ones perish. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Confronting a Brother Who Sins Against You</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 18:15">15</verse-number>“Now if your brother sins against you, go correct him between you and him alone. If he listens to you, you have gained your brother. <verse-number id="Mt 18:16">16</verse-number>But if he does not listen, take with you in addition one or two <supplied>others</supplied>, so that by <idiom-start/>the testimony<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the mouth”</note> of two or three witnesses every matter may be established. <verse-number id="Mt 18:17">17</verse-number>And if he refuses to listen to them, tell <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to the church. But if he refuses to listen to the church also, let him be to you as a Gentile and a tax collector. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 18:18">18</verse-number>“Truly I say to you, whatever you bind on earth will be bound in heaven, and whatever you release on earth will be released in heaven. <verse-number id="Mt 18:19">19</verse-number>Again, truly I say to you that if two of you agree on earth about any matter that they ask, it will be done for them from my Father <supplied>who is</supplied> in heaven. <verse-number id="Mt 18:20">20</verse-number>For where two or three are gathered in my name, I am there in the midst of them.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Parable of the Unforgiving Slave</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 18:21">21</verse-number>Then Peter came up to him <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said,<note>Some manuscripts have “Then Peter came up <supplied>and</supplied> said to him”</note> “Lord, how many times will my brother sin against me and I will forgive him? Up to seven times?” <verse-number id="Mt 18:22">22</verse-number>Jesus said to him, “I do not say to you up to seven times, but up to seventy times seven!<note>Or “seventy-seven times”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 18:23">23</verse-number>“For this <supplied>reason</supplied> the kingdom of heaven may be compared to a man—a king—who wanted to settle accounts with his slaves. <verse-number id="Mt 18:24">24</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“began”)</note> he began to settle <supplied>them</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> someone was brought to him who owed ten thousand talents. <verse-number id="Mt 18:25">25</verse-number>And <supplied>because</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“have”) which is understood as causal</note> he did not have <supplied>enough</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to repay <supplied>it</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> the master ordered him to be sold, and his<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> wife and his<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> children and everything that he had, and to be repaid. <verse-number id="Mt 18:26">26</verse-number>Then the slave threw himself to the ground <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“threw himself to the ground”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> began to do obeisance to him, saying, ‘Be patient with me, and I will pay back everything to you!’ <verse-number id="Mt 18:27">27</verse-number>So the master of that slave, <supplied>because he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had compassion”) which is understood as causal</note> had compassion, released him and forgave him the loan. <verse-number id="Mt 18:28">28</verse-number>But that slave went out <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went out”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> found one of his fellow slaves who owed him a hundred denarii, and taking hold of him, he began to choke <supplied>him</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> saying, ‘Pay back everything that you owe!’ <verse-number id="Mt 18:29">29</verse-number>Then his fellow slave threw himself to the ground <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“threw himself to the ground”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> began to implore<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to implore”)</note> him, saying, ‘Be patient with me and I will repay you!’ <verse-number id="Mt 18:30">30</verse-number>But he did not want to, but rather he went <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> threw him into prison until he would repay what was owed. <verse-number id="Mt 18:31">31</verse-number>So <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> his fellow slaves saw what had happened, they were extremely distressed, and went <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> reported to their master everything that had happened. <verse-number id="Mt 18:32">32</verse-number>Then his master summoned him <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“summoned”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to him, ‘Wicked slave! I forgave you all that debt because you implored me! <verse-number id="Mt 18:33">33</verse-number>Should you not also have shown mercy to your fellow slave as I also showed mercy to you?’ <verse-number id="Mt 18:34">34</verse-number>And <supplied>because he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was angry”) which is understood as causal</note> was angry, his master handed him over to the merciless jailers<note>Or “torturers”</note> until he would repay everything that was owed. <verse-number id="Mt 18:35">35</verse-number>So also my heavenly Father will do to you, unless each of you forgives his brother from your hearts!” </p>
		</chapter>