<chapter id="Mt 19">
			<pericope>On Divorce</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 19:1">1</verse-number> And it happened that when Jesus had finished these statements, he went away from Galilee and came into the region of Judea on the other side of the Jordan. <verse-number id="Mt 19:2">2</verse-number>And large crowds followed him, and he healed them there. <verse-number id="Mt 19:3">3</verse-number>And Pharisees came up to him <supplied>in order to</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>in order to</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“test”) which is understood as purpose</note> test him, and asked<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the participle (“asked”) is translated as a finite verb because of English style</note> if it was permitted for a man to divorce his wife for any cause. <verse-number id="Mt 19:4">4</verse-number>And he answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “Have you not read that the one who created <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> from the beginning made them male and female <verse-number id="Mt 19:5">5</verse-number>and said, ‘On account of this a man will leave his<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> father and his<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> mother and will be joined to his wife, and the two will become one flesh’?<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ge 2:24">Gen 2:24</cite></note> <verse-number id="Mt 19:6">6</verse-number>So then, they are no longer two but one flesh. Therefore what God has joined together, man must not separate.” <verse-number id="Mt 19:7">7</verse-number>They said to him, “Why then did Moses command <supplied>us</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to give a document—a certificate of divorce—and to divorce her?” <verse-number id="Mt 19:8">8</verse-number>He said to them, “Moses, with reference to your hardness of heart, permitted you to divorce your wives, but from the beginning it was not like this. <verse-number id="Mt 19:9">9</verse-number>Now I say to you that whoever divorces his wife, except on the basis of sexual immorality, and marries another commits adultery, and whoever marries her who is divorced commits adultery.”<note>Some manuscripts omit “and whoever marries her who is divorced commits adultery”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 19:10">10</verse-number>The disciples<note>Some manuscripts have “His disciples”</note> said to him, “If this is the case of a man with his<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> wife, it would be better not to marry!” <verse-number id="Mt 19:11">11</verse-number>But he said to them, “Not everyone can accept this saying but <supplied>those</supplied> to whom it has been given. <verse-number id="Mt 19:12">12</verse-number>For there are eunuchs who were born as such from <supplied>their</supplied> mother’s womb, and there are eunuchs who were made eunuchs by people, and there are eunuchs who have made themselves <supplied>eunuchs</supplied><note>An understood repetition of the term from earlier in the verse</note> for the sake of the kingdom of heaven. The one who is able to accept <supplied>this</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> let him accept <supplied>it</supplied>.”<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Little Children Brought to Jesus</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 19:13">13</verse-number>Then children were brought to him so that he could lay his<note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> hands on them and pray, but the disciples rebuked them. <verse-number id="Mt 19:14">14</verse-number>But Jesus said, “Allow the children, and do not forbid them to come to me, <idiom-start/>for to such belongs<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for of such is”</note> the kingdom of heaven.” <verse-number id="Mt 19:15">15</verse-number>And he laid his<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> hands on them <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“laid”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> traveled on from there. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A Rich Young Man</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 19:16">16</verse-number>And behold, someone came up to him <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “Teacher, what good <supplied>thing</supplied> must I do so that I will have eternal life?” <verse-number id="Mt 19:17">17</verse-number>And he said to him, “Why are you asking me about <supplied>what is</supplied> good? There is one <supplied>who is</supplied> good. But if you want to enter into life, keep the commandments!” <verse-number id="Mt 19:18">18</verse-number>He said to him, “Which <supplied>ones</supplied>?” And Jesus said, “Do not commit murder, do not commit adultery, do not steal, do not give false testimony, <verse-number id="Mt 19:19">19</verse-number>honor your<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> father and your<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> mother, and love your neighbor as yourself.” <verse-number id="Mt 19:20">20</verse-number>The young man said to him, “All these I have observed. What do I still lack?” <verse-number id="Mt 19:21">21</verse-number>Jesus said to him, “If you want to be perfect, go, sell your possessions and give <supplied>the proceeds</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to the poor—and you will have treasure in heaven—and come, follow me.” <verse-number id="Mt 19:22">22</verse-number>But <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> the young man heard the statement, he went away sorrowful, because he was one who had many possessions. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 19:23">23</verse-number>And Jesus said to his disciples, “Truly I say to you that with difficulty a rich person will enter into the kingdom of heaven! <verse-number id="Mt 19:24">24</verse-number>And again I say to you, it is easier <supplied>for</supplied> a camel to go through the eye of a needle than a rich person into<note>Some manuscripts have “to enter into”</note> the kingdom of God.” <verse-number id="Mt 19:25">25</verse-number>So <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> the disciples heard <supplied>this</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> they were extremely amazed, saying, “Then who can be saved?” <verse-number id="Mt 19:26">26</verse-number>But Jesus looked at <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“looked at”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to them, “With human beings this is impossible, but with God all <supplied>things</supplied> <supplied>are</supplied> possible.” <verse-number id="Mt 19:27">27</verse-number>Then Peter answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to him, “Behold, we have left everything and followed you. What then will there be for us?” <verse-number id="Mt 19:28">28</verse-number>And Jesus said to them, “Truly I say to you that in the renewal <supplied>of the world</supplied>,<note>The words “of the world” are supplied as a clarification of “renewal”</note> when the Son of Man sits on his glorious throne, you who have followed me—you also will sit on twelve thrones judging the twelve tribes of Israel. <verse-number id="Mt 19:29">29</verse-number>And everyone who has left houses or brothers or sisters or father or mother or wife<note>Some manuscripts omit “or wife”</note> or children or fields on account of my name will receive a hundred times as much, and will inherit eternal life. <verse-number id="Mt 19:30">30</verse-number>But many <supplied>who are</supplied> first will be last, and the last first. </p>
		</chapter>