<chapter id="Mt 20">
			<pericope>The Parable of the Workers in the Vineyard</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 20:1">1</verse-number> “For the kingdom of heaven is like a man—the master of the house—who went out early in the morning to hire workers for his vineyard. <verse-number id="Mt 20:2">2</verse-number>And <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“coming to an agreement”) which is understood as temporal</note> coming to an agreement with the workers for a denarius per day, he sent them into his vineyard. <verse-number id="Mt 20:3">3</verse-number>And going out about the third hour, he saw others standing idle in the marketplace. <verse-number id="Mt 20:4">4</verse-number>And to those <supplied>people</supplied> he said, ‘You also go into the vineyard, and I will give you whatever is right.’ <verse-number id="Mt 20:5">5</verse-number>So they went. Going out<note>Some manuscripts have “And going out”</note> again about the sixth and ninth hour he did the same <supplied>thing</supplied>. <verse-number id="Mt 20:6">6</verse-number>And about the eleventh <supplied>hour</supplied> he went out <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went out”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> found others standing <supplied>there</supplied> and said to them, ‘Why are you standing here the whole day unemployed?’ <verse-number id="Mt 20:7">7</verse-number>They said to him, ‘Because no one hired us.’ He said to them, ‘You go also into the vineyard.’ <verse-number id="Mt 20:8">8</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“came”)</note> evening came, the owner of the vineyard said to his manager, ‘Call the workers and pay them their<note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> wages, beginning from the last up to the first.’ <verse-number id="Mt 20:9">9</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied> the ones <supplied>hired</supplied> about the eleventh hour came, they received a denarius apiece. <verse-number id="Mt 20:10">10</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“came”) which is understood as temporal</note> the first came, they thought that they would receive more, and they also received a denarius apiece. <verse-number id="Mt 20:11">11</verse-number>And <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“received”) which is understood as temporal</note> received <supplied>it</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> they began to complain<note>The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to complain”)</note> against the master of the house, <verse-number id="Mt 20:12">12</verse-number>saying, ‘These last <supplied>people</supplied> worked one hour and you made them equal to us who have endured the burden of the day and the burning heat!’ <verse-number id="Mt 20:13">13</verse-number>But he answered one of them <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, ‘Friend, I am not doing you wrong. Did you not come to an agreement with me for a denarius? <verse-number id="Mt 20:14">14</verse-number>Take <supplied>what is</supplied> yours and go! But I want to give to this last <supplied>person</supplied> <supplied>the same</supplied> as <supplied>I gave</supplied><note>The words “<supplied>I gave</supplied>” are an implied repetition from the verb earlier in the verse</note> to you also. <verse-number id="Mt 20:15">15</verse-number>Is it not<note>Some manuscripts have “Or <supplied>is it</supplied> not”</note> permitted for me to do whatever I want with <supplied>what is</supplied> mine? Or is your eye evil because I am generous?’ <verse-number id="Mt 20:16">16</verse-number>Thus the last will be first and the first last.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus Predicts His Death and Resurrection a Third Time</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 20:17">17</verse-number>And <supplied>as</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was going up”) which is understood as temporal</note> Jesus was going up to Jerusalem, he took the twelve disciples by themselves and said to them on the way, <verse-number id="Mt 20:18">18</verse-number>“Behold, we are going up to Jerusalem, and the Son of Man will be handed over to the chief priests and scribes, and they will condemn him to death, <verse-number id="Mt 20:19">19</verse-number>and will hand him over to the Gentiles to mock <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and flog <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and crucify <supplied>him</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and on the third day he will be raised.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A Request by the Mother of James and John</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 20:20">20</verse-number>Then the mother of the sons of Zebedee came up to him with her sons, <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the participle (“kneeling down”) has been translated as a finite verb in keeping with English style</note> kneeling down <supplied>she</supplied> asked<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the participle (“asked”) is translated as a finite verb because of English style</note> something from him. <verse-number id="Mt 20:21">21</verse-number>And he said to her, “What do you want?” She said to him, “Say that these two sons of mine may sit one at your right hand and one at your left in your kingdom.” <verse-number id="Mt 20:22">22</verse-number>But Jesus answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “You do not know what you are asking! Are you able to drink the cup that I am about to drink?” They said to him, “We are able.” <verse-number id="Mt 20:23">23</verse-number>He said to them, “You will indeed drink my cup, but to sit at my right hand and at my left is not mine<note>Some manuscripts have “this is not mine”</note> to grant, but <supplied>is</supplied> for those for whom it has been prepared by my Father.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 20:24">24</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> the ten heard <supplied>this</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> they were indignant concerning the two brothers. <verse-number id="Mt 20:25">25</verse-number>But Jesus called them to himself <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“called … to himself”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “You know that the rulers of the Gentiles lord it over them, and those in high positions exercise authority over them. <verse-number id="Mt 20:26">26</verse-number>It will not be like this among you! But whoever wants to become great among you must be your servant, <verse-number id="Mt 20:27">27</verse-number>and whoever wants to be most prominent among you must be your slave—<verse-number id="Mt 20:28">28</verse-number>just as the Son of Man did not come to be served, but to serve, and to give his life <supplied>as</supplied> a ransom for many.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Two Blind Men Healed at Jericho</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 20:29">29</verse-number>And <supplied>as</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“were going out”)</note> they were going out of Jericho, a large crowd followed him. <verse-number id="Mt 20:30">30</verse-number>And behold, <supplied>there were</supplied> two blind men sitting beside the road. <supplied>When they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> heard that Jesus was passing by, they called out, saying, “Lord, have mercy on us,<note>Some manuscripts have “Have mercy on us, Lord”</note> Son of David!” <verse-number id="Mt 20:31">31</verse-number>And the crowd rebuked them so that they would be quiet. But they called out all the more, saying, “Lord, have mercy on us,<note>Some manuscripts have “Have mercy on us, Lord”</note> Son of David!” <verse-number id="Mt 20:32">32</verse-number>And Jesus stopped,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the participle (“stopped”) is translated as a finite verb because of English style</note> called them, and said, “What do you want me to do for you?” <verse-number id="Mt 20:33">33</verse-number>They said to him, “Lord, that our eyes be opened!” <verse-number id="Mt 20:34">34</verse-number>And having compassion, Jesus touched their eyes, and immediately they received <supplied>their</supplied> sight and followed him. </p>
		</chapter>