<chapter id="Mt 21">
			<pericope>The Triumphal Entry</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 21:1">1</verse-number> And when they drew near to Jerusalem and came to Bethphage at the Mount of Olives, then Jesus sent two disciples, <verse-number id="Mt 21:2">2</verse-number>saying to them, “Go into the village before you, and right away you will find a donkey tied and a colt with her. Untie <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“untie”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> bring <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to me. <verse-number id="Mt 21:3">3</verse-number>And if anyone says anything to you, you will say, ‘The Lord <idiom-start/>needs them<idiom-end/>,’<note>Literally “has need of them”</note> and he will send them at once.” <verse-number id="Mt 21:4">4</verse-number>Now this took place so that what was spoken through the prophet would be fulfilled, saying, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Mt 21:5">5</verse-number>“Say to the daughter of Zion, </li1>
				<li2>‘Behold, your king is coming to you, </li2>
				<li1>humble and mounted on a donkey, </li1>
				<li2>and<note>Or “even”</note> on a colt, the foal of a pack animal.’ ”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Zec 9:9">Zech 9:9</cite></note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 21:6">6</verse-number>So the disciples went<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the participle (“went”) is translated as a finite verb because of English style</note> and did<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the participle (“did”) is translated as a finite verb because of English style</note> just as Jesus directed them, <verse-number id="Mt 21:7">7</verse-number><supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participles (“went” and “did” in the previous verse) have been translated as finite verbs</note> brought the donkey and the colt and put their<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> cloaks on them, and he sat on them. <verse-number id="Mt 21:8">8</verse-number>And a very large crowd spread their cloaks on the road, and others were cutting branches from the trees and spreading <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> on the road. <verse-number id="Mt 21:9">9</verse-number>And the crowds who went ahead of him and the ones who followed were shouting, saying, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Hosanna to the Son of David! </li1>
				<li1>Blessed <supplied>is</supplied> the one who comes in the name of the Lord!<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 118:25–26">Ps 118:25–26</cite></note> </li1>
				<li2>Hosanna in the highest <supplied>heaven</supplied>!”<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here “heaven” is understood</note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 21:10">10</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“entered”)</note> he entered into Jerusalem, the whole city was stirred up, saying, “Who is this?” <verse-number id="Mt 21:11">11</verse-number>And the crowds were saying, “This is the prophet Jesus from Nazareth of Galilee!” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Cleansing of the Temple</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 21:12">12</verse-number>And Jesus entered the temple <supplied>courts</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>courts</supplied>” is supplied to distinguish this area from the interior of the temple building itself</note> and drove out all those who were selling and buying in the temple, and overturned the tables of the money changers and the chairs of those who were selling doves. <verse-number id="Mt 21:13">13</verse-number>And he said to them, “It is written, ‘My house will be called a house of prayer,’<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 56:7">Isa 56:7</cite></note> but you have made it a cave of robbers!” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 21:14">14</verse-number>And the blind and the lame came up to him in the temple <supplied>courts</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>courts</supplied>” is supplied to distinguish this area from the interior of the temple building itself</note> and he healed them. <verse-number id="Mt 21:15">15</verse-number>But <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> the chief priests and the scribes saw the wonderful <supplied>things</supplied> that he did, and the children shouting in the temple <supplied>courts</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>courts</supplied>” is supplied to distinguish this area from the interior of the temple building itself</note> and saying, “Hosanna to the Son of David!” they were indignant. <verse-number id="Mt 21:16">16</verse-number>And they said to him, “Do you hear what these <supplied>children</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The word “<supplied>children</supplied>” is not in the Greek text but is implied</note> are saying?” So Jesus said to them, “Yes, have you never read, ‘Out of the mouths of children and nursing babies you have prepared for yourself praise’?”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 8:2">Ps 8:2</cite></note> <verse-number id="Mt 21:17">17</verse-number>And leaving them, he went outside of the city to Bethany and spent the night there. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A Barren Fig Tree Cursed</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 21:18">18</verse-number>Now early in the morning, <supplied>as he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was returning”) which is understood as temporal</note> was returning to the city, he was hungry. <verse-number id="Mt 21:19">19</verse-number>And seeing a single fig tree by the road, he went to it and found nothing on it except leaves only. And he said to it, “May there be no more fruit from you <idiom-start/>forever<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to the age”</note> and the fig tree withered at once. <verse-number id="Mt 21:20">20</verse-number>And <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> saw <supplied>it</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> the disciples were astonished, saying, “How did the fig tree wither at once?” <verse-number id="Mt 21:21">21</verse-number>And Jesus answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to them, “Truly I say to you, if you have faith and do not doubt, you will do not only <supplied>what was done to</supplied> the fig tree, but even if you say to this mountain, ‘Be lifted up and thrown into the sea,” it will happen! <verse-number id="Mt 21:22">22</verse-number>And whatever you ask in prayer, <supplied>if you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>if</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“believe”) which is understood as conditional</note> believe, you will receive.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus’ Authority Challenged</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 21:23">23</verse-number>And <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“arrived”)</note> he arrived at the temple, the chief priests and the elders of the people came up to him <supplied>while he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was teaching”) which is understood as temporal</note> was teaching, saying, “By what authority are you doing these <supplied>things</supplied>? And who gave you this authority?” <verse-number id="Mt 21:24">24</verse-number>And Jesus answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to them, “I also will ask you one question. If you tell <supplied>the answer</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to me, I also will tell you by what authority I am doing these <supplied>things</supplied>. <verse-number id="Mt 21:25">25</verse-number>From where was the baptism of John—from heaven or from men?” And they began to discuss<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to discuss”)</note> <supplied>this</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> among themselves, saying, “If we say ‘From heaven,’ he will say to us, ‘Why then did you not believe him?’ <verse-number id="Mt 21:26">26</verse-number>But if we say, ‘From men,’ we are afraid of the crowd, because they all look upon John as a prophet.” <verse-number id="Mt 21:27">27</verse-number>And they answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to Jesus, “We do not know.” And he said to them, “Neither will I tell you by what authority I am doing these <supplied>things</supplied>. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Parable of the Two Sons</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 21:28">28</verse-number>“Now what do you think? A man had two sons. <supplied>He</supplied> approached<note>Some manuscripts have “And he approached”</note> the first <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“approached”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, ‘Son, go work in the vineyard today.’ <verse-number id="Mt 21:29">29</verse-number>And he answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, ‘I do not want to!’ But later <supplied>he</supplied> changed his mind <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“changed his mind”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> went. <verse-number id="Mt 21:30">30</verse-number>And <supplied>he</supplied> approached the second<note>Some manuscripts have “the other”</note> <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“approached”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said the same <supplied>thing</supplied>. So he answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, ‘I <supplied>will</supplied>, sir,’ and he did not go. <verse-number id="Mt 21:31">31</verse-number>Which of the two did the will of <supplied>his</supplied><note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> father?” They said, “The first.” Jesus said to them, “Truly I say to you that the tax collectors and the prostitutes are going ahead of you into the kingdom of God! <verse-number id="Mt 21:32">32</verse-number>For John came to you in the way of righteousness and you did not believe him, but the tax collectors and the prostitutes did believe him. And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> you saw <supplied>it</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> you did not even change your minds later <supplied>so as</supplied> to believe in him. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Parable of the Tenant Farmers in the Vineyard</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 21:33">33</verse-number>“Listen to another parable: There was a man—a master of a house—who planted a vineyard, and put a fence <supplied>around</supplied> it, and dug a winepress in it, and built a watchtower, and leased it to tenant farmers, and went on a journey. <verse-number id="Mt 21:34">34</verse-number>And when the season of fruit drew near, he sent his slaves to the tenant farmers to collect his fruit. <verse-number id="Mt 21:35">35</verse-number>And the tenant farmers seized his slaves, <supplied>one of</supplied> whom they beat, and <supplied>one of</supplied> whom they killed, and <supplied>one of</supplied> whom they stoned. <verse-number id="Mt 21:36">36</verse-number>Again, he sent other slaves, more than the first <supplied>ones</supplied>, and they did the same <supplied>thing</supplied> to them. <verse-number id="Mt 21:37">37</verse-number>So finally he sent his son to them, saying, ‘They will respect my son.’ <verse-number id="Mt 21:38">38</verse-number>But <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> the tenant farmers saw the son, they said among themselves, ‘This is the heir. Come, let us kill him and have his inheritance!’ <verse-number id="Mt 21:39">39</verse-number>And they seized him <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“seized”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> threw <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> out of the vineyard and killed <supplied>him</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <verse-number id="Mt 21:40">40</verse-number>Now when the master of the vineyard arrives, what will he do to those tenant farmers?” <verse-number id="Mt 21:41">41</verse-number>They said to him, “He will destroy those evil <supplied>men</supplied> completely and lease the vineyard to other tenant farmers who will give him the fruits in their season.” <verse-number id="Mt 21:42">42</verse-number>Jesus said to them, “Have you never read in the scriptures, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>‘The stone which the builders rejected, </li1>
				<li2>this has become <idiom-start/>the cornerstone<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the head of the corner”</note> </li2>
				<li1>This came about from the Lord, </li1>
				<li2>and it is marvelous in our eyes’?<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 118:22–23">Ps 118:22–23</cite></note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 21:43">43</verse-number>For this <supplied>reason</supplied>, I tell you that the kingdom of God will be taken away from you and will be given to a people<note>Or “nation”</note> who produce its fruits. <verse-number id="Mt 21:44">44</verse-number>And the one who falls on this stone will be broken to pieces, and <supplied>the one</supplied> on whom it falls—it will crush him!” <verse-number id="Mt 21:45">45</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> the chief priests and the Pharisees heard his parables, they knew that he was speaking about them, <verse-number id="Mt 21:46">46</verse-number>and <supplied>although they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>although</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“wanted”) which is understood as concessive</note> wanted to arrest him, they were afraid of the crowds, because they looked upon him as a prophet. </p>
		</chapter>