<chapter id="Mt 22">
			<pericope>The Parable of the Wedding Celebration</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 22:1">1</verse-number> And continuing, Jesus spoke to them again in parables, saying, <verse-number id="Mt 22:2">2</verse-number>“The kingdom of heaven may be compared to a man—a king—who gave a wedding celebration for his son. <verse-number id="Mt 22:3">3</verse-number>And he sent his slaves to summon those who had been invited to the wedding celebration, and they did not want to come. <verse-number id="Mt 22:4">4</verse-number>Again he sent other slaves, saying, ‘Tell those who have been invited, “Behold, I have prepared my dinner; my oxen and fattened <supplied>cattle</supplied> have been slaughtered, and everything <supplied>is</supplied> ready. Come to the wedding celebration!” ’ <verse-number id="Mt 22:5">5</verse-number>But they paid no attention <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“paid no attention”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> went away—this one to his own field, that one to his business. <verse-number id="Mt 22:6">6</verse-number>And the others, seizing his slaves, mistreated <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and killed <supplied>them</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <verse-number id="Mt 22:7">7</verse-number>And the king was angry and sent his troops <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“sent”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> destroyed those murderers and burned their city. <verse-number id="Mt 22:8">8</verse-number>Then he said to his slaves, ‘The wedding celebration is ready, but those who had been invited were not worthy. <verse-number id="Mt 22:9">9</verse-number>Therefore, go out to the <supplied>places where</supplied> the roads exit the city and invite to the wedding celebration as many <supplied>people</supplied> as you find.’ <verse-number id="Mt 22:10">10</verse-number>And those slaves went out into the roads <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went out”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> gathered everyone whom they found, both evil and good, and the wedding celebration was filled <idiom-start/>with dinner guests<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “with those reclining at table”</note> <verse-number id="Mt 22:11">11</verse-number>But <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“came in”) which is understood as temporal</note> the king came in to see the <idiom-start/>dinner guests<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “ones reclining at table”</note> he saw a man there not dressed <supplied>in</supplied> wedding clothes. <verse-number id="Mt 22:12">12</verse-number>And he said to him, ‘Friend, how did you come in here, not having wedding clothes?’ But <idiom-start/>he could say nothing<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “he was silent”</note> <verse-number id="Mt 22:13">13</verse-number>Then the king said to the servants, ‘Tie him up <idiom-start/>hand and foot<idiom-end/><note>Literally “feet and hands”</note> <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“tie”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> throw him into the outer darkness. In that place there will be weeping and gnashing of teeth!’ <verse-number id="Mt 22:14">14</verse-number>For many are called but few <supplied>are</supplied> chosen.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Paying Taxes to Caesar</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 22:15">15</verse-number>Then the Pharisees went <idiom-start/>and consulted<idiom-end/><note>Literally “took counsel”</note> so that they could entrap him with a statement. <verse-number id="Mt 22:16">16</verse-number>And they sent their disciples to him with the Herodians, saying, “Teacher, we know that you are truthful and teach the way of God in truth, and <idiom-start/>you do not care what anyone thinks<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “it is not a care to you concerning anyone”</note> <idiom-start/>because you do not regard the opinion of people<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “because you do not look at the face of men”</note> <verse-number id="Mt 22:17">17</verse-number>Therefore tell us what you think. Is it permitted to pay taxes to Caesar or not?” <verse-number id="Mt 22:18">18</verse-number>But <supplied>because he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“knew”) which is understood as causal</note> knew their maliciousness, Jesus said, “Hypocrites! Why are you testing me? <verse-number id="Mt 22:19">19</verse-number>Show me the coin for the tax!” So they brought him a denarius. <verse-number id="Mt 22:20">20</verse-number>And he said to them, “Whose image and inscription <supplied>is</supplied> this?” <verse-number id="Mt 22:21">21</verse-number>They said to him, “Caesar’s.” Then he said to them, “Therefore give to Caesar the things of Caesar, and to God the things of God!” <verse-number id="Mt 22:22">22</verse-number>And <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> heard <supplied>this</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> they were astonished, and they left him <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“left”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> went away. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A Question About Marriage and the Resurrection</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 22:23">23</verse-number>On that day Sadducees—who say there is no resurrection—came up to him and asked him, <verse-number id="Mt 22:24">24</verse-number>saying, “Teacher, Moses said if someone dies without having children, his brother is to marry his wife and <idiom-start/>father<idiom-end/><note>Literally “raise up”</note> descendants for his brother. <verse-number id="Mt 22:25">25</verse-number>Now there were seven brothers with us. And the first died <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“getting married”) which is understood as temporal</note> getting married, and <supplied>because he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“have”) which is understood as causal</note> did not have descendants, he left his wife to his brother. <verse-number id="Mt 22:26">26</verse-number>So also the second and the third, up to the seventh. <verse-number id="Mt 22:27">27</verse-number>And last of all the woman died. <verse-number id="Mt 22:28">28</verse-number>In the resurrection, therefore, whose wife of the seven will she be? For they all had her <supplied>as wife</supplied>.”<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The words “<supplied>as wife</supplied>” are not in the Greek text but are implied</note> <verse-number id="Mt 22:29">29</verse-number>But Jesus answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to them, “You are mistaken, <supplied>because</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“know”) which is understood as causal</note> you do not know the scriptures or the power of God! <verse-number id="Mt 22:30">30</verse-number>For in the resurrection they neither marry nor are given in marriage, but are like angels of God<note>Some manuscripts omit “of God”</note> in heaven. <verse-number id="Mt 22:31">31</verse-number>Now concerning the resurrection of the dead, have you not read what was spoken to you by God, who said, <verse-number id="Mt 22:32">32</verse-number>“I am the God of Abraham and the God of Isaac and the God of Jacob”?<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ex 3:6">Exod 3:6</cite></note> He is not the God of the dead, but of the living!” <verse-number id="Mt 22:33">33</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> the crowds heard <supplied>this</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> they were amazed at his teaching. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Greatest Commandment</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 22:34">34</verse-number>Now <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> the Pharisees heard that he had silenced the Sadducees, they assembled at the same <supplied>place</supplied>.<note>Or “they assembled together”</note> <verse-number id="Mt 22:35">35</verse-number>And one of them, a legal expert, put a question to <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to test him: <verse-number id="Mt 22:36">36</verse-number>“Teacher, which commandment <supplied>is</supplied> greatest in the law?” <verse-number id="Mt 22:37">37</verse-number>And he said to him, “ ‘You shall love the Lord your God with all your heart and with all your soul and with all your mind.’<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Dt 6:5">Deut 6:5</cite></note> <verse-number id="Mt 22:38">38</verse-number>This is the greatest and first commandment. <verse-number id="Mt 22:39">39</verse-number>And the second <supplied>is</supplied> like it: ‘You shall love your neighbor as yourself.’<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Le 19:18">Lev 19:18</cite></note> <verse-number id="Mt 22:40">40</verse-number>On these two commandments depend all the law and the prophets.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>David’s Son and Lord</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 22:41">41</verse-number>Now <supplied>while</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“assembled”)</note> the Pharisees were assembled, Jesus asked them, <verse-number id="Mt 22:42">42</verse-number>saying, “What do you think about the Christ? Whose son is he?” They said to him, “David’s.” <verse-number id="Mt 22:43">43</verse-number>He said to them, “How then does David, by the Spirit, call him ‘Lord,’ saying, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Mt 22:44">44</verse-number>‘The Lord said to my Lord, </li1>
				<li2>“Sit at my right hand </li2>
				<li1>until I put your enemies </li1>
				<li2>under your feet” ’?<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 110:1">Ps 110:1</cite></note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 22:45">45</verse-number>If then David calls him ‘Lord,’ how is he his son?” <verse-number id="Mt 22:46">46</verse-number>And no one was able to answer him a word, nor did anyone dare from that day <supplied>on</supplied> to ask him any more <supplied>questions</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The word “<supplied>questions</supplied>” is not in the Greek text but is implied</note> </p>
		</chapter>