<chapter id="Mt 23">
			<pericope>Seven Woes Pronounced on the Scribes and Pharisees</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 23:1">1</verse-number> Then Jesus spoke to the crowds and to his disciples, <verse-number id="Mt 23:2">2</verse-number>saying, “The scribes and the Pharisees sit on the seat of Moses. <verse-number id="Mt 23:3">3</verse-number>Therefore do and observe everything that they tell you, but do not do as <idiom-start/>they do<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “their deeds”</note> for they tell <supplied>others to do something</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The words “<supplied>others to do something</supplied>” are not in the Greek text but are implied</note> and do not do <supplied>it themselves</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The words “<supplied>it themselves</supplied>” are not in the Greek text but are implied</note> <verse-number id="Mt 23:4">4</verse-number>And they tie up heavy burdens<note>Some manuscripts have “burdens that are heavy and hard to bear”</note> and put <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> on people’s shoulders, but <supplied>they</supplied> themselves are not willing with their finger to move them. <verse-number id="Mt 23:5">5</verse-number>And they do all their deeds in order to be seen by people, for they make their phylacteries broad and make their<note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> tassels long. <verse-number id="Mt 23:6">6</verse-number>And they love the place of honor at banquets and the best seats in the synagogues <verse-number id="Mt 23:7">7</verse-number>and the greetings in the marketplaces and to be called ‘Rabbi’ by people. <verse-number id="Mt 23:8">8</verse-number>But you are not to be called ‘Rabbi,’ because one is your teacher, and you are all brothers, <verse-number id="Mt 23:9">9</verse-number>And do not call <supplied>anyone</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> your father on earth, for one is your heavenly Father. <verse-number id="Mt 23:10">10</verse-number>And do not be called teachers, because one is your teacher, the Christ. <verse-number id="Mt 23:11">11</verse-number>And the greatest among you will be your servant. <verse-number id="Mt 23:12">12</verse-number>And whoever exalts himself will be humbled, and whoever humbles himself will be exalted. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 23:13">13</verse-number>“But woe to you, scribes and Pharisees—hypocrites!—because you shut the kingdom of heaven before people! For you do not enter, nor permit those wanting to go in<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the present tense has been translated as voluntative (“wanting to go in”)</note> to enter.<note>The most important Greek manuscripts omit v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Mt 23:14">14</cite>, “Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees—hypocrites!—because you devour widows’ houses and for show you pray long prayers! Therefore you will receive the greater condemnation.”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 23:15">15</verse-number>“Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees—hypocrites!—because you travel around the sea and the dry <supplied>land</supplied> to make one convert, and when he becomes <supplied>one</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> you make him twice as much a son of hell <supplied>as</supplied> you <supplied>are</supplied>! </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 23:16">16</verse-number>“Woe to you, blind guides, who say, ‘Whoever swears by the temple, it is nothing! But whoever swears by the gold of the temple is bound <supplied>by his oath</supplied>.’<note>The phrase “<supplied>by his oath</supplied>” is not in the Greek text but is implied</note> <verse-number id="Mt 23:17">17</verse-number>Fools and blind <supplied>people</supplied>! For which is greater, the gold or the temple that makes the gold holy? <verse-number id="Mt 23:18">18</verse-number>And, ‘Whoever swears by the altar, it is nothing! But whoever swears by the gift <supplied>that is</supplied> on it is bound <supplied>by his oath</supplied>.’<note>The phrase “<supplied>by his oath</supplied>” is not in the Greek text but is implied</note> <verse-number id="Mt 23:19">19</verse-number>Blind <supplied>people</supplied>! For which <supplied>is</supplied> greater, the gift or the altar that makes the gift holy? <verse-number id="Mt 23:20">20</verse-number>Therefore the one who swears by the altar swears by it and by everything <supplied>that is</supplied> on it. <verse-number id="Mt 23:21">21</verse-number>And the one who swears by the temple swears by it and by the one who dwells <supplied>in</supplied> it. <verse-number id="Mt 23:22">22</verse-number>And the one who swears by heaven swears by the throne of God and by the one who sits on it. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 23:23">23</verse-number>“Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees—hypocrites!—because you pay a tenth of mint and dill and cumin, and neglect the more important <supplied>matters</supplied> of the law—justice and mercy and faithfulness! It was necessary<note>Some manuscripts have “But it was necessary”</note> to do these <supplied>things</supplied> <idiom-start/>while not neglecting those<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “and those not to neglect”</note> <verse-number id="Mt 23:24">24</verse-number>Blind guides who filter out a gnat and swallow a camel! </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 23:25">25</verse-number>“Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees—hypocrites!—because you cleanse the outside of the cup and the dish, but inside they are full of greed and self-indulgence! <verse-number id="Mt 23:26">26</verse-number>Blind Pharisee! First clean the inside of the cup and the dish,<note>Some manuscripts omit “and the dish”</note> so that the outside of it may become clean also. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 23:27">27</verse-number>“Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees—hypocrites!—because you are like whitewashed tombs which on the outside appear beautiful, but on the inside are full of the bones of the dead and of everything unclean! <verse-number id="Mt 23:28">28</verse-number>In the <supplied>same</supplied> way, on the outside you also appear righteous to people, but inside you are full of hypocrisy and lawlessness. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 23:29">29</verse-number>“Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees—hypocrites!—because you build the tombs of the prophets and decorate the graves of the righteous, <verse-number id="Mt 23:30">30</verse-number>and you say, ‘If we had lived in the days of our fathers, we would not have been partners with them in the blood of the prophets!’ <verse-number id="Mt 23:31">31</verse-number>Thus you testify against yourselves that you are descendants of those who murdered the prophets! <verse-number id="Mt 23:32">32</verse-number>And you—fill up the measure of your fathers! <verse-number id="Mt 23:33">33</verse-number>Serpents! Offspring of vipers! How will you escape from the condemnation to hell? <verse-number id="Mt 23:34">34</verse-number>For this <supplied>reason</supplied>, behold, I am sending to you prophets and wise men and scribes. <supplied>Some</supplied> of them you will kill and crucify, and some of them you will flog in your synagogues and will pursue from town to town, <verse-number id="Mt 23:35">35</verse-number>so that upon you will come all the righteous blood shed on the earth from the blood of righteous Abel up to the blood of Zechariah son of Barachiah, whom you murdered between the temple and the altar. <verse-number id="Mt 23:36">36</verse-number>Truly I say to you, all these <supplied>things</supplied> will come upon this generation! </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Lament over Jerusalem</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 23:37">37</verse-number>“Jerusalem, Jerusalem, who kills the prophets and stones those who are sent to her! How many times I wanted to gather your children together <idiom-start/>the way<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the manner in which”</note> a hen gathers her young together under <supplied>her</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> wings, and you were not willing! <verse-number id="Mt 23:38">38</verse-number>Behold, your house has been left to you desolate! <verse-number id="Mt 23:39">39</verse-number>For I tell you, you will never see me from now <supplied>on</supplied> until you say, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>‘Blessed <supplied>is</supplied> the one who comes in the name of the Lord!’ ”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 118:26">Ps 118:26</cite></note> </li1>
			</ul>
		</chapter>