<chapter id="Mt 26">
			<pericope>The Chief Priests and Elders Plot to Kill Jesus</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 26:1">1</verse-number> And it happened that when Jesus had finished all these sayings, he said to his disciples, <verse-number id="Mt 26:2">2</verse-number>“You know that after two days the Passover takes place, and the Son of Man will be handed over<note>Or “will be delivered up”</note> in order to be crucified.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 26:3">3</verse-number>Then the chief priests and the elders of the people assembled in the palace of the high priest, who was named Caiaphas, <verse-number id="Mt 26:4">4</verse-number>and plotted in order that they could arrest Jesus by stealth and kill <supplied>him</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <verse-number id="Mt 26:5">5</verse-number>But they were saying, “Not during the feast, so that there will not be an uproar among the people.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus’ Anointing at Bethany</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 26:6">6</verse-number>Now <supplied>while</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was”)</note> Jesus was at Bethany in the house of Simon the leper, <verse-number id="Mt 26:7">7</verse-number>a woman came up to him holding an alabaster flask of very expensive perfumed oil, and poured <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> out on his head <supplied>while he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was reclining at table”)</note> was reclining at table. <verse-number id="Mt 26:8">8</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> the disciples saw <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> they were indignant, saying, “<idiom-start/>Why<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for what” <supplied>reason</supplied></note> this waste? <verse-number id="Mt 26:9">9</verse-number>For this could have been sold for a large sum and given to the poor!” <verse-number id="Mt 26:10">10</verse-number>But Jesus, knowing <supplied>this</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> said to them, “Why do you cause trouble for the woman? For she has done a good deed for me. <verse-number id="Mt 26:11">11</verse-number>For the poor you always have with you, but you do not always have me. <verse-number id="Mt 26:12">12</verse-number>For <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“poured”) which is understood as temporal</note> this woman poured this ointment on my body, she did <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> in order to prepare me for burial. <verse-number id="Mt 26:13">13</verse-number>Truly I say to you, wherever this gospel is proclaimed in the whole world, what this woman has done will also be told in memory of her.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Judas Arranges to Betray Jesus</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 26:14">14</verse-number>Then one of the twelve, the one named Judas Iscariot, went to the chief priests <verse-number id="Mt 26:15">15</verse-number><supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the participle in the previous verse (“went”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “What are you willing to give me if I in turn deliver him to you?” So they set out for him thirty silver coins. <verse-number id="Mt 26:16">16</verse-number>And from that time on, he began seeking a favorable opportunity in order that he could betray him. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus’ Final Passover with the Disciples</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 26:17">17</verse-number>Now on the first <supplied>day</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the word “<supplied>day</supplied>” is not in the Greek text but is implied</note> of the feast of Unleavened Bread the disciples came up to Jesus, saying, “Where do you want us to prepare for you to eat the Passover?” <verse-number id="Mt 26:18">18</verse-number>And he said, “Go into the city to a certain man and tell him, ‘The Teacher says, “My time is near. I am celebrating the Passover with you with my disciples.” ’ <verse-number id="Mt 26:19">19</verse-number>And the disciples did as Jesus directed them, and they prepared the Passover. <verse-number id="Mt 26:20">20</verse-number>And <supplied>when it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was”)</note> was evening, he was reclining at table with the twelve disciples.<note>Some manuscripts omit “disciples”</note> <verse-number id="Mt 26:21">21</verse-number>And <supplied>while</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“were eating”)</note> they were eating he said, “Truly I say to you, that one of you will betray me.” <verse-number id="Mt 26:22">22</verse-number>And greatly distressed, each one began to say to him, “<idiom-start/>Surely I am not he, am I<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “surely I am not”; the negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here, indicated in the translation by “am I”</note> Lord?” <verse-number id="Mt 26:23">23</verse-number>And he answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “The one who dips his<note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> hand in the bowl with me—this one will betray me. <verse-number id="Mt 26:24">24</verse-number>The Son of Man is going just as it is written about him, but woe to that man by whom the Son of Man is betrayed! It would be better for him if that man had not been born.” <verse-number id="Mt 26:25">25</verse-number>And Judas, the one who was betraying him, answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “<idiom-start/>Surely I am not he, am I<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “surely I am not”; the negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here, indicated in the translation by “am I”</note> Rabbi?” He said to him, “You have said <supplied>it</supplied>.”<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Lord’s Supper</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 26:26">26</verse-number>Now <supplied>while</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“were eating”)</note> they were eating Jesus took bread and, <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“giving thanks”) which is understood as temporal</note> giving thanks, he broke <supplied>it</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and giving <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to the disciples, he said, “Take, eat, this is my body.” <verse-number id="Mt 26:27">27</verse-number>And <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“taking”) which is understood as temporal</note> taking the cup and giving thanks he gave <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to them, saying, “Drink from it, all of you, <verse-number id="Mt 26:28">28</verse-number>for this is my blood of the covenant which is poured out for many for the forgiveness of sins. <verse-number id="Mt 26:29">29</verse-number>But I tell you, from now <supplied>on</supplied> I will never drink of this fruit of the vine until that day when I drink it new with you in the kingdom of my Father.” <verse-number id="Mt 26:30">30</verse-number>And <supplied>after they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had sung the hymn”) which is understood as temporal</note> had sung the hymn, they went out to the Mount of Olives. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus Predicts Peter’s Denial</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 26:31">31</verse-number>Then Jesus said to them, “You will all fall away because of me during this night, for it is written, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>‘I will strike the shepherd </li1>
				<li2>and the sheep of the flock will be scattered.’<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Zec 13:7">Zech 13:7</cite></note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 26:32">32</verse-number>But after I am raised, I will go ahead of you into Galilee.” <verse-number id="Mt 26:33">33</verse-number>But Peter answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to him, “If they all fall away because of you, I will never fall away!” <verse-number id="Mt 26:34">34</verse-number>Jesus said to him, “Truly I say to you that during this night, before the rooster crows, you will deny me three times!” <verse-number id="Mt 26:35">35</verse-number>Peter said to him, “Even if it is necessary for me to die with you, I will never deny you!” And all the disciples said the same <supplied>thing</supplied>. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Prayer in Gethsemane</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 26:36">36</verse-number>Then Jesus went with them to a place called Gethsemane, and he said to the disciples, “Sit here while I go over there <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“go”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> pray.” <verse-number id="Mt 26:37">37</verse-number>And taking along Peter and the two sons of Zebedee, he began to be distressed and troubled. <verse-number id="Mt 26:38">38</verse-number>Then he said to them, “My soul is deeply grieved, to the point of death. Remain here and stay awake with me.” <verse-number id="Mt 26:39">39</verse-number>And going forward a little he fell down on his face, praying and saying, “My Father, if it is possible, let this cup pass from me. Nevertheless, not as I will, but as you <supplied>will</supplied>.”<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the verb “<supplied>will</supplied>” is an understood repetition of the verb earlier in this verse</note> <verse-number id="Mt 26:40">40</verse-number>And he came to the disciples and found them sleeping, and he said to Peter, “So, were you not able to stay awake with me one hour? <verse-number id="Mt 26:41">41</verse-number>Stay awake and pray that you will not enter into temptation. The spirit <supplied>is</supplied> willing, but the flesh <supplied>is</supplied> weak!” <verse-number id="Mt 26:42">42</verse-number>Again for the second time he went away <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went away”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> prayed, saying, “My Father, if this cannot pass unless I drink it, your will must be done.” <verse-number id="Mt 26:43">43</verse-number>And he came again <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came again”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> found them sleeping, <idiom-start/>for they could not keep their eyes open<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “for their eyes were weighed down”</note> <verse-number id="Mt 26:44">44</verse-number>And leaving them again, he went away <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went away”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> prayed for the third <supplied>time</supplied>, saying the same thing again. <verse-number id="Mt 26:45">45</verse-number>Then he came to the disciples and said to them, “Are you still sleeping and resting? Behold, the hour is near, and the Son of Man is being betrayed into the hands of sinners. <verse-number id="Mt 26:46">46</verse-number>Get up, let us go! Behold, the one who is betraying me is approaching!” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Betrayal and Arrest of Jesus</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 26:47">47</verse-number>And <supplied>while</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was … speaking”)</note> he was still speaking, behold, Judas—one of the twelve—arrived, and with him a large crowd with swords and clubs, from the chief priests and elders of the people. <verse-number id="Mt 26:48">48</verse-number>Now the one who was betraying him had given them a sign, saying, “<supplied>The one</supplied> whom I kiss—he is <supplied>the one</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the predicate nominative (“<supplied>the one</supplied>”) is implied</note> Arrest him!” <verse-number id="Mt 26:49">49</verse-number>And he came up to Jesus immediately <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “Greetings, Rabbi,” and kissed him. <verse-number id="Mt 26:50">50</verse-number>And Jesus said to him, “Friend, <supplied>do that</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The words “<supplied>do that</supplied>” are not in the Greek text but are implied</note> for which you have come.”<note>The meaning of this phrase is disputed: (1) some take it as a declarative (as in the translation); (2) others understand it as some form of a question, often with supplied words: (a) “Friend, <supplied>are you misusing the kiss</supplied> for that <supplied>purpose</supplied> for which you are here?” (b) “Friend, in connection with that for which you have appeared <supplied>do you kiss me</supplied>?” (c) “Friend, are you here for this purpose?” (d) “Friend, what are you here for?”; this last option, though often suggested, is doubtful because of lack of evidence for the relative pronoun used as an interrogative in direct questions</note> Then they came up <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> laid hands on Jesus and arrested him. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 26:51">51</verse-number>And behold, one of those with Jesus extended his<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> hand <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“extended”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> drew his sword, and striking the slave of the high priest, cut off his ear. <verse-number id="Mt 26:52">52</verse-number>Then Jesus said to him, “Put your sword back into its place! For all who take up the sword will die by the sword. <verse-number id="Mt 26:53">53</verse-number>Or do you think that I cannot call upon my Father, and he would put at my disposal at once more than twelve legions of angels? <verse-number id="Mt 26:54">54</verse-number>How then would the scriptures be fulfilled that it must happen in this way?” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 26:55">55</verse-number>At that time Jesus said to the crowds, “Have you come out with swords and clubs, as against a robber, to arrest me? Every day in the temple <supplied>courts</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>courts</supplied>” is supplied to distinguish this area from the interior of the temple building itself</note> I sat teaching, and you did not arrest me! <verse-number id="Mt 26:56">56</verse-number>But all this has happened in order that the scriptures of the prophets would be fulfilled.” Then the disciples all abandoned him <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“abandoned”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> fled. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus Before the Sanhedrin</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 26:57">57</verse-number>Now those who had arrested Jesus led <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> away to Caiaphas the high priest, where the scribes and the elders had gathered. <verse-number id="Mt 26:58">58</verse-number>But Peter was following him from a distance, as far as the courtyard of the high priest. And he went inside <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> was sitting with the officers to see the outcome. <verse-number id="Mt 26:59">59</verse-number>Now the chief priests and the whole Sanhedrin were looking for false testimony against Jesus in order that they could put him to death. <verse-number id="Mt 26:60">60</verse-number>And they did not find <supplied>it</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <supplied>although</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>although</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“came forward”) which is understood as concessive</note> many false witnesses came forward. And finally two came forward <verse-number id="Mt 26:61">61</verse-number><supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the participle in the previous verse (“came forward”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “This man said, ‘I am able to destroy the temple of God and rebuild <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> within three days.’ ” <verse-number id="Mt 26:62">62</verse-number>And the high priest stood up <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“stood up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to him, “Do you reply nothing? What are these <supplied>people</supplied> testifying against you?” <verse-number id="Mt 26:63">63</verse-number>But Jesus was silent. And the high priest said to him, “I put you under oath by the living God, that you tell us if you are the Christ, the Son of God!” <verse-number id="Mt 26:64">64</verse-number>Jesus said to him, “You have said <supplied>it</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> But I tell you, from now <supplied>on</supplied> you will see the Son of Man sitting at the right hand of the Power<note>An indirect way of referring to God</note> and coming on the clouds of heaven.” <verse-number id="Mt 26:65">65</verse-number>Then the high priest tore his robes, saying, “He has blasphemed! What further need do we have of witnesses? Behold, you have just now heard the blasphemy! <verse-number id="Mt 26:66">66</verse-number>What do you think?” And they answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “<idiom-start/>He deserves death<idiom-end/>!”<note>Literally “he is deserving of death”</note> <verse-number id="Mt 26:67">67</verse-number>Then they spat in his face and struck him with their fists, and they slapped <supplied>him</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <verse-number id="Mt 26:68">68</verse-number>saying, “Prophesy for us, <supplied>you</supplied> Christ! Who is it who hit you?” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Peter Denies Jesus Three Times</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 26:69">69</verse-number>Now Peter was sitting outside in the courtyard, and a female slave came up to him <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “You also were with Jesus the Galilean.” <verse-number id="Mt 26:70">70</verse-number>But he denied <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> in the presence of <supplied>them</supplied> all, saying, “I do not know what you mean!” <verse-number id="Mt 26:71">71</verse-number>And <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“went out”) which is understood as temporal</note> went out to the gateway, another <supplied>female slave</supplied><note>The words “<supplied>female slave</supplied>” are not in the Greek text but are implied by the feminine singular form</note> saw him and said to those <supplied>who were</supplied> there, “This man was with Jesus the Nazarene.” <verse-number id="Mt 26:72">72</verse-number>And again he denied <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> with an oath, “I do not know the man!” <verse-number id="Mt 26:73">73</verse-number>And after a little <supplied>while</supplied> those who were standing there came up <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to Peter, “You really are <supplied>one</supplied> of them also, because even your accent <idiom-start/>reveals who you are<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “makes you evident”</note> <verse-number id="Mt 26:74">74</verse-number>Then he began to curse and to swear with an oath, “I do not know the man!” And immediately a rooster crowed. <verse-number id="Mt 26:75">75</verse-number>And Peter remembered the statement Jesus had said, “Before the rooster crows, you will deny me three times,” and he went outside <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> wept bitterly. </p>
		</chapter>