<chapter id="Mt 27">
			<pericope>Jesus Taken to Pilate</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 27:1">1</verse-number> Now <supplied>when it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was”)</note> was early morning, all the chief priests and the elders of the people took counsel against Jesus in order to put him to death. <verse-number id="Mt 27:2">2</verse-number>And <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“tying”) which is understood as temporal</note> tying him up, they led <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> away and handed <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> over to Pilate the governor. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Suicide of Judas Iscariot</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 27:3">3</verse-number>Then <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> Judas, the one who had betrayed him, saw that he had been condemned, he regretted <supplied>what he had done</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“regretted”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> returned the thirty silver coins to the chief priests and elders, <verse-number id="Mt 27:4">4</verse-number>saying, “I have sinned <supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“betraying”) which is understood as means</note> betraying innocent blood!” But they said, “What <supplied>is that</supplied> to us? You see to <supplied>it</supplied>!”<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <verse-number id="Mt 27:5">5</verse-number>And throwing the silver coins into the temple he departed. And he went away <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went away”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> hanged himself. <verse-number id="Mt 27:6">6</verse-number>But the chief priests took the silver coins <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“took”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “It is not permitted to put them into the temple treasury, because it is <idiom-start/>blood money<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “the price of blood”</note> <verse-number id="Mt 27:7">7</verse-number>And <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“taking”) which is understood as temporal</note> taking counsel, they purchased <idiom-start/>with<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for”</note> them the Potter’s Field, for a burial place for strangers. <verse-number id="Mt 27:8">8</verse-number>(For this reason that field has been called the Field of Blood until today.) <verse-number id="Mt 27:9">9</verse-number>Then what was spoken by the prophet Jeremiah was fulfilled, who said, “And they took the thirty silver coins, the price of the one who had been priced, <supplied>on</supplied> whom a price had been set by the sons of Israel, <verse-number id="Mt 27:10">10</verse-number>and they gave them for the potter’s field, just as the Lord directed me.”<note>A quotation from various passages in Jeremiah including <cite title="BibleLEB2:Je 18:2–6">18:2–6</cite>; <cite title="BibleLEB2:Je 19:1–13">19:1–13</cite>; <cite title="BibleLEB2:Je 32:6–15">32:6–15</cite>; see also <cite title="BibleLEB2: Zec 11:12–13">Zech 11:12–13</cite></note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus Before Pilate</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 27:11">11</verse-number>So Jesus stood before the governor, and the governor asked him, saying, “Are you the king of the Jews?” And Jesus said, “You say <supplied>so</supplied>.” <verse-number id="Mt 27:12">12</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>when he was being accused<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the him being accused”</note> by the chief priests and elders he answered nothing. <verse-number id="Mt 27:13">13</verse-number>Then Pilate said to him, “Do you not hear how many <supplied>things</supplied> they are testifying against you?” <verse-number id="Mt 27:14">14</verse-number>And he did not reply to him, not even with reference to one statement, so that the governor was very astonished. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Pilate Releases Barabbas</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 27:15">15</verse-number>Now at each feast, the governor was accustomed to release one prisoner to the crowd—the one whom they wanted. <verse-number id="Mt 27:16">16</verse-number>And at that time they had a notorious prisoner named Jesus<note>Although many manuscripts omit “Jesus” here, it is so hard to explain why a scribe would have added it that the reading is probably original</note> Barabbas.<note>“Barabbas” means “son of the father” in Aramaic</note> <verse-number id="Mt 27:17">17</verse-number>So <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“had assembled”)</note> they had assembled, Pilate said to them, “Whom do you want me to release for you—Jesus<note>Although many manuscripts omit “Jesus” here, it is so hard to explain why a scribe would have added it that the reading is probably original</note> Barabbas or Jesus who is called Christ?” <verse-number id="Mt 27:18">18</verse-number>(For he knew that they had handed him over because of envy. <verse-number id="Mt 27:19">19</verse-number>And <supplied>while</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was sitting”)</note> he was sitting on the judgment seat, his wife sent <supplied>a message</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to him, saying, “<idiom-start/>Have nothing to do with that righteous man<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “nothing to you and to that righteous man”</note> for I have suffered much as a result of a dream today because of him.”) <verse-number id="Mt 27:20">20</verse-number>But the chief priests and the elders persuaded the crowds that they should ask for Barabbas and put Jesus to death. <verse-number id="Mt 27:21">21</verse-number>So the governor answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to them, “Which of the two do you want me to release for you?” And they said, “Barabbas!” <verse-number id="Mt 27:22">22</verse-number>Pilate said to them, “What then should I do <supplied>with</supplied> Jesus, the one who is called Christ?” They all said, “Let him be crucified!” <verse-number id="Mt 27:23">23</verse-number>And he said, “Why? What wrong has he done?” But they began to shout<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to shout”)</note> even louder, saying, “Let him be crucified!” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 27:24">24</verse-number>So Pilate, <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> saw that he was accomplishing nothing, but instead an uproar was developing, took water <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“took”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> washed his<note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> hands before the crowd, saying, “I am innocent of the blood of this man. You see to <supplied>it</supplied>!”<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <verse-number id="Mt 27:25">25</verse-number>And all the people answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “His blood <supplied>be</supplied> on us and on our children!” <verse-number id="Mt 27:26">26</verse-number>Then he released Barabbas for them, but <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“flogged”) which is understood as temporal</note> he had Jesus flogged, he handed <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> over so that he could be crucified. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus Is Mocked</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 27:27">27</verse-number>Then the soldiers of the governor took Jesus into the governor’s residence <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“took”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> gathered the whole cohort to him. <verse-number id="Mt 27:28">28</verse-number>And they stripped him <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“stripped”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> put a scarlet military cloak around him, <verse-number id="Mt 27:29">29</verse-number>and weaving a crown of thorns, they put <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> on his head, and <supplied>put</supplied><note>This is an understood repetition of the verb from earlier in the verse</note> a reed in his right hand. And kneeling down before him, they mocked him, saying, “Hail, king of the Jews!” <verse-number id="Mt 27:30">30</verse-number>And they spat on him <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“spat”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> took the reed and repeatedly struck<note>The imperfect tense has been translated as iterative here (“repeatedly struck”)</note> <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> on his head. <verse-number id="Mt 27:31">31</verse-number>And when they had mocked him, they stripped him of the military cloak and put his <supplied>own</supplied> clothes on him, and led him away in order to crucify <supplied>him</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus Is Crucified</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 27:32">32</verse-number>And <supplied>as they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“were going out”) which is understood as temporal</note> were going out, they found a man of Cyrene <idiom-start/>named<idiom-end/><note>Literally “by name”</note> Simon. They forced this man to carry his cross. <verse-number id="Mt 27:33">33</verse-number>And <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“came”) which is understood as temporal</note> came to a place called <i>Golgotha</i> (which <idiom-start/>means Place of a Skull<idiom-end/>),<note>Literally “is called Place of a Skull”</note> <verse-number id="Mt 27:34">34</verse-number>they gave him wine mixed with gall to drink, and <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“tasted”) which is understood as temporal</note> tasted <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> he did not want to drink <supplied>it</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <verse-number id="Mt 27:35">35</verse-number>And <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had crucified”) which is understood as temporal</note> had crucified him, they divided his clothes among themselves<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “among themselves” reflects the middle voice of the verb “divided”</note> <supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“casting”) which is understood as means</note> casting lots. <verse-number id="Mt 27:36">36</verse-number>And they sat down <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“sat down”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> were watching over him there. <verse-number id="Mt 27:37">37</verse-number>And they put above his head the charge against him <idiom-start/>in writing<idiom-end/>:<note>Literally “written”</note> “This is Jesus, the king of the Jews.” <verse-number id="Mt 27:38">38</verse-number>Then two robbers were crucified with him, one on <supplied>his</supplied> right and one on <supplied>his</supplied> left. <verse-number id="Mt 27:39">39</verse-number>And those who passed by reviled him, shaking their heads <verse-number id="Mt 27:40">40</verse-number>and saying, “The one who would destroy the temple and rebuild <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> in three days, save yourself! If you are the Son of God, come down from the cross!” <verse-number id="Mt 27:41">41</verse-number>In the same way also the chief priests, along with the scribes and elders, were mocking <supplied>him</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> saying, <verse-number id="Mt 27:42">42</verse-number>“He saved others; he is not able to save himself! He is the king of Israel! Let him come down now from the cross, and we will believe in him! <verse-number id="Mt 27:43">43</verse-number>He trusts in God; let him deliver him now if he wants to,<note>Or “let him deliver <supplied>him</supplied> now if he wants him”</note> because he said, ‘I am the Son of God’!” <verse-number id="Mt 27:44">44</verse-number>And in the same <supplied>way</supplied> even the robbers who were crucified with him were reviling him. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus Dies on the Cross</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 27:45">45</verse-number>Now from the sixth hour, darkness came over all the land until the ninth hour. <verse-number id="Mt 27:46">46</verse-number>And about the ninth hour Jesus cried out with a loud voice, saying, “<i>Eli, Eli, lema sabachthani?</i>” (that is, “My God, my God, why have you forsaken me?”)<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 22:1">Ps 22:1</cite></note> <verse-number id="Mt 27:47">47</verse-number>And some of those who were standing there, <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> heard <supplied>it</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> said, “This man is summoning Elijah!” <verse-number id="Mt 27:48">48</verse-number>And immediately one of them ran and took a sponge and filled <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> with sour wine and put <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> on a reed <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participles (“ran … took … filled … put”) have been translated as finite verbs</note> gave <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to him to drink. <verse-number id="Mt 27:49">49</verse-number>But the others said, “Leave <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> alone! let us see if Elijah is coming to save him.” <verse-number id="Mt 27:50">50</verse-number>And Jesus cried out again with a loud voice <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“cried out”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> gave up his<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> spirit. <verse-number id="Mt 27:51">51</verse-number>And behold, the curtain of the temple was torn in two from top to bottom, and the earth shook and the rocks were split. <verse-number id="Mt 27:52">52</verse-number>And the tombs were opened, and many bodies of the saints who had fallen asleep were raised, <verse-number id="Mt 27:53">53</verse-number>and coming out of the tombs after his resurrection, they went into the holy city and appeared to many. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 27:54">54</verse-number>Now the centurion and those with him who were guarding Jesus, <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> saw the earthquake and the things that took place, were extremely frightened, saying, “Truly this man was God’s Son!” <verse-number id="Mt 27:55">55</verse-number>And there were many women there, observing from a distance, who had followed Jesus from Galilee, serving him, <verse-number id="Mt 27:56">56</verse-number>among whom were Mary Magdalene, and Mary the mother of James and Joseph, and the mother of the sons of Zebedee. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus Is Buried</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 27:57">57</verse-number>Now <supplied>when it</supplied> was evening, a rich man from Arimathea named Joseph came, who also was a disciple of Jesus himself. <verse-number id="Mt 27:58">58</verse-number>This man approached Pilate <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“approached”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> asked for the body of Jesus. Then Pilate ordered <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to be given <supplied>to him</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The words “<supplied>to him</supplied>” are not in the Greek text but are implied</note> <verse-number id="Mt 27:59">59</verse-number>And Joseph took the body <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“took”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> wrapped it in a clean linen cloth, <verse-number id="Mt 27:60">60</verse-number>and placed it in his <supplied>own</supplied> new tomb that he had cut in the rock. And he rolled a large stone to the entrance of the tomb <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“rolled”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> went away. <verse-number id="Mt 27:61">61</verse-number>Now Mary Magdalene and the other Mary were there, sitting opposite the tomb. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Tomb Is Sealed and Guarded</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 27:62">62</verse-number>Now <supplied>on</supplied> the next day, which is after the day of preparation, the chief priests and the Pharisees assembled before Pilate, <verse-number id="Mt 27:63">63</verse-number>saying, “Sir, we remember that <supplied>while</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“alive”) which is understood as temporal</note> that deceiver was still alive he said, ‘After three days I will rise.’ <verse-number id="Mt 27:64">64</verse-number>Therefore give orders that the tomb be made secure until the third day, lest his disciples come <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“come”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> steal him and tell the people, ‘He has been raised from the dead,’ and the last deception will be worse than the first.” <verse-number id="Mt 27:65">65</verse-number>Pilate said to them, “You have a guard of soldiers. Go, make <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> as secure as you know how.” <verse-number id="Mt 27:66">66</verse-number>So they went with the guard of soldiers <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> made the tomb secure <supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“sealing”) which is understood as means</note> sealing the stone. </p>
		</chapter>