<chapter id="Mt 28">
			<pericope>Jesus Is Raised</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 28:1">1</verse-number> Now after the Sabbath, at the dawning on the first <supplied>day</supplied> of the week, Mary Magdalene and the other Mary came to view the tomb. <verse-number id="Mt 28:2">2</verse-number>And behold, there was a great earthquake, for an angel of the Lord descended from heaven and came up <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participles (“descended” and “came up”) have been translated as finite verbs</note> rolled away the stone and sat down<note>Or “was sitting”; here “sat down” reflects an ingressive nuance (beginning of a process or entry into a state) in the translation of the imperfect verb</note> on it. <verse-number id="Mt 28:3">3</verse-number>Now his appearance was like lightning and his clothing white as snow. <verse-number id="Mt 28:4">4</verse-number>And the guards trembled from the fear of him and became like dead men. <verse-number id="Mt 28:5">5</verse-number>But the angel answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to the women, “Do not be afraid, for I know that you are looking for Jesus, who was crucified. <verse-number id="Mt 28:6">6</verse-number>He is not here, for he has been raised, just as he said. Come, see the place where he was lying. <verse-number id="Mt 28:7">7</verse-number>And go quickly, tell his disciples, ‘He has been raised from the dead, and behold, he is going ahead of you into Galilee. You will see him there.’ Behold, I have told you.” <verse-number id="Mt 28:8">8</verse-number>And they departed quickly from the tomb with fear and great joy, <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“departed”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> ran to tell his disciples. <verse-number id="Mt 28:9">9</verse-number>And behold, Jesus met them, saying, “Greetings!” And they came up <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> took hold of his feet and worshiped him. <verse-number id="Mt 28:10">10</verse-number>Then Jesus said to them, “Do not be afraid! Go tell my brothers that they should go to Galilee, and there they will see me.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Guards Report the Body Stolen</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 28:11">11</verse-number>And <supplied>while</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“were going”)</note> they were going, behold, some of the guard of soldiers went into the city <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> reported to the chief priests everything that had happened. <verse-number id="Mt 28:12">12</verse-number>And <supplied>after they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had assembled”) which is understood as temporal</note> had assembled with the elders and had taken counsel, they gave a rather large sum of money to the soldiers, <verse-number id="Mt 28:13">13</verse-number>telling <supplied>them</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> “Say ‘His disciples came during the night <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> stole him <supplied>while</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“were sleeping”)</note> we were sleeping.’ <verse-number id="Mt 28:14">14</verse-number>And if this <supplied>matter</supplied> is heard before the governor, we will satisfy him and <idiom-start/>keep you out of trouble<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “make you free from care”</note> <verse-number id="Mt 28:15">15</verse-number>So they took the money <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“took”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> did as they were told, and spread abroad this report among the Jews until this very day. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Great Commission</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mt 28:16">16</verse-number>So the eleven disciples proceeded to Galilee, to the mountain which Jesus had designated for them. <verse-number id="Mt 28:17">17</verse-number>And <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> saw him, they worshiped <supplied>him</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> but some doubted. <verse-number id="Mt 28:18">18</verse-number>And Jesus approached <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“approached”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> spoke to them, saying, “All authority in heaven and on earth has been given to me. <verse-number id="Mt 28:19">19</verse-number>Therefore, go<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*As a participle of attendant circumstance this participle carries imperatival force picked up from the main verb (“make disciples”)</note> <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“go”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> make disciples of all the nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father and of the Son and of the Holy Spirit, <verse-number id="Mt 28:20">20</verse-number>teaching them to observe everything I have commanded you, and behold, I am with you all the days until the end of the age.” </p>
		</chapter>