<chapter id="1 Ti 1">
			<pericope>Greeting</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ti 1:1">1</verse-number> Paul, an apostle of Christ Jesus according to the command of God our Savior and of Christ Jesus our hope, <verse-number id="1 Ti 1:2">2</verse-number>to Timothy, <supplied>my</supplied> true child in the faith. Grace, mercy, <supplied>and</supplied> peace from God the Father and Christ Jesus our Lord. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Instructions for Timothy in Ephesus</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ti 1:3">3</verse-number>Just as I urged you <supplied>when I</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“traveled”) which is understood as temporal</note> traveled to Macedonia, remain in Ephesus, so that you may instruct certain people not to teach other doctrine, <verse-number id="1 Ti 1:4">4</verse-number>and not to pay attention to myths and endless genealogies, which cause useless speculations rather than God’s plan <supplied>that is</supplied> by faith. <verse-number id="1 Ti 1:5">5</verse-number>But the goal of our instruction is love from a pure heart and a good conscience and a faith without hypocrisy, <verse-number id="1 Ti 1:6">6</verse-number>from which some have deviated, <supplied>and</supplied> have turned away into fruitless discussion, <verse-number id="1 Ti 1:7">7</verse-number>wanting to be teachers of the law, <supplied>although they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>although</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“understand”) which is understood as concessive</note> do not understand either <supplied>the things</supplied> which they are saying or <supplied>the things</supplied> concerning which they are speaking confidently. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ti 1:8">8</verse-number>But we know that the law <supplied>is</supplied> good, if anyone makes use of it lawfully, <verse-number id="1 Ti 1:9">9</verse-number>knowing this, that the law <supplied>is</supplied> not given for a righteous <supplied>person</supplied> but for the lawless and rebellious, for the ungodly and sinners, for the unholy and totally worldly, for the one who kills his father and the one who kills his mother, for murderers, <verse-number id="1 Ti 1:10">10</verse-number>sexually immoral people, homosexuals, kidnappers, liars, perjurers, and <idiom-start/>whatever<idiom-end/><note>Literally “if anything”</note> else is opposed to sound teaching, <verse-number id="1 Ti 1:11">11</verse-number>according to the glorious gospel of the blessed God that I was entrusted with. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Paul’s Thankfulness for the Mercy Shown to Him</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ti 1:12">12</verse-number><idiom-start/>I give thanks<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I have thankfulness”</note> to the one who strengthens me, Christ Jesus our Lord, because he considered me faithful, placing <supplied>me</supplied> into ministry,<note>Or “service”</note> <verse-number id="1 Ti 1:13">13</verse-number><supplied>although I</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>although</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was”) which is understood as concessive</note> was formerly a blasphemer and a persecutor and a violent man, but I was shown mercy because I acted ignorantly in unbelief, <verse-number id="1 Ti 1:14">14</verse-number>and the grace of our Lord abounded with the faith and love <supplied>that are</supplied> in Christ Jesus. <verse-number id="1 Ti 1:15">15</verse-number>The saying <supplied>is</supplied> trustworthy and worthy of all acceptance: Christ Jesus came into the world to save sinners, of whom I am the foremost. <verse-number id="1 Ti 1:16">16</verse-number>But because of this I was shown mercy, in order that in me foremost, Christ Jesus might demonstrate his total patience, for an example for those who are going to believe in him for eternal life. <verse-number id="1 Ti 1:17">17</verse-number>Now to the King of the ages, immortal, invisible, to the only God, <supplied>be</supplied> honor and glory <idiom-start/>forever and ever<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the ages of the ages”</note>. Amen. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Paul’s Charge to Timothy</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ti 1:18">18</verse-number>I am setting before you this instruction, Timothy <supplied>my</supplied> child, in accordance with the prophecies spoken long ago about you, in order that by them you may fight the good fight, <verse-number id="1 Ti 1:19">19</verse-number>having faith and a good conscience, which some, <supplied>because they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“have rejected”) which is understood as causal</note> have rejected <supplied>these</supplied>, have suffered shipwreck concerning their faith, <verse-number id="1 Ti 1:20">20</verse-number>among whom are Hymenaeus and Alexander, whom I have handed over to Satan, in order that they may be taught not to blaspheme. </p>
		</chapter>