<chapter id="1 Ti 2">
			<pericope>Instructions to Pray for All People</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ti 2:1">1</verse-number> Therefore, I urge first of all <supplied>that</supplied> petitions, prayers, requests, <supplied>and</supplied> thanksgiving be made on behalf of all people, <verse-number id="1 Ti 2:2">2</verse-number>on behalf of kings and all those who are in authority, in order that we may live a tranquil and quiet life in all godliness and dignity. <verse-number id="1 Ti 2:3">3</verse-number>This <supplied>is</supplied> good and acceptable before God our Savior, <verse-number id="1 Ti 2:4">4</verse-number>who wants all people to be saved and to come to a knowledge of the truth. <verse-number id="1 Ti 2:5">5</verse-number>For <supplied>there is</supplied> one God and one mediator between God and human beings, the man Christ Jesus, <verse-number id="1 Ti 2:6">6</verse-number>who gave himself a ransom for all, the testimony at the proper time, <verse-number id="1 Ti 2:7">7</verse-number>for which I was appointed a herald and an apostle—I am speaking the truth, <supplied>I am</supplied> not lying—a teacher of the Gentiles in faith and truth. <verse-number id="1 Ti 2:8">8</verse-number>Therefore I want the men in every place to pray, lifting up holy hands without anger and dispute. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Instructions for Women</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ti 2:9">9</verse-number>Likewise also the women should adorn themselves in appropriate clothing, with modesty and self-control, not with braided hair and gold jewelry or pearls or expensive clothing, <verse-number id="1 Ti 2:10">10</verse-number>but with good deeds which are fitting for women who profess godliness. <verse-number id="1 Ti 2:11">11</verse-number>A woman must learn in quietness with all submission. <verse-number id="1 Ti 2:12">12</verse-number>But I do not permit a woman to teach or to exercise authority over a man, but <idiom-start/>to remain quiet<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to be in quietness”</note>. <verse-number id="1 Ti 2:13">13</verse-number>For Adam was formed first, then Eve, <verse-number id="1 Ti 2:14">14</verse-number>and Adam was not deceived, but the woman, <supplied>because she</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was deceived”) which is understood as causal</note> was deceived, came into transgression. <verse-number id="1 Ti 2:15">15</verse-number>But she will be saved through the bearing of children, if she continues in faith and love and holiness with self-control. </p>
		</chapter>