<chapter id="1 Ti 3">
			<pericope>Qualifications for Overseers</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ti 3:1">1</verse-number> The saying <supplied>is</supplied> trustworthy: if anyone aspires to supervision, he desires a good work. <verse-number id="1 Ti 3:2">2</verse-number>Therefore the overseer must be irreproachable, the husband of one wife, temperate, self-controlled, respectable, hospitable, skillful in teaching, <verse-number id="1 Ti 3:3">3</verse-number>not addicted to wine, not a violent person, but gentle, peaceable, not loving money, <verse-number id="1 Ti 3:4">4</verse-number>managing his own household well, having children in submission with all dignity <verse-number id="1 Ti 3:5">5</verse-number>(but if someone does not know how to manage his own household, how will he take care of the church of God?), <verse-number id="1 Ti 3:6">6</verse-number>not newly converted, lest he become conceited <supplied>and</supplied> fall into the condemnation of the devil. <verse-number id="1 Ti 3:7">7</verse-number>But <supplied>he</supplied> must also have a good testimony from those outside, in order that he may not fall into disgrace and the trap of the devil. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Qualifications for Deacons</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ti 3:8">8</verse-number>Deacons likewise <supplied>must be</supplied> dignified, not insincere, not devoted to much wine, not fond of dishonest gain, <verse-number id="1 Ti 3:9">9</verse-number>holding the mystery of the faith with a clear conscience, <verse-number id="1 Ti 3:10">10</verse-number>and these also must be tested first; then let them serve <supplied>if they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>if</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“are”) which is understood as conditional</note> are above reproach. <verse-number id="1 Ti 3:11">11</verse-number>The wives<note>Or “The women”</note> likewise <supplied>must be</supplied> dignified, not slanderous, temperate, faithful in all <supplied>things</supplied>. <verse-number id="1 Ti 3:12">12</verse-number>Deacons must be husbands of one wife, managing <supplied>their</supplied> children and their own households well. <verse-number id="1 Ti 3:13">13</verse-number>For those who have served well acquire a good standing for themselves, and great boldness in the faith <supplied>that is</supplied> in Christ Jesus. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Mystery of Godliness Described</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ti 3:14">14</verse-number>I am writing these <supplied>things</supplied> to you, hoping to come to you in a short time. <verse-number id="1 Ti 3:15">15</verse-number>But if I am delayed, <supplied>I am writing</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The words “I am writing” are not in the Greek text, but are an understood repetition from the previous clause</note> in order that you may know how one must conduct oneself in the household of God, which is the church of the living God, the pillar and mainstay<note>Or “basis”; or “support”</note> of the truth. <verse-number id="1 Ti 3:16">16</verse-number>And most certainly, great is the mystery of godliness: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>Who was revealed in the flesh, </li1>
				<li2>was vindicated by<note>Or perhaps “in”</note> the Spirit, </li2>
				<li1>was seen by angels, </li1>
				<li2>was proclaimed among the Gentiles<note>Or “nations”; the same Greek word can be translated “nations” or “Gentiles” depending on the context</note>, </li2>
				<li1>was believed on in the world, </li1>
				<li2>was taken up in glory. </li2>
			</ul>
		</chapter>