<chapter id="1 Ti 4">
			<pericope>The Coming Apostasy</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ti 4:1">1</verse-number> Now the Spirit explicitly says that in the last times some will depart from the faith, paying attention to deceitful spirits and teachings of demons, <verse-number id="1 Ti 4:2">2</verse-number>by the hypocrisy of liars, who are seared in their own conscience, <verse-number id="1 Ti 4:3">3</verse-number>who forbid marrying <supplied>and insist on</supplied> abstaining from foods that God created for sharing in with thankfulness by those who believe and who know the truth, <verse-number id="1 Ti 4:4">4</verse-number>because everything created by God <supplied>is</supplied> good and nothing <supplied>is to be</supplied> rejected <supplied>if it is</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>if</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“received”) which is understood as conditional</note> received with thankfulness, <verse-number id="1 Ti 4:5">5</verse-number>for it is made holy by the word of God and prayer. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Good Servant of Christ</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ti 4:6">6</verse-number><supplied>By</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“teaching”) which is understood as means</note> teaching these <supplied>things</supplied> to the brothers, you will be a good servant of Christ Jesus, trained in the words of the faith and of the good teaching that you have followed faithfully. <verse-number id="1 Ti 4:7">7</verse-number>But reject those <idiom-start/>worthless myths told by elderly women<idiom-end/><note>Literally “worthless and characteristic of an elderly woman myths”</note>, and train yourself for godliness. <verse-number id="1 Ti 4:8">8</verse-number>For the training of the body is <idiom-start/>somewhat<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for a little”</note> profitable, but godliness is profitable for everything, <supplied>because it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“holds”) which is understood as causal</note> holds promise for the present life and for the <supplied>life</supplied> to come. <verse-number id="1 Ti 4:9">9</verse-number>The statement <supplied>is</supplied> trustworthy and deserving of complete acceptance. <verse-number id="1 Ti 4:10">10</verse-number>For to this <supplied>end</supplied> we labor and suffer reproach,<note>Some manuscripts have “and strive”</note> because we have put our hope in <supplied>the</supplied> living God, who is the Savior of all people, especially of believers. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ti 4:11">11</verse-number>Command these <supplied>things</supplied> and teach <supplied>them</supplied>. <verse-number id="1 Ti 4:12">12</verse-number>Let no one look down on your youth, but be an example for the believers in word, in conduct, in love, in faith, in purity. <verse-number id="1 Ti 4:13">13</verse-number>Until I come, pay attention to the <supplied>public</supplied> reading,<note>Many English translations supply “of scripture” here to clarify what is to be read aloud</note> to exhortation, to teaching. <verse-number id="1 Ti 4:14">14</verse-number>Do not neglect the gift <supplied>that is</supplied> in you, that was granted to you through prophecy with the laying on of hands by the council of elders. <verse-number id="1 Ti 4:15">15</verse-number>Practice these <supplied>things</supplied>. Be <supplied>diligent</supplied><note>Literally “be in these <supplied>things</supplied>,” though most English versions supply a predicate here</note> in these <supplied>things</supplied>, in order that your progress may be evident to everyone. <verse-number id="1 Ti 4:16">16</verse-number>Fix <supplied>your</supplied> attention on yourself and on your teaching. Continue in them, for <supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“doing”) which is understood as means</note> doing this you will save both yourself and those who hear you. </p>
		</chapter>