<chapter id="1 Ti 6">
			<pericope>Slaves and Masters</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ti 6:1">1</verse-number> All those who are under the yoke as slaves must regard their own masters as worthy of all honor, lest the name of God and the teaching be slandered. <verse-number id="1 Ti 6:2">2</verse-number>And those who have believing masters must not look down on <supplied>them</supplied> because they are brothers, but rather they must serve, because those who benefit by their service are believers and dearly loved. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>False Teachers and the Love of Money</pericope>
			<p>Teach and encourage these <supplied>things</supplied>. <verse-number id="1 Ti 6:3">3</verse-number>If anyone teaches other doctrine and does not devote himself to the sound words of our Lord Jesus Christ and the teaching <supplied>that is</supplied> in accordance with godliness, <verse-number id="1 Ti 6:4">4</verse-number>he is conceited, understanding nothing, but having a morbid interest concerning controversies and disputes about words, from which come envy, strife, slanders, evil suspicions, <verse-number id="1 Ti 6:5">5</verse-number>constant wrangling by people of depraved mind and deprived of the truth, who consider godliness to be a means of gain. <verse-number id="1 Ti 6:6">6</verse-number>But godliness with contentment is a great means of gain. <verse-number id="1 Ti 6:7">7</verse-number>For we have brought nothing into the world, so that neither can we bring anything out. <verse-number id="1 Ti 6:8">8</verse-number>But <supplied>if we</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>if</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“having”) which is understood as conditional</note> have food and clothing, with these <supplied>things</supplied> we will be content. <verse-number id="1 Ti 6:9">9</verse-number>But those who want to be rich fall into temptation and a trap and many foolish and harmful desires, which plunge those people into ruin and destruction. <verse-number id="1 Ti 6:10">10</verse-number>For the love of money is a root of all evil, by which some, <supplied>because they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“desire”) which is understood as causal</note> desire <supplied>it</supplied>, have gone astray from the faith and have pierced themselves with many pains. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Renewed Charge to Timothy</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ti 6:11">11</verse-number>But you, O man of God, flee from these <supplied>things</supplied>, and pursue righteousness, godliness, faith, love, patient endurance, gentleness. <verse-number id="1 Ti 6:12">12</verse-number>Fight the good fight of the faith; take hold of the eternal life to which you were called, and confessed the good confession in the presence of many witnesses. <verse-number id="1 Ti 6:13">13</verse-number>I command you, in the sight of God who gives life to all <supplied>things</supplied> and Christ Jesus who testified the good confession before Pontius Pilate, <verse-number id="1 Ti 6:14">14</verse-number><supplied>that</supplied> you observe the commandment without fault, irreproachable until the appearing of our Lord Jesus Christ, <verse-number id="1 Ti 6:15">15</verse-number>which he will make known in his own time, the blessed and only Sovereign, the King of those who reign as kings and Lord of those who rule as lords, <verse-number id="1 Ti 6:16">16</verse-number>the <supplied>one who</supplied> alone possesses immortality, who lives <supplied>in</supplied> unapproachable light, whom no human being has seen nor is able to see, to whom <supplied>be</supplied> honor and eternal power. Amen. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Instructions to the Rich</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ti 6:17">17</verse-number>Command those <supplied>who are</supplied> rich in this present age not to be proud and not to put their hope in the uncertainty of riches, but in God, who provides us all <supplied>things</supplied> richly for enjoyment, <verse-number id="1 Ti 6:18">18</verse-number>to do good, to be rich in good works, to be generous, sharing freely, <verse-number id="1 Ti 6:19">19</verse-number>storing up for themselves a good foundation for the future, in order that they may take hold of <supplied>what is</supplied> truly life. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Final Charge and Benediction</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ti 6:20">20</verse-number>O Timothy, guard what has been entrusted <supplied>to you</supplied>. Turn away from pointless empty talk and contradictions of <supplied>what is</supplied> falsely called knowledge, <verse-number id="1 Ti 6:21">21</verse-number>which some, <supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“professing”) which is understood as means</note> professing <supplied>it</supplied>, have deviated concerning the faith. Grace <supplied>be</supplied> with you <supplied>all</supplied>. </p>
		</chapter>