<chapter id="Le 2">
			<pericope>Laws for Grain Offerings</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 2:1">1</verse-number>“ ‘When a person<note>Or “a soul”</note> brings a grain offering to Yahweh, his offering must be finely milled flour, and he must pour out oil on it and place frankincense on it. <verse-number id="Le 2:2">2</verse-number>And he shall bring it to the sons of Aaron, the priests, and he<note>That is, the priest—see v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Le 2:9">9</cite></note> shall take <idiom-start/>his handful from its finely milled flour<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from there his handful from its finely milled flour”</note> and from its oil in addition to all its frankincense. The priest<note>Or “And the priest”</note> shall turn its token portion into smoke on the altar <supplied>as</supplied> an offering made <supplied>by</supplied> fire, <supplied>as</supplied> an appeasing fragrance for Yahweh. <verse-number id="Le 2:3">3</verse-number>The remainder<note>Or “And the remainder”</note> of the grain <supplied>offering</supplied> <idiom-start/>belongs to<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for”</note> Aaron and to his sons—<idiom-start/>it is a most holy thing<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a holiness of holinesses”</note> from the offerings made by fire for<note>Hebrew “of”</note> Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 2:4">4</verse-number>“ ‘But if you bring a grain offering of something oven-baked, <supplied>it must be of</supplied> finely milled flour <supplied>as</supplied> ring-shaped unleavened bread <supplied>mixed</supplied> with oil or wafers of unleavened bread smeared with oil. <verse-number id="Le 2:5">5</verse-number>If your offering <supplied>is</supplied> a <supplied>grain</supplied> offering <supplied>baked</supplied> on a<note>Hebrew “the”</note> flat baking pan, it must be finely milled flour, unleavened bread mixed with oil; <verse-number id="Le 2:6">6</verse-number>break it into pieces and pour out oil on it; it <supplied>is</supplied> a grain <supplied>offering</supplied>. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 2:7">7</verse-number>“ ‘If<note>Or “And if”</note> your offering <supplied>is</supplied> a grain <supplied>offering</supplied> <supplied>prepared in</supplied> a cooking pan, it must be <supplied>with</supplied> finely milled flour in oil. <verse-number id="Le 2:8">8</verse-number>And you shall bring the grain <supplied>offering</supplied> that is made from these things to Yahweh, and <supplied>the offerer</supplied><note>Changing from 2ms in the first verb to 3ms in the second verb apparently moves from general to specific; NET takes the second verb as an imperative (“Present it”), and NJPS translates it as an indefinite 3ms, making it passive (“it shall be brought”)</note> shall bring it to the priest, and he shall bring it to the altar. <verse-number id="Le 2:9">9</verse-number>And the priest shall take away from the grain <supplied>offering</supplied> its token portion, and he shall turn <supplied>it</supplied> into smoke on the altar <supplied>as</supplied> an offering made <supplied>by</supplied> fire, <supplied>as</supplied> an appeasing fragrance for Yahweh. <verse-number id="Le 2:10">10</verse-number>And the remainder of the grain <supplied>offering</supplied> <idiom-start/>belongs to<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for”</note> Aaron and to his sons—<idiom-start/>it is a most holy thing<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a holiness of holinesses”</note> from the offerings made by fire for<note>Hebrew “of”</note> Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 2:11">11</verse-number>“ ‘Every grain <supplied>offering</supplied> you<note>The first time a plural 2m verb has been employed since 1:2</note> bring to Yahweh must not be made of yeasted food, because you must not turn into smoke any yeast or any honey from<note>Hebrew “from it”</note> an offering made by fire for Yahweh. <verse-number id="Le 2:12">12</verse-number><supplied>As</supplied> an offering of <supplied>the</supplied> choicest portion, you<note>Another occurrence of the 2mp</note> may bring them to Yahweh, but they must not be offered on the altar <supplied>as</supplied> an appeasing fragrance. <verse-number id="Le 2:13">13</verse-number>Also all<note>Or “And all”</note> of your grain offerings you must season with salt; you<note>Or “and you”</note> must not omit the salt of your God’s covenant from your offering. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 2:14">14</verse-number>“ ‘And if you bring to Yahweh a grain <supplied>offering</supplied> of firstfruits, you must bring an ear of new grain roasted by fire, coarsely crushed ripe grain, <supplied>as</supplied> the grain <supplied>offering</supplied> of your firstfruits. <verse-number id="Le 2:15">15</verse-number>And you shall put oil on it and place frankincense on it; it <supplied>is</supplied> a grain <supplied>offering</supplied>. <verse-number id="Le 2:16">16</verse-number>The<note>Or “And the”</note> priest shall turn into smoke its token portion from its coarsely crushed grain together with all of its frankincense—<supplied>it is</supplied> an offering made by fire for Yahweh.’ ” </p>
		</chapter>