<chapter id="Le 3">
			<pericope>Laws for Fellowship Offerings</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 3:1">1</verse-number>“ ‘Now if<note>Or “And if”</note> his offering <supplied>is</supplied> a sacrifice of fellowship offering, if he brings it from the cattle,<note>Or “the herd”</note> whether male or female, he must bring it without defect before Yahweh. <verse-number id="Le 3:2">2</verse-number>He<note>Or “And he”</note> must lay his hand on the head of his offering and slaughter it at the entrance of the tent of assembly, and Aaron’s sons shall sprinkle the blood on the altar all around. <verse-number id="Le 3:3">3</verse-number>He shall present<note>Or “And he shall present”</note> from the sacrifice of the fellowship offering an offering made by fire for Yahweh <supplied>consisting of</supplied><note>The Hebrew accusative implies this transition</note> the fat covering the inner parts<note>Or “entrails”</note> and all the fat that <supplied>is</supplied> on the inner parts,<note>Or “entrails”</note> <verse-number id="Le 3:4">4</verse-number>the two kidneys,<note>Or “and the two kidneys”</note> and the fat that <supplied>is</supplied> on them, which <supplied>is</supplied> on the loins, and he must remove the lobe on the liver in addition to the kidneys. <verse-number id="Le 3:5">5</verse-number>Aaron’s sons shall turn it to smoke on the altar in addition to the burnt offering that <supplied>is</supplied> on the wood, which <supplied>is</supplied> on the fire; it <supplied>is</supplied> an offering made by fire <supplied>as</supplied> an appeasing fragrance for Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 3:6">6</verse-number>“ ‘But if his offering for a sacrifice of fellowship offering for Yahweh <supplied>is</supplied> from the flock,<note>The Hebrew term refers collectively to both sheep and goats (small livestock animals)</note> he must bring a male or a female without defect. <verse-number id="Le 3:7">7</verse-number>If he brings a sheep <supplied>as</supplied> his offering, then<note>Or “and”</note> he shall present it before Yahweh, <verse-number id="Le 3:8">8</verse-number>and he shall lay his hand on the head of his offering, and he shall slaughter it before the tent of assembly, and Aaron’s sons shall sprinkle its blood on the altar all around. <verse-number id="Le 3:9">9</verse-number>He shall present<note>Or “And he shall present”</note> from the sacrifice of the fellowship offering an offering made by fire for Yahweh: he must remove its fat, the entire fat tail near the tailbone, and the fat covering the inner parts<note>Or “entrails”</note> and all the fat that <supplied>is</supplied> on the inner parts,<note>Or “entrails”</note> <verse-number id="Le 3:10">10</verse-number>the two kidneys,<note>Or “and the two kidneys”</note> and the fat that <supplied>is</supplied> on them, which <supplied>is</supplied> on the loins, and he must remove the lobe on the liver in addition to the kidneys. <verse-number id="Le 3:11">11</verse-number>The priest<note>Or “And the priest”</note> shall turn it into smoke on the altar <supplied>as</supplied> a food offering made by fire for Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 3:12">12</verse-number>“ ‘And<note>Or “But”</note> if his offering is a goat, then<note>Or “and”</note> he shall bring it before Yahweh, <verse-number id="Le 3:13">13</verse-number>and he shall lay his hand on the head of his offering, and he shall slaughter it before the tent of assembly, and Aaron’s sons shall sprinkle its blood on the altar all around. <verse-number id="Le 3:14">14</verse-number>He shall present<note>Or “And he shall present”</note> his offering from it <supplied>as</supplied> an offering made by fire for Yahweh: the fat covering the inner parts<note>Or “entrails”</note> and all the fat that <supplied>is</supplied> on the inner parts,<note>Or “entrails”</note> <verse-number id="Le 3:15">15</verse-number>the two kidneys,<note>Or “and the two kidneys”</note> and the fat that <supplied>is</supplied> on them, which <supplied>is</supplied> on the loins, and he must remove the lobe on the liver in addition to the kidneys. <verse-number id="Le 3:16">16</verse-number>The priest<note>Or “And the priest”</note> shall turn them into smoke on the altar <supplied>as</supplied> a food <supplied>offering</supplied>;<note>Compare v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Le 3:11">11</cite></note> all the fat <supplied>is</supplied> an offering made by fire <supplied>as</supplied> an appeasing fragrance for Yahweh. <verse-number id="Le 3:17">17</verse-number><supplied>This is</supplied><note>Understood by context</note> a lasting statute for your generations in all your dwellings: you must not eat any fat or any blood.’ ” </p>
		</chapter>