<chapter id="Le 4">
			<pericope>Laws for Sin Offerings</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 4:1">1</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Le 4:2">2</verse-number>“Speak to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> saying, ‘If a person<note>Or “a soul”</note> sins by an unintentional wrong from any of Yahweh’s commands that should not be <idiom-start/>violated<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “done”</note> and he <idiom-start/>violates<idiom-end/><note>Literally “does”</note> <idiom-start/>any of them<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from one from them”; see NET</note>— <verse-number id="Le 4:3">3</verse-number>if the anointed priest sins, <idiom-start/>bringing guilt on the people<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to the guilt of the people”</note> then,<note>Or “and”</note> concerning the sin that he has <idiom-start/>committed<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sinned”</note> he shall bring <idiom-start/>a young bull<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a bull, a son of cattle”</note> without defect for Yahweh as a sin offering. <verse-number id="Le 4:4">4</verse-number>He shall bring<note>Or “And he shall bring”</note> the bull to <supplied>the</supplied> tent of assembly’s entrance before Yahweh, place<note>Or “And place”</note> his hand on the bull’s head, and slaughter the bull before Yahweh. <verse-number id="Le 4:5">5</verse-number>The anointed priest<note>Or “And the anointed priest”</note> shall take <idiom-start/>some of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> the bull’s blood and shall bring it to <supplied>the</supplied> tent of assembly, <verse-number id="Le 4:6">6</verse-number>and the priest shall dip his finger in the blood and shall spatter <idiom-start/>some of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> the blood seven times before Yahweh in front of the sanctuary’s curtain. <verse-number id="Le 4:7">7</verse-number>The priest<note>Or “And the priest”</note> shall put <idiom-start/>some of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> the blood on the horns of the altar of fragrant incense before Yahweh, which <supplied>is</supplied> in <supplied>the</supplied> tent of assembly, and all <supplied>the rest</supplied><note>Implied by the context</note> of the bull’s blood he must pour out on the base of the altar of the burnt offering, which <supplied>is at the</supplied> entrance of <supplied>the</supplied> tent of assembly. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 4:8">8</verse-number>“ ‘He must remove<note>Or “And he must remove”</note> all the fat from the bull of the sin offering: the fat that covers the inner parts<note>Or “entrails”</note> and all of the fat that <supplied>is</supplied> on the inner parts,<note>Or “entrails”</note> <verse-number id="Le 4:9">9</verse-number>the two<note>Or “and the two”</note> kidneys and the fat that <supplied>is</supplied> on them, and the liver’s lobe <supplied>that</supplied> he must remove in addition to the kidneys— <verse-number id="Le 4:10">10</verse-number>just as it is removed from the ox of the fellowship offerings’ sacrifice—and the priest shall turn them into smoke on the altar of the burnt offering. <verse-number id="Le 4:11">11</verse-number>But<note>Or “And”</note> the bull’s skin and its meat, in addition to its head, <idiom-start/>its lower leg bones<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “and in addition to its lower leg bones”</note> its<note>Or “and its”</note> inner parts,<note>Or “entrails”</note> and its offal— <verse-number id="Le 4:12">12</verse-number>he shall carry<note>Or “and he shall carry out”</note> all of the bull <idiom-start/>outside the camp<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to from an outside place of the camp”</note> to a ceremonially clean place, to the fatty ashes’ dump, and he shall burn it on wood in the fire; it must be burned up on the fatty ashes’ dump. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 4:13">13</verse-number>“ ‘If<note>Or “And if”</note> Israel’s whole assembly did wrong unintentionally and the matter<note>Or “thing”</note> was concealed from the assembly’s eyes, and they acted<note>Or “did”</note> <supplied>against</supplied> <idiom-start/>any of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “one from all of”</note> Yahweh’s commands that should not be <idiom-start/>violated<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “done”</note> so that<note>Or “and”</note> they incur guilt, <verse-number id="Le 4:14">14</verse-number>when<note>Or “and”</note> the sin that they have <idiom-start/>committed<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sinned”</note> against <supplied>that command</supplied><note>The 3fs pronominal suffix may refer to “one of Yahweh’s commands”—“one” is also fs</note> becomes known, the assembly<note>Or “and the assembly”</note> shall present <idiom-start/>a young bull<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a bull, a son of cattle”</note> as a sin offering, and they shall bring it before <supplied>the</supplied> tent of assembly. <verse-number id="Le 4:15">15</verse-number>And the elders of the community shall place their hands on the bull’s head before Yahweh, and he<note>Or “someone”; see NET—the 3ms refers to either one of the elders or the priest</note> shall slaughter the bull before Yahweh. <verse-number id="Le 4:16">16</verse-number>Then the anointed priest shall bring <idiom-start/>some of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> the bull’s blood to <supplied>the</supplied> tent of assembly, <verse-number id="Le 4:17">17</verse-number>and the priest shall dip his finger in<note>Or “from”</note> the blood and shall spatter it seven times before Yahweh in front of the curtain. <verse-number id="Le 4:18">18</verse-number>He must put<note>Or “And he must put”</note> <idiom-start/>some of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> the blood on the altar’s horns before Yahweh <idiom-start/>in the tent of assembly<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “which <supplied>is</supplied> in <supplied>the</supplied> tent of assembly”—the reference is to the altar</note> and all <supplied>the rest</supplied><note>Indicated by the context</note> of the blood he must pour out on the base of the altar of the burnt offering, which <supplied>is at the</supplied> tent of assembly’s entrance. <verse-number id="Le 4:19">19</verse-number>He must remove<note>Or “And he must remove”</note> all its fat from it, and he shall turn <supplied>it</supplied> into smoke on the altar. <verse-number id="Le 4:20">20</verse-number>He shall do<note>Or “And he shall do”</note> to the bull <idiom-start/>just as<idiom-end/><note>Literally “as that”</note> he did to the sin offering’s bull, so he must do to it. The priest<note>Or “And the priest”</note> shall make atonement for them, and <idiom-start/>they will be forgiven<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “it shall be forgiven to them”</note> <verse-number id="Le 4:21">21</verse-number>He shall bring<note>Or “And he shall bring out”</note> <supplied>the rest of</supplied><note>Indicated by the context</note> the bull <idiom-start/>outside the camp<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to from an outside place of the camp”</note> and he shall burn it <idiom-start/>just as<idiom-end/><note>Literally “as that”</note> he burned the first bull; it <supplied>is</supplied> the sin offering for the assembly. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 4:22">22</verse-number>“ ‘When a leader sins and commits<note>Or “does”</note> an unintentional wrong <supplied>against</supplied> <idiom-start/>any of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “one from all of”</note> the commands of Yahweh his God that should not be <idiom-start/>violated<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “done”</note> so that<note>Or “and”</note> he incurs guilt, <verse-number id="Le 4:23">23</verse-number>or his sin he has <idiom-start/>committed<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sinned”</note> is made known to him, he shall bring<note>Or “and he shall bring” or “then he shall bring”</note> <idiom-start/>a male goat<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a he-goat of goats a male”</note> without defect <supplied>as</supplied> his offering. <verse-number id="Le 4:24">24</verse-number>He shall place<note>Or “And he shall place”</note> his hand on the he-goat’s head and slaughter it in the place where he slaughtered the burnt offering before Yahweh; it <supplied>is</supplied> a sin offering. <verse-number id="Le 4:25">25</verse-number>The priest<note>Or “And the priest”</note> shall take <idiom-start/>some of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> the sin offering’s blood with his finger, and he shall put <supplied>it</supplied> on the horns of the altar of the burnt offering, and he must pour out <supplied>the rest of</supplied><note>Indicated by context</note> its blood on the base of the altar of the burnt offering. <verse-number id="Le 4:26">26</verse-number>He<note>Or “And he”; the antecedent is the priest (cp. vv. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Le 4:10">10</cite>, 31)</note> must turn all of its fat into smoke on the altar like the fat of the fellowship offerings’ sacrifice, and the priest shall make atonement for him <idiom-start/>because of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> his sin, and <idiom-start/>he will be forgiven<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “it shall be forgiven to him”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 4:27">27</verse-number>“ ‘If<note>Or “And if”</note> <idiom-start/>anyone<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a soul one”</note> of the people of the land sins by an unintentional wrong by <idiom-start/>violating<idiom-end/><note>Literally “doing”</note> one of Yahweh’s commands that should not be <idiom-start/>violated<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “done”</note> so that<note>Or “and”</note> he incurs guilt, <verse-number id="Le 4:28">28</verse-number>or his sin he has <idiom-start/>committed<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sinned”</note> is made known to him, he shall bring<note>Or “and he shall bring” or “then he shall bring”</note> <supplied>as</supplied> his offering <idiom-start/>a female goat without defect<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a she-goat of goats without defect a female”</note> <supplied>as</supplied> his offering for his sin that he <idiom-start/>committed<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sinned”</note> <verse-number id="Le 4:29">29</verse-number>He shall place<note>Or “And he shall place”</note> his hand on the sin offering’s head and slaughter the sin offering in the place of the burnt offering. <verse-number id="Le 4:30">30</verse-number>The priest<note>Or “And the priest”</note> shall take <idiom-start/>some of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> its blood with his finger, and he shall put <supplied>it</supplied> on the horns of the altar of the burnt offering, and he must pour out all <supplied>the rest of</supplied><note>Indicated by context</note> its blood on the altar’s base. <verse-number id="Le 4:31">31</verse-number>He<note>Or “And he”</note> must remove all of its fat <idiom-start/>just as<idiom-end/><note>Literally “as that”</note> <supplied>the</supplied> fat was removed from<note>Or “from on” or “from upon”</note> the fellowship offerings’ sacrifice, and the priest shall turn <supplied>it</supplied> into smoke on the altar as an appeasing fragrance for Yahweh. The priest<note>Or “And the priest”</note> shall make atonement for him, and <idiom-start/>he will be forgiven<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “it shall be forgiven to him”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 4:32">32</verse-number>“ ‘But<note>Or “And”</note> if he brings a lamb <supplied>as</supplied> his offering for a sin offering, he must bring a female without defect. <verse-number id="Le 4:33">33</verse-number>He shall place<note>Or “And he shall place”</note> his hand on the sin offering’s head, and he shall slaughter it as a sin offering in the place where he slaughtered the burnt offering. <verse-number id="Le 4:34">34</verse-number>The priest<note>Or “And the priest”</note> shall take <idiom-start/>some of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> the sin offering’s blood with his finger, and he shall put <supplied>it</supplied> on the horns of the altar of the burnt offering, and he must pour out all <supplied>the rest</supplied><note>Indicated by context</note> of its blood on the altar’s base. <verse-number id="Le 4:35">35</verse-number>He must remove<note>Or “And he must remove”</note> all of its fat <idiom-start/>just as<idiom-end/><note>Literally “as that”</note> the lamb’s fat from the fellowship offerings’ sacrifice was removed, and the priest shall turn them into smoke on the altar upon Yahweh’s offerings made by fire; and the priest shall make atonement for him because of<note>Or “for”</note> his sin that he <idiom-start/>committed<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sinned”</note> and <idiom-start/>he will be forgiven<idiom-end/>.’ ”<note>Literally “it will be forgiven to him”</note> </p>
		</chapter>