<chapter id="Le 5">
			<pericope>More Laws Regarding Sin Offerings</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 5:1">1</verse-number>“ ‘When a person<note>Or “a soul”</note> sins in that<note>Or “and”</note> he hears <supplied>the</supplied> utterance of a curse and he <supplied>is</supplied> a witness or he sees or he knows, if he does not make <supplied>it</supplied> known, then<note>Or “and”</note> he shall bear his guilt. <verse-number id="Le 5:2">2</verse-number>Or if a person<note>Or “a soul”</note> touches anything unclean, <idiom-start/>whether<idiom-end/><note>Literally “or”</note> an unclean <supplied>wild</supplied><note>Implied by the following phrase specifying domestic animals</note> animal’s dead body or an unclean domestic animal’s dead body or an unclean swarmer’s dead body, but<note>Or “and”</note> <idiom-start/>he is unaware of it<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “it is concealed from him”</note> he <supplied>is</supplied> unclean and he is guilty. <verse-number id="Le 5:3">3</verse-number>Or when he touches human uncleanness, <idiom-start/>namely<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for” or “to” (see HALOT 510)</note> any uncleanness of his by which he might become unclean, but<note>Or “and”</note> <idiom-start/>he is unaware of it<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “it is concealed from him”</note> and he himself finds out, then<note>Or “and”</note> he will be guilty. <verse-number id="Le 5:4">4</verse-number>Or when a person<note>Or “a soul”</note> swears, speaking thoughtlessly with <supplied>his</supplied> lips, to do evil or to do good <idiom-start/>with regard to<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for” or “to” (see HALOT 510)</note> anything that <idiom-start/>the person<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the man”</note> in a sworn oath speaks thoughtlessly, but<note>Or “and”</note> <idiom-start/>he is unaware of it<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “it is concealed from him”</note> he will be guilty <idiom-start/>in any of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for one of”</note> these. <verse-number id="Le 5:5">5</verse-number>When he becomes guilty <idiom-start/>in any of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for one of”</note> these, he shall confess<note>Or “and he shall confess”</note> what he has sinned <idiom-start/>regarding<idiom-end/><note>Literally “upon” or “against”</note> it, <verse-number id="Le 5:6">6</verse-number>and he shall bring his guilt offering to<note>Or “for”</note> Yahweh for his sin that he has <idiom-start/>committed<idiom-end/>:<note>Literally “sinned”</note> a female from the flock,<note>The Hebrew term refers collectively to both sheep and goats (small livestock animals)</note> a ewe-lamb or <idiom-start/>a she-goat<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “a she-goat of goats”</note> as a sin offering, and the priest shall make atonement for him for<note>Hebrew “from”</note> his sin. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 5:7">7</verse-number>“ ‘If<note>Or “And if”</note> <idiom-start/>he cannot afford a sheep<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “his hand does not touch enough of small livestock”</note> he shall bring <supplied>as</supplied> his guilt offering <supplied>for</supplied> what he sinned two turtledoves or two <idiom-start/>young doves<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons of dove” or “children of dove”</note> for Yahweh, one for a sin offering and one for a burnt offering. <verse-number id="Le 5:8">8</verse-number>He shall bring<note>Or “And he shall bring”</note> them to the priest, and he shall present that which <supplied>is</supplied> for the sin offering first, and <supplied>the priest</supplied><note>Required by the previous action (see NET)</note> shall wring its head off <idiom-start/>at the back of its neck<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from opposite its neck”</note> but<note>Or “and”</note> he must not sever <supplied>it</supplied>, <verse-number id="Le 5:9">9</verse-number>and he shall spatter <idiom-start/>some of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> the sin offering’s blood on the altar’s side, and the leftover blood must be drained out on the altar’s base; it <supplied>is</supplied> a sin offering. <verse-number id="Le 5:10">10</verse-number>The second<note>Or “And the second”</note> <supplied>bird</supplied> he must prepare <supplied>as</supplied> a burnt offering according to the regulation, and the priest shall make atonement for him for his sin that he has <idiom-start/>committed<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sinned”</note> and he shall be forgiven. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 5:11">11</verse-number>“ ‘But<note>Or “And”</note> if <idiom-start/>he cannot afford<idiom-end/><note>Literally “his hand cannot produce for”</note> two turtledoves or two <idiom-start/>young doves<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons of dove” or “children of dove”</note> then,<note>Or “and”</note> because he has sinned, he shall bring <supplied>as</supplied> his offering a tenth of an<note>Hebrew “the”</note> ephah <supplied>of</supplied> finely milled flour as a sin offering. He must not put<note>Or “And he must not put”</note> oil on it, nor should he put frankincense on it, because it <supplied>is</supplied> a sin offering. <verse-number id="Le 5:12">12</verse-number>He shall bring<note>Or “And he shall bring”</note> it to the priest, and the priest <idiom-start/>shall take a handful of it<idiom-end/><note>Literally “shall scoop up from it the fullness of his handful”</note> <supplied>for</supplied> its token portion, and he shall turn it to smoke on the altar <idiom-start/>in addition to<idiom-end/><note>Literally “on” or “upon”</note> the offerings made by fire <supplied>to</supplied> Yahweh; it <supplied>is</supplied> a sin offering. <verse-number id="Le 5:13">13</verse-number>Thus<note>Or “And”</note> the priest shall make atonement for him because of the sin that he has <idiom-start/>committed<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sinned”</note> <idiom-start/>in any of these<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from one from these”</note> and he shall be forgiven. It shall be<note>Or “And it shall be”</note> for the priest, like the grain offering.’ ” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Laws for Guilt Offerings</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 5:14">14</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Le 5:15">15</verse-number>“When a person<note>Or “a soul”</note> <idiom-start/>displays infidelity<idiom-end/><note>Literally “acts unfaithfully infidelity” or “is unfaithful <supplied>in</supplied> unfaithfulness”</note> and he sins in an unintentional wrong <idiom-start/>in any of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> Yahweh’s holy things, then<note>Or “and”</note> he shall bring his guilt offering to<note>Or “for”</note> Yahweh: a ram without defect from the flock<note>The Hebrew term refers collectively to both sheep and goats (small livestock animals)</note> as a guilt offering by your valuation <supplied>in</supplied> silver shekels<note>Or “convertible into silver shekels” (NET, NRSV, TNK), “of the proper value in silver” (NIV; cp. ESV “valued in silver shekels,” CSB), or “or you may buy one of equal value with silver” (NLT)</note> according to the sanctuary shekel. <verse-number id="Le 5:16">16</verse-number>And he shall make restitution <supplied>for</supplied> what he sinned <idiom-start/>because of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from” (see HALOT 598)</note> a holy thing and shall add one-fifth of <idiom-start/>its value<idiom-end/><note>Literally “it”</note> onto it and shall give it to the priest. The priest<note>Or “And the priest”</note> shall make atonement for him with the ram of the guilt offering, and he will be forgiven. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 5:17">17</verse-number>“If<note>Or “And if”</note> a person<note>Or “a soul”</note> when he sins <idiom-start/>violates<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and she/it does”</note> one from all of Yahweh’s commands that should not <idiom-start/>be violated<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “they are to be done”</note> but<note>Or “and”</note> he did not know, then<note>Or “and”</note> he is guilty and he shall bear his guilt. <verse-number id="Le 5:18">18</verse-number>He shall bring<note>Or “And he shall bring”</note> to the priest a ram without defect from the flock<note>The Hebrew term refers collectively to both sheep and goats (small livestock animals)</note> as a guilt offering by your valuation, and the priest shall make atonement for him because of his unintentional wrong (although<note>Or “and”</note> he himself did not know), and he will be forgiven. <verse-number id="Le 5:19">19</verse-number>It is a guilt offering; he certainly was guilty before Yahweh.” </p>
		</chapter>