<chapter id="Le 6">
			<pericope>Additional Laws for Burnt Offerings</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 6:1">1</verse-number><note><cite title="BibleLEB2: Le 6:1–30">Leviticus 6:1–30 </cite>in the English Bible is 5:20–6:23 in the Hebrew Bible</note> Then<note>Or “And”</note> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Le 6:2">2</verse-number>“When a person<note>Or “a soul”</note> <idiom-start/>displays infidelity<idiom-end/><note>Literally “acts unfaithfully infidelity” or “is unfaithful <supplied>in</supplied> unfaithfulness”</note> against Yahweh and he deceives his fellow citizen regarding<note>Literally “in”</note> something entrusted or <idiom-start/>a pledge<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a pledge of a hand”</note> or stealing or he exploits his fellow citizen, <verse-number id="Le 6:3">3</verse-number>or he finds lost property and lies about it and swears <idiom-start/>falsely<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in accordance with deception”</note> <idiom-start/>in regard to<idiom-end/><note>Literally “on” or “upon”</note> any one of these things by which <idiom-start/>a person<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the man”</note> might commit sin, <verse-number id="Le 6:4">4</verse-number><idiom-start/>and when<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and it will be when”</note> he sins and is guilty, then<note>Or “and”</note> he shall bring back <idiom-start/>the things he had stolen<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the robbed things that he had stolen”</note> or <idiom-start/>what he had extorted<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the extortion that he had extorted”</note> or <idiom-start/>something with which he had been entrusted<idiom-end/><note>Literally “something entrusted that had been entrusted <supplied>to</supplied> him”</note> or the lost property that he had found, <verse-number id="Le 6:5">5</verse-number>or <idiom-start/>regarding<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> anything about which he has sworn <idiom-start/>falsely<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “in accordance with deception”</note> then<note>Or “and”</note> he shall repay it <idiom-start/>according to<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in”</note> its value and shall add one-fifth of its value to it—he must give it <idiom-start/>to whom it belongs<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to whom it is to him”</note> on the day of his guilt offering. <verse-number id="Le 6:6">6</verse-number>And he must bring as his guilt offering to Yahweh a ram without defect from the flock<note>The Hebrew term refers collectively to both sheep and goats (small livestock animals)</note> by your valuation<note>See 5:15 and 18</note> as a guilt offering to the priest, <verse-number id="Le 6:7">7</verse-number>and the priest shall make atonement for him <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> Yahweh, and he shall be forgiven <idiom-start/>anything<idiom-end/><note>Literally “one”</note> from all that he might do <idiom-start/>by which he might incur guilt<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “which he might do for <supplied>incurring</supplied> guilt by it”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 6:8">8</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Le 6:9">9</verse-number>“Command Aaron and his sons, saying, ‘This <supplied>is</supplied> the regulation of the burnt offering: <idiom-start/>The burnt offering must remain on the hearth<idiom-end/><note>Literally “It <supplied>shall be</supplied> the burnt offering on a hearth”</note> on the altar all night until the morning, and the altar’s fire must be kept burning on it. <verse-number id="Le 6:10">10</verse-number>And the priest shall put on his linen robe, and he must put his linen undergarments on his body, and he shall take away the fatty ashes <supplied>of</supplied> the burnt offering that the fire has consumed on the altar, and he shall place them<note>Hebrew “him/it”—plural required by the English “fatty ashes”</note> beside the altar. <verse-number id="Le 6:11">11</verse-number>And he shall take off his garments and put on other garments, and he shall bring out the fatty ashes <idiom-start/>outside the camp<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to from an outside place of the camp”</note> to a ceremonially clean place, <verse-number id="Le 6:12">12</verse-number>but<note>Or “and”</note> the fire on the altar must be kept burning on it; it must not be quenched. And the priest must burn wood <idiom-start/>every morning<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the morning in the morning”</note> on it,<note>Antecedent for this 3fs suffix is “fire” (“altar” is ms)</note> and he shall arrange the burnt offering on it,<note>Antecedent for this 3fs suffix is “fire” (“altar” is ms)</note> and he shall turn into smoke the fat portions of the fellowship offerings on it.<note>Antecedent for this 3fs suffix is “fire” (“altar” is ms)</note> <verse-number id="Le 6:13">13</verse-number>A perpetual fire must be kept burning on the altar; it must not be quenched. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Additional Laws for Grain Offerings</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 6:14">14</verse-number>“ ‘And this <supplied>is</supplied> the regulation of the grain offering. Aaron’s sons shall present it <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> Yahweh <idiom-start/>in front of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> the altar, <verse-number id="Le 6:15">15</verse-number>and he<note>That is, the priest; understood by context and 3ms verb</note> in his fist shall take away from it <idiom-start/>some of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> the grain offering’s finely milled flour, and <idiom-start/>some of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> its oil and all of the frankincense that <supplied>is</supplied> on the grain offering, and he shall turn into smoke its token portion on the altar <supplied>as</supplied> an appeasing fragrance to Yahweh. <verse-number id="Le 6:16">16</verse-number>And Aaron and his sons must eat the remainder of it; they must eat it <supplied>as</supplied> unleavened bread in a holy place—in the tent of assembly’s courtyard they must eat it. <verse-number id="Le 6:17">17</verse-number>It must not be baked <supplied>with</supplied> yeast. I have given it <supplied>as</supplied> their share from my offerings made by fire. It <supplied>is</supplied> <idiom-start/>a most holy thing<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “a holiness of holinesses”</note> like the sin offering and like the guilt offering. <verse-number id="Le 6:18">18</verse-number>Every male among Aaron’s sons may eat it <supplied>as</supplied> a lasting rule among your generations from the offerings made by fire <idiom-start/>belonging to<idiom-end/><note>Literally “of”</note> Yahweh. Anything that<note>Or “Everyone who”</note> touches them will become holy.’ ” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 6:19">19</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Le 6:20">20</verse-number>“This is the offering of Aaron and his sons that they shall present to Yahweh on the day of his being anointed: a tenth of an<note>Hebrew “the”</note> ephah of finely milled flour <supplied>as</supplied> a perpetual grain offering, half of it in the morning and half of it in the evening. <verse-number id="Le 6:21">21</verse-number>It must be made<note>Or “prepared”</note> in<note>Or “with”</note> oil on a flat baking pan; you<note>Singular masculine</note> must bring it well-mixed; you must present pieces of a grain offering’s baked goods<note>Or “broken bits” (JPS, NET, NIV)</note> <supplied>as</supplied> an appeasing fragrance to Yahweh. <verse-number id="Le 6:22">22</verse-number>And the anointed priest <supplied>taking</supplied> his place from <supplied>among</supplied> his sons must do it. <supplied>As</supplied> a lasting rule, it must be turned into smoke totally for Yahweh. <verse-number id="Le 6:23">23</verse-number>And every grain offering of a priest must be a whole burnt offering; it must not be eaten.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Additional Laws for Sin Offerings</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 6:24">24</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Le 6:25">25</verse-number>“Speak to Aaron and his sons, saying, ‘This is the regulation of the sin offering: In <supplied>the</supplied> place where the sin offering is slaughtered, the sin offering must be slaughtered <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> Yahweh; it <supplied>is</supplied> <idiom-start/>a most holy thing<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “a holiness of holinesses”</note> <verse-number id="Le 6:26">26</verse-number>The priest <idiom-start/>who offers the sin offering<idiom-end/><note>Literally “one who offers it a sin offering”</note> must eat it in a holy place—in the tent of assembly’s courtyard. <verse-number id="Le 6:27">27</verse-number>Anything that<note>Or “Everyone who”</note> touches its flesh will become holy, and <supplied>when</supplied> <idiom-start/>some of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> its blood spatters on a<note>Hebrew “the”</note> garment, what was spattered on it you<note>Singular masculine</note> shall wash in a holy place. <verse-number id="Le 6:28">28</verse-number>And a clay vessel in which it was boiled must be broken, but<note>Or “and”</note> if it was boiled in a bronze vessel, then<note>Or “and”</note> it shall be thoroughly scoured and rinsed with water. <verse-number id="Le 6:29">29</verse-number>Any male among the priests may eat it; it <supplied>is</supplied> <idiom-start/>a most holy thing<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “a holiness of holinesses”</note> <verse-number id="Le 6:30">30</verse-number>But<note>Or “And”</note> any sin offering <supplied>from</supplied> which <idiom-start/>some of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> its blood is brought to the tent of assembly to make atonement in the sanctuary must not be eaten; it must be burned in the fire.’ ” </p>
		</chapter>