<chapter id="Le 7">
			<pericope>Additional Laws for Guilt Offerings</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 7:1">1</verse-number>“ ‘And this <supplied>is</supplied> the regulation of the guilt offering; it <supplied>is</supplied> <idiom-start/>a most holy thing<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “a holiness of holinesses”</note> <verse-number id="Le 7:2">2</verse-number>In the place where they slaughter the burnt offering,<note>Or, taking the verb as an indefinite (thus passive) imperfect 3mp, “the sin offering is slaughtered”</note> they must slaughter the guilt offering,<note>Or, taking the verb as an indefinite (thus passive) imperfect 3mp, “the guilt offering must be slaughtered”</note> and he<note>That is, the priest; understood by context and 3ms verb</note> must sprinkle its blood upon the altar all around. <verse-number id="Le 7:3">3</verse-number>And he must present all of its fat:<note>Hebrew “all of its fat from it”</note> the fat tail and the fat that covers the inner parts,<note>Or “entrails”</note> <verse-number id="Le 7:4">4</verse-number>and the two kidneys, and the fat that <supplied>is</supplied> on them, which <supplied>is</supplied> on the loins, and he must remove the lobe on the liver in addition to the kidneys. <verse-number id="Le 7:5">5</verse-number>And the priest shall turn it into smoke it on the altar <supplied>as</supplied> a food offering made by fire for Yahweh; it <supplied>is</supplied> a guilt offering. <verse-number id="Le 7:6">6</verse-number>Every male among the priests may eat it; it must be eaten in a holy place; it <supplied>is</supplied> <idiom-start/>a most holy thing<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “a holiness of holinesses”</note> <verse-number id="Le 7:7">7</verse-number><supplied>The</supplied> instruction <supplied>is</supplied> <idiom-start/>the same for the guilt offering as for the sin offering<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “as the sin offering as the guilt offering one for them”</note> <idiom-start/>it belongs to<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for him it shall be” or “it will become his”</note> the priest, who makes atonement with it. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Portions for the Priests</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 7:8">8</verse-number>“ ‘And<note>Or “As for”</note> the priest who presents <idiom-start/>a person’s<idiom-end/><note>Literally “of a man”</note> burnt offering, to that<note>Hebrew “the”</note> priest <idiom-start/>belongs<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to/for him it shall be”</note> the skin of the burnt offering that he presented. <verse-number id="Le 7:9">9</verse-number>And every grain offering that is baked in the oven and all that is prepared in a<note>Hebrew “the”</note> cooking pan or<note>Or “and”</note> on a flat baking pan <idiom-start/>belongs to<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for him it shall be” or “it will become his”</note> the priest who presented it. <verse-number id="Le 7:10">10</verse-number>And every grain offering, <supplied>whether</supplied> mixed with oil or dry, shall be for all of Aaron’s sons <idiom-start/>equally<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “each as his brother”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Additional Laws for Fellowship Offerings</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 7:11">11</verse-number>“ ‘And this <supplied>is</supplied> the regulation of the fellowship offerings that he must present to Yahweh: <verse-number id="Le 7:12">12</verse-number>If he presents it for thanksgiving, in addition to the thanksgiving sacrifice he shall present ring-shaped unleavened bread mixed with oil and unleavened bread wafers smeared with oil and well-mixed ring-shaped bread cakes of finely milled flour mixed with oil. <verse-number id="Le 7:13">13</verse-number>In addition to ring-shaped cakes of bread <supplied>with</supplied> yeast, he must present his <supplied>grain</supplied><note>Implied by v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Le 7:12">12</cite></note> offering together with<note>Or “in addition to”</note> his sacrifice of thanksgiving peace offerings. <verse-number id="Le 7:14">14</verse-number>And he shall present one of each kind of <supplied>grain</supplied><note>Implied by v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Le 7:12">12</cite></note> offering <supplied>as</supplied> a contribution for Yahweh; <idiom-start/>it belongs to<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for him it shall be” or “it will become his”</note> the priest who sprinkles the fellowship offerings’ blood. <verse-number id="Le 7:15">15</verse-number>And the meat of the sacrifice of his thanksgiving fellowship offerings must be eaten on the day of his offering; he must not leave it until morning. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 7:16">16</verse-number>“ ‘But<note>Or “And”</note> if his sacrifice <supplied>is</supplied> <supplied>for</supplied> a vow or <supplied>as</supplied> a freewill offering, it must be eaten on the day of his presenting his sacrifice, and on the next day the remainder<note>Or “and the remainder”</note> from it may be eaten, <verse-number id="Le 7:17">17</verse-number>but<note>Or “and”</note> the remainder from the sacrifice’s meat must be burned up in the fire on the third day. <verse-number id="Le 7:18">18</verse-number>And if indeed some of the meat of his fellowship offerings’ sacrifice is eaten on the third day, it will not be accepted; it will not be considered <supplied>of benefit</supplied> for the one who presented it—it shall be unclean <supplied>meat</supplied>, and the person<note>Or “soul”</note> who eats it shall bear his guilt. <verse-number id="Le 7:19">19</verse-number>And the meat that touches anything unclean must not be eaten; it must be burned with fire, and as for the <supplied>clean</supplied><note>Understood by context</note> meat, anyone who is clean may eat the meat. <verse-number id="Le 7:20">20</verse-number>And the person<note>Or “the soul”</note> who eats meat from the fellowship offerings’ sacrifice, which <supplied>is</supplied> for Yahweh, and whose uncleanness <supplied>is</supplied> upon him—that person<note>Or “the soul”</note> shall be cut off from his people. <verse-number id="Le 7:21">21</verse-number>And when a person<note>Or “a soul”</note> touches anything unclean, <supplied>whether</supplied> human uncleanness or an unclean animal or any unclean detestable thing, and he eats from the meat of the fellowship offerings’ sacrifice, which <supplied>is</supplied> for Yahweh, then<note>Or “and”</note> that person<note>Or “the soul”</note> shall be cut off from his people.’ ” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Instructions for the People</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 7:22">22</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Le 7:23">23</verse-number>“Speak to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> saying, ‘You<note>Plural</note> must not eat any fat of ox, or<note>Or “and”</note> sheep, or<note>Or “and”</note> goat; <verse-number id="Le 7:24">24</verse-number>and a dead body’s fat or<note>Or “and”</note> mangled carcass’s fat may be used for any <idiom-start/>purpose<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “work”</note> but<note>Or “and”</note> you<note>Plural</note> certainly must not eat it. <verse-number id="Le 7:25">25</verse-number>When anyone eats fat from the domestic animal from which he presented an offering made by fire for Yahweh, then<note>Or “and”</note> that person<note>Or “the soul”</note> who ate shall be cut off from his people. <verse-number id="Le 7:26">26</verse-number>And in any of your<note>Plural</note> dwellings, you must not eat any blood <idiom-start/>belonging to<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to/of”</note> birds<note>Hebrew “the bird”; generic article with a collective noun</note> or<note>Or “and”</note> domestic animals.<note>Hebrew “the domestic animal”; generic article with a collective noun</note> <verse-number id="Le 7:27">27</verse-number>Any person<note>Or “any soul” or “all soul(s)”</note> who eats any blood, that person<note>Or “and that soul”</note> shall be cut off from his people.’ ” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Portions of Fellowship Offerings for Priests</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 7:28">28</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Le 7:29">29</verse-number>“Speak to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> saying, ‘The one who presents his fellowship offerings’ sacrifice for Yahweh shall bring his offering to Yahweh from his fellowship offerings’ sacrifice. <verse-number id="Le 7:30">30</verse-number>His <supplied>own</supplied> hands must bring Yahweh’s offerings made by fire. He must bring the fat in addition to the breast section to wave the breast section <supplied>as</supplied> a wave offering before Yahweh, <verse-number id="Le 7:31">31</verse-number>and the priest shall turn the fat into smoke on the altar, and the breast section shall be for Aaron and his<note>Hebrew “for his”</note> sons. <verse-number id="Le 7:32">32</verse-number>And the right upper thigh you<note>Plural</note> must give <supplied>as</supplied> a contribution for the priest from your<note>Plural</note> fellowship offerings’ sacrifice. <verse-number id="Le 7:33">33</verse-number><supplied>As for</supplied> the one from Aaron’s sons who presents the blood of the fellowship offerings and the fat, the right upper thigh <idiom-start/>shall belong to him<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for him it shall be”</note> <supplied>as</supplied> his share, <verse-number id="Le 7:34">34</verse-number>because I have taken the wave offering’s breast section and the contribution <supplied>offering’s</supplied> upper thigh from the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> out of their fellowship offerings’ sacrifices, and I have given them to Aaron the priest and his<note>Hebrew “to his”</note> sons from the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> <supplied>as</supplied> a lasting rule.’ ” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 7:35">35</verse-number>This <supplied>is</supplied> Aaron’s allotted portion and his sons’ allotted portion from Yahweh’s offerings made by fire <idiom-start/>when<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in a day”</note> he brought them forward to serve as priests for Yahweh. <verse-number id="Le 7:36">36</verse-number>This is what Yahweh commanded to give them from the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> on the day of his anointing them; <supplied>it is</supplied> a lasting statute for their generations. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Concluding Summary Concerning the Offerings</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 7:37">37</verse-number>This <supplied>is</supplied> the regulation for the burnt offering, for the grain offering and for the sin offering and for the guilt offering and for the consecration <supplied>offering</supplied> and for the fellowship offerings’ sacrifice, <verse-number id="Le 7:38">38</verse-number>which Yahweh commanded Moses on <idiom-start/>Mount Sinai<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the mountain of Sinai”</note> on the day of his commanding the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> to present their offerings to Yahweh in the desert of Sinai. </p>
		</chapter>