<chapter id="Le 8">
			<pericope>Installing the Priests</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 8:1">1</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Le 8:2">2</verse-number>“Take Aaron and his sons with him, and the garments and the anointing oil and the bull of the sin offering and the two rams and the basket of the unleavened bread, <verse-number id="Le 8:3">3</verse-number>and summon all of the community to the entrance to<note>Or “of”</note> the tent of assembly.” <verse-number id="Le 8:4">4</verse-number>So<note>Or “And”</note> Moses did <supplied>just</supplied> as Yahweh commanded him, and the community gathered by the entrance to<note>Or “of”</note> the tent of assembly. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 8:5">5</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Moses said to the community, “This <supplied>is</supplied> the word that Yahweh has commanded to be done.”<note>Or “to do” or “<supplied>me</supplied> to do”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 8:6">6</verse-number>So<note>Or “And”</note> Moses brought Aaron and his sons near, and he washed them with water. <verse-number id="Le 8:7">7</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> he put the tunic on him and tied<note>Or “he tied”</note> the sash <supplied>around</supplied> him; then<note>Or “and”</note> he clothed him with the robe and put<note>Or “he put”</note> the ephod on him; then<note>Or “and”</note> he tied the ephod’s waistband <supplied>around</supplied> him and fastened<note>Or “he fastened”</note> <supplied>the ephod</supplied><note>Understood by context</note> to him with it. <verse-number id="Le 8:8">8</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> he placed the breastpiece on him and put<note>Or “he put”</note> the Urim and the Thummim into the breastpiece; <verse-number id="Le 8:9">9</verse-number>and he placed the turban on his head, and on <idiom-start/>the front of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the front of his faces”</note> the turban he placed the gold rosette, the holy diadem, <supplied>just</supplied> as Yahweh had commanded Moses. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 8:10">10</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Moses took the anointing oil and anointed<note>Or “he anointed”</note> the tabernacle and all that <supplied>was</supplied> in it, and he consecrated them. <verse-number id="Le 8:11">11</verse-number>And he spattered <idiom-start/>part of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> it on the altar seven times—thus<note>Or “and”</note> he anointed the altar and all of its utensils, and the basin and its stand, to consecrate them. <verse-number id="Le 8:12">12</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> he poured out <idiom-start/>part of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> the anointing oil on Aaron’s head—thus<note>Or “and”</note> he anointed him <supplied>in order</supplied> to consecrate him. <verse-number id="Le 8:13">13</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Moses brought Aaron’s sons near and clothed<note>Or “he clothed”</note> them <supplied>with</supplied> tunics and tied<note>Or “he tied”</note> a sash <supplied>around</supplied> <idiom-start/>each one<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “them”</note> and he bound headbands on<note>Or “to”</note> them, <supplied>just</supplied> as Yahweh had commanded Moses. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Offerings for Consecration</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 8:14">14</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> he brought forth the bull of the sin offering, and Aaron and his sons placed their hands on the head of the bull of the sin offering, <verse-number id="Le 8:15">15</verse-number>and he slaughtered <supplied>it</supplied>, and Moses took the blood and put<note>Or “he put”</note> <supplied>it</supplied> with his finger on the altar’s horns all around and purified the altar; then<note>Or “and”</note> he poured the blood out on the altar’s base—thus<note>Or “and”</note> he consecrated it <supplied>in order</supplied> to make atonement for it.<note>Or “to make atonement upon it” (see NET, Tanakh)</note> <verse-number id="Le 8:16">16</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> he took all the fat that <supplied>was</supplied> on the inner parts<note>Or “entrails”</note> and the lobe on the liver and the two kidneys and their fat, and Moses turned <supplied>them</supplied> into smoke on the altar, <verse-number id="Le 8:17">17</verse-number>but<note>Or “and”</note> he burned the bull and its skin and its meat and its offal in the fire <idiom-start/>outside the camp<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from an outside place of the camp”</note> <supplied>just</supplied> as Yahweh had commanded Moses. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 8:18">18</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> he brought the ram of the burnt offering near, and Aaron and his sons placed their hands on the ram’s head, <verse-number id="Le 8:19">19</verse-number>and he slaughtered <supplied>it</supplied>. Then<note>Or “And”</note> Moses sprinkled the blood on the altar all around. <verse-number id="Le 8:20">20</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> he cut the ram into pieces, and Moses turned into smoke the head and the pieces and the suet, <verse-number id="Le 8:21">21</verse-number>but<note>Or “and”</note> he washed the inner parts<note>Or “entrails”</note> and the lower leg bones with water, and Moses turned into smoke all of the ram on the altar; it <supplied>was</supplied> a burnt offering as an appeasing fragrance, an offering made by fire for<note>Or “to”</note> Yahweh, <supplied>just</supplied> as Yahweh had commanded Moses. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 8:22">22</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> he brought the second ram near, the ram of the consecration, and Aaron and his sons placed their hands on the ram’s head, <verse-number id="Le 8:23">23</verse-number>and he slaughtered <supplied>it</supplied>. Then<note>Or “And”</note> Moses took <idiom-start/>some of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> its blood and put<note>Or “he put”</note> <supplied>it</supplied> on Aaron’s right ear lobe and on his right hand’s thumb and on his right foot’s big toe. <verse-number id="Le 8:24">24</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> he brought Aaron’s sons near, and Moses put <idiom-start/>some of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> the blood on their right ear lobe and on their right hand’s thumb and on their right foot’s big toe, and Moses sprinkled the blood on the altar all around. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 8:25">25</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> he took the fat and the fat tail and all of the fat that <supplied>was</supplied> on the inner parts<note>Or “entrails”</note> and the lobe of the liver and the two kidneys and their fat and the right upper thigh; <verse-number id="Le 8:26">26</verse-number>and from the basket of the unleavened bread that <supplied>was</supplied> before Yahweh he took one ring-shaped unleavened bread and one ring-shaped bread with<note>Or “of”</note> oil and one wafer, and he placed <supplied>them</supplied> on the <idiom-start/>fat parts<idiom-end/><note>Literally “fats”</note> and on the right upper thigh. <verse-number id="Le 8:27">27</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> he put <idiom-start/>all of these<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the all”</note> on Aaron’s palms and on his sons’ palms, and he waved them <supplied>as</supplied> a wave offering <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> Yahweh. <verse-number id="Le 8:28">28</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Moses took them from upon their palms, and he turned <supplied>them</supplied> into smoke upon the burnt offering on the altar; they <supplied>were</supplied> a consecration offering as an appeasing fragrance—it <supplied>was</supplied> an offering made by fire for<note>Or “to”</note> Yahweh. <verse-number id="Le 8:29">29</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Moses took the breast section, and he waved it <supplied>as</supplied> a wave offering <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> Yahweh from the ram of the consecration offering; it <supplied>was</supplied> Moses’ share, <supplied>just</supplied> as Yahweh had commanded Moses. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Anointing the Priests and Their Garments</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 8:30">30</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Moses took <idiom-start/>some of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> the anointing oil and <idiom-start/>some of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> the blood that <supplied>was</supplied> on the altar, and he spattered <supplied>them</supplied> on Aaron, on his garments, and on Aaron’s sons and on his sons’ garments with him—thus<note>Or “and”</note> he consecrated Aaron, his garments, and his sons and his sons’ garments with him. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 8:31">31</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Moses said to Aaron and to his sons, “Boil the meat in <supplied>the</supplied> entrance to<note>Or “of”</note> <supplied>the</supplied> tent of assembly, and there you must eat it and the bread that <supplied>is</supplied> in the basket of the consecration offering, <supplied>just</supplied> as I have commanded, saying, ‘Aaron and his sons must eat it,’ <verse-number id="Le 8:32">32</verse-number>but<note>Or “and”</note> the remainder of the meat and the bread you<note>Plural</note> must burn in the fire. <verse-number id="Le 8:33">33</verse-number>And you must not go out from the entrance to<note>Or “of”</note> <supplied>the</supplied> tent of assembly <supplied>for</supplied> seven days, until <supplied>the</supplied> day of fulfilling the days of your<note>Plural</note> consecration, because <idiom-start/>it will take seven days to ordain you<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “seven of days it will fill your (plural) hand”</note> <verse-number id="Le 8:34">34</verse-number><supplied>Just</supplied> as was done<note>Or “he did”</note> on this day, Yahweh commanded to be done<note>Or “to do”</note> <supplied>in order</supplied> to make atonement for you.<note>Plural</note> <verse-number id="Le 8:35">35</verse-number>And you<note>Plural</note> must stay <supplied>at the</supplied> entrance to<note>Or “of”</note> <supplied>the</supplied> tent of assembly day and night <supplied>for</supplied> seven days, and you<note>Plural</note> shall keep the obligation from<note>Or “of”</note> Yahweh, so you<note>Plural</note> might not die, for thus I have been commanded.” <verse-number id="Le 8:36">36</verse-number>So<note>Or “And”</note> Aaron and his sons did all the things that Yahweh had commanded <idiom-start/>through<idiom-end/><note>Literally “by the hand of”</note> Moses. </p>
		</chapter>