<chapter id="Le 9">
			<pericope>Worship at the Tent of Assembly</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 9:1">1</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And it happened”</note> on the eighth day Moses summoned Aaron and his sons and Israel’s elders, <verse-number id="Le 9:2">2</verse-number>and he said to Aaron, “Take for yourself <idiom-start/>a bull calf<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a bull-calf a son of cattle” or “a bull-calf a son of <supplied>the</supplied> herd”</note> as a sin offering and a ram as a burnt offering, without defect,<note>An adjective in masculine plural to modify both animals; see NET</note> and present <supplied>them</supplied> <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> Yahweh. <verse-number id="Le 9:3">3</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> you<note>Singular</note> must speak to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> saying, ‘Take <idiom-start/>a he-goat<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a he-goat of goats”</note> as a sin offering and a bull calf and a male sheep, <idiom-start/>yearlings<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons of a year”</note> without defect,<note>An adjective in masculine plural to modify both animals; see NET</note> as a burnt offering, <verse-number id="Le 9:4">4</verse-number>and an ox and a ram as fellowship offerings to sacrifice <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> Yahweh, and a grain offering mixed with oil, because today Yahweh will appear to you.”<note>Plural</note> <verse-number id="Le 9:5">5</verse-number>So<note>Or “And”</note> they took what Moses had commanded to <supplied>the</supplied> <idiom-start/>front of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> <supplied>the</supplied> tent of assembly, and the whole community presented <supplied>themselves</supplied>, and they stood <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 9:6">6</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Moses said, “This <supplied>is</supplied> the word that Yahweh commanded you<note>Plural</note> to do <idiom-start/>so that<idiom-end/><note>Or “and”</note> the glory of Yahweh might appear to you.”<note>Plural</note> <verse-number id="Le 9:7">7</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Moses said to Aaron, “Approach<note>Or “Draw near unto”</note> the altar and <idiom-start/>sacrifice<idiom-end/><note>Literally “do” or “make”</note> your sin offering and your burnt offering, and make atonement for yourself and for the people. And <idiom-start/>sacrifice<idiom-end/><note>Literally “do” or “make”</note> the people’s offering and make atonement for them, <supplied>just</supplied> as Yahweh has commanded.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 9:8">8</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Aaron approached<note>Or “drew near unto”</note> the altar, and he slaughtered the bull calf of the sin offering, which was for himself. <verse-number id="Le 9:9">9</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Aaron’s sons presented the blood to him, and he dipped his finger in the blood, and he put <supplied>it</supplied> on the altar’s horns, and he poured out the blood on the altar’s base. <verse-number id="Le 9:10">10</verse-number>And the fat and the kidneys and the lobe <idiom-start/>from the sin offering’s liver<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from the liver from the sin offering”</note> he turned into smoke on the altar, <supplied>just</supplied> as Yahweh had commanded Moses, <verse-number id="Le 9:11">11</verse-number>but<note>Or “and”</note> the meat and the skin he burned <idiom-start/>with fire<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the fire”</note> <idiom-start/>outside the camp<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “from an outside place to/of the camp”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 9:12">12</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> he slaughtered the burnt offering, and Aaron’s sons brought the blood to him, and he sprinkled it on the altar all around; <verse-number id="Le 9:13">13</verse-number>and they brought the burnt offering to him by its pieces, as well as<note>Or “and”</note> the head, and he turned <supplied>them</supplied> into smoke on the altar; <verse-number id="Le 9:14">14</verse-number>and he washed the inner parts<note>Or “entrails”</note> and the lower leg bones, then<note>Or “and”</note> he turned <supplied>them</supplied> into smoke upon the burnt offering on the altar. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 9:15">15</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> he presented the people’s offering, and he took the goat of the sin offering, which <supplied>was</supplied> for the people, and he slaughtered it and offered<note>Or “he offered”</note> it <supplied>as</supplied> a sin offering like the first one. <verse-number id="Le 9:16">16</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> he presented the burnt offering, and he <idiom-start/>sacrificed<idiom-end/><note>Literally “did” or “made”</note> it according to the regulation. <verse-number id="Le 9:17">17</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> he presented the grain offering, and he filled his palm <idiom-start/>with some of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> it, and he turned it into smoke on the altar besides the morning’s burnt offering. <verse-number id="Le 9:18">18</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> he slaughtered the ox and the ram, the fellowship offerings that <supplied>are</supplied> for the people, and Aaron’s sons brought the blood to him, and he sprinkled it on the altar all around. <verse-number id="Le 9:19">19</verse-number>And <supplied>as for</supplied> the fat portions from the ox and from the ram (the fat tail and the layer of fat and the kidneys and the lobe of the liver), <verse-number id="Le 9:20">20</verse-number>they placed the fat portions on the breast sections, and he turned the fat portions into smoke on the altar. <verse-number id="Le 9:21">21</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Aaron waved the breast sections and the right upper thigh <supplied>as</supplied> a wave offering <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> Yahweh, <supplied>just</supplied> as Moses had commanded. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 9:22">22</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Aaron lifted his hand toward<note>Or “to”</note> the people, and he blessed them, and he came down <idiom-start/>after<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> <idiom-start/>sacrificing<idiom-end/><note>Literally “doing” or “making”</note> the sin offering and the burnt offering and the fellowship offerings. <verse-number id="Le 9:23">23</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Moses and Aaron entered <supplied>the</supplied> tent of assembly. When<note>Or “And”</note> they came out, they blessed<note>Or “and they blessed”</note> the people, and Yahweh’s glory appeared to all the people. <verse-number id="Le 9:24">24</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> a fire went out <idiom-start/>from before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from to the faces of”</note> Yahweh, and it consumed the burnt offering and the fat portions on the altar. And all the people saw <supplied>it</supplied>, so<note>Or “and”</note> they shouted <supplied>for joy</supplied>, and they fell on their faces. </p>
		</chapter>