<chapter id="Le 10">
			<pericope>The Deaths of Nadab and Abihu</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 10:1">1</verse-number>And Aaron’s sons Nadab and Abihu each took his censer, and they put fire in them and placed incense on it;<note>That is, the fire</note> then<note>Or “and”</note> they presented <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> Yahweh illegitimate fire, which he had not commanded them. <verse-number id="Le 10:2">2</verse-number>So<note>Or “And”</note> fire went out <idiom-start/>from before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from to the faces of”</note> Yahweh, and it consumed them so that<note>Or “and”</note> they died <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> Yahweh. <verse-number id="Le 10:3">3</verse-number>Therefore<note>Or “And”</note> Moses said to Aaron, “This <supplied>is</supplied> what Yahweh spoke, saying, ‘Among those who are close to me I will show myself holy, and <idiom-start/>in the presence of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “upon the faces of”</note> all the people I will display my glory.’ ”<note>Or “I will be glorified”</note> So<note>Or “And”</note> Aaron was silent. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 10:4">4</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Moses summoned Mishael and Elzaphan the sons of Uzziel, Aaron’s uncle, and he said to them, “Come forward.<note>Or “Come near” or “Approach”</note> Carry your brothers from <idiom-start/>the front of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the faces of”</note> the sanctuary to <idiom-start/>outside the camp<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “from an outside place of the camp”</note> <verse-number id="Le 10:5">5</verse-number>So<note>Or “And”</note> they came forward,<note>Or “came near” or “approached”</note> and they carried them <idiom-start/>outside the camp<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to from an outside place of the camp”</note> in their tunics, just as Moses had ordered. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 10:6">6</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Moses said to Aaron and to his sons Eleazar and Ithamar, “You must not let your hair hang loosely, and you must not tear your garments, so that<note>Or “and”</note> you will not die and he<note>That is, God</note> will be angry with all the community. But<note>Or “And”</note> your brothers, all the house of Israel, may weep <supplied>because of</supplied> <idiom-start/>the burning that Yahweh caused<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the burning that Yahweh burned”</note> <verse-number id="Le 10:7">7</verse-number>but<note>Or “and”</note> you must not go out from <supplied>the</supplied> entrance to<note>Or “of”</note> <supplied>the</supplied> tent of assembly lest you die, because Yahweh’s anointing oil <supplied>is</supplied> on you.” So<note>Or “And”</note> they did according to Moses’ word. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Lasting Statutes</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 10:8">8</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Yahweh spoke to Aaron, saying, <verse-number id="Le 10:9">9</verse-number>“You and your sons with you may not drink wine or<note>Or “and”</note> strong drink when you come to <supplied>the</supplied> tent of assembly, so that<note>Or “and”</note> you will not die—<supplied>it is</supplied> a lasting statute for your<note>Plural</note> generations— <verse-number id="Le 10:10">10</verse-number>and to distinguish between the holy and the unholy,<note>Or “the common”</note> as well as<note>Or “and”</note> between the unclean and the clean, <verse-number id="Le 10:11">11</verse-number>and to teach the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> all the rules that Yahweh has spoken to them <idiom-start/>through<idiom-end/><note>Literally “by the hand of”</note> Moses.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 10:12">12</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Moses spoke to Aaron and to his sons Eleazar and Ithamar, “<supplied>As for</supplied> the remaining <supplied>parts</supplied>,<note>Implied by plural form of noun and the immediate context</note> take the remainder <supplied>of</supplied> the grain offering from Yahweh’s offerings made by fire and eat it, <supplied>the</supplied> unleavened bread, beside the altar, because it <supplied>is</supplied> <idiom-start/>a most holy thing<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “a holiness of holinesses”</note> <verse-number id="Le 10:13">13</verse-number>And you shall eat it in a holy place, because it <supplied>is</supplied> your allotted portion and the allotted portion of your sons from Yahweh’s offerings made by fire, for so I have been commanded. <verse-number id="Le 10:14">14</verse-number>And the wave offering’s breast section and the upper thigh of the contribution <supplied>offering</supplied> you<note>Plural</note> must eat in a clean place, you and your sons and your daughters with you, because they are given <supplied>as</supplied> your allotted portion and your sons’ allotted portion from the sacrifices of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>’<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> fellowship offerings. <verse-number id="Le 10:15">15</verse-number>They must bring the thigh of the contribution <supplied>offering</supplied> and the breast section of the wave offering in addition to the offerings made by fire, <supplied>consisting</supplied> of the fat portions, to wave as a wave offering <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> Yahweh; and it will be for you and for your sons with you as a lasting rule, <supplied>just</supplied> as Yahweh had commanded.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Problem of the Uneaten Sin Offering</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 10:16">16</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Moses sought all over <supplied>for</supplied> the goat of the sin offering and behold, it was burned up. So<note>Or “And”</note> he was angry with Aaron’s remaining sons Eleazar and Ithamar, saying, <verse-number id="Le 10:17">17</verse-number>“Why did you not eat the sin offering on the sanctuary’s site, because it <supplied>is</supplied> <idiom-start/>a most holy thing<idiom-end/>?<note>Literally “a holiness of holinesses”</note> And he gave it to you to remove the community’s guilt, to make atonement for them <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> Yahweh. <verse-number id="Le 10:18">18</verse-number>Look, its blood was not brought <idiom-start/>inside the sanctuary<idiom-end/>.<note>Or “to the sanctuary inside” or “to the sanctuary within”</note> Certainly you should have eaten it in the sanctuary, as I commanded.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 10:19">19</verse-number>So<note>Or “And”</note> Aaron said to Moses, “Look, today they presented their sin offering and their burnt offering <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> Yahweh, and <supplied>things</supplied> such as these have happened to me, and <supplied>if</supplied> I were to eat a sin offering today, would it have been good in Yahweh’s eyes?” <verse-number id="Le 10:20">20</verse-number>When<note>Or “And”</note> Moses heard, it<note>Or “and it”</note> was good in his eyes. </p>
		</chapter>