<chapter id="Le 11">
			<pericope>Clean and Unclean Animals</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 11:1">1</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Yahweh spoke to Moses and to Aaron, saying to them, <verse-number id="Le 11:2">2</verse-number>“Speak to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> saying, ‘These <supplied>are</supplied> the animals that you may eat from all the animals that <supplied>are</supplied> on the land: <verse-number id="Le 11:3">3</verse-number>Any among the animals that has a divided hoof and has a split cleft in<note>Hebrew “of”</note> <supplied>the</supplied> hoof, such<note>Hebrew “her/it”</note> you may eat. <verse-number id="Le 11:4">4</verse-number>However,<note>Or “Only”</note> these<note>By context; Hebrew “this”</note> you may not eat from those that chew the cud and from those that have a<note>Hebrew “the”</note> divided hoof: the camel, because it <supplied>is</supplied> a chewer of cud but it does not have a hoof that is divided—it <supplied>is</supplied> unclean for you; <verse-number id="Le 11:5">5</verse-number>and the coney, because it <supplied>is</supplied> a chewer of cud but it does not have a hoof that is divided—it <supplied>is</supplied> unclean for you; <verse-number id="Le 11:6">6</verse-number>and the hare, because it <supplied>is</supplied> a chewer of cud but it does not have a hoof that is divided—it <supplied>is</supplied> unclean for you; <verse-number id="Le 11:7">7</verse-number>and the pig, because it has a divided hoof and has a split cleft in<note>Hebrew “of”</note> the hoof but it does not chew cud—it <supplied>is</supplied> unclean for you. <verse-number id="Le 11:8">8</verse-number>You must not eat from their meat, and you must not touch their dead body—they are unclean for you. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 11:9">9</verse-number>“ ‘These<note>By context; Hebrew “This”</note> you may eat from all that <supplied>are</supplied> in the water: any in the water that has a fin and scales, <supplied>whether</supplied> in the seas or<note>Or “and”</note> in the streams—such<note>Hebrew “them”</note> you may eat. <verse-number id="Le 11:10">10</verse-number>But any that does not have a fin and scales, <supplied>whether</supplied> in the seas or<note>Or “and”</note> in the streams, <idiom-start/>among<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> all the water’s swarmers among all the living creatures that <supplied>are</supplied> in the water—they <supplied>are</supplied> a detestable thing to you. <verse-number id="Le 11:11">11</verse-number>And they shall be detestable to you; you must not eat from their meat, and you must detest their dead body. <verse-number id="Le 11:12">12</verse-number>Any that does not have a fin and scales in the water—it <supplied>is</supplied> a detestable thing to you. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 11:13">13</verse-number>“ ‘And these you must detest from the birds; they must not be eaten—they <supplied>are</supplied> detestable: the eagle and the vulture and the short-toed eagle, <verse-number id="Le 11:14">14</verse-number>and the red kite and the black kite according to its kind, <verse-number id="Le 11:15">15</verse-number>every crow according to its kind, <verse-number id="Le 11:16">16</verse-number>and <idiom-start/>the ostrich<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the daughter of the ostrich”</note> and the short-eared owl and the seagull and the hawk according to its kind, <verse-number id="Le 11:17">17</verse-number> and the little owl and the cormorant and the great owl, <verse-number id="Le 11:18">18</verse-number>and the barn owl and the desert owl and the carrion vulture, <verse-number id="Le 11:19">19</verse-number>and the stork, the heron according to its kind and the hoopoe and the bat. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 11:20">20</verse-number>“ ‘Any <idiom-start/>winged insect<idiom-end/><note>Literally “swarmer of the wing”</note> that walks on <supplied>all</supplied> fours <supplied>is</supplied> detestable to you. <verse-number id="Le 11:21">21</verse-number>Only this may you eat from any of <idiom-start/>the winged insects<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the swarmer of the wing”</note> that walk on <supplied>all</supplied> fours—<supplied>that</supplied> which has jointed legs above its feet for leaping upon the land. <verse-number id="Le 11:22">22</verse-number><idiom-start/>From these<idiom-end/><note>Literally “These from them”</note> you may eat the locust according to its kind and the bald locust according to its kind and the cricket according to its kind and the grasshopper according to its kind. <verse-number id="Le 11:23">23</verse-number>But<note>Or “And”</note> any <supplied>other</supplied><note>Implied by context</note> <idiom-start/>winged insect<idiom-end/><note>Literally “swarmer of wing”</note> that has four legs <supplied>is</supplied> detestable to you. <verse-number id="Le 11:24">24</verse-number>And by these you shall become unclean—anyone who touches their dead body shall become unclean until the evening, <verse-number id="Le 11:25">25</verse-number>and anyone who carries their dead body must wash his garments, and he shall be unclean until the evening. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 11:26">26</verse-number>“ ‘<supplied>With regard</supplied> to any animal that has a divided hoof but does not split the hoof, or<note>Or “and”</note> does not have a cud <supplied>for</supplied> chewing<note>So HALOT 830 s.v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Le 11:4">4</cite></note>—they <supplied>are</supplied> unclean for you; anyone who touches them shall become unclean. <verse-number id="Le 11:27">27</verse-number>And anything that walks upon its paws among any of the animals<note>Collective singular = plural by context</note> that walks on <supplied>all</supplied> fours—they <supplied>are</supplied> unclean for you; anyone who touches their dead body shall become unclean until the evening, <verse-number id="Le 11:28">28</verse-number>and the one who carries their dead body must wash his garments, and he shall be unclean until the evening—they <supplied>are</supplied> unclean for you. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 11:29">29</verse-number>“ ‘And these<note>By context; Hebrew “this”</note> <supplied>are</supplied> the unclean for you among the swarmers<note>Collective singular = plural</note> that swarm on the land: the weasel and the mouse and the thorn-tailed lizard according to its kind, <verse-number id="Le 11:30">30</verse-number>and the gecko and the land crocodile and the lizard and the sand lizard and the chameleon. <verse-number id="Le 11:31">31</verse-number>These <supplied>are</supplied> the unclean for you among all the swarmers; anyone who touches them at their death shall become unclean until the evening. <verse-number id="Le 11:32">32</verse-number>And anything on which <idiom-start/>one of them<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from them”</note> falls at their death shall become unclean: any object of wood or garment or skin or sackcloth—any object that has performed work—must be placed in water, and it shall be unclean until the evening, and <supplied>then</supplied> it shall be clean. <verse-number id="Le 11:33">33</verse-number>And any clay vessel<note>Context indicates a vessel as distinguished from a tool or utensil</note> into which it falls shall become unclean, and you must break it. <verse-number id="Le 11:34">34</verse-number>Any of the food that could be eaten on which water <supplied>from such a vessel</supplied> comes shall become unclean, and any liquid that could be drunk in any <supplied>such</supplied> vessel shall become unclean. <verse-number id="Le 11:35">35</verse-number>And anything on which <idiom-start/>one of their dead bodies<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from their dead body”</note> falls shall become unclean: an oven or<note>Or “and”</note> a stove must be broken<note>Or “smashed” (NASB, HCSB, NET, NJPS) or “broken in pieces” (ASV, ESV, NRSV)</note>—they <supplied>are</supplied> unclean and shall be unclean for you. <verse-number id="Le 11:36">36</verse-number>Surely<note>So HALOT 45</note> a spring or<note>Or “and”</note> a cistern collecting water shall be clean, but that which touches their dead body shall become unclean. <verse-number id="Le 11:37">37</verse-number>And when <idiom-start/>one of their dead bodies<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from their dead body”</note> falls on any <idiom-start/>seed for sowing<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “seed plant that is to be sown”</note> it <supplied>is</supplied> clean. <verse-number id="Le 11:38">38</verse-number>But<note>Or “And”</note> when water is put on <supplied>the</supplied> seed and <idiom-start/>one of their dead bodies<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from their dead body”</note> falls on it, it <supplied>is</supplied> unclean for you. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 11:39">39</verse-number>“ ‘And when <idiom-start/>one of the animals<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from the animal”</note> dies that is for you to eat, the one who touches its dead body shall become unclean until the evening. <verse-number id="Le 11:40">40</verse-number>And the one who eats <idiom-start/>some of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> its dead body must wash his garments, and he shall be unclean until the evening; and the one who carries its dead body must wash his garments, and he shall be unclean until the evening. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 11:41">41</verse-number>“ ‘And any swarmer that swarms on the land <supplied>is</supplied> detestable; it must not be eaten. <verse-number id="Le 11:42">42</verse-number>You must not eat<note>Hebrew “eat them”</note> anything that moves upon its belly or<note>Or “and”</note> that walks on <supplied>all</supplied> fours, even any <supplied>with</supplied> numerous feet <supplied>belonging</supplied> to any swarmer that swarms on the land, because they <supplied>are</supplied> detestable. <verse-number id="Le 11:43">43</verse-number>You must not defile yourselves with any swarmer that swarms, and you must not make yourselves unclean by them and <supplied>so</supplied> be made unclean by them, <verse-number id="Le 11:44">44</verse-number>because I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh your God, and you must keep yourselves sanctified, so that<note>Or “and”</note> you shall be holy, because I <supplied>am</supplied> holy. And you must not make yourselves unclean with any swarmer that moves along on the land, <verse-number id="Le 11:45">45</verse-number>because I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh, who brought you up from the land of Egypt to be for you as God. Thus<note>Or “And”</note> you shall be holy, because I <supplied>am</supplied> holy. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 11:46">46</verse-number>“ ‘This is the regulation of the animals<note>Collective singulars in this verse are plural by context</note> and the birds and all living creatures that move along in the water and <idiom-start/>concerning<idiom-end/><note>Literally “of”</note> all the creatures that swarm on the land, <verse-number id="Le 11:47">47</verse-number>to distinguish between the unclean and the clean and between the animal that is to be eaten and the animal that must not be eaten.’ ” </p>
		</chapter>