<chapter id="Le 12">
			<pericope>Purification After Childbirth</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 12:1">1</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Le 12:2">2</verse-number>“Speak to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> saying, ‘When a woman becomes pregnant and she gives birth to a male,<note>Or “son”</note> then<note>Or “and”</note> she shall be unclean seven days—as <supplied>in</supplied> the time of her menstrual bleeding, she shall become unclean. <verse-number id="Le 12:3">3</verse-number>And on the eighth day his foreskin’s flesh shall be circumcised. <verse-number id="Le 12:4">4</verse-number>And <supplied>for</supplied> thirty-three days she shall stay in the blood of <supplied>her</supplied> cleansing; she must not touch any holy <supplied>object</supplied>, and she may not come to the sanctuary until the fulfilling of the days of her cleansing. <verse-number id="Le 12:5">5</verse-number>But<note>Or “And”</note> if she gives birth to a female,<note>Or “daughter”</note> then<note>Or “and”</note> she shall be unclean <supplied>for</supplied> two weeks as <supplied>in</supplied> her menstruation, and <supplied>for</supplied> sixty-six days she shall stay <idiom-start/>through<idiom-end/><note>Or “at” or “on”</note> the blood of <supplied>her</supplied> cleansing. <verse-number id="Le 12:6">6</verse-number>And at the fulfilling of the days of her cleansing, <supplied>whether</supplied> for a son or for a daughter, she must bring to the priest at the tent of assembly’s entrance a <idiom-start/>yearling<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a son of his year”</note> male lamb as a burnt offering and <idiom-start/>young dove<idiom-end/><note>Literally “son of a dove”</note> or a turtledove as a sin offering. <verse-number id="Le 12:7">7</verse-number>And <supplied>the priest</supplied> shall present it <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> Yahweh, and he shall make atonement for her, so that<note>Or “and”</note> she shall be clean from the flow of her blood. This <supplied>is</supplied> the regulation of childbearing<note>Literally “the childbearing”</note> for the male<note>Or “son”</note> or for the female.<note>Or “daughter”</note> <verse-number id="Le 12:8">8</verse-number>And if <idiom-start/>she cannot afford<idiom-end/><note>Literally “her hand does not find enough”</note> a sheep,<note>Or “small livestock”</note> then<note>Or “and”</note> she shall take two turtledoves or two <idiom-start/>young doves<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons of a dove”</note>—one as a burnt offering and one as a sin offering—and the priest shall make atonement for her, so that<note>Or “and”</note> she shall be clean.’ ” </p>
		</chapter>