<chapter id="Le 13">
			<pericope>Regulations About Defiling Skin Diseases</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 13:1">1</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Yahweh spoke to Moses and to Aaron, saying, <verse-number id="Le 13:2">2</verse-number>“When a <idiom-start/>person<idiom-end/><note>Literally “man”</note> has on his body’s skin a swelling or an epidermal eruption or a spot and it becomes<note>Perfect of הָיָה followed by לְ; see HALOT 244 s.v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Le 13:7">7</cite>.c</note> an infectious skin disease on his body’s skin, then<note>Or “and”</note> he shall be brought to Aaron the priest or to one of his sons the priests. <verse-number id="Le 13:3">3</verse-number>And the priest shall examine the infection on his body’s skin, and <supplied>if</supplied> <supplied>the</supplied> hair in the infection turns white and the appearance of the infection <supplied>is</supplied> deeper than his body’s skin, it <supplied>is</supplied> an infectious skin disease, and the priest shall examine it, and he shall declare him unclean. <verse-number id="Le 13:4">4</verse-number>But<note>Or “And”</note> if a spot <supplied>is</supplied> white on his body’s skin and its appearance is not deeper than the skin and its hair does not turn white, then<note>Or “and”</note> the priest shall confine the afflicted person <supplied>for</supplied> seven days. <verse-number id="Le 13:5">5</verse-number>And the priest shall examine it on the seventh day, and <idiom-start/>if<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “look” or “behold”</note> in his eyes, the infection has stayed <supplied>unchanged</supplied>, the infection has not spread on the skin, then<note>Or “and”</note> the priest shall confine him <supplied>for</supplied> seven days <supplied>a</supplied> second <supplied>time</supplied>. <verse-number id="Le 13:6">6</verse-number>And the priest shall examine him on the seventh day <supplied>for a</supplied> second <supplied>time</supplied>, and <idiom-start/>if<idiom-end/><note>Literally “look” or “behold”</note> the infection has faded and the infection has not spread on the skin, then<note>Or “and”</note> the priest shall declare him clean—it <supplied>is</supplied> an epidermal eruption; and he shall wash his garments, and so he shall be clean. <verse-number id="Le 13:7">7</verse-number>But<note>Or “And”</note> if the epidermal eruption spreads further on the skin after showing himself to the priest for his cleansing, then<note>Or “and”</note> he shall appear <supplied>a</supplied> second <supplied>time</supplied> to the priest. <verse-number id="Le 13:8">8</verse-number>And the priest shall examine <supplied>it</supplied>,<note>The direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and <idiom-start/>if<idiom-end/><note>Literally “look” or “behold”</note> the epidermal eruption has spread on the skin, then<note>Or “and”</note> the priest shall declare him unclean—it is an infectious skin disease. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 13:9">9</verse-number>“When an infectious skin disease is on a person and he is brought to the priest, <verse-number id="Le 13:10">10</verse-number>the priest shall examine <supplied>it</supplied>,<note>The direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and <idiom-start/>if<idiom-end/><note>Literally “look” or “behold”</note> a white swelling <supplied>is</supplied> on the skin and it turns <supplied>the</supplied> hair white and <idiom-start/>raw flesh<idiom-end/><note>Literally “living of living flesh”</note> <supplied>is</supplied> in the swelling, <verse-number id="Le 13:11">11</verse-number>it <supplied>is</supplied> a chronic infectious skin disease on his body’s skin, and the priest shall declare him unclean; he shall not confine him, because he <supplied>is</supplied> unclean. <verse-number id="Le 13:12">12</verse-number>And if the infectious skin disease breaks out all over on the skin and the infectious skin disease covers all of the afflicted person’s skin from his head to his feed, <idiom-start/>so far as the priest can see<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “for all the sight of the eyes of the priest”</note> <verse-number id="Le 13:13">13</verse-number>then<note>Or “and”</note> the priest shall examine <supplied>it</supplied>,<note>The direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and <idiom-start/>if<idiom-end/><note>Literally “look” or “behold”</note> the infectious skin disease covers his whole body, then<note>Or “and”</note> he shall pronounce the afflicted person clean—all of it has turned white; he is clean. <verse-number id="Le 13:14">14</verse-number>But<note>Or “And”</note> <idiom-start/>whenever<idiom-end/><note>Literally “on a day”</note> <idiom-start/>raw flesh<idiom-end/><note>Literally “living flesh”</note> appears on him, he shall become unclean. <verse-number id="Le 13:15">15</verse-number>And the priest shall examine the <idiom-start/>raw flesh<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “living flesh”</note> and he shall pronounce him unclean—the <idiom-start/>raw flesh<idiom-end/><note>Literally “living flesh”</note> <supplied>is</supplied> unclean; it <supplied>is</supplied> an infectious skin disease. <verse-number id="Le 13:16">16</verse-number>Or, when the <idiom-start/>raw flesh<idiom-end/><note>Literally “living flesh”</note> returns and it has changed to white, then<note>Or “and”</note> he shall come to the priest, <verse-number id="Le 13:17">17</verse-number>and the priest shall examine him, and <idiom-start/>if<idiom-end/><note>Literally “look” or “behold”</note> the infection has changed to white, then<note>Or “and”</note> the priest shall pronounce the afflicted person clean—he is clean. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 13:18">18</verse-number>“And when <supplied>someone’s</supplied> body <idiom-start/>has<idiom-end/><note>Literally “becomes on it”</note> a skin sore on his skin and it is healed <verse-number id="Le 13:19">19</verse-number>and a white swelling or a <idiom-start/>pinkish<idiom-end/><note>Literally “white red”</note> spot appears in the skin sore’s place, then<note>Or “and”</note> he shall show himself to the priest. <verse-number id="Le 13:20">20</verse-number>And the priest shall examine <supplied>it</supplied>,<note>The direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and <idiom-start/>if<idiom-end/><note>Literally “look” or “behold”</note> its appearance <supplied>is</supplied> deeper than the skin and its hair has changed to white, then<note>Or “and”</note> the priest shall declare him unclean—it is an infectious skin disease; it has broken out in the skin sore. <verse-number id="Le 13:21">21</verse-number>And if the priest examines it and <idiom-start/>if<idiom-end/><note>Literally “look” or “behold”</note> there is no white hair in it and it is not deeper than the skin and it <supplied>is</supplied> faded, then<note>Or “and”</note> the priest shall confine him <supplied>for</supplied> seven days. <verse-number id="Le 13:22">22</verse-number>But<note>Or “And”</note> if it has spread further on the skin, then<note>Or “and”</note> the priest shall declare him unclean—it <supplied>is</supplied> an infection. <verse-number id="Le 13:23">23</verse-number>But<note>Or “And”</note> if the spot has stayed <supplied>unchanged</supplied>, it has not spread, it <supplied>is</supplied> the skin sore’s scar, so<note>Or “and”</note> the priest shall declare him clean. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 13:24">24</verse-number>“Or when a body <idiom-start/>has<idiom-end/><note>Literally “it becomes”</note> a burn-spot <idiom-start/>from<idiom-end/><note>Literally “of”</note> fire on its skin and the <idiom-start/>raw flesh<idiom-end/><note>Literally “living”</note> of the burn-spot <supplied>is</supplied> <idiom-start/>pinkish<idiom-end/><note>Literally “white red”</note> or white, <verse-number id="Le 13:25">25</verse-number>then<note>Or “and”</note> the priest shall examine it, and <idiom-start/>if<idiom-end/><note>Literally “look” or “behold”</note> the hair turns white in the spot and its appearance <supplied>is</supplied> deeper than the skin, it <supplied>is</supplied> an infectious skin disease—it has broken out in the burn-spot; so<note>Or “and”</note> the priest shall declare him unclean—it <supplied>is</supplied> an infectious skin disease. <verse-number id="Le 13:26">26</verse-number>But<note>Or “And”</note> if the priest examines it and <idiom-start/>if<idiom-end/><note>Literally “look” or “behold”</note> there is not white hair in the spot and it is not deeper than the skin and it <supplied>is</supplied> faded, then<note>Or “and”</note> the priest shall confine him <supplied>for</supplied> seven days. <verse-number id="Le 13:27">27</verse-number>And the priest shall examine him on the seventh day; if it has spread further on the skin, then<note>Or “and”</note> the priest shall declare him unclean—it <supplied>is</supplied> an infectious skin disease. <verse-number id="Le 13:28">28</verse-number>But<note>Or “And”</note> if it the spot has stayed <supplied>unchanged</supplied> in its place, it has not spread on the skin and it <supplied>is</supplied> faded, <supplied>then</supplied> it is the burn-spot’s swelling, so<note>Or “and”</note> the priest shall declare him clean, because it <supplied>is</supplied> the burn-spot’s scar. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 13:29">29</verse-number>“And when a man or a woman <idiom-start/>has<idiom-end/><note>Literally “becomes on him”</note> an infection on <supplied>the</supplied> head or in <supplied>the</supplied> beard, <verse-number id="Le 13:30">30</verse-number>then<note>Or “and”</note> the priest shall examine the infection, and <idiom-start/>if<idiom-end/><note>Literally “look” or “behold”</note> its appearance <supplied>is</supplied> deeper than the skin and in it <supplied>is</supplied> thin bright red hair, then<note>Or “and”</note> the priest shall declare it unclean—it <supplied>is</supplied> a diseased area of skin; it <supplied>is</supplied> an infectious skin disease of the head or the beard. <verse-number id="Le 13:31">31</verse-number>But<note>Or “And”</note> if the priest examines the diseased area of the skin’s infection and <idiom-start/>if<idiom-end/><note>Literally “look” or “behold”</note> its appearance is not deeper than the skin and there is no black hair in it, then<note>Or “and”</note> the priest shall confine the afflicted person <supplied>with</supplied> the diseased area of skin <supplied>for</supplied> seven days. <verse-number id="Le 13:32">32</verse-number>And the priest shall examine the infection on the seventh day, and <idiom-start/>if<idiom-end/><note>Literally “look” or “behold”</note> the diseased area of skin has not spread and it does not have bright red hair in it and the diseased area of the skin’s appearance is not deeper than the skin, <verse-number id="Le 13:33">33</verse-number>then<note>Or “and”</note> he shall shave himself, but<note>Or “and”</note> he shall not shave the diseased area of skin, and the priest shall confine <supplied>the person with</supplied><note>The direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> the diseased area of skin <supplied>a</supplied> second <supplied>time</supplied> <supplied>for</supplied> seven days. <verse-number id="Le 13:34">34</verse-number>And the priest shall examine the diseased area of skin on the seventh day, and <idiom-start/>if<idiom-end/><note>Literally “look” or “behold”</note> the diseased area has not spread on the skin and its appearance is not deeper than the skin, then<note>Or “and”</note> the priest shall pronounce him clean, and he shall wash his garments, and he shall be clean. <verse-number id="Le 13:35">35</verse-number>But<note>Or “And”</note> if the diseased area of skin has not spread further on the skin after his cleansing, <verse-number id="Le 13:36">36</verse-number>then<note>Or “and”</note> the priest shall examine him, and <idiom-start/>if<idiom-end/><note>Literally “look” or “behold”</note> the diseased area of skin has spread on the skin, the priest shall not inspect <supplied>for</supplied> bright<note>Hebrew “the bright”</note> red hair—he is unclean. <verse-number id="Le 13:37">37</verse-number>But<note>Or “And”</note> if, in his eyes, the diseased area of skin has stayed <supplied>unchanged</supplied> and black hair has grown in it, the diseased area of skin is healed—he is clean, and the priest shall pronounce him clean. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 13:38">38</verse-number>“And when a man or a woman <idiom-start/>has<idiom-end/><note>Literally “becomes”</note> spots on their body’s skin, white spots, <verse-number id="Le 13:39">39</verse-number>then<note>Or “and”</note> the priest shall examine <supplied>them</supplied>,<note>The direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and <idiom-start/>if<idiom-end/><note>Literally “look” or “behold”</note> <supplied>the</supplied> spots on their body’s skin <supplied>are</supplied> <supplied>a</supplied> faded white, it <supplied>is</supplied> a skin rash; it has broken out on the skin—it <supplied>is</supplied> clean. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 13:40">40</verse-number>“And if a man becomes bald, his head <supplied>is</supplied> bald, he <supplied>is</supplied> clean. <verse-number id="Le 13:41">41</verse-number>And if he becomes bald <idiom-start/>from his forehead<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from the forehead of his face”</note> his head <supplied>is</supplied> bald, he <supplied>is</supplied> clean. <verse-number id="Le 13:42">42</verse-number>But<note>Or “And”</note> if a <idiom-start/>pinkish<idiom-end/><note>Literally “white red”</note> infection occurs<note>Or “becomes” or “happens”</note> on the bald spot or on the bald forehead, it <supplied>is</supplied> an infectious skin disease that sprouts on his bald spot or on his bald forehead. <verse-number id="Le 13:43">43</verse-number>So<note>Or “And”</note> the priest shall examine him, and <idiom-start/>if<idiom-end/><note>Literally “look” or “behold”</note> the infection’s swelling <supplied>is</supplied> <idiom-start/>pinkish<idiom-end/><note>Literally “white red”</note> on his bald spot or on his bald forehead, like <supplied>the</supplied> appearance of an infectious skin disease <supplied>on</supplied><note>Literally “of”</note> the body, <verse-number id="Le 13:44">44</verse-number>he <supplied>is</supplied> a man afflicted with a skin disease—he <supplied>is</supplied> unclean; the priest certainly shall declare him unclean—his infection <supplied>is</supplied> on his head. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 13:45">45</verse-number>“As for<note>Or “And”</note> the person who is afflicted with a skin disease, his garments must be torn and his <idiom-start/>hair<idiom-end/><note>Literally “head”</note> must <supplied>be allowed to</supplied> hang loosely, and he must cover <supplied>his</supplied> upper lip, and he must call out, ‘Unclean! Unclean!’ <verse-number id="Le 13:46">46</verse-number><supplied>For</supplied> all <supplied>the</supplied> days <supplied>during</supplied> which the infection <supplied>is</supplied> on him, he shall be unclean; he must live alone; his dwelling <supplied>must be</supplied> <idiom-start/>outside the camp<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “from an outside place of the camp”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Regulations About Contaminated Fabrics</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 13:47">47</verse-number>“And when the garment <idiom-start/>has<idiom-end/><note>Literally “becomes”</note> an infectious skin disease<note>Perhaps better translated “mold” rather than “skin disease”</note> on it, on a wool garment<note>Literally “a garment of wool”</note> or on a linen garment,<note>Literally “a garment of linen”</note> <verse-number id="Le 13:48">48</verse-number>or on woven material or on a linen fabric, or<note>Or “and”</note> on wool or on leather or on any work of leather, <verse-number id="Le 13:49">49</verse-number>and <supplied>if</supplied> the infection is yellowish green or reddish on the garment or on the leather or on the woven material or on the fabric or on any leather object,<note>Literally “an object of leather”</note> it <supplied>is</supplied> an infectious skin disease<note>Perhaps better translated “mold” rather than “skin disease”</note> and it shall be shown <supplied>to</supplied> the priest. <verse-number id="Le 13:50">50</verse-number>And the priest shall examine the infection, and he shall confine the infected article <supplied>for</supplied> seven days. <verse-number id="Le 13:51">51</verse-number>And he shall examine the infection on the seventh day; if the infection has spread on the garment or on the woven material or on the fabric or on the leather, for any work for which the leather is used, the infection <supplied>is</supplied> a destructive skin disease<note>Perhaps better translated “mold” rather than “skin disease”</note>—it <supplied>is</supplied> unclean. <verse-number id="Le 13:52">52</verse-number>And he shall burn the garment or the woven material or the fabric, <idiom-start/>whether wool or linen<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “in/on the wool or in/on the linen”</note> or any leather object that <idiom-start/>has<idiom-end/><note>Literally “becomes on/in it”</note> the infection, because it <supplied>is</supplied> an infectious skin disease,<note>Perhaps better translated “mold” rather than “skin disease”</note> <supplied>which is</supplied> destructive—it must be burned in the fire. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 13:53">53</verse-number>“But<note>Or “And”</note> if the priest examines <supplied>it</supplied><note>The direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and <idiom-start/>if<idiom-end/><note>Literally “look” or “behold”</note> the infection has not spread on the garment or on the woven material or on the fabric or on any leather object, <verse-number id="Le 13:54">54</verse-number>then<note>Or “and”</note> the priest shall command, and <idiom-start/>someone<idiom-end/><note>Literally “he”</note> shall wash that on which the infection <supplied>is</supplied>, and he shall confine it <supplied>a</supplied> second <supplied>time</supplied> <supplied>for</supplied> seven days. <verse-number id="Le 13:55">55</verse-number>And the priest shall examine <supplied>it</supplied><note>The direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> after the infection has been washed off, and <idiom-start/>if<idiom-end/><note>Literally “look” or “behold”</note> the infection has not changed its outward appearance and the infection has not spread, it <supplied>is</supplied> unclean; he must burn it in the fire; it <supplied>is</supplied> a fungus on its back or on its front. <verse-number id="Le 13:56">56</verse-number>But<note>Or “And”</note> if the priest examines <supplied>it</supplied><note>The direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and <idiom-start/>if<idiom-end/><note>Literally “look” or “behold”</note> the infection <supplied>is</supplied> faded after it has been washed off, then<note>Or “and”</note> he shall tear it from the garment or from the leather or from the woven material or from the fabric. <verse-number id="Le 13:57">57</verse-number>And if it appears again on the garment or on the woven material or on the fabric or on any leather object, it <supplied>is</supplied> spreading; you<note>Singular</note> must burn in the fire that which <supplied>has</supplied> the infection in it. <verse-number id="Le 13:58">58</verse-number>And the garment or the woven material or the fabric or any leather object that he might wash and the infection is removed from them then<note>Or “and”</note> shall be washed <supplied>a</supplied> second <supplied>time</supplied>, and it shall be clean.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 13:59">59</verse-number>This <supplied>is</supplied> the regulation of the infectious skin disease<note>Perhaps better translated “mold” rather than “skin disease”</note> in<note>Hebrew “of”</note> the wool garment or the linen or the woven material or the fabric or any leather object to declare it clean or to declare it unclean. </p>
		</chapter>