<chapter id="Le 14">
			<pericope>Instructions for Cleansing Infectious Skin Diseases</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 14:1">1</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Le 14:2">2</verse-number>“This is the regulation of the person afflicted with a skin disease <idiom-start/>at the time of<idiom-end/><note>Or “on the day of”</note> his cleansing. And he shall be brought to the priest, <verse-number id="Le 14:3">3</verse-number>and the priest shall go <idiom-start/>outside the camp<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to from an outside place of the camp”</note> and the priest shall examine <supplied>him</supplied>,<note>The direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and <idiom-start/>if<idiom-end/><note>Literally “look” or “behold”</note> the skin disease’s infection is healed on<note>Hebrew “from”</note> the afflicted person, <verse-number id="Le 14:4">4</verse-number>then<note>Or “and”</note> the priest shall command, and he shall take two living, clean birds and <idiom-start/>cedar wood<idiom-end/><note>Literally “wood of cedar”</note> and <idiom-start/>a crimson thread<idiom-end/><note>Literally “crimson thread of <supplied>the</supplied> worm”</note> and hyssop for the one who presents himself for cleansing. <verse-number id="Le 14:5">5</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> the priest shall command <supplied>someone</supplied><note>The direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to slaughter one bird over fresh water in a clay vessel. <verse-number id="Le 14:6">6</verse-number>He must take the living bird and the <idiom-start/>cedar wood<idiom-end/><note>Literally “wood of cedar”</note> and <idiom-start/>the crimson thread<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the crimson thread of the worm”</note> and the hyssop, and he shall dip them and the living bird in the bird’s blood slaughtered over the fresh water. <verse-number id="Le 14:7">7</verse-number>And he shall spatter <supplied>the blood</supplied><note>The direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> seven times on the one who presents himself for cleansing from the infectious skin disease, and he shall declare him clean, and he shall send the living bird <idiom-start/>into the open field<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “toward the faces of the field”</note> <verse-number id="Le 14:8">8</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> the one who presents himself for cleansing shall wash his garments, and he shall shave off all his hair, and he shall wash himself in the water; thus<note>Or “and”</note> he shall be clean, and afterward he shall enter the camp, but<note>Or “and”</note> he shall stay <idiom-start/>outside his tent<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from an outside place of his tent”</note> <supplied>for</supplied> seven days. <verse-number id="Le 14:9">9</verse-number><idiom-start/>And then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And it shall be”</note> on the seventh day he must shave off all his hair—he must shave his head and his beard and <idiom-start/>his eyebrows<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the rims of his eyes”</note> and all <supplied>the rest</supplied><note>Implied by context</note> of his hair—and he shall wash his garments, and he shall wash his body in the water; thus<note>Or “and”</note> he shall be clean. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 14:10">10</verse-number>“And on the eighth day he must take two male lambs without defect and one ewe-lamb <idiom-start/>in its first year<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a daughter of her year”</note> without defect and three-tenths <supplied>of an ephah</supplied><note>Implied by context</note> of finely milled flour mixed with oil <supplied>as</supplied> a grain offering and one log of oil. <verse-number id="Le 14:11">11</verse-number>And the priest who cleanses <supplied>him</supplied><note>The direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> shall present the man who presents himself for cleansing and <idiom-start/>these things<idiom-end/><note>Literally “with them”</note> <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> the tent of assembly’s entrance. <verse-number id="Le 14:12">12</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> the priest shall take the one male lamb, and he shall present it as a guilt offering, and the log of oil, and he shall wave them <supplied>as</supplied> a wave offering <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> Yahweh. <verse-number id="Le 14:13">13</verse-number>And he shall slaughter the male lamb in the place where he slaughters the sin offering and the burnt offering in the sanctuary’s space,<note>Or “place” or “area”</note> because as the sin offering belongs to the priest, so <supplied>also</supplied> the guilt offering—<idiom-start/>it is a most holy thing<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “a holiness of holinesses <supplied>is</supplied> it”</note> <verse-number id="Le 14:14">14</verse-number>And the priest shall take <idiom-start/>some of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> the guilt offering’s blood, and the priest shall put <supplied>it</supplied><note>The direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> on the right ear’s lobe of the one who presents himself for cleansing and on his right hand’s thumb and on his right foot’s big toe. <verse-number id="Le 14:15">15</verse-number>And the priest shall take <idiom-start/>some of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> the log of oil, and he shall pour <supplied>it</supplied><note>The direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> on his<note>Hebrew “the priest’s”</note> left palm; <verse-number id="Le 14:16">16</verse-number>and the priest shall dip his right finger in the oil that <supplied>is</supplied> on his left palm, and he shall spatter <idiom-start/>some of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> the oil with his finger seven times <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> Yahweh. <verse-number id="Le 14:17">17</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> the priest shall put <idiom-start/>some of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> the remaining oil, which <supplied>is</supplied> on his palm, on the right ear’s lobe of the one to be cleansed and on his right hand’s thumb and on his right foot’s big toe, on <supplied>top of</supplied> the guilt offering’s blood.<note>See v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Le 14:14">14</cite></note> <verse-number id="Le 14:18">18</verse-number>And the remaining oil that <supplied>is</supplied> on the priest’s palm he shall put on the head of the one who presents himself for cleansing, and the priest shall make atonement for him <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> Yahweh. <verse-number id="Le 14:19">19</verse-number>Thus<note>Or “And”</note> the priest shall <idiom-start/>sacrifice<idiom-end/><note>Literally “do” or “make”</note> the sin offering, and he shall make atonement for the one who presents himself for cleansing from his uncleanness, and afterward he shall slaughter the burnt offering. <verse-number id="Le 14:20">20</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> the priest shall offer the burnt offering and the grain offering on the altar, and the priest shall make atonement for him, and so he shall be clean. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 14:21">21</verse-number>“But<note>Or “And”</note> if he <supplied>is</supplied> poor and <idiom-start/>he cannot afford<idiom-end/><note>Literally “his hand is not producing”</note> <supplied>it</supplied>,<note>The direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> then<note>Or “and”</note> he shall take one male lamb <supplied>for</supplied> a guilt offering as a wave offering to make atonement for himself and one-tenth <supplied>of an ephah</supplied><note>Implied by context</note> of finely milled flour mixed with oil for a grain offering, and a log of oil, <verse-number id="Le 14:22">22</verse-number>and two turtledoves or two <idiom-start/>young doves<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons of dove”</note> that <idiom-start/>he can afford<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “his hand can produce”</note> and one shall be a sin offering and the <idiom-start/>other<idiom-end/><note>Literally “one”</note> a burnt offering. <verse-number id="Le 14:23">23</verse-number>And he shall bring them to the priest at the tent of assembly’s entrance <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> Yahweh on the eighth day for his cleansing. <verse-number id="Le 14:24">24</verse-number>And the priest shall take the male lamb <supplied>for</supplied> the guilt offering and the log of oil, and the priest shall wave them <supplied>as</supplied> a wave offering <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> Yahweh; <verse-number id="Le 14:25">25</verse-number>and he shall slaughter the male lamb of the guilt offering, and the priest shall take <idiom-start/>some of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> the guilt offering’s blood, and he shall put <supplied>it</supplied><note>The direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> on the right ear’s lobe of the one who presents himself for cleansing and on his right hand’s thumb and on his right foot’s big toe. <verse-number id="Le 14:26">26</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> the priest shall pour out <idiom-start/>some of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> the oil on his own<note>Hebrew “the priest’s”</note> left palm, <verse-number id="Le 14:27">27</verse-number>and with his right finger the priest shall spatter <idiom-start/>some of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> the oil that <supplied>is</supplied> on his left palm seven times <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> Yahweh. <verse-number id="Le 14:28">28</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> the priest shall put <idiom-start/>some of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> the oil that <supplied>is</supplied> on his palm on the right ear’s lobe of the one who presents himself for cleansing and on his right hand’s thumb and on his right foot’s big toe on the place of the guilt offering’s blood. <verse-number id="Le 14:29">29</verse-number>And the remaining oil that <supplied>is</supplied> on the priest’s palm he shall put on the head of the one who presents himself for cleansing to make atonement for him <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> Yahweh. <verse-number id="Le 14:30">30</verse-number>And he shall <idiom-start/>sacrifice<idiom-end/><note>Literally “do” or “make”</note> one of the turtledoves or the <idiom-start/>young doves<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons of dove”</note> that <idiom-start/>he can afford<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “his hand can produce”</note> <verse-number id="Le 14:31">31</verse-number><supplied>even</supplied><note>Implied by context</note> what <idiom-start/>he can afford<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “his hand can produce”</note> the one <supplied>as</supplied> a sin offering and the <idiom-start/>other<idiom-end/><note>Literally “one”</note> <supplied>as</supplied> a burnt offering in addition to the grain offering, and the priest shall make atonement for the one who presents himself for cleansing <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> Yahweh. <verse-number id="Le 14:32">32</verse-number>This <supplied>is</supplied> the regulation of <supplied>the one</supplied> on whom <supplied>is</supplied> an infectious skin disease who <idiom-start/>cannot afford<idiom-end/><note>Literally “his hand cannot produce”</note> <supplied>the cost</supplied><note>The direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> for his cleansing.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Instructions for Cleansing Houses</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 14:33">33</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Yahweh spoke to Moses and to Aaron, saying, <verse-number id="Le 14:34">34</verse-number>“When you come into the land of Canaan, which I <supplied>am about to</supplied> give to you <supplied>as your</supplied> possession, and I put <idiom-start/>mildew<idiom-end/><note>Literally “an infection of skin disease”</note> in a house <supplied>in</supplied> the land of your possession, <verse-number id="Le 14:35">35</verse-number>then<note>Or “and”</note> the one who <idiom-start/>owns the house<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the house <supplied>is</supplied> for him”</note> shall come and tell the priest, saying, ‘It appears to me <supplied>that</supplied> an infection <supplied>is</supplied> in the house.’ <verse-number id="Le 14:36">36</verse-number>And the priest shall <supplied>issue a</supplied> command, and they shall clear out the house before the priest comes to examine the infection, so that<note>Or “and”</note> all that <supplied>is</supplied> in the house might not become unclean; and <idiom-start/>afterward<idiom-end/><note>Literally “after thus”</note> the priest shall go to examine the house. <verse-number id="Le 14:37">37</verse-number>And he shall examine the infection, and <idiom-start/>if<idiom-end/><note>Literally “look” or “behold”</note> the infection on the house’s wall <supplied>has</supplied> yellowish-green or reddish spots and its appearance <supplied>is</supplied> deeper than <supplied>the surface of</supplied><note>Implied by the context</note> the wall, <verse-number id="Le 14:38">38</verse-number>then<note>Or “and”</note> the priest shall go out from the house to the house’s entrance, and he shall confine<note>Or “close up”</note> the house <supplied>for</supplied> seven days. <verse-number id="Le 14:39">39</verse-number>And the priest shall return on the seventh day, and he shall examine <supplied>the infection</supplied>,<note>The direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and <idiom-start/>if<idiom-end/><note>Literally “look” or “behold”</note> the infection has spread on the house’s wall, <verse-number id="Le 14:40">40</verse-number>the priest shall <supplied>issue a</supplied> command and they shall remove the stones on which <supplied>is</supplied> the infection, and they shall throw them <idiom-start/>outside the city<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to from an outside place of the city”</note> on an unclean place. <verse-number id="Le 14:41">41</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> they<note>Hebrew “he”</note> shall scrape off <supplied>the plaster</supplied><note>The direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> from all around the house, and they shall pour out the plaster,<note>See HALOT 862 s.v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Le 14:3">3</cite>.b</note> which they scraped off, <idiom-start/>outside the city<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to from an outside place of the city”</note> on an unclean place. <verse-number id="Le 14:42">42</verse-number>And they shall take other stones, and they shall <idiom-start/>put<idiom-end/><note>Literally “bring”</note> <supplied>them</supplied> in place of <supplied>those</supplied> stones, and they<note>Hebrew “he”</note> shall take other plaster,<note>See HALOT 862 s.v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Le 14:3">3</cite>.b</note> and they<note>Hebrew “he”</note> shall replaster<note>Implied by the context; Hebrew “plaster”</note> the house. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 14:43">43</verse-number>“But<note>Or “And”</note> if the infection should return and it breaks out in the house after they<note>Hebrew “he”</note> have removed the stones and after scraping off <supplied>the plaster</supplied><note>The direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> of the house and after it has been replastered,<note>Implied by the context; or “plaster”</note> <verse-number id="Le 14:44">44</verse-number>then<note>Or “and”</note> the priest shall come, and he shall examine <supplied>the infection</supplied>,<note>The direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and <idiom-start/>if<idiom-end/><note>Literally “look” or “behold”</note> the infection has spread in the house, it <supplied>is</supplied> a destructive <idiom-start/>mildew<idiom-end/><note>Literally “infectious disease”</note> in the house—it <supplied>is</supplied> unclean. <verse-number id="Le 14:45">45</verse-number>So<note>Or “And”</note> he shall break down the house, its stones and its wood and all of the house’s plaster,<note>See HALOT 862 s.v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Le 14:3">3</cite>.b</note> and he shall bring <supplied>it all</supplied><note>The direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <idiom-start/>outside the city<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to from an outside place of the city”</note> to an unclean place. <verse-number id="Le 14:46">46</verse-number>And the person who enters into the house <supplied>during</supplied> all <supplied>the</supplied> days <supplied>that</supplied> he<note>That is, the priest</note> confined<note>Or “closed up”</note> it shall become unclean until the evening. <verse-number id="Le 14:47">47</verse-number>And the person who sleeps in the house must wash his garments, and the person who eats in the house shall wash his garments. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 14:48">48</verse-number>“And if the priest comes again and examines <supplied>the house</supplied><note>The direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and <idiom-start/>if<idiom-end/><note>Literally “look” or “behold”</note> the infection has not spread in the house after being replastered,<note>Implied by the context; or “plaster”</note> then<note>Or “and”</note> the priest shall pronounce the house clean, because the infection is healed. <verse-number id="Le 14:49">49</verse-number>And he shall take two birds and <idiom-start/>cedar wood<idiom-end/><note>Literally “wood of cedar”</note> and a <idiom-start/>crimson thread<idiom-end/><note>Literally “crimson thread of <supplied>the</supplied> worm”</note> and hyssop to cleanse the house; <verse-number id="Le 14:50">50</verse-number>and he shall slaughter the first bird over fresh water on a clay vessel. <verse-number id="Le 14:51">51</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> he shall take the <idiom-start/>cedar wood<idiom-end/><note>Literally “wood of cedar”</note> and the hyssop and <idiom-start/>the crimson thread<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the crimson thread of the worm”</note> and the living bird, and he shall dip them in the slaughtered bird’s blood and in the fresh water, and he shall spatter <supplied>them</supplied><note>The direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> on the house seven times. <verse-number id="Le 14:52">52</verse-number>Thus<note>Or “And”</note> he shall purify the house with the bird’s blood and with the fresh water and with the living bird and with the <idiom-start/>cedar wood<idiom-end/><note>Literally “wood of cedar”</note> and with the hyssop and with <idiom-start/>the crimson thread<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the crimson thread of the worm”</note> <verse-number id="Le 14:53">53</verse-number>And he shall send the living bird <idiom-start/>outside the city<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to from an outside place of the city”</note> <idiom-start/>into the open field<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “to the faces of the field”</note> and so he shall make atonement for the house, and it shall be clean. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 14:54">54</verse-number>“This <supplied>is</supplied> the instruction for any infectious skin disease and for the diseased area of skin, <verse-number id="Le 14:55">55</verse-number>and for a <idiom-start/>mildew<idiom-end/><note>Literally “infectious skin disease”</note> of the garment and for the house, <verse-number id="Le 14:56">56</verse-number>and for the swelling and for the epidermal eruption and for the spot, <verse-number id="Le 14:57">57</verse-number>to teach <idiom-start/>when something is unclean and when something is clean<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “on the day of the unclean and on the day of the clean”</note> This <supplied>is</supplied> the regulation of the infectious skin disease.” </p>
		</chapter>