<chapter id="Le 15">
			<pericope>Instructions About Bodily Discharges</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 15:1">1</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Yahweh spoke to Moses and to Aaron, saying, <verse-number id="Le 15:2">2</verse-number>“Speak to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and you shall say to them, ‘<idiom-start/>Any man<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a man a man”</note> when a fluid discharge occurs<note>Or “becomes” or “shall be”</note> from his body, his fluid discharge <supplied>is</supplied> unclean. <verse-number id="Le 15:3">3</verse-number>And this becomes his uncleanness in his fluid discharge: <supplied>whether</supplied> his body secretes his fluid discharge or his body blocks his fluid discharge, it <supplied>is</supplied> his uncleanness. <verse-number id="Le 15:4">4</verse-number>Any bed upon which the person who discharges lies down becomes unclean, and any object upon which he sits becomes unclean. <verse-number id="Le 15:5">5</verse-number>And anyone who touches his bed must wash his garments and shall wash<note>Or “bathe”</note> <supplied>himself</supplied><note>The direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> with water, and he shall be unclean until evening. <verse-number id="Le 15:6">6</verse-number>And the person who sits on the object upon which the person who discharges has sat must wash his garments, and he shall wash<note>Or “bathe”</note> <supplied>himself</supplied><note>The direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> with water, and he shall be unclean until the evening. <verse-number id="Le 15:7">7</verse-number>And the person who touches the body of the person who discharges must wash his garments, and he shall wash<note>Or “bathe”</note> <supplied>himself</supplied><note>The direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> with water, and he shall be unclean until the evening. <verse-number id="Le 15:8">8</verse-number>And if the person who discharges spits on <supplied>one who is</supplied><note>The generic article designating a class of persons or things</note> clean, then<note>Or “and”</note> that one<note>Hebrew “he”</note> shall wash is garments, and he shall wash <supplied>himself</supplied><note>The direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> with water, and he shall be unclean until the evening. <verse-number id="Le 15:9">9</verse-number>And any saddle upon which the person who discharges rides becomes unclean. <verse-number id="Le 15:10">10</verse-number>And any person who touches anything that happened to be under him becomes unclean until the evening, and the person who carries them must wash his garments, and he shall wash <supplied>himself</supplied><note>The direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> with water, and he shall be unclean until the evening. <verse-number id="Le 15:11">11</verse-number>And anyone whom the person who discharges might touch <idiom-start/>without<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and not”</note> rinsing off his hands with water shall wash his garments, and he shall wash <supplied>himself</supplied><note>The direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> with water, and he shall be unclean until the evening. <verse-number id="Le 15:12">12</verse-number>But<note>Or “And”</note> a clay vessel that the person who discharges touches must be broken, and any <idiom-start/>wood object<idiom-end/><note>Literally “object of wood”</note> must be rinsed with water. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 15:13">13</verse-number>“ ‘And when the person who discharges becomes clean from his body fluid discharge, he shall count<note>Literally “and he shall count”</note> for himself seven days for his cleansing; then<note>Or “and”</note> he shall wash his garments, and he shall wash his body with <idiom-start/>fresh<idiom-end/><note>Or “running”; literally “living”</note> water, and he shall be clean. <verse-number id="Le 15:14">14</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> on the eighth day he shall take for himself two turtledoves or two <idiom-start/>young doves<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons of dove”</note> and he shall come <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> Yahweh at <supplied>the</supplied> tent of assembly’s entrance, and he shall give them to the priest. <verse-number id="Le 15:15">15</verse-number>And the priest shall <idiom-start/>sacrifice<idiom-end/><note>Literally “do” or “make”</note> one <supplied>as</supplied> a sin offering and <idiom-start/>the other<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the one”</note> <supplied>as</supplied> a burnt offering, and so the priest shall make atonement for him <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> Yahweh from his body fluid discharge. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 15:16">16</verse-number>“ ‘And if an emission of semen goes out from anyone, then<note>Or “and”</note> he shall wash all of his body with water, and he shall be unclean until the evening. <verse-number id="Le 15:17">17</verse-number>And any garment and anything leather on which is an emission of semen shall be washed with water, and it shall be unclean until the evening. <verse-number id="Le 15:18">18</verse-number>If<note>Or “And”</note> <supplied>there is</supplied> a woman with whom a man lies down <supplied>and there is</supplied> an emission of semen, then<note>Or “and”</note> they shall wash <supplied>themselves</supplied><note>The direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> with water, and they shall be unclean until the evening. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 15:19">19</verse-number>“ ‘And when a woman <idiom-start/>is menstruating<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “is discharging blood”</note> her body fluid discharge occurs in<note>Or “from”</note> her body; for seven days she shall be in her menstruation, and any person who touches her shall become unclean until the evening. <verse-number id="Le 15:20">20</verse-number>And anything upon which she lies down during her menstruation shall become unclean, and anything upon which she sits shall become unclean. <verse-number id="Le 15:21">21</verse-number>And any person who touches her bed must wash his garments, and he shall wash <supplied>himself</supplied><note>The direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> with water, and he shall be unclean until the evening. <verse-number id="Le 15:22">22</verse-number>And any person who touches any object on which she sat must wash his garments, and he shall wash <supplied>himself</supplied><note>The direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> with water, and he shall be unclean until the evening. <verse-number id="Le 15:23">23</verse-number>And if it <supplied>is</supplied> on the bed or on the object on which she sits, at his touching it he becomes unclean until the evening. <verse-number id="Le 15:24">24</verse-number>And if a man indeed lies with her and her menstruation occurs on him, then<note>Or “and”</note> he shall be unclean <supplied>for</supplied> seven days, and any bed on which he lies down becomes unclean. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 15:25">25</verse-number>“ ‘And when a woman discharges a body fluid <supplied>consisting</supplied> of her blood <supplied>for</supplied> many days, <supplied>but</supplied> not <supplied>at</supplied> the time of her menstruation, or when she discharges in addition to<note>Or “beyond”</note> her menstruation, all the days of her unclean body fluid discharge she shall become unclean as <supplied>in</supplied> the days of her menstruation. <verse-number id="Le 15:26">26</verse-number>Any bed on which she lies <supplied>during</supplied> all the days of her body fluid discharge shall become for her as her bed of menstruation, and any object on which she sits becomes unclean as her menstruation’s uncleanness. <verse-number id="Le 15:27">27</verse-number>And any person who touches them becomes unclean, and he shall wash his garments, and he shall wash <supplied>himself</supplied><note>The direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> with water, and he shall be unclean until the evening. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 15:28">28</verse-number>“ ‘And if she is clean from her body fluid discharge, then<note>Or “and”</note> she shall count for herself seven days, and afterward she becomes clean. <verse-number id="Le 15:29">29</verse-number>And on the eighth day she shall take for herself two turtledoves or two <idiom-start/>young doves<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons of dove”</note> and she shall bring them to the priest at <supplied>the</supplied> tent of assembly’s entrance. <verse-number id="Le 15:30">30</verse-number>And the priest shall <idiom-start/>sacrifice<idiom-end/><note>Literally “do” or “make”</note> the one <supplied>as</supplied> a sin offering and the <idiom-start/>other<idiom-end/><note>Literally “one”</note> <supplied>as</supplied> a burnt offering, and so the priest shall make atonement for her <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the the faces of”</note> Yahweh from her unclean body fluid discharge.’ </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 15:31">31</verse-number>“And you shall keep the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> separate from their uncleanness so that they might not die because of<note>Or “by” or “in”</note> their uncleanness by their making my tabernacle, which <supplied>is</supplied> in their midst, unclean. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 15:32">32</verse-number>“This <supplied>is</supplied> the regulation of <supplied>the one with</supplied> the body fluid discharge and <supplied>the one</supplied> from whom an emission of semen goes out so that he becomes unclean by it <verse-number id="Le 15:33">33</verse-number>and <idiom-start/>concerning<idiom-end/><note>Literally “of”</note> the menstruating <supplied>woman</supplied> in her bleeding<note>See similar idiom at 12:2</note> and the person who discharges his body fluid, for the male and for the female and for a man who lies with an unclean woman.” </p>
		</chapter>