<chapter id="Le 16">
			<pericope>The Day of Atonement</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 16:1">1</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Yahweh spoke to Moses after the death of Aaron’s two sons, when they had come near <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “before faces of”</note> Yahweh and they died. <verse-number id="Le 16:2">2</verse-number>And Yahweh said to Moses, “Tell<note>Or “Speak to”</note> your brother Aaron <supplied>that</supplied> he should not enter at any time into the sanctuary <idiom-start/>behind<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from the interior/inside to”</note> the curtain <idiom-start/>in front of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> the atonement cover that <supplied>is</supplied> on the ark, so that he might not die, because I appear in the cloud over the atonement cover. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 16:3">3</verse-number>“Aaron must enter the sanctuary with this: <idiom-start/>a young bull<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a bull a son of cattle”</note> as a sin offering and a ram as a burnt offering. <verse-number id="Le 16:4">4</verse-number>He must put on <idiom-start/>a holy linen tunic<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “a tunic of linen of holiness”</note> and linen undergarments must be on his body, and he must fasten <supplied>himself</supplied><note>The direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> with a linen sash, and he must wrap a linen turban around <supplied>his head</supplied><note>Supplied from context in the English translation</note>—they <supplied>are</supplied> holy garments, and he shall wash his body with water, then<note>Or “and”</note> he shall put them on. <verse-number id="Le 16:5">5</verse-number>And he must take from the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>’<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> community two he-goats as a sin offering and one ram as a burnt offering. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 16:6">6</verse-number>“And Aaron shall present the sin offering’s bull, which <supplied>is</supplied> for himself, and so he shall make atonement for himself and for his family. <verse-number id="Le 16:7">7</verse-number>And he shall take the two goats, and he shall present them <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> Yahweh <supplied>at the</supplied> tent of assembly’s entrance. <verse-number id="Le 16:8">8</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Aaron shall cast lots for the two goats: one lot for Yahweh and one for Azazel. <verse-number id="Le 16:9">9</verse-number>And Aaron shall present the goat on which the lot for Yahweh fell, and he shall <idiom-start/>sacrifice<idiom-end/><note>Literally “do” or “make”</note> it <supplied>as</supplied> a sin offering. <verse-number id="Le 16:10">10</verse-number>But<note>Or “And”</note> he must present alive <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> Yahweh the goat on which the lot for Azazel fell to make atonement for himself, to send it away into the desert to Azazel. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 16:11">11</verse-number>“And Aaron shall present the sin offering’s bull, which <supplied>is</supplied> for himself, and so he shall make atonement for himself and for his family; then<note>Or “and”</note> he shall slaughter the sin offering’s bull, which <supplied>is</supplied> for himself. <verse-number id="Le 16:12">12</verse-number>And he shall take a<note>Hebrew “the”</note> censer full of <idiom-start/>burning charcoal<idiom-end/><note>Literally “burning charcoal of fire”</note> from upon the altar from <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> Yahweh and <idiom-start/>two handfuls<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the fullness of the hollow of his hands”</note> of incense of powdered fragrant perfumes, and he shall bring <supplied>it</supplied> <idiom-start/>from behind<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from the interior/inside of”</note> the curtain, <verse-number id="Le 16:13">13</verse-number>and he shall put the incense on the fire <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> Yahweh so that the cloud of incense might cover the atonement cover, which <supplied>is</supplied> on the <idiom-start/>covenant text<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “testimony”</note> so that he might not die. <verse-number id="Le 16:14">14</verse-number>And he shall take <idiom-start/>some of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> the bull’s blood, and he shall spatter <supplied>it</supplied><note>The direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> with his finger on the atonement cover’s surface on the eastern <supplied>side</supplied>, and <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> the atonement cover he shall spatter <idiom-start/>some of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> the blood with his finger seven times. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 16:15">15</verse-number>“And he shall slaughter the sin offering’s goat, which <supplied>is</supplied> for the people, and he shall bring its blood <idiom-start/>from behind<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from the interior/inside of”</note> the curtain, and he shall do with its blood as that which he did with<note>Hebrew “to”</note> the bull’s blood, and he shall spatter it on the atonement cover and <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> the atonement cover. <verse-number id="Le 16:16">16</verse-number>Thus<note>Or “And”</note> he shall make atonement for the sanctuary from the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>’<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> impurities and from their transgressions for all their sins; and so he must do for <supplied>the</supplied> tent of assembly, which dwells with them in the midst of their impurities. <verse-number id="Le 16:17">17</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>no person<idiom-end/><note>Literally “any man not”</note> shall be in <supplied>the</supplied> tent of assembly when he enters to make atonement in the sanctuary until he comes out, and so he shall make atonement for himself and for his family and for all of Israel’s assembly. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 16:18">18</verse-number>“Then<note>Or “And”</note> he shall go out to the altar that <supplied>is</supplied> <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> Yahweh, and he shall make atonement for it; and he shall take <idiom-start/>some of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> the bull’s blood and <idiom-start/>some of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> the goat’s blood, and he shall put <supplied>it</supplied><note>The direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> all around on the altar’s horns. <verse-number id="Le 16:19">19</verse-number>And he shall spatter <idiom-start/>some of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> the blood on it seven times with his finger, and he shall cleanse it and consecrate<note>Literally “he shall consecrate”</note> it from the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>’<note>Literally “of the sons/children of Israel”</note> impurities. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 16:20">20</verse-number>“And he shall finish making atonement <supplied>for</supplied> the sanctuary and <supplied>the</supplied> tent of assembly and the altar; then<note>Or “and”</note> he shall present the living goat. <verse-number id="Le 16:21">21</verse-number>And Aaron shall place his two hands on the living goat’s head, and he shall confess over it all the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>’<note>Literally “of the sons/of the children of Israel”</note> iniquities and all their transgressions for all their sins, and he shall put them on the goat’s head, and he shall send <supplied>it</supplied><note>The direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> away into the desert <idiom-start/>with<idiom-end/><note>Literally “by <supplied>the</supplied> hand of”</note> a man <supplied>standing</supplied> ready.<note>Or “at hand”</note> <verse-number id="Le 16:22">22</verse-number>Thus<note>Or “And”</note> the goat shall bear on it to <idiom-start/>a barren region<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a land of separation” or “a land of infertility”</note> all their guilt, and he shall send the goat away into the desert. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 16:23">23</verse-number>“And Aaron shall enter <supplied>the</supplied> tent of assembly, and he shall take off the linen garments that he put on at his coming to the sanctuary, and he shall leave them there. <verse-number id="Le 16:24">24</verse-number>And he shall wash his body with water in a holy place, and he shall put on his garments and go out and <idiom-start/>sacrifice<idiom-end/><note>Literally “he shall do” or “he shall make”</note> his burnt offering and the people’s burnt offering, and so he shall make atonement for himself and for people. <verse-number id="Le 16:25">25</verse-number>And he must turn into smoke the sin offering’s fat on the altar. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 16:26">26</verse-number>“And the person who sends out the goat for Azazel shall wash his garments, and he shall wash his body with water, and <idiom-start/>afterward<idiom-end/><note>Literally “after thus”</note> he shall come to the camp. <verse-number id="Le 16:27">27</verse-number>And the sin offering’s bull and the sin offering’s goat, whose blood was brought to make atonement in the sanctuary, shall be brought <idiom-start/>outside the camp<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to from an outside place of the camp”</note> and they shall burn their hide and their flesh and their offal in the fire. <verse-number id="Le 16:28">28</verse-number>And the person who burns them shall wash his garments, and he shall wash his body with water, and <idiom-start/>afterward<idiom-end/><note>Literally “after thus”</note> he must come to the camp. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 16:29">29</verse-number>“And this shall be <idiom-start/>a lasting statute<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a statute of eternity” or “a statute of long duration”</note> for you: in the seventh month, on the tenth of the month, you must deny yourselves and you must not do any work, <supplied>whether</supplied> the native or<note>Or “and”</note> the alien who is dwelling in your midst, <verse-number id="Le 16:30">30</verse-number>because on this day he shall make atonement for you to cleanse you; you must be clean from all your sins <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> Yahweh. <verse-number id="Le 16:31">31</verse-number>It <supplied>is</supplied> <idiom-start/>a Sabbath of complete rest<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a Sabbath of ‘Sabbathation.’ ” “Sabbathation” is not a real word, but it is devised as an attempt to convey the sounds of the related nouns in the Hebrew phrase</note> for you, and you shall deny yourselves—<supplied>it is</supplied> <idiom-start/>a lasting statute<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “a statute of eternity” or “a statute of long duration”</note> <verse-number id="Le 16:32">32</verse-number>And the priest who is anointed and who is <idiom-start/>ordained<idiom-end/><note>Literally “filled his hand”</note> to serve as a priest in place of his father shall make atonement; thus<note>Or “and”</note> he shall put on the linen garments, the holy garments, <verse-number id="Le 16:33">33</verse-number>and he shall make atonement for the sanctuary’s holy place, and he shall make atonement for <supplied>the</supplied> tent of assembly and the altar, and he shall make atonement for the priests and for all of the assembly’s people. <verse-number id="Le 16:34">34</verse-number>And this shall be <idiom-start/>a lasting statute<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a statute of eternity” or “a statute of long duration”</note> for you to make atonement for the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> one time in a year from all their sins.” </p>
		</chapter>