<chapter id="Le 17">
			<pericope>The Place of Sacrifice</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 17:1">1</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Le 17:2">2</verse-number>“Speak to Aaron and to his sons and to all the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and you shall say to them, ‘This is the word that Yahweh has commanded, saying, <verse-number id="Le 17:3">3</verse-number>“<idiom-start/>Any man<idiom-end/><note>Literally “A man a man”</note> from the house of Israel who slaughters an ox or a sheep or a goat in the camp or who slaughters <supplied>it</supplied> <idiom-start/>outside the camp<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from an outside place of the camp”</note> <verse-number id="Le 17:4">4</verse-number>and he does not bring it to the tent of assembly’s entrance to present an offering to Yahweh <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> Yahweh’s tabernacle, then<note>Or “and”</note> that man shall be accounted bloodguilty—he has poured out blood, and that man shall be cut off from the midst of his people. <verse-number id="Le 17:5">5</verse-number><supplied>This is</supplied> so that the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> may bring their sacrifices that they are sacrificing <idiom-start/>in the open field<idiom-end/><note>Literally “on the faces of the field”</note> and bring<note>Or “they shall bring”</note> them for Yahweh to <supplied>the</supplied> tent of assembly’s entrance to the priest, and they shall sacrifice fellowship offerings for Yahweh with them. <verse-number id="Le 17:6">6</verse-number>And the priest shall sprinkle the blood on Yahweh’s altar <supplied>at the</supplied> tent of assembly’s entrance, and he shall <idiom-start/>burn<idiom-end/><note>Literally “turn into smoke”</note> the fat as an appeasing fragrance for Yahweh. <verse-number id="Le 17:7">7</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>they may no longer sacrifice<idiom-end/><note>Literally “not they may sacrifice again”</note> their sacrifices to the goat-idols after which they were prostituting. This is <idiom-start/>a lasting statute<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a statute of eternity” or “a statute of long duration”</note> for them <idiom-start/>throughout<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to”</note> their generations.” ’ </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Instructions Against Eating Blood</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 17:8">8</verse-number>“And you shall say to them, ‘<supplied>if there is</supplied> <idiom-start/>anyone<idiom-end/><note>Literally “A man a man”</note> from the house of Israel or<note>Or “and”</note> from the alien who dwells in their midst who offers a burnt offering or a sacrifice <verse-number id="Le 17:9">9</verse-number>and he does not bring it to <supplied>the</supplied> tent of assembly’s entrance to <idiom-start/>sacrifice<idiom-end/><note>Literally “do” or “make”</note> it for Yahweh, then<note>Or “and”</note> that man shall be cut off from his people. <verse-number id="Le 17:10">10</verse-number>And <supplied>if there is</supplied> <idiom-start/>anyone<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a man a man”</note> from the house of Israel or<note>Or “and”</note> from the alien who is dwelling in their midst who eats any blood, then<note>Or “and”</note> I will set my face against the person who eats the blood, and I will cut him off from among his people. <verse-number id="Le 17:11">11</verse-number>Indeed<note>Or “Because”</note> the flesh’s life <supplied>is</supplied> in the blood, and I have given it to you on the altar to make atonement for your lives, because it <supplied>is</supplied> the blood with the life that makes atonement. <verse-number id="Le 17:12">12</verse-number><idiom-start/>Therefore<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Unto thus”</note> I said to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> ‘<idiom-start/>None of you<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all of individual self from you not”</note> may eat blood, nor<note>Or “and not”</note> may the alien who is dwelling in your midst eat blood.’ </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 17:13">13</verse-number>“And <supplied>if there is</supplied> <idiom-start/>anyone<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a man a man”</note> from the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> or<note>Or “and”</note> from the alien who is dwelling in their midst who hunts a wild game animal or a bird that may be eaten, then<note>Or “and”</note> he shall pour out its blood, and he shall cover it with the soil. <verse-number id="Le 17:14">14</verse-number>Indeed,<note>Or “Because”</note> <supplied>the</supplied> life of all flesh, its blood, <supplied>is</supplied> in its life, so<note>Or “and”</note> I said to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> ‘You may not eat <supplied>the</supplied> blood of any flesh, because <supplied>the</supplied> life of all flesh <supplied>is</supplied> its blood; anyone who eats it must be cut off.’ </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 17:15">15</verse-number>“And <supplied>if there is</supplied> any person who eats a dead body or<note>Or “and”</note> a mangled carcass, <supplied>whether</supplied> among the native or<note>Or “and”</note> among the alien, then<note>Or “and”</note> he shall wash his garments, and he shall wash <supplied>himself</supplied><note>The direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> with water, and he shall be unclean until the evening, and he shall be clean. <verse-number id="Le 17:16">16</verse-number>But<note>Or “And”</note> if he does not wash <supplied>his garments</supplied><note>The direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and he does not wash his body, then<note>Or “and”</note> he shall bear his guilt.” </p>
		</chapter>