<chapter id="Le 18">
			<pericope>Unlawful Sexual Relations</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 18:1">1</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Le 18:2">2</verse-number>“Speak to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and say to them, ‘I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh your God. <verse-number id="Le 18:3">3</verse-number>You must not <idiom-start/>carry out<idiom-end/><note>Literally “do”</note> the practices of the land of Egypt, in which you lived, and you must not <idiom-start/>carry out<idiom-end/><note>Literally “do”</note> the practices of the land of Canaan, to which I am bringing you; and you must not follow their statutes. <verse-number id="Le 18:4">4</verse-number>You must <idiom-start/>carry out<idiom-end/><note>Literally “do”</note> my regulations, and you must observe<note>Or “keep”</note> my statutes by following them; I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh your God. <verse-number id="Le 18:5">5</verse-number>And you shall observe<note>Or “keep”</note> my statutes and my regulations <idiom-start/>by which the person doing them shall live<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “which the man does them and he shall live in them”</note> I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 18:6">6</verse-number>“ ‘<idiom-start/>None<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a man a man … not”</note> <supplied>of</supplied> you shall approach anyone <supplied>who is</supplied> <idiom-start/>his close relative<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the flesh of his body”</note> to expose nakedness; I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh. <verse-number id="Le 18:7">7</verse-number>You must not expose your father’s nakedness or<note>Or “and”</note> your mother’s nakedness—she <supplied>is</supplied> your mother; you must not expose her nakedness. <verse-number id="Le 18:8">8</verse-number>You must not expose the nakedness of your father’s wife—it is your father’s nakedness. <verse-number id="Le 18:9">9</verse-number><supplied>As for</supplied> your sister’s nakedness, <supplied>whether</supplied> your father’s daughter or your mother’s daughter, <supplied>whether</supplied> <idiom-start/>born at home<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a relative of house”</note> or <idiom-start/>born abroad<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “a relative of an outside place”</note> you must not expose their nakedness. <verse-number id="Le 18:10">10</verse-number><supplied>As for</supplied> the nakedness of your son’s daughter or your daughter’s daughter, you must not expose their nakedness, because they <supplied>are</supplied> your nakedness. <verse-number id="Le 18:11">11</verse-number><supplied>As for</supplied> the nakedness of the daughter of your father’s wife, she <supplied>is</supplied> your sister, a relative of your father; you must not expose her nakedness. <verse-number id="Le 18:12">12</verse-number>You must not expose the nakedness of your father’s sister; she <supplied>is</supplied> <idiom-start/>your father’s close relative<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the flesh of your father”</note> <verse-number id="Le 18:13">13</verse-number>You must not expose the nakedness of your mother’s sister, because she <supplied>is</supplied> <idiom-start/>your mother’s close relative<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the flesh of your mother”</note> <verse-number id="Le 18:14">14</verse-number>You must not expose the nakedness of your father’s brother; you must not <idiom-start/>have sex with<idiom-end/><note>Literally “approach”</note> his wife—she <supplied>is</supplied> your aunt. <verse-number id="Le 18:15">15</verse-number>You must not expose your daughter-in-law’s nakedness; she <supplied>is</supplied> your son’s wife; you must not expose her nakedness. <verse-number id="Le 18:16">16</verse-number>You must not expose the nakedness of your brother’s wife; she <supplied>is</supplied> your brother’s nakedness. <verse-number id="Le 18:17">17</verse-number>You must not expose the nakedness of a woman and her daughter, or her son’s daughter, or her daughter’s daughter; you must not take <supplied>her as wife</supplied><note>The verb לקח is used to speak of marrying (“taking <supplied>a wife</supplied>”)</note> to expose her nakedness; they <supplied>are</supplied> <idiom-start/>close relatives<idiom-end/><note>Literally “flesh”; see vv. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Le 18:6">6</cite>, 12, 13</note>—that <supplied>is</supplied> wickedness. <verse-number id="Le 18:18">18</verse-number>And you must not take <supplied>as wife</supplied><note>The verb לקח is used to speak of marrying (“taking <supplied>a wife</supplied>”)</note> a woman with her sister, to be a rival-wife, to expose her nakedness before her <idiom-start/>during<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in”</note> her life. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 18:19">19</verse-number>“ ‘And you must not <idiom-start/>have sex with<idiom-end/><note>Literally “approach”</note> a woman to expose her nakedness <idiom-start/>during<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in”</note> her menstrual uncleanness. <verse-number id="Le 18:20">20</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>you must not have sex<idiom-end/><note>Literally “you shall not give your lying down for semen”</note> with your fellow citizen’s<note>Or “neighbor’s”</note> wife, becoming unclean with her. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 18:21">21</verse-number>“ ‘And you shall not give <idiom-start/>any of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> your offspring<note>Or “descendants”</note> in order to sacrifice <supplied>them</supplied> to Molech, nor<note>Or “and not”</note> shall you profane the name of your God; I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh. <verse-number id="Le 18:22">22</verse-number>And you shall not lie with a male as lying <idiom-start/>with<idiom-end/><note>Literally “of”</note> a woman; that <supplied>is</supplied> a detestable thing. <verse-number id="Le 18:23">23</verse-number>And you shall not <idiom-start/>have sexual relations<idiom-end/><note>Literally “give your lying down”</note> with any animal, becoming unclean with it; and a woman shall not stand <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> an animal to copulate with it—that <supplied>is</supplied> a perversion. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 18:24">24</verse-number>“ ‘You must not make yourself unclean in any of these <supplied>things</supplied>, because the nations whom I am driving out from your presence were made unclean by all of these. <verse-number id="Le 18:25">25</verse-number>So<note>Or “And”</note> the land became unclean, and <idiom-start/>I have brought the punishment of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I have visited”</note> its guilt upon it, and the land has vomited out its inhabitants. <verse-number id="Le 18:26">26</verse-number>But<note>Or “And”</note> you (<supplied>neither</supplied> the native nor<note>Or “and”</note> the alien who is dwelling in your midst) shall keep my statutes and my regulations, and you shall not <idiom-start/>practice<idiom-end/><note>Literally “do”</note> any of these detestable things <verse-number id="Le 18:27">27</verse-number>(because the people of the land, who <supplied>were</supplied> <idiom-start/>before you<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to the faces of you”</note> did all these detestable things, so the land became unclean), <verse-number id="Le 18:28">28</verse-number>so that the land will not vomit you out when you make it unclean <supplied>just</supplied> as it vomited out the nation that <supplied>was</supplied> <idiom-start/>before you<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to the faces of you”</note> <verse-number id="Le 18:29">29</verse-number>Indeed, anyone who does any of these detestable things, even<note>Or “and”</note> those persons who do so shall be cut off from the midst of their people. <verse-number id="Le 18:30">30</verse-number>Thus<note>Or “And”</note> you shall keep my obligation to not do any of the statutes <idiom-start/>regarding<idiom-end/><note>Literally “of”</note> the detestable things that they did <idiom-start/>before you<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to the faces of you”</note> so that you will not make yourselves unclean by them; I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh your God.’ ” </p>
		</chapter>