<chapter id="Le 19">
			<pericope>Yahweh Is Holy</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 19:1">1</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Le 19:2">2</verse-number>“Speak to all the community of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and say to them, ‘You<note>Plural</note> must be holy, because I, Yahweh your<note>Plural</note> God, <supplied>am</supplied> holy. <verse-number id="Le 19:3">3</verse-number>Each <supplied>of you</supplied> must revere your mother<note>Hebrew “his mother”</note> and your father,<note>Hebrew “his father”</note> and you<note>Plural</note> must keep my Sabbaths; I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh your<note>Plural</note> God. <verse-number id="Le 19:4">4</verse-number>You<note>Plural</note> must not turn to idols, and you<note>Plural</note> must not make for yourselves gods of cast metal; I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh your<note>Plural</note> God. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 19:5">5</verse-number>“ ‘And when you<note>Plural</note> sacrifice a sacrifice of fellowship offerings to Yahweh, you<note>Plural</note> must sacrifice it for your<note>Plural</note> acceptance. <verse-number id="Le 19:6">6</verse-number>It must be eaten on the day of your<note>Plural</note> sacrifice and the next day; but<note>Or “and”</note> the remainder must be burned up in the fire by the third day. <verse-number id="Le 19:7">7</verse-number>And if it is indeed eaten on the third day, it <supplied>is</supplied> unclean meat; it shall not be regarded as accepted. <verse-number id="Le 19:8">8</verse-number>And the one who eats it shall bear his guilt, because he has profaned Yahweh’s holiness, and that person shall be cut off from his people. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Love Your Neighbor as Yourself</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 19:9">9</verse-number>“ ‘And at your<note>Plural</note> reaping the harvest of your<note>Plural</note> land you<note>Singular</note> must not finish reaping the edge of your<note>Singular</note> field, and you<note>Singular</note> must not glean the remnants of your<note>Singular</note> harvest. <verse-number id="Le 19:10">10</verse-number>And you<note>Singular</note> must not glean your<note>Singular</note> vineyard, and you<note>Singular</note> must not gather your<note>Singular</note> vineyard’s fallen grapes; you<note>Singular</note> must leave them behind for the needy and for the alien; I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh your<note>Plural</note> God. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 19:11">11</verse-number>“ ‘You<note>Plural</note> shall not steal, and you<note>Plural</note> shall not deceive, and you<note>Plural</note> shall not lie <idiom-start/>to one another<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “a man to his fellow citizen”</note> <verse-number id="Le 19:12">12</verse-number>and you<note>Plural</note> shall not swear <idiom-start/>falsely<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the deception”</note> in my name, and so <supplied>one of</supplied> you<note>Singular</note> profane<note>Or “you shall profane”</note> the name of your<note>Singular</note> God; I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 19:13">13</verse-number>“ ‘You<note>Singular</note> shall not exploit your<note>Singular</note> neighbor, and you<note>Singular</note> shall not rob <supplied>him</supplied>; a hired worker’s wage you<note>Singular</note> shall not <idiom-start/>withhold<idiom-end/><note>Literally “leave with you”</note> overnight until morning. <verse-number id="Le 19:14">14</verse-number>You<note>Singular</note> shall not curse <supplied>the</supplied> deaf, and you<note>Singular</note> shall not put a stumbling block <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> a blind person, but<note>Or “and”</note> you<note>Singular</note> shall revere your<note>Singular</note> God; I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 19:15">15</verse-number>“ ‘You<note>Plural</note> shall not do injustice in judgment; <idiom-start/>you<note>Singular</note> shall not show partiality to the powerless<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “you shall not lift up the faces of the poor/powerless”</note> you<note>Singular</note> shall not give preference <idiom-start/>to the powerful<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “faces of the great”</note> you<note>Singular</note> shall judge your<note>Singular</note> fellow citizen with justice. <verse-number id="Le 19:16">16</verse-number>You<note>Singular</note> shall not go <supplied>about with</supplied> slander among your<note>Singular</note> people; <idiom-start/>you<note>Singular</note> shall not endanger your<note>Singular</note> neighbor’s life<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “you shall not stand on the blood of your neighbor”</note> I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 19:17">17</verse-number>“ ‘You<note>Singular</note> shall not hate your<note>Singular</note> brother in your<note>Singular</note> heart; you<note>Singular</note> shall surely rebuke your<note>Singular</note> fellow citizen, so that you<note>Singular</note> do not incur sin <idiom-start/>along with<idiom-end/><note>Or “in addition to him”; literally “upon him”</note> him. <verse-number id="Le 19:18">18</verse-number>You<note>Singular</note> shall not seek vengeance, and you<note>Singular</note> shall not harbor a grudge <supplied>against</supplied> <idiom-start/>your<note>Singular</note> fellow citizens<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “the sons of your people”</note> and you<note>Singular</note> shall love your<note>Singular</note> neighbor like yourself; <note>Singular</note> I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>You Shall Keep My Statutes</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 19:19">19</verse-number>“ ‘You<note>Plural</note> must keep my statutes: <supplied>as for</supplied> your<note>Singular</note> domestic animals, you<note>Singular</note> shall not cause two differing kinds to breed; <supplied>as for</supplied> your<note>Singular</note> field, you<note>Singular</note> shall not sow two differing kinds of seed; and, a garment of two differing kinds <supplied>of</supplied> woven material should not be worn on you.<note>Singular</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 19:20">20</verse-number>“ ‘And when a man lies with a woman <supplied>and there is</supplied> an emission of semen and she <supplied>is</supplied> a female slave promised to a man, but<note>Or “and”</note> she indeed has not been ransomed or freedom has not be given to her, <supplied>there</supplied> shall be an obligation to compensate; they shall not be put to death, because she has not been freed. <verse-number id="Le 19:21">21</verse-number>And he shall bring his guilt offering to Yahweh at the tent of assembly’s entrance: a ram <supplied>for</supplied> a guilt offering. <verse-number id="Le 19:22">22</verse-number>And the priest shall make atonement for him <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> Yahweh with the ram of the guilt offering for his sin that he <idiom-start/>committed<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sinned”</note> and so his sin that he <idiom-start/>committed<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sinned”</note> shall be forgiven him. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 19:23">23</verse-number>“ ‘And when you<note>Plural</note> have come into the land and you<note>Plural</note> plant any tree for<note>Hebrew “of”</note> food, <idiom-start/>you<note>Plural</note> shall regard its fruit as unharvestable<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “and you shall regard its foreskin as uncircumcised its fruit”</note> <supplied>for</supplied> three years it shall be forbidden for you; <note>Plural</note> it shall not be eaten. <verse-number id="Le 19:24">24</verse-number>But<note>Or “And”</note> in the fourth year all its fruit shall be holy, offerings of praise for Yahweh. <verse-number id="Le 19:25">25</verse-number>And in the fifth year you<note>Plural</note> shall eat its fruit to increase its yield for you; <note>Plural</note> I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh your<note>Plural</note> God. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 19:26">26</verse-number>“ ‘You<note>Plural</note> must not eat <supplied>anything</supplied> with the blood; you<note>Plural</note> shall not practice divination, nor shall you<note>Plural</note> interpret signs. <verse-number id="Le 19:27">27</verse-number>You<note>Plural</note> shall not round off the corner <supplied>hair</supplied> of your<note>Plural</note> head, and you<note>Singular</note> shall not trim the corner of your<note>Singular</note> beard. <verse-number id="Le 19:28">28</verse-number>And you<note>Plural</note> shall not make a slash in your<note>Plural</note> body for a dead person, nor shall you<note>Plural</note> make on yourselves a tattoo’s mark; I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 19:29">29</verse-number>“ ‘You<note>Singular</note> shall not profane your<note>Singular</note> daughter by making her a prostitute, <idiom-start/>lest the land be prostituted and the land fill up with depravity<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “and the land does not prostitute and the land fills up depravity” or “so that the land does not prostitute and the land fills up depravity”</note> <verse-number id="Le 19:30">30</verse-number>You<note>Plural</note> shall keep my Sabbaths, and you<note>Plural</note> shall revere my sanctuary; I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 19:31">31</verse-number>“ ‘You<note>Plural</note> shall not turn to the mediums and to the soothsayers; you<note>Plural</note> shall not seek <supplied>them</supplied> to become unclean with them; I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh your<note>Plural</note> God. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 19:32">32</verse-number>“ ‘<idiom-start/>Before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from the faces of”</note> old age you<note>Singular</note> shall get up, and you<note>Singular</note> shall show respect for an old person; and you<note>Singular</note> shall revere your God; I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 19:33">33</verse-number>“ ‘And when an alien dwells with you<note>Singular</note> in your<note>Plural</note> land, you<note>Plural</note> shall not oppress him. <verse-number id="Le 19:34">34</verse-number>The alien who is dwelling with you<note>Plural</note> shall be like a native among you,<note>Plural</note> and you<note>Singular</note> shall love him like yourself, <note>Singular</note> because you<note>Plural</note> were aliens in the land of Egypt; I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh your<note>Plural</note> God. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 19:35">35</verse-number>“ ‘You<note>Plural</note> shall not commit injustice in regulation, in measurement, in weight, or<note>Or “and”</note> volume. <verse-number id="Le 19:36">36</verse-number>You<note>Plural</note> must have honest balances, honest weights, an honest ephah, and an honest hin; I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh your<note>Plural</note> God who brought you<note>Plural</note> out from the land of Egypt. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 19:37">37</verse-number>“ ‘<supplied>Thus</supplied> you<note>Plural</note> shall keep all my statutes and all my regulations, and you<note>Plural</note> shall do them; I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh.’ ” </p>
		</chapter>