<chapter id="Le 20">
			<pericope>Molech Worship and Spiritism</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 20:1">1</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Le 20:2">2</verse-number>“And to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> you shall say, ‘<supplied>If there is</supplied> <idiom-start/>anyone<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a man a man”</note> from the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> or<note>Or “and”</note> from the alien who is dwelling in Israel, who gives <idiom-start/>any of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> his offspring to Molech, he must surely be put to death; the people of the land must stone him with stones.<note>Hebrew “the stone”</note> <verse-number id="Le 20:3">3</verse-number>And I myself will set my face against that man, and I will cut him off from the midst of his people, because he has given <idiom-start/>some of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> his offspring to Molech, so that <idiom-start/>he makes my sanctuary unclean<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to make unclean my sanctuary”</note> and profanes<note>Hebrew “to profane”</note> <idiom-start/>my holy name<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the name of my holiness”</note> <verse-number id="Le 20:4">4</verse-number>And if the people of the land ever shut their eyes from<note>Or “disregard”</note> that man at his giving <idiom-start/>some of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> his offspring to Molech, not putting him to death, <verse-number id="Le 20:5">5</verse-number>then<note>Or “and”</note> I myself will set my face against that man and against his clan, and I will cut him off and all those from the midst of their people who prostitute after Molech. <verse-number id="Le 20:6">6</verse-number>As for<note>Or “And”</note> the person who turns to the mediums and the soothsayers to prostitute after them, I will set<note>Hebrew “and I will set”</note> my face against that person, and I will cut him off from the midst of his people. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 20:7">7</verse-number>“ ‘And you shall consecrate yourselves, and you shall be holy, because I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh your God. <verse-number id="Le 20:8">8</verse-number>And you shall keep my statutes, and you shall do them; I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh who consecrates you. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Family and Sexual Offenses</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 20:9">9</verse-number>“ ‘If <supplied>there is</supplied> <idiom-start/>anyone<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a man a man”</note> who curses his father or his mother, he shall surely be put to death; he has cursed his father and his mother—his blood <supplied>is</supplied> upon him. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 20:10">10</verse-number>“ ‘As for<note>Or “And”</note> a man who commits adultery with a man’s wife, who commits adultery with his neighbor’s wife, <supplied>both</supplied> the man who commits adultery and the woman who commits adultery shall surely be put to death. <verse-number id="Le 20:11">11</verse-number>As for<note>Or “And”</note> a man who lies with his father’s wife, he has exposed his father’s nakedness; both of them shall be put to death—their blood <supplied>is</supplied> on them. <verse-number id="Le 20:12">12</verse-number>As for<note>Or “And”</note> a man who lies with his daughter-in-law, both of them shall be put to death; they have committed a perversion—their blood <supplied>is</supplied> on them. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 20:13">13</verse-number>“ ‘As for<note>Or “And”</note> the man who lies with a male <supplied>as</supplied> lying <supplied>with</supplied> a woman, they have committed a detestable thing; they shall surely be put to death—their blood <supplied>is</supplied> on them. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 20:14">14</verse-number>“ ‘As for<note>Or “And”</note> a man who marries a woman and her mother, that <supplied>is</supplied> depravity; they shall burn him and them, so that it shall not become depravity in the midst of you <supplied>all</supplied>. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 20:15">15</verse-number>“ ‘As for<note>Or “And”</note> a man who <idiom-start/>has sexual relations<idiom-end/><note>Literally “he gives his lying down”</note> with an animal, he shall surely be put to death, and you must kill the animal. <verse-number id="Le 20:16">16</verse-number>As for<note>Or “And”</note> a woman who approaches any animal to copulate with it, you shall kill<note>Or “and you shall kill”</note> the woman and the animal; they shall surely be put to death—their blood <supplied>is</supplied> on them. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 20:17">17</verse-number>“ ‘As for<note>Or “And”</note> a man who takes his sister, his father’s daughter or his mother’s daughter, and he sees her nakedness and she herself sees his nakedness, it <supplied>is</supplied> a disgrace, and they shall be cut off <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in”</note> the eyes of <idiom-start/>their people<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “the sons/children of their people”</note> he has exposed his sister’s nakedness—he must bear his guilt. <verse-number id="Le 20:18">18</verse-number>As for<note>Or “And”</note> a man who lies with a menstruating woman, he exposes<note>Or “and he exposes”</note> her nakedness—her source he exposes and she herself reveals her blood’s source—both of them shall be cut off from the midst of their people. <verse-number id="Le 20:19">19</verse-number>And you shall not expose the nakedness of your mother’s sister, and you shall not expose your father’s sister, because such a person<note>Hebrew “he”</note> has dishonored his close relative—they must bear their guilt. <verse-number id="Le 20:20">20</verse-number>As for<note>Or “And”</note> a man who lies with his aunt, he has exposed his uncle’s nakedness—they shall bear their sin; they shall die childless. <verse-number id="Le 20:21">21</verse-number>As for<note>Or “And”</note> a man who marries his brother’s wife, it <supplied>is</supplied> an abomination; he has exposed his brother’s nakedness—they shall be childless. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>You Shall Be Holy</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 20:22">22</verse-number>“ ‘And you shall keep all my statutes and all my regulations, and you shall do them, so that<note>Or “and”</note> the land, to which I am bringing you to inhabit it, shall not vomit you out. <verse-number id="Le 20:23">23</verse-number>And you shall not follow the statutes of the nation that I am driving out <idiom-start/>from before you<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from your faces”</note> because they did all these things, and I detested them. <verse-number id="Le 20:24">24</verse-number>So<note>Or “And”</note> I said to you, “You yourselves shall take possession of their land, and I myself shall give it to you to possess it—a land flowing with milk and honey”; I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh your God, who <idiom-start/>has set you apart<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I have set you apart”</note> from the nations. <verse-number id="Le 20:25">25</verse-number>And you shall distinguish between the clean and the unclean animal and between the unclean and the clean bird; and you shall not defile yourselves with the animal or<note>Or “and”</note> with the bird or<note>Or “and”</note> with anything that moves along the ground that I have set apart for you <idiom-start/>as unclean<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to make unclean”</note> <verse-number id="Le 20:26">26</verse-number>And you shall be holy for me, because I, Yahweh, <supplied>am</supplied> holy, and I have singled you out from the nations to be mine. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 20:27">27</verse-number>“ ‘And a man or a woman, if a spirit of the dead or a spirit of divination is in them, they shall surely be put to death; they shall stone them with stones<note>Hebrew “the stone”</note>—their blood <supplied>is</supplied> on them.’ ” </p>
		</chapter>