<chapter id="Le 21">
			<pericope>Regulations Concerning Priests</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 21:1">1</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Yahweh said to Moses, “Speak to the priests, Aaron’s sons, and say to them, ‘One must not make himself unclean for a dead person among his <supplied>own</supplied> people, <verse-number id="Le 21:2">2</verse-number>except for his direct relative closest to him: his mother and his father, and his son and his daughter, and his brother, <verse-number id="Le 21:3">3</verse-number>and for his sister, a virgin, <supplied>who is</supplied> closest to him, <idiom-start/>who has not had a husband<idiom-end/><note>Literally “who is not for a man/husband”</note>—for her he may defile himself. <verse-number id="Le 21:4">4</verse-number>He must not make himself unclean <supplied>as</supplied> <idiom-start/>a kinsman by marriage<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “a husband among his people”</note> defiling himself. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 21:5">5</verse-number>“ ‘And they shall not shave bald patches on their head, and they shall not shave off the corner of their beard, and they shall not make a cut in their body. <verse-number id="Le 21:6">6</verse-number>They shall be holy to their God, and they shall not profane the name of their God, because they are bringing near the offerings made by fire to<note>Hebrew “of”</note> Yahweh—their God’s food—and they shall be holy. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 21:7">7</verse-number>“ ‘They shall not <idiom-start/>marry<idiom-end/><note>Literally “take”</note> a woman <supplied>who is</supplied> a prostitute and defiled, nor shall they <idiom-start/>marry<idiom-end/><note>Literally “take”</note> a woman divorced from her husband, because each priest<note>Hebrew “he”; singular antecedent specified from the context</note> <supplied>is</supplied> holy for his God. <verse-number id="Le 21:8">8</verse-number>And you shall consecrate him, because he is bringing near your God’s food; he shall be holy to you, since I, Yahweh, who consecrates you, <supplied>am</supplied> holy. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 21:9">9</verse-number>“ ‘As for<note>Or “And”</note> the daughter of any priest, if she is defiled by prostituting, she is disgracing her father—she shall be burned in the fire. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 21:10">10</verse-number>“ ‘As for<note>Or “And”</note> the priest <supplied>who is</supplied> higher than his brothers, on whose head the oil of anointment is poured and <idiom-start/>he was ordained<idiom-end/><note>Literally “he has filled up his hand”</note> to wear the garments, he shall not dishevel his head, and he shall not tear his garments. <verse-number id="Le 21:11">11</verse-number>And he shall not go near any dead person, nor shall he make himself unclean for his father or<note>Or “and”</note> for his mother. <verse-number id="Le 21:12">12</verse-number>And he shall not go out from the sanctuary, and he shall not profane his God’s sanctuary, because the dedication of his God’s oil of anointment <supplied>is</supplied> on him; I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 21:13">13</verse-number>“ ‘And he himself must take a wife in her virginity. <verse-number id="Le 21:14">14</verse-number>A widow or<note>Or “and”</note> a divorced woman or<note>Or “and”</note> a defiled <supplied>woman</supplied>, a prostitute—these he must not take; he shall take only<note>Or “instead”</note> a virgin from his people <supplied>as</supplied> wife. <verse-number id="Le 21:15">15</verse-number>And he shall not profane his offspring among his people, because I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh, who consecrates him.’ ” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 21:16">16</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Le 21:17">17</verse-number>“Speak to Aaron, saying, ‘A man from your offspring throughout their generations, in whom is a physical defect, shall not come near to present your God’s food. <verse-number id="Le 21:18">18</verse-number>Indeed,<note>Or “For”</note> any man in whom is a physical defect shall not come near: a blind man or lame or disfigured or deformed, <verse-number id="Le 21:19">19</verse-number>or a man in whom is a broken foot or a broken hand, <verse-number id="Le 21:20">20</verse-number>or a hunchback or a dwarf, or a spot in his eye or a skin disorder or a skin eruption or a crushed testicle. <verse-number id="Le 21:21">21</verse-number>Any man from Aaron the priest’s offspring in whom is a physical defect shall not come near to present offerings made by fire to<note>Hebrew “of”</note> Yahweh; a physical defect <supplied>is</supplied> in him; he shall not come near to present his God’s food. <verse-number id="Le 21:22">22</verse-number>He may eat his God’s food, from <idiom-start/>the most holy things<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the holy things of the holy things”</note> and from the holy things. <verse-number id="Le 21:23">23</verse-number>But he must not enter the curtain, and he must not come near to the altar, because a physical defect <supplied>is</supplied> in him, and he must not profane my sanctuary, because I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh, who consecrates them.’ ” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 21:24">24</verse-number>Thus<note>Or “And”</note> Moses spoke to Aaron and to his sons and to all the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> </p>
		</chapter>