<chapter id="Le 22">
			<pericope>Priests and Their Food</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 22:1">1</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Le 22:2">2</verse-number>“Tell<note>Or “Speak to”</note> Aaron and his sons<note>Literally “to Aaron and to his sons”</note> that<note>Or “and”</note> they must deal respectfully with the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>’<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> votive offerings, and they must not profane my holy name, which they are consecrating to me; I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 22:3">3</verse-number>“Say to them, ‘Throughout your generations, any man from any of your offspring who comes near the votive offerings that the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> consecrate to Yahweh with<note>Or “and”</note> his uncleanness on him, that person shall be cut off<note>Or “and that person shall be cut off”</note> from <idiom-start/>before me<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “to the faces of me”</note> I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 22:4">4</verse-number>“ ‘<idiom-start/>Anyone<idiom-end/><note>Literally “A man a man”</note> from Aaron’s offspring, if<note>Or “and”</note> he <supplied>is</supplied> afflicted with a skin disease or a fluid discharge, shall not eat in the sanctuary <idiom-start/>until<idiom-end/><note>Literally “until which”</note> he is clean; and the one who touches any unclean person or a man from whom an emission of semen goes out, <verse-number id="Le 22:5">5</verse-number>or a man who touches any swarmer that is unclean for him or <supplied>who touches</supplied> a person who is unclean for him <idiom-start/>due to<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for”</note> whatever his uncleanness, <verse-number id="Le 22:6">6</verse-number>a person who touches such a thing<note>Hebrew “him” or “it”</note> shall be unclean until the evening, and he shall not eat from the votive offerings, except<note>Or “but if” or “but rather”</note> <supplied>when</supplied> he washes<note>Or “bathes”</note> his body with water <verse-number id="Le 22:7">7</verse-number>and <idiom-start/>the sun sets<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the sun goes” or “the sun enters”</note> and he shall be clean; then<note>Or “and”</note> afterward he may eat from the votive offerings, because it <supplied>is</supplied> his food. <verse-number id="Le 22:8">8</verse-number>He shall not eat a <supplied>naturally</supplied> dead body or<note>Or “and”</note> a mangled carcass, <idiom-start/>so that he becomes unclean<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to become unclean”</note> by it; I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 22:9">9</verse-number>“ ‘And they shall keep my obligation, and they shall not incur guilt because of it, so that<note>Or “and”</note> they die through it, because they have profaned it; I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh who consecrates them. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 22:10">10</verse-number>“ ‘<idiom-start/>No stranger shall eat<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And any stranger shall not eat”</note> <supplied>the</supplied> votive offering; nor shall a temporary resident with<note>Hebrew “of”</note> a priest or<note>Or “and”</note> a hired worker eat <supplied>the</supplied> votive offering. <verse-number id="Le 22:11">11</verse-number>But<note>Or “And”</note> a priest, if <supplied>with</supplied> his money he buys a person <supplied>as</supplied> <idiom-start/>his possession<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “property of”</note> that one may eat it, and the descendants of his house themselves may eat his food. <verse-number id="Le 22:12">12</verse-number>And a priest’s daughter, when <idiom-start/>she marries a layman<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “she becomes for a strange man”</note> she herself may not eat <idiom-start/>the votive offering<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the offering/lifting of the votive offering”</note> <verse-number id="Le 22:13">13</verse-number>But<note>Or “And”</note> a priest’s daughter, when she becomes a widow or<note>Or “and”</note> divorced or there is no offspring for her, and she returns to her father’s house as <supplied>in</supplied> her childhood, she may eat from her father’s food, but<note>Or “and”</note> <idiom-start/>no layman may eat it<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “any stranger shall not eat it”</note> <verse-number id="Le 22:14">14</verse-number>And if a man eats <supplied>the</supplied> votive offering unintentionally, then<note>Or “and”</note> he shall add to it a fifth of it, and he shall give the votive offering to the priest. <verse-number id="Le 22:15">15</verse-number>And they shall not profane the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>’<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> votive offerings that they present to Yahweh, <verse-number id="Le 22:16">16</verse-number>and so cause them, by their eating their votive offerings, to bear guilt requiring a guilt offering, because I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh, who consecrates them.’ ” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Acceptable Offerings</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 22:17">17</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Le 22:18">18</verse-number>“Speak to Aaron and to his sons and to all the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and say to them, ‘Anyone from the house of Israel or<note>Or “and”</note> from the alien in Israel who presents his offering for any of their vows or<note>Or “and”</note> for any of their freewill offerings that they present to Yahweh as a burnt offering, <verse-number id="Le 22:19">19</verse-number><supplied>it must be</supplied> without defect <idiom-start/>to be acceptable for you<idiom-end/>:<note>Literally “for your acceptance”</note> a male among the cattle, among the sheep, or<note>Or “and”</note> among the goats. <verse-number id="Le 22:20">20</verse-number>You shall not present any <supplied>animal</supplied> in which <supplied>is</supplied> a physical defect, because it shall not be <idiom-start/>acceptable<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for acceptance”</note> for you. <verse-number id="Le 22:21">21</verse-number>And if anyone brings a sacrifice of fellowship offerings for Yahweh to fulfill a vow or as a freewill offering from<note>Or “among”</note> the cattle or from<note>Or “among”</note> the flock,<note>The Hebrew term refers collectively to both sheep and goats (small livestock animals)</note> it must be without defect <idiom-start/>to be acceptable<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “for acceptance”</note> there must not be any physical defect in it. <verse-number id="Le 22:22">22</verse-number><supplied>The</supplied> blind or <supplied>the</supplied> injured or <supplied>the</supplied> maimed or <supplied>the</supplied> seeping or <supplied>one with a</supplied> skin disorder or <supplied>one with a</supplied> skin eruption—these you shall not present to Yahweh, nor shall you give from them an offering made by fire on the altar for Yahweh. <verse-number id="Le 22:23">23</verse-number>As for<note>Or “And”</note> an ox or sheep that is deformed or<note>Or “and”</note> that is stunted, you may present it <supplied>as</supplied> a freewill offering, but<note>Or “and”</note> for a vow it will not be accepted. <verse-number id="Le 22:24">24</verse-number>And you shall not present <supplied>anything</supplied> for Yahweh <supplied>with</supplied> bruised or<note>Or “and”</note> shattered or<note>Or “and”</note> torn or<note>Or “and”</note> cut-off <supplied>testicles</supplied>, and you shall not <idiom-start/>sacrifice<idiom-end/><note>Literally “do” or “make”</note> <supplied>such</supplied> in your land. <verse-number id="Le 22:25">25</verse-number>And you shall not present your God’s food from any of these by the hand of <idiom-start/>a foreigner<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “a son of a foreign land”</note> because their deformity <supplied>is</supplied> in them; a physical defect <supplied>is</supplied> in them; they shall not be accepted for you.’ ” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 22:26">26</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Le 22:27">27</verse-number>“When an ox or a sheep or a goat is born, then<note>Or “and”</note> it shall be under its mother <supplied>for</supplied> seven days, and from the eighth day and beyond it is acceptable as an offering made by fire for Yahweh. <verse-number id="Le 22:28">28</verse-number>And you shall not slaughter an ox or a sheep and <idiom-start/>its young<idiom-end/><note>Literally “his son” or “his child”</note> on <idiom-start/>the same day<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “on day one” or “in one day”</note> <verse-number id="Le 22:29">29</verse-number>And when you sacrifice a sacrifice of thanksgiving to Yahweh, you must sacrifice <supplied>it</supplied> to be acceptable for you. <verse-number id="Le 22:30">30</verse-number>It must be eaten on that day; you must not leave over <supplied>anything</supplied> from it until morning; I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 22:31">31</verse-number>“Thus<note>Or “And”</note> you shall keep my commands, and you shall do them; I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 22:32">32</verse-number>“And you shall not profane my holy name, so that I may be consecrated in the midst of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh, who consecrates you, <verse-number id="Le 22:33">33</verse-number>the one who brought you out from the land of Egypt to be as God for you; I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh.” </p>
		</chapter>