<chapter id="Le 23">
			<pericope>Yahweh’s Feasts</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 23:1">1</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Le 23:2">2</verse-number>“Speak to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and say to them, ‘The festivals of Yahweh that you shall proclaim <supplied>are</supplied> holy assemblies; these <supplied>are</supplied> my appointed times. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Yahweh’s Sabbath</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 23:3">3</verse-number>“ ‘<supplied>For</supplied> six days work is to be done, and on the seventh day <supplied>shall be</supplied> <idiom-start/>a Sabbath of complete rest<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “a Sabbath of ‘Sabbathation.’ ” “Sabbathation” is not a real word, but it is devised as an attempt to convey the sounds of the related nouns in the Hebrew phrase</note> a holy assembly; you shall not do any work; it <supplied>shall be</supplied> a Sabbath for Yahweh in all your dwellings. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Passover</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 23:4">4</verse-number>“ ‘These <supplied>are</supplied> Yahweh’s appointed times, holy assemblies, which you shall proclaim at<note>Or “on”</note> their appointed time. <verse-number id="Le 23:5">5</verse-number>In the first month, on the fourteenth of the month at the evening <supplied>is</supplied> Yahweh’s Passover. <verse-number id="Le 23:6">6</verse-number>And on the fifteenth day of this month <supplied>is</supplied> Yahweh’s Feast of Unleavened Bread; <supplied>for</supplied> seven days you shall eat unleavened bread. <verse-number id="Le 23:7">7</verse-number>On the first day <supplied>there</supplied> shall be a holy assembly for you; you shall not do <idiom-start/>any regular work<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “all work of labor”</note> <verse-number id="Le 23:8">8</verse-number>And you shall present an offering for Yahweh made by fire <supplied>for</supplied> seven days; on the seventh day <supplied>there shall be</supplied> a holy assembly; you shall not do <idiom-start/>any regular work<idiom-end/>.’ ”<note>Literally “all work of labor”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Feast of Firstfruits</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 23:9">9</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Le 23:10">10</verse-number>“Speak to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and say to them, ‘When you come to the land that I <supplied>am about</supplied> to give to you and you reap its harvest, then<note>Or “and”</note> you shall bring a sheaf of the firstfruit of your harvest to the priest. <verse-number id="Le 23:11">11</verse-number>And he shall wave the sheaf <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> Yahweh for your acceptance; the priest shall wave it <idiom-start/>on the day after<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from the next day of”</note> the Sabbath. <verse-number id="Le 23:12">12</verse-number>And on the day of your waving the sheaf you shall <idiom-start/>offer<idiom-end/><note>Or “sacrifice”; literally “do” or “make”</note> a <idiom-start/>yearling<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a son of its year”</note> male lamb without defect as a burnt offering to Yahweh. <verse-number id="Le 23:13">13</verse-number>And its grain offering <supplied>shall be</supplied> two-tenths <supplied>of an ephah</supplied><note>Supplied by context</note> of finely milled flour mixed with oil, an offering made by fire for Yahweh, an appeasing fragrance; and its libation <supplied>shall be</supplied> a fourth of a hin<note>Hebrew “the hin”</note> of wine. <verse-number id="Le 23:14">14</verse-number>And you shall not eat bread or<note>Or “and”</note> roasted grain or<note>Or “and”</note> ripe grain until <idiom-start/>this very same day<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the exactly of this day”</note> until you present your God’s offering. <supplied>This must be</supplied> <idiom-start/>a lasting statute<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a statute of eternity” or “a statute of long duration”</note> for your generations in all your dwellings. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Feast of Weeks</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 23:15">15</verse-number>“ ‘And you shall count for yourselves <idiom-start/>from the day after<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from the next day of”</note> the Sabbath, from the day of your bringing the wave offering’s sheaf—<supplied>there</supplied> shall be seven full weeks. <verse-number id="Le 23:16">16</verse-number>Until <idiom-start/>the day after<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from the next day of”</note> the seventh Sabbath you shall count fifty days; then<note>Or “and”</note> you shall present a new grain offering for Yahweh. <verse-number id="Le 23:17">17</verse-number>You shall bring from your dwellings for a wave offering two <supplied>loaves of</supplied> bread <idiom-start/>made with<idiom-end/><note>Literally “they shall be”</note> two-tenths <supplied>of an ephah</supplied><note>Supplied by context</note> of finely milled flour; they must be baked with leaven—<supplied>the</supplied> firstfruits <idiom-start/>belonging to<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to”</note> Yahweh. <verse-number id="Le 23:18">18</verse-number>And, in addition to the bread, you shall present seven <idiom-start/>yearling<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a son of its year”</note> male lambs without defects and one <idiom-start/>young bull<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a bull a son of cattle”</note> and two rams—they shall be a burnt offering for Yahweh with<note>Or “and”</note> their grain offering and their libations, an offering made by fire, an appeasing fragrance for Yahweh. <verse-number id="Le 23:19">19</verse-number>And you shall <idiom-start/>offer<idiom-end/><note>Or “sacrifice”; literally “do” or “make”</note> one he-goat as a sin offering and two <idiom-start/>yearling<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a son of its year”</note> male lambs as a sacrifice of fellowship offerings. <verse-number id="Le 23:20">20</verse-number>And the priest shall wave them with the bread of the firstfruits <supplied>as</supplied> a wave offering <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> Yahweh; in addition to <supplied>the</supplied> two male lambs, they shall be holy for Yahweh for the priest. <verse-number id="Le 23:21">21</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>you shall make a proclamation<idiom-end/><note>Literally “you shall proclaim”</note> on <idiom-start/>this very same day<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “the exactly of this day”</note> it shall be a holy assembly for you; you shall not do <idiom-start/>any regular work<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “all work of labor”</note> <supplied>this is</supplied> a <idiom-start/>lasting statute<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a statute of eternity” or “a statute of long duration”</note> in all your dwellings throughout<note>Or “for”</note> your generations. <verse-number id="Le 23:22">22</verse-number>And when you<note>Plural</note> reap the harvest of your<note>Plural</note> land, you<note>Singular</note> must not finish the edge of your<note>Singular</note> field at your reaping, and you<note>Singular</note> must not glean the remnants of your<note>Singular</note> harvest—you<note>Singular</note> shall leave them behind for the needy and for the alien; I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh your<note>Plural</note> God.’ ” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Feast of Trumpets</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 23:23">23</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Le 23:24">24</verse-number>“Speak to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> saying, ‘In the seventh month, on <supplied>the</supplied> first <supplied>day</supplied> of the month, <idiom-start/>you must have<idiom-end/><note>Literally “it must be for yourselves”</note> a rest period, a remembrance of <supplied>the trumpet</supplied> blast, a holy assembly. <verse-number id="Le 23:25">25</verse-number>You must not do <idiom-start/>any regular work<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “all work of labor”</note> and you shall present an offering made by fire to Yahweh.’ ” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Day of Atonement</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 23:26">26</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Le 23:27">27</verse-number>“Surely the Day of Atonement <supplied>is</supplied> on the tenth <supplied>day</supplied> of the seventh month; it shall be a holy assembly for you, and you shall deny yourselves, and you shall present an offering made by fire to Yahweh. <verse-number id="Le 23:28">28</verse-number>And you must not do <idiom-start/>any regular work<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all work of labor”</note> on <idiom-start/>this very same day<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the exactly of this day”</note> because it <supplied>is</supplied> the Day of Atonement to make atonement for you <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> Yahweh your God. <verse-number id="Le 23:29">29</verse-number>If <supplied>there is</supplied> any person who does not deny <supplied>himself</supplied> on <idiom-start/>this very same day<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the exactly of this day”</note> then<note>Or “and”</note> he shall be cut off from his people. <verse-number id="Le 23:30">30</verse-number>As for<note>Or “And”</note> any person who does any work on <idiom-start/>this very same day<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the exactly of this day”</note> I will exterminate that person from the midst of his people. <verse-number id="Le 23:31">31</verse-number>You must not do any work; <supplied>it is</supplied> a <idiom-start/>lasting statute<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a statute of eternity” or “a statute of long duration”</note> throughout your generations in all your dwellings. <verse-number id="Le 23:32">32</verse-number>It <supplied>is</supplied> <idiom-start/>a Sabbath of complete rest<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a Sabbath of ‘Sabbathation.’ ” “Sabbathation” is not a real word, but it is devised as an attempt to convey the sounds of the related nouns in the Hebrew phrase</note> for you, and you shall deny yourselves on the ninth <supplied>day</supplied> of the month in the evening—from evening to evening you must observe your <supplied>extraordinary</supplied><note>Supplied from the immediate context within this verse</note> Sabbath.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Feast of Booths</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 23:33">33</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Le 23:34">34</verse-number>“Speak to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> saying, ‘On the fifteenth day of the seventh month, this <supplied>shall be</supplied> the Feast of Booths <supplied>for</supplied> seven days for Yahweh. <verse-number id="Le 23:35">35</verse-number>On the first day <supplied>there shall be</supplied> a holy assembly; you must not do any <idiom-start/>regular work<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “work of labor”</note> <verse-number id="Le 23:36">36</verse-number><supplied>For</supplied> seven days you must present an offering made by fire to Yahweh. On the eighth day it shall be a holy assembly for you, and you shall present an offering made by fire to Yahweh; it <supplied>is</supplied> a celebration; you must not do <idiom-start/>any regular work<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “all work of labor”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Summary</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 23:37">37</verse-number>“ ‘These <supplied>are</supplied> Yahweh’s festivals, which you must proclaim, holy assemblies to present an offering made by fire to Yahweh—burnt offering and grain offering, sacrifice and libations, <idiom-start/>each on its proper day<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a thing of a day on its day”</note>— <verse-number id="Le 23:38">38</verse-number><idiom-start/>besides<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from to alone”</note> Yahweh’s Sabbaths and <idiom-start/>besides<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from to alone”</note> your gifts and <idiom-start/>besides<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from to alone”</note> your vows and <idiom-start/>besides<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from to alone”</note> all your freewill offerings that you give to Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 23:39">39</verse-number>“ ‘Surely on the fifteenth day of the seventh month, at your gathering the land’s produce, you shall hold Yahweh’s festival for seven days; on the first day <supplied>there shall be</supplied> a rest period and on the eighth day a rest period. <verse-number id="Le 23:40">40</verse-number>And on the first day you shall take for yourselves the first fruit of majestic trees, branches of palm trees and branches<note>Collective singular</note> of a leafy tree and of a brook’s poplar trees, and you shall rejoice <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> Yahweh your God <supplied>for</supplied> seven days. <verse-number id="Le 23:41">41</verse-number>And you must hold it <supplied>as</supplied> a festival for Yahweh <supplied>for</supplied> seven days in the year; <supplied>it shall be</supplied> a <idiom-start/>lasting statute<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a statute of eternity” or “a statute of long duration”</note> throughout your generations; in the seventh month you must hold it. <verse-number id="Le 23:42">42</verse-number>You must live in the booths <supplied>for</supplied> seven days; all the natives in Israel must live in the booths, <verse-number id="Le 23:43">43</verse-number>so that your generations shall know that I made the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> live in booths when I brought them from the land of Egypt; I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh your God.’ ” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 23:44">44</verse-number>Thus<note>Or “And”</note> Moses announced to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> Yahweh’s appointed times. </p>
		</chapter>