<chapter id="Le 24">
			<pericope>The Sanctuary’s Lamp and Bread</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 24:1">1</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Le 24:2">2</verse-number>“Command the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> that<note>Or “and”</note> they should bring pure olive oil <supplied>from</supplied> beaten <supplied>olives</supplied> for the light to <idiom-start/>present<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to cause raising up”; or “set up” (HALOT 830 s.v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Le 24:4">4</cite>.d)</note> a lamp continually. <verse-number id="Le 24:3">3</verse-number>Aaron shall arrange for it <idiom-start/>outside<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from the outside of to”</note> the curtain of the testimony in <supplied>the</supplied> tent of assembly from evening until morning <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> Yahweh continually; <supplied>it shall be</supplied> a <idiom-start/>lasting statute<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a statute of eternity” or “a statute of long duration”</note> throughout your generations. <verse-number id="Le 24:4">4</verse-number>On the pure <supplied>golden</supplied><note>Supplied by context and the description of the lampstand in <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ex 25:31">Exod 25:31</cite></note> lampstand he shall arrange for the lamps <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> Yahweh continually. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 24:5">5</verse-number>“And you shall take finely milled flour, and you shall bake <supplied>with</supplied> it twelve ring-shaped bread cakes: each one <supplied>shall be</supplied> two-tenths <supplied>of an ephah</supplied>. <verse-number id="Le 24:6">6</verse-number>And you shall place them <supplied>in</supplied> two rows, six <supplied>to the</supplied> row, on the pure <supplied>gold</supplied><note>Supplied by context and the description of the table in <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ex 25:24">Exod 25:24</cite></note> table <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> Yahweh. <verse-number id="Le 24:7">7</verse-number>And you shall put pure frankincense on each<note>Hebrew “the”</note> row so that<note>Or “and”</note> it shall be for the bread as a memorial offering, an offering made by fire for Yahweh. <verse-number id="Le 24:8">8</verse-number><idiom-start/>On every Sabbath<idiom-end/><note>Literally “On the day of the Sabbath on the day of the Sabbath”</note> he shall arrange it in rows <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> Yahweh continually; <supplied>they are</supplied> from the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> <supplied>as</supplied> an everlasting<note>Or “eternal” or “enduring” or “perpetual”</note> covenant. <verse-number id="Le 24:9">9</verse-number>And it shall be for Aaron and for his sons, and they shall eat it in a holy place, because it <supplied>is</supplied> <idiom-start/>a most holy thing<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a holy thing of holy things”</note> for him from Yahweh’s offerings made by fire—a <idiom-start/>lasting rule<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “rule of eternity” or “rule of long duration”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Punishment for Blasphemy</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 24:10">10</verse-number>And an Israelite woman’s son, and he <supplied>was</supplied> an Egyptian man’s son, went out in the midst of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and the Israelite woman’s son and an<note>Hebrew “the”</note> Israelite man fought in the camp. <verse-number id="Le 24:11">11</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> the Israelite woman’s son blasphemed the name, and he cursed, so<note>Or “and”</note> they brought him to Moses—and the name of his mother <supplied>was</supplied> Shelomith the daughter of Dibri, of the tribe of Dan. <verse-number id="Le 24:12">12</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> they put him in custody <idiom-start/>so that<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to”</note> <supplied>the matter</supplied> might be made clear to them in accordance with the mouth of Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 24:13">13</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Le 24:14">14</verse-number>“Bring the curser <idiom-start/>outside the camp<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to from an outside place of the camp”</note> and all the hearers shall place their hands on his head, and the whole community shall stone him. <verse-number id="Le 24:15">15</verse-number>And you shall speak to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> saying, ‘<idiom-start/>Any man<idiom-end/><note>Literally “A man a man”</note> when he curses his God shall bear<note>Or “and he shall bear”</note> his sin. <verse-number id="Le 24:16">16</verse-number>And he who blasphemes Yahweh’s name certainly shall be put to death; the whole community certainly shall stone him. As the alien, so the native shall be put to death at blaspheming his name. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 24:17">17</verse-number>“ ‘And when a man kills any human being, he certainly shall be put to death. <verse-number id="Le 24:18">18</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>he who kills<idiom-end/><note>Literally “he who kills the soul of” or “he who kills the life of”</note> a domestic animal must repay <supplied>for</supplied> it life in place of life. <verse-number id="Le 24:19">19</verse-number>And when a man <idiom-start/>causes<idiom-end/><note>Literally “gives”</note> a physical defect in his fellow citizen <idiom-start/>according to<idiom-end/><note>Literally “as that”</note> what he has done, so it shall be done to him: <verse-number id="Le 24:20">20</verse-number>fracture in place of fracture, eye in place of eye, tooth in place of tooth—<idiom-start/>according to<idiom-end/><note>Literally “as that”</note> <supplied>the</supplied> physical defect he <idiom-start/>causes<idiom-end/><note>Literally “gives”</note> to the person, likewise it shall be <idiom-start/>caused<idiom-end/><note>Literally “given”</note> to him. <verse-number id="Le 24:21">21</verse-number>And a killer of a domestic animal must repay <supplied>for</supplied> it, and a killer of a human shall be put to death. <verse-number id="Le 24:22">22</verse-number><idiom-start/>You must have<idiom-end/><note>Literally “it shall be for you”</note> one norm; as <supplied>for</supplied> the alien, so<note>Hebrew “as”</note> it must be <supplied>for</supplied> the native, because I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh your God.’ ” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 24:23">23</verse-number>Thus<note>Or “And”</note> Moses spoke to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and they brought the curser <idiom-start/>outside the camp<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to from an outside place of the camp”</note> and they stoned him <supplied>with</supplied> stones, and the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> did <supplied>just</supplied> as Yahweh had commanded Moses. </p>
		</chapter>