<chapter id="Le 25">
			<pericope>The Sabbath Year</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 25:1">1</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Yahweh spoke to Moses on <idiom-start/>Mount Sinai<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the mountain of Sinai”</note> saying, <verse-number id="Le 25:2">2</verse-number>“Speak to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and say to them, ‘When you<note>Plural</note> come into the land that I <supplied>am about to</supplied> give to you,<note>Plural</note> then<note>Or “and”</note> the land shall observe a Sabbath for Yahweh. <verse-number id="Le 25:3">3</verse-number>Six years you<note>Singular throughout this verse</note> shall sow your field, and six years you shall prune your vineyard, and you shall gather its yield. <verse-number id="Le 25:4">4</verse-number>But<note>Or “And”</note> in the seventh year it shall be <idiom-start/>a Sabbath of complete rest<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a Sabbath of ‘Sabbathation.’ ” “Sabbathation” is not a real word, but it is devised as an attempt to convey the sounds of the related nouns in the Hebrew phrase</note> for the land—a Sabbath for Yahweh; you<note>Singular throughout this verse</note> must not sow your field, and you must not prune your vineyard. <verse-number id="Le 25:5">5</verse-number>You<note>Singular throughout this verse</note> must not reap your harvest’s aftergrowth, and you must not harvest the grapes of your unpruned vines—it shall be <idiom-start/>a year of complete rest<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a year of a rest period”</note> for the land. <verse-number id="Le 25:6">6</verse-number>And a Sabbath of the land shall be for food for you:<note>Plural</note> for you<note>Singular here and through the rest of this verse</note> and for your slave and for your slave woman and for your hired worker and for your temporary residents<note>Collective singular; Hebrew “temporary resident”</note> who are dwelling as aliens with you; <verse-number id="Le 25:7">7</verse-number>and all its yield shall be for your<note>Singular throughout this verse</note> domestic animal and for the wild animal, which <supplied>are</supplied> in your land to eat. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Year of Jubilee</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 25:8">8</verse-number>“ ‘And you<note>Singular throughout this verse</note> shall count for yourself seven Sabbaths of years, seven times seven years, and they shall be for you <idiom-start/>time periods of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “days of”</note> years: <idiom-start/>forty-nine<idiom-end/><note>Literally “nine and forty”</note> years. <verse-number id="Le 25:9">9</verse-number>And you<note>Singular</note> shall cause <idiom-start/>a loud horn blast<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a ram’s horn of a blast”</note> to be heard on the seventh month on the tenth of the month; on the Day of Atonement you<note>Plural</note> shall cause a ram’s horn to be heard in all your<note>Plural</note> land. <verse-number id="Le 25:10">10</verse-number>And you<note>Plural throughout this verse</note> shall consecrate the fiftieth year, and you shall proclaim a release in the land for all its inhabitants. It <supplied>is</supplied> a Jubilee; it shall be for you, and you shall return. You must return—everyone to his property and everyone to his clan.<note>Or “each of you must return to his property and to his clan”</note> <verse-number id="Le 25:11">11</verse-number><idiom-start/>You<note>Plural throughout this verse</note> shall have the fiftieth year as a Jubilee<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “a Jubilee it the year of the fiftieth year it shall be for you”</note> you must not reap its aftergrowth, and you must not harvest its unpruned vines. <verse-number id="Le 25:12">12</verse-number>Because it is a Jubilee, it shall be holy to you. You must eat its<note>That is, the field’s</note> produce from the field. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 25:13">13</verse-number>“ ‘In this Year of Jubilee <idiom-start/>each of you<note>Plural</note> shall return<idiom-end/><note>Literally “you shall return a man” or “you shall return everyone”</note> to his property. <verse-number id="Le 25:14">14</verse-number>And when you<note>Plural</note> sell something to your<note>Singular</note> fellow citizen or <supplied>you</supplied> buy from your<note>Singular</note> neighbor’s hand, you<note>Plural</note> must not oppress <idiom-start/>one another<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “a man his brother”</note> <verse-number id="Le 25:15">15</verse-number>You<note>Singular throughout this verse</note> must buy from your fellow citizen according to <supplied>the</supplied> number of years after the Jubilee; he must sell to you according to <supplied>the</supplied> number of years of yield. <verse-number id="Le 25:16">16</verse-number>You<note>Singular throughout this verse</note> must increase its price <idiom-start/>according to a greater number of years<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to the mouth of many of the years”</note> but<note>Or “and”</note> you must decrease its price <idiom-start/>according to a lesser number of years<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to the mouth of few of the years”</note> because he is selling <supplied>its</supplied> yields to you. <verse-number id="Le 25:17">17</verse-number>And you<note>Plural</note> must not oppress <idiom-start/>one another<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “a man his citizen”</note> but<note>Or “and”</note> you<note>Singular</note> shall revere your God, because I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh, your<note>Plural</note> God. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 25:18">18</verse-number>“ ‘And you<note>Plural throughout this verse</note> shall do my statutes, and you must keep my regulations, and you shall do them, so that<note>Or “and”</note> you shall live <idiom-start/>securely<idiom-end/><note>Literally “with confidence”</note> on the land. <verse-number id="Le 25:19">19</verse-number>And the land shall give its fruit, and you<note>Plural throughout this verse</note> shall eat <idiom-start/>your fill<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to contentment”</note> and you shall live <idiom-start/>securely<idiom-end/><note>Literally “with confidence”</note> on it. <verse-number id="Le 25:20">20</verse-number>And if you<note>Plural</note> should say, “What shall we eat in the seventh year, <idiom-start/>if<idiom-end/><note>Literally “look”</note> we do not sow and we do not gather its yield?” <verse-number id="Le 25:21">21</verse-number>then<note>Or “and”</note> I will command my blessing for you<note>Plural</note> in the sixth year, so that<note>Or “and”</note> it will make<note>Or “produce”</note> the yield for three years. <verse-number id="Le 25:22">22</verse-number>And you<note>Plural throughout this verse</note> will sow <supplied>in</supplied> the eighth year, and you shall eat from the old yield;<note>The verse divides here</note> until the ninth year, until the coming of its yield, you shall eat <supplied>the</supplied> old <supplied>yield</supplied>. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 25:23">23</verse-number>“ ‘But<note>Or “And”</note> the land must not be sold in<note>Or “for”</note> perpetuity, because the land <supplied>is</supplied> mine, because you<note>Plural</note> <supplied>are</supplied> aliens and temporary residents with me. <verse-number id="Le 25:24">24</verse-number>And in all your<note>Plural</note> property’s land you<note>Plural</note> must provide redemption for the land. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 25:25">25</verse-number>“ ‘When your<note>Singular</note> brother becomes poor and he sells part of his property, then<note>Or “and”</note> <idiom-start/>his nearest redeemer<idiom-end/><note>Literally “his redeemer the nearest to him”</note> shall come, and he shall redeem the thing sold by his brother. <verse-number id="Le 25:26">26</verse-number>But<note>Or “And”</note> if<note>Or “when”</note> a man <idiom-start/>does not have<idiom-end/><note>Literally “it is not for him”</note> a redeemer, then<note>Or “and”</note> <idiom-start/>he prospers<idiom-end/><note>Literally “his hand produces”</note> and he finds enough for his redemption, <verse-number id="Le 25:27">27</verse-number>then<note>Or “and”</note> he shall calculate the years of its selling, and he shall refund the balance to the man to whom he sold <supplied>it</supplied>, and he shall return to his property. <verse-number id="Le 25:28">28</verse-number>But<note>Or “And”</note> if his hand does not find enough to refund to him, then<note>Or “and”</note> <idiom-start/>what he has sold<idiom-end/><note>Literally “his thing sold”</note> shall be in the buyer’s hand until the Year of Jubilee; and it shall go out <supplied>of the buyer’s hand</supplied><note>Meaning derived from context; an alternative translation could be “shall not be released” (cf. NKJV, NRSV, ESV, NJPS) or “shall not revert” (NASB, NET)</note> in the Jubilee, and he shall return to his property. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 25:29">29</verse-number>“ ‘And if a man sells <idiom-start/>a residential house in a walled city<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “a house of a dwelling of a city wall”</note> then<note>Or “and”</note> it shall be his redemption until completing <idiom-start/>a year after his selling<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “a year of his selling”</note> its redemption <idiom-start/>shall last<idiom-end/><note>Literally “shall be”</note> <idiom-start/>a year<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “days”</note> <verse-number id="Le 25:30">30</verse-number>But<note>Or “And”</note> if it is not redeemed <idiom-start/>before a full year has passed<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “until the fulfilling of for him/it an entire year”</note> then<note>Or “and”</note> the house that <supplied>is</supplied> <idiom-start/>in the walled city<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the city that for it a wall”</note> shall belong to the buyer in<note>Hebrew “for”</note> perpetuity throughout his generations; it shall not go out <supplied>of the buyer’s hand</supplied><note>Meaning derived from context; an alternative translation could be “shall not be released” (cf. NKJV, NRSV, ESV, NJPS) or “shall not revert” (NASB, NET)</note> in the Jubilee. <verse-number id="Le 25:31">31</verse-number>However,<note>Or “And” or “But”</note> village houses that have no surrounding wall shall be considered <idiom-start/>open country<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “the field of the land”</note> <supplied>there</supplied> is redemption for it, and in the Jubilee it shall go out <supplied>of the buyer’s hand</supplied>.<note>Meaning derived from context; an alternative translation could be “shall not be released” (cf. NKJV, NRSV, ESV, NJPS) or “shall not revert” (NASB, NET)</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 25:32">32</verse-number>“ ‘As for<note>Or “And”</note> the cities of the Levites, <supplied>that is</supplied>, the houses in<note>Hebrew “of”</note> their property’s cities, it shall be <idiom-start/>a lasting redemption<idiom-end/><note>Or “a permanent redemption”; literally “redemption of eternity” or “redemption of long duration”</note> for the Levites. <verse-number id="Le 25:33">33</verse-number>And whatever <supplied>anyone</supplied> redeems from the Levites then<note>Or “and”</note> must go out <supplied>of the buyer’s hand</supplied><note>Meaning derived from context; an alternative translation could be “shall not be released” (cf. NKJV, NRSV, ESV, NJPS) or “shall not revert” (NASB, NET)</note> in the Jubilee, <supplied>including</supplied> a house’s selling <idiom-start/>in his city’s property<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the city of his property”</note> because the houses in<note>Hebrew “of”</note> the cities of the Levites <supplied>are</supplied> their property in the midst of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> <verse-number id="Le 25:34">34</verse-number>But<note>Or “And”</note> a<note>Hebrew “the”</note> field of their cities’ pastureland must not be sold, because <idiom-start/>it is their property for all time<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “a property of eternity it <supplied>is</supplied> for them” or “a property of long duration it <supplied>is</supplied> for them”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 25:35">35</verse-number>“ ‘And if your<note>Singular throughout this verse</note> countryman<note>Or “brother”</note> becomes poor and <idiom-start/>if he becomes dependent on you<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “and his hand is shaky with you”</note> then<note>Or “and”</note> you shall support him <supplied>like</supplied> an alien and <supplied>like</supplied> a temporary resident, and he shall live with you. <verse-number id="Le 25:36">36</verse-number>You<note>Singular throughout this verse</note> must not take interest or<note>Or “and”</note> usury from him, but<note>Or “and”</note> you shall revere your God, and your countryman<note>Or “brother”</note> shall live with you. <verse-number id="Le 25:37">37</verse-number>You<note>Singular throughout this verse</note> must not give your money to him with interest or<note>Or “and”</note> give your food for<note>Or “in” or “with”</note> profit. <verse-number id="Le 25:38">38</verse-number>I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh your<note>Plural throughout this verse</note> God, who brought you out from the land of Egypt to give <idiom-start/>you<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to you”</note> the land of Canaan, to be as God for you. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 25:39">39</verse-number>“ ‘And if your<note>Singular throughout this verse</note> countryman<note>Or “brother”</note> <supplied>who is</supplied> with you becomes poor, and he is sold to you, <idiom-start/>you shall not treat him as a slave<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “you shall not let him work <supplied>the</supplied> work of a slave” or “you shall not enslave him <supplied>the</supplied> work of a slave”</note> <verse-number id="Le 25:40">40</verse-number>He shall be with you like a hired worker, like a temporary resident; he shall work with you until the Year of Jubilee. <verse-number id="Le 25:41">41</verse-number>And he and his sons with him shall go out from you, and he shall return to his clan, and to the property of his ancestors<note>Or “fathers”</note> he shall return. <verse-number id="Le 25:42">42</verse-number>Because they <supplied>are</supplied> my servants whom I brought out from the land of Egypt, they shall not be sold <idiom-start/>as a slave<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “a selling of a slave”</note> <verse-number id="Le 25:43">43</verse-number>You<note>Singular throughout this verse</note> shall not rule over him with ruthlessness, but<note>Or “and”</note> you shall revere your God. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 25:44">44</verse-number>“ ‘As for<note>Or “And”</note> your<note>Singular</note> slave and your<note>Singular</note> slave woman who are<note>Or “may be” (permission; cf. NASU, ESV, NRSV) or “can be” (ability)</note> yours,<note>Singular</note> from the nations that <supplied>are</supplied> all around you,<note>Plural</note> from them you<note>Plural</note> may buy a slave or<note>Or “and”</note> a slave woman. <verse-number id="Le 25:45">45</verse-number>And you<note>Plural throughout this verse</note> may buy also from the children<note>Or “sons”</note> of the temporary residents who are dwelling with you as aliens and from their clan who are with you, who have children in your land; indeed,<note>Or “and”</note> they may be as property for you. <verse-number id="Le 25:46">46</verse-number>And you<note>Plural</note> may pass them on as an inheritance to your<note>Plural</note> sons<note>Or “children”</note> after you<note>Plural</note> to take possession of as property <idiom-start/>for all time<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to eternity” or “forever” or “for a long duration”</note>—you<note>Plural</note> may let them work. But<note>Or “And”</note> <supplied>as for</supplied> your<note>Plural</note> countrymen,<note>Or “brothers”</note> the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> you<note>Singular</note> shall not rule with ruthlessness over <idiom-start/>one another<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “a man over his brother”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 25:47">47</verse-number>“ ‘And if <supplied>the</supplied> alien or<note>Or “and”</note> <supplied>the</supplied> temporary resident <supplied>who are</supplied> with you<note>Singular throughout this verse</note> <idiom-start/>prosper<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the hand produces”</note> but<note>Or “and”</note> your countryman<note>Or “brother”</note> <supplied>who is</supplied> with him becomes poor and he is sold to an alien, a temporary resident <supplied>who is</supplied> with you, or to a descendant of an alien’s clan, <verse-number id="Le 25:48">48</verse-number>after he is sold redemption shall be for him; one of his brothers may redeem him, <verse-number id="Le 25:49">49</verse-number>or his uncle or his uncle’s son may redeem him, or <idiom-start/>one of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> <idiom-start/>his close relatives<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the direct relative of his flesh”</note> from his clan may redeem him; or <supplied>if</supplied> <idiom-start/>he prospers<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “his hand produces”</note> he may redeem himself. <verse-number id="Le 25:50">50</verse-number>And he shall calculate with his buyer from the year of <idiom-start/>his selling himself<idiom-end/><note>Literally “his being sold for him”</note> until the Jubilee; and the value of his selling shall be according to the number of years—it shall be with him like<note>Or “as”</note> a hired worker’s days. <verse-number id="Le 25:51">51</verse-number>If <supplied>there are</supplied> still many years, <idiom-start/>in keeping with them<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the mouth of them”</note> he shall restore his redemption <idiom-start/>in proportion to his purchase price<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “from the price of his acquisition”</note> <verse-number id="Le 25:52">52</verse-number>And if <supplied>there are</supplied> a few years left until the Year of Jubilee, then<note>Or “and”</note> he shall calculate for himself; he shall restore his redemption <idiom-start/>according to the number of his years<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “according to the mouth of his years”</note> <verse-number id="Le 25:53">53</verse-number>He shall be with him <idiom-start/>as a yearly hired worker<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “as a hired worker of a year in a year”</note> he shall not rule over him with ruthlessness <idiom-start/>in your<note>Singular</note> sight<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to your eyes” or “for your eyes”</note> <verse-number id="Le 25:54">54</verse-number>And if he is not redeemed by<note>Or “in”</note> <supplied>any of</supplied> these <supplied>ways</supplied>,<note>Bracketed words provided from the sense of the context</note> then<note>Or “and”</note> he and his sons with him shall go out in the Year of Jubilee. <verse-number id="Le 25:55">55</verse-number>Indeed,<note>Emphatic use of כִּי, since there is no indication of direct causation to only what precedes in vv. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Le 25:47–54">47–54</cite>; or “Because”</note> the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> <supplied>are</supplied> servants for me; they <supplied>are</supplied> my servants whom I brought out from the land of Egypt. I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh your<note>Plural</note> God.’ ” </p>
		</chapter>