<chapter id="Le 26">
			<pericope>Blessings for Obedience</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 26:1">1</verse-number>“ ‘You<note>Plural throughout the entire chapter</note> shall not make for yourselves idols and divine images, and you shall not raise up stone pillars for yourselves, and you shall not put a sculptured stone in your land in order to<note>Or “to”</note> worship before it, because I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh your God. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 26:2">2</verse-number>“ ‘You shall keep my Sabbaths, and you shall revere my sanctuary; I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 26:3">3</verse-number>“ ‘If you walk in my statutes and you keep my commands and you do them, <verse-number id="Le 26:4">4</verse-number>then<note>Or “and”</note> I will give you rains in their time, and the land shall give its produce, and the trees of the field shall give their fruit. <verse-number id="Le 26:5">5</verse-number>And for you <supplied>the</supplied> threshing season shall overtake <supplied>the</supplied> grape harvest, and the grape harvest shall overtake <supplied>the</supplied> sowing, and you shall eat your food <idiom-start/>to your fill<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to contentment”</note> and you shall live <idiom-start/>securely<idiom-end/><note>Literally “with confidence”</note> in your land. <verse-number id="Le 26:6">6</verse-number>And I will give peace in the land, and you shall lie down, and there shall not be <idiom-start/>anybody who makes you afraid<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “who makes afraid” or “making afraid”</note> and I will remove harmful animals from the land, and <idiom-start/>no sword shall pass through your land<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “a sword shall not pass through in your land”</note> <verse-number id="Le 26:7">7</verse-number>And you shall pursue your enemies, and they shall fall by the sword <idiom-start/>before you<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to your faces”</note> <verse-number id="Le 26:8">8</verse-number>And five of<note>Hebrew “from”</note> you shall pursue a hundred, and a hundred of<note>Hebrew “from”</note> you shall pursue a myriad;<note>Or “ten thousand”</note> and your enemies shall fall by the sword <idiom-start/>before you<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to your faces”</note> <verse-number id="Le 26:9">9</verse-number>And I will turn to you, and I will make you fruitful, and I will make you numerous; and I will keep my covenant with you. <verse-number id="Le 26:10">10</verse-number>And you shall eat <idiom-start/>old grain<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “old what is stale”</note> and <idiom-start/>you shall clear away the old before the new<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “old from the faces of new you shall bring out”</note> <verse-number id="Le 26:11">11</verse-number>And I will put my dwelling place in your midst, and my inner self<note>Or “soul”</note> shall not abhor you. <verse-number id="Le 26:12">12</verse-number>And I will walk about in your midst, and I shall be your God,<note>Or “as a God for you”</note> and you shall be my people.<note>Or “as a people for me”</note> <verse-number id="Le 26:13">13</verse-number>I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh, your God who brought you out from the land of Egypt, from being their slaves; and I broke the bars of your yoke, and I caused you to walk erectly. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Punishment for Disobedience</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 26:14">14</verse-number>“ ‘But<note>Or “And”</note> if you do not listen to me and you do not carry out<note>Or “you do not do” or “you do not observe” or “you do not perform”</note> all these commands, <verse-number id="Le 26:15">15</verse-number>and if you reject my statutes and if your inner self<note>Or “soul”</note> abhors my regulations, to not carry out<note>Or “do” or “observe” or “perform”</note> all my commands <supplied>by</supplied> your breaking my covenant, <verse-number id="Le 26:16">16</verse-number>I <idiom-start/>in turn<idiom-end/><note>Literally “also” or “indeed”</note> will do this to you: then<note>Or “and”</note> I will summon onto you horror, the wasting disease, and the fever that wastes eyes and that drains away life; and you shall sow your seed <idiom-start/>in vain<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “for the emptiness”</note> and your enemies shall eat it. <verse-number id="Le 26:17">17</verse-number>And I will set my face against you, and you shall be defeated <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> your enemies; and your haters shall rule over you, and you shall flee away, but<note>Or “and”</note> there shall not be <idiom-start/>anybody who is pursuing<idiom-end/><note>Literally “who pursues” or “pursuing”</note> you. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 26:18">18</verse-number>“ ‘And if in spite of these <supplied>things</supplied> you do not listen to me, then<note>Or “and”</note> I will continue to discipline you seven times for your sins. <verse-number id="Le 26:19">19</verse-number>And I will break the pride of your strength; and I will make your heaven like iron<note>Or “iron ore”</note> and your land like copper. <verse-number id="Le 26:20">20</verse-number>And your strength shall be consumed <idiom-start/>in vain<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “to the emptiness”</note> and your land shall not give its produce, and the land’s trees shall not give their fruit. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 26:21">21</verse-number>“ ‘And if you go against me <supplied>in</supplied> hostility and you are not willing to listen to me, then<note>Or “and”</note> I will add a plague onto you seven times according to your sins. <verse-number id="Le 26:22">22</verse-number>And I will send <idiom-start/>wild animals<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the animals of the field”</note> out among you, and they shall make you childless, and they shall cut down your domestic animals, and they shall make you fewer; and your roads shall be desolate. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 26:23">23</verse-number>“ ‘And if you do not accept correction from<note>Hebrew “for” or “to”</note> me through these <supplied>things</supplied>, but<note>Or “and”</note> you go against me <supplied>in</supplied> hostility, <verse-number id="Le 26:24">24</verse-number>then<note>Or “and”</note> I myself<note>Emphatic personal pronoun</note> will also go against you in hostility, and I myself<note>Emphatic personal pronoun</note> also will strike you seven times for your sins. <verse-number id="Le 26:25">25</verse-number>And I will bring upon you a sword that seeks vengeance <supplied>for the</supplied> covenant, and you shall be gathered to your cities; and I will send a plague in your midst, and you shall be given into <supplied>the</supplied> hand of an enemy. <verse-number id="Le 26:26">26</verse-number>At my breaking <supplied>the</supplied> <idiom-start/>supply<idiom-end/><note>Literally “staff”</note> of bread<note>Or “food”</note> for you, then<note>Or “and”</note> ten women shall bake your bread in one oven, and they shall return your bread by weight; and you shall eat <supplied>it</supplied>, and you shall not be satisfied. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 26:27">27</verse-number>“ ‘And if through this you do not listen to me and you go against me in hostility, <verse-number id="Le 26:28">28</verse-number>then<note>Or “and”</note> I will go against you in hostile anger, and also<note>Or “surely”</note> I myself<note>Emphatic personal pronoun</note> will discipline you seven times for your sins. <verse-number id="Le 26:29">29</verse-number>And you shall eat the flesh of your sons; and the flesh of your daughters you shall eat. <verse-number id="Le 26:30">30</verse-number>And I will destroy your high places, and I will cut down your incense altars, and I will place your corpses on your idols’ corpses; and my inner self<note>Or “soul”</note> shall abhor you. <verse-number id="Le 26:31">31</verse-number>And I will lay your cities <supplied>in</supplied> ruins, and I will lay waste your sanctuaries; and I shall not smell your <supplied>sacrifices’</supplied><note>Implied by the use of the same phraseology in regard to the sacrifices in the early chapters of the book</note> appeasing fragrance. <verse-number id="Le 26:32">32</verse-number>And I myself<note>Emphatic personal pronoun</note> will lay waste the land, and your enemies who are living in it shall be appalled over it. <verse-number id="Le 26:33">33</verse-number>And I will scatter you among the nations, and I will draw a sword behind you; and your land shall be a desolation, and your cities shall be a ruin. <verse-number id="Le 26:34">34</verse-number>Then the land shall enjoy its Sabbaths all the days of its lying desolate, and you <supplied>shall be</supplied> in the land of your enemies; then the land shall rest, and it shall enjoy its Sabbaths. <verse-number id="Le 26:35">35</verse-number>All the days of its lying desolate it shall rest <supplied>for the time</supplied><note>Implied by context</note> that it had not rested during your Sabbaths while you were living on it. <verse-number id="Le 26:36">36</verse-number>As for<note>Or “And”</note> the ones who remain among you, I will bring<note>Or “and I will bring”</note> fearfulness in their hearts in the land of their enemies; and a sound of a windblown leaf shall pursue them, and they shall flee <supplied>like</supplied> flight <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “of”</note> a sword, and they shall fall, but<note>Or “and”</note> there shall not be a pursuer. <verse-number id="Le 26:37">37</verse-number>And they shall stumble over <idiom-start/>one another<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a man on his brother”</note> as <idiom-start/>from before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from the faces of”</note> a sword, but<note>Or “and”</note> there shall not be a pursuer; and <idiom-start/>you shall have no resistance<idiom-end/><note>Literally “it shall not be for you resistance”</note> <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> your enemies. <verse-number id="Le 26:38">38</verse-number>And you shall perish among the nations, and the land of your enemies shall eat you. <verse-number id="Le 26:39">39</verse-number>And because of their guilt, the ones among you who remain shall decay in the land of their enemies; and also because of the iniquities of their ancestors,<note>Or “fathers”</note> they shall decay with them. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 26:40">40</verse-number>“ ‘But<note>Or “And”</note> when they confess their guilt and the guilt of their ancestors<note>Or “fathers”</note> in their infidelity that they displayed against me, and moreover that they went against me in hostility— <verse-number id="Le 26:41">41</verse-number>I myself<note>Emphatic personal pronoun</note> also<note>Or “surely”</note> went against them in hostility, and I brought them into the land of their enemies—or <supplied>if</supplied> then their uncircumcised heart is humbled and then they pay for their guilt, <verse-number id="Le 26:42">42</verse-number>I will remember<note>Or “and I will remember”</note> my covenant <supplied>with</supplied> Jacob; and I will remember also my covenant <supplied>with</supplied> Isaac and also my covenant <supplied>with</supplied> Abraham, and I will remember the land. <verse-number id="Le 26:43">43</verse-number>And the land shall be deserted by them, and it shall enjoy its Sabbaths in its being desolate from them, and they themselves<note>Emphatic personal pronoun</note> must pay for their guilt, <idiom-start/>simply because<idiom-end/><note>Literally “because and in because”</note> they rejected my regulations, and their inner self<note>Or “soul”</note> abhorred my statutes. <verse-number id="Le 26:44">44</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>in spite of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “also even” or “moreover also” or “moreover even”</note> this, <idiom-start/>when they are<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in their being”</note> in the land of their enemies I will not reject them, and I will not abhor them to destroy them, to break my covenant with them, because I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh their God. <verse-number id="Le 26:45">45</verse-number>And I will remember <supplied>the</supplied> first covenant for them<note>Or “on behalf of them” or “on their behalf”</note>—whom I brought out from the land of Egypt <idiom-start/>in the sight of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the eyes of” or “for the eyes of”</note> the nations <idiom-start/>to be their God<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to be for them for God” or “to be for them as a God”</note> I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh.’ ” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 26:46">46</verse-number>These are the rules and the regulations and the laws that Yahweh gave between himself and the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> on <idiom-start/>Mount Sinai<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the mountain of Sinai”</note> <idiom-start/>through<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in/by the hand of”</note> Moses. </p>
		</chapter>