<chapter id="Le 27">
			<pericope>Instructions About Vows</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 27:1">1</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Le 27:2">2</verse-number>“Speak to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and say<note>Or “and you shall say”</note> to them, ‘When a man makes a vow according to your<note>Singular when modifying “proper value” throughout the entire chapter</note> proper value <supplied>of</supplied> persons to Yahweh, <verse-number id="Le 27:3">3</verse-number>if<note>Or “and”</note> your proper value is <supplied>for</supplied> a male<note>Hebrew “the male”</note> from <idiom-start/>twenty years of age<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a son of twenty years”</note> up to<note>Or “and up to”</note> <idiom-start/>sixty years of age<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “a son of sixty years”</note> then<note>Or “and”</note> your proper value shall be fifty shekels <supplied>of</supplied> money according to the sanctuary’s shekel. <verse-number id="Le 27:4">4</verse-number>But<note>Or “And”</note> if it <supplied>is for</supplied> a female, then<note>Or “and”</note> your proper value shall be thirty shekels. <verse-number id="Le 27:5">5</verse-number>And if from <idiom-start/>five years of age<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a son of five years”</note> up to<note>Or “and up to”</note> <idiom-start/>twenty years of age<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “a son of twenty years”</note> then<note>Or “and”</note> your proper value shall be twenty shekels <supplied>for</supplied> the male and ten shekels for the female. <verse-number id="Le 27:6">6</verse-number>And if from <idiom-start/>a month of age<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a son of a month”</note> up to<note>Or “and up to”</note> <idiom-start/>five years of age<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “a son of five years”</note> then<note>Or “and”</note> your proper value shall be five shekels <supplied>of</supplied> money <supplied>for</supplied> the male, and your proper value for the female <supplied>shall be</supplied> three shekels <supplied>of</supplied> money. <verse-number id="Le 27:7">7</verse-number>And if from <idiom-start/>sixty years of age<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a son of sixty years”</note> and above: if a male, then<note>Or “and”</note> your proper value shall be fifteen shekels; and for the female, ten shekels. <verse-number id="Le 27:8">8</verse-number>But<note>Or “And”</note> if he <supplied>is</supplied> poorer than your proper value, then<note>Or “and”</note> he shall present himself <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> the priest, and the priest shall set a value <supplied>on</supplied> him; the priest shall value him <idiom-start/>according to<idiom-end/><note>Literally “on a mouth of”</note> what the person who made a vow <idiom-start/>can afford<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “his hand produces”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 27:9">9</verse-number>“ ‘And if <supplied>it is</supplied> a domestic animal from which they present an offering for Yahweh, all that he gives from it for Yahweh shall be a holy object. <verse-number id="Le 27:10">10</verse-number>He shall not replace it, nor shall he exchange it, <supplied>either</supplied> good with bad or bad with good; and if he indeed exchanges a domestic animal with a domestic animal, then<note>Or “and”</note> <idiom-start/>it and its substitution shall be a holy object<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “it shall be and its substitution shall be holy”</note> <verse-number id="Le 27:11">11</verse-number>But<note>Or “And”</note> if <supplied>it is</supplied> any unclean animal from which they may not present an offering for Yahweh, then<note>Or “and”</note> he shall present the animal <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> the priest. <verse-number id="Le 27:12">12</verse-number>And the priest shall set a value on it, <idiom-start/>either good or bad<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “between good and between bad”</note> as the priest <supplied>sets</supplied> your proper value, so it shall be. <verse-number id="Le 27:13">13</verse-number>And if he indeed wants to redeem it, then<note>Or “and”</note> he shall add a fifth of it onto your proper value. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 27:14">14</verse-number>“ ‘And if a man consecrates his house <supplied>as</supplied> a holy object for Yahweh, then<note>Or “and”</note> the priest shall set a value on it, <idiom-start/>either good or bad<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “between good and between bad”</note> <supplied>just</supplied> as the priest sets a value on it, so it shall remain. <verse-number id="Le 27:15">15</verse-number>But<note>Or “And”</note> if the one who consecrates <supplied>it</supplied> wants to redeem his house, then<note>Or “and”</note> he shall add a fifth of your proper value’s money onto it, and it shall be his. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 27:16">16</verse-number>“ ‘And if a man consecrates <idiom-start/>some of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> his property’s fields<note>Collective singular; Hebrew “field”</note> for Yahweh, then<note>Or “and”</note> your proper value shall be <idiom-start/>in accordance with its seed requirements<idiom-end/>:<note>Literally “to the number of its seed”</note> a homer of barley seed for fifty shekels of money. <verse-number id="Le 27:17">17</verse-number>If he consecrates his field from the Year of Jubilee, it shall stand as your proper value. <verse-number id="Le 27:18">18</verse-number>But<note>Or “And”</note> if he consecrates his field after the Jubilee, then<note>Or “and”</note> the priest shall calculate the money for him <idiom-start/>according to the number of years<idiom-end/><note>Literally “on the mouth of the years”</note> that are left over until the Year of Jubilee; and it shall be deducted from your proper value. <verse-number id="Le 27:19">19</verse-number>And if he indeed redeems the field that is consecrated, then<note>Or “and”</note> he shall add a fifth of your proper value’s money onto it, and it shall stand for<note>Or “remain for” or “belong to”</note> him. <verse-number id="Le 27:20">20</verse-number>And if he does not redeem the field and if he sells the field to another man, it may not be redeemed again, <verse-number id="Le 27:21">21</verse-number>and the field shall be a holy object for Yahweh when it goes out<note>Or “is released” or “reverts”</note> in the Jubilee, like a devoted<note>Or “permanently set apart”; a different Hebrew word than previously translated “consecrated” in this chapter</note> field; <idiom-start/>it shall be the priest’s property<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to/for the priest it shall be his property”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 27:22">22</verse-number>“ ‘And if he consecrates for Yahweh his acquired<note>Or “purchased”</note> field that <supplied>is</supplied> not the field of his <supplied>inherited</supplied> possession, <verse-number id="Le 27:23">23</verse-number>then<note>Or “and”</note> the priest shall calculate for him the <idiom-start/>amount<idiom-end/><note>Literally “number”</note> of your proper value until the year of the Jubilee, and he shall give your proper value on that day <supplied>as</supplied> a holy object for Yahweh. <verse-number id="Le 27:24">24</verse-number>In the Year of the Jubilee the field shall return to the one who bought it from him, to the one whose property the land <supplied>is</supplied>. <verse-number id="Le 27:25">25</verse-number>And every proper value of yours shall be in the sanctuary’s shekel—the shekel shall be twenty gerahs. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 27:26">26</verse-number>“ ‘However, a man shall not consecrate a firstborn among livestock, which belongs as firstborn to Yahweh; whether an ox <idiom-start/>or<idiom-end/><note>Literally “whether” or “if”</note> small livestock, it is for Yahweh. <verse-number id="Le 27:27">27</verse-number>And if <supplied>it is</supplied> among the unclean animals, then<note>Or “and”</note> he shall ransom <supplied>it</supplied> according to your proper value, and he shall add a fifth of its <supplied>value</supplied> onto it; and if it is not redeemed, then<note>Or “and”</note> it shall be sold according to your proper value. <verse-number id="Le 27:28">28</verse-number>However, anything devoted<note>Or “permanently set apart”; a different Hebrew word than previously translated “consecrated” in this chapter</note> that a man has devoted to Yahweh <idiom-start/>from all that he has<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from all that <supplied>is</supplied> for him”</note> from human or<note>Or “and”</note> animal, or<note>Or “and”</note> from the field of his property, may not be sold, and it may not be redeemed; anything devoted <supplied>is</supplied> <idiom-start/>a most holy thing<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a holy thing of holy things”</note> for Yahweh. <verse-number id="Le 27:29">29</verse-number>Anyone devoted who is devoted from <idiom-start/>human beings<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the human”</note> cannot be ransomed—he shall surely be put to death. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 27:30">30</verse-number>“ ‘And any tithe of the land from the land’s seed <supplied>or</supplied> from the fruit of the trees <supplied>is</supplied> for Yahweh; it <supplied>is</supplied> a holy object for Yahweh. <verse-number id="Le 27:31">31</verse-number>And if a man indeed redeems from his tithe, he shall add a fifth of its <supplied>value</supplied> onto it. <verse-number id="Le 27:32">32</verse-number>As for<note>Or “And”</note> every tithe of cattle or<note>Or “and”</note> of the flock,<note>The Hebrew term refers collectively to both sheep and goats (small livestock animals)</note> all which crosses under the rod, the tenth shall be a holy object for Yahweh. <verse-number id="Le 27:33">33</verse-number>He shall not inspect between <supplied>the</supplied> good and <supplied>the</supplied> bad, and he shall not exchange it; but<note>Or “and”</note> if he indeed exchanges it, then<note>Or “and”</note> <idiom-start/>it and its substitution shall be<idiom-end/><note>Literally “it shall be and its substitution shall be”</note> a holy object—it shall not be redeemed.’ ” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Le 27:34">34</verse-number>These <supplied>are</supplied> the commands that Yahweh commanded Moses for the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> on <idiom-start/>Mount Sinai<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the mountain of Sinai”</note> </p>
		</chapter>