<chapter id="Jas 1">
			<pericope>Greeting</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jas 1:1">1</verse-number> James, a slave of God and of the Lord Jesus Christ, to the twelve tribes in the dispersion. Greetings! </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Trials, Testing, and Faith</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jas 1:2">2</verse-number>Consider <supplied>it</supplied> all joy, my brothers, whenever you encounter various trials, <verse-number id="Jas 1:3">3</verse-number><supplied>because you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“know”) which is understood as causal</note> know that the testing of your faith produces endurance. <verse-number id="Jas 1:4">4</verse-number>And let endurance have <supplied>its</supplied> perfect effect, so that you may be mature and complete, lacking in nothing. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jas 1:5">5</verse-number>Now if any of you lacks wisdom, let him ask for <supplied>it</supplied> from God, who gives to all without reservation and not reproaching, and it will be given to him. <verse-number id="Jas 1:6">6</verse-number>But let him ask for <supplied>it</supplied> in faith, without any doubting, for the one who doubts is like the surf of the sea, driven by the wind and tossed about. <verse-number id="Jas 1:7">7</verse-number>For that person must not suppose that he will receive anything from the Lord; <verse-number id="Jas 1:8">8</verse-number><supplied>he is</supplied> a double-minded man, unstable in all his ways. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jas 1:9">9</verse-number>Now let the brother of humble circumstances boast in his high position, <verse-number id="Jas 1:10">10</verse-number>but the rich person in his humiliation, because he will pass away like a flower of the grass. <verse-number id="Jas 1:11">11</verse-number>For the sun rises with its burning heat and dries up the grass, and its flower falls off, and the beauty of its appearance is lost. So also the rich person in his pursuits<note>Or “on his (business) journeys”; or “in his ways”</note> will wither away. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jas 1:12">12</verse-number>Blessed <supplied>is</supplied> the person<note>Literally “the man,” but clearly in a generic sense here meaning “someone, a person”</note> who endures testing, because <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“is”) which is understood as temporal</note> is approved he will receive the crown of life that he<note>Most manuscripts read “the Lord” here, while others read “God”</note> has promised to those who love him. <verse-number id="Jas 1:13">13</verse-number>No one who is being tempted should say, “I am being tempted by God,” for God <idiom-start/>cannot be tempted<idiom-end/><note>Literally “is without temptation”</note> by evil, and he himself tempts no one. <verse-number id="Jas 1:14">14</verse-number>But each one is tempted <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“is dragged away”) which is understood as temporal</note> is dragged away and enticed by his own desires. <verse-number id="Jas 1:15">15</verse-number>Then desire, <supplied>after it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“has conceived”) which is understood as temporal</note> has conceived, gives birth to sin, and sin, <supplied>when it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“is brought to completion”) which is understood as temporal</note> is brought to completion, gives birth to death. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jas 1:16">16</verse-number>Do not be deceived, my dear brothers. <verse-number id="Jas 1:17">17</verse-number>Every good gift and every perfect gift is from above, coming down from the Father of lights, with whom there is no variation or shadow of change. <verse-number id="Jas 1:18">18</verse-number><supplied>By his</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“will”) which is understood as means</note> will he gave birth to us through the message of truth, so that we should be a kind of first fruits of his creatures. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Doers of the Message, Not Just Hearers</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jas 1:19">19</verse-number>Understand <supplied>this</supplied>, my dear brothers: every person must be quick to hear, slow to speak, slow to anger, <verse-number id="Jas 1:20">20</verse-number>for human<note>Literally “man’s”</note> anger does not accomplish the righteousness of God. <verse-number id="Jas 1:21">21</verse-number>Therefore, putting aside all moral uncleanness and wicked excess, welcome<note>Or “receive”</note> with humility the implanted message which is able to save your souls. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jas 1:22">22</verse-number>But be doers of the message and not hearers only,<note>Some manuscripts have “not only hearers”</note> deceiving yourselves, <verse-number id="Jas 1:23">23</verse-number>because if anyone is a hearer of the message and not a doer, this one is like someone<note>Literally “a man,” but clearly in a generic sense here meaning “someone, a person”</note> staring at <idiom-start/>his own face<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the face of his existence”</note> in a mirror, <verse-number id="Jas 1:24">24</verse-number>for he looks at himself and goes away and immediately forgets what sort of <supplied>person</supplied> he was. <verse-number id="Jas 1:25">25</verse-number>But the one who looks into the perfect law of liberty and continues <supplied>to do it</supplied>, not being a forgetful hearer but a doer who acts, this one will be blessed <idiom-start/>in what he does<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in his doing”</note>. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jas 1:26">26</verse-number>If anyone thinks he is religious, <supplied>although he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>although</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“bridle”) which is understood as concessive</note> does not bridle his tongue but deceives his heart, this person’s religion <supplied>is</supplied> worthless. <verse-number id="Jas 1:27">27</verse-number>Pure and undefiled religion in the sight of our<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> God and Father is this: to look after orphans and widows in their affliction, <supplied>and</supplied> to keep oneself unstained by the world. </p>
		</chapter>