<chapter id="Jas 4">
			<pericope>Subject Yourselves to God</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jas 4:1">1</verse-number> From where <supplied>are</supplied> conflicts and from where <supplied>are</supplied> quarrels among you? <supplied>Is it</supplied> not from this, from your pleasures that wage war among your members? <verse-number id="Jas 4:2">2</verse-number>You desire and do not have; you murder and are filled with envy, and are not able to obtain; you fight and quarrel. You do not have because you do not ask. <verse-number id="Jas 4:3">3</verse-number>You ask and do not receive, because you ask with wrong motives, in order that you may spend <supplied>it</supplied> on your pleasures. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jas 4:4">4</verse-number>Adulterous people! Do you not know that friendship with the world is enmity with God? Therefore whoever wants to be a friend of the world makes <supplied>himself</supplied> an enemy of God. <verse-number id="Jas 4:5">5</verse-number>Or do you think that in vain the scripture says, “The spirit which he caused to dwell in us desires jealously”?<note>This translation takes “spirit” to be the capacity within people that produces a divided mind and conflicts regarding God; other translations take this to refer to the Holy Spirit: “He (God) jealously desires the Spirit which he caused to dwell in us”</note> <verse-number id="Jas 4:6">6</verse-number>But he gives greater grace. Therefore it says, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“God opposes the proud, </li1>
				<li2>but gives grace to the humble.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Pr 3:34">Prov 3:34</cite></note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Jas 4:7">7</verse-number>Therefore subject yourselves to God. But resist the devil, and he will flee from you. <verse-number id="Jas 4:8">8</verse-number>Draw near to God, and he will draw near to you. Cleanse <supplied>your</supplied> hands, <supplied>you</supplied> sinners, and purify <supplied>your</supplied> hearts, <supplied>you</supplied> double-minded! <verse-number id="Jas 4:9">9</verse-number>Lament and mourn and weep! Let your laughter be turned to mourning, and your<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> joy to gloominess. <verse-number id="Jas 4:10">10</verse-number>Humble yourselves before the Lord, and he will exalt you. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jas 4:11">11</verse-number>Do not speak evil of one another, brothers. The one who speaks evil of a brother or judges his brother speaks evil of the law and judges the law. But if you judge the law, you are not a doer of the law but a judge <supplied>of the law</supplied>.<note>The words “of the law” are not in the Greek text, but are an understood repetition from the previous clause</note> <verse-number id="Jas 4:12">12</verse-number>There is one lawgiver and judge who is able to save and to destroy. But who are you to judge your<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> neighbor? </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Arrogant Boasting About the Future</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jas 4:13">13</verse-number>Come now, you who say, “Today or tomorrow we will travel to such and such a city and spend a year there, and carry on business and make a profit,” <verse-number id="Jas 4:14">14</verse-number>you who do not know <idiom-start/>what will happen tomorrow<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the <supplied>circumstance</supplied> of tomorrow”</note>, <idiom-start/>what your life will be like<idiom-end/><note>Literally “of what sort your life”</note>. For you are a smoky vapor that appears for a short time and then disappears. <verse-number id="Jas 4:15">15</verse-number>Instead you should say, “If the Lord wills, we will live and do this or that.” <verse-number id="Jas 4:16">16</verse-number>But now you boast in your arrogance. All such boasting is evil. <verse-number id="Jas 4:17">17</verse-number>Therefore, to the one who knows to do good and does not do <supplied>it</supplied>, to him it is sin. </p>
		</chapter>