<chapter id="2 Ch 2">
			<pericope>Solomon Petitions the King of Tyre</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 2:1">1</verse-number><note><cite title="BibleLEB2: 2 Ch 2:1–18">2 Chronicles 2:1–18 </cite>in the English Bible is 1:18–2:17 in the Hebrew Bible</note> And Solomon planned to build a house for the name of Yahweh and a <idiom-start/>royal palace for himself<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “house for his kingdom”</note> <verse-number id="2 Ch 2:2">2</verse-number>And Solomon assigned seventy thousand men <idiom-start/>to bear burdens<idiom-end/><note>Literally “carriers”</note> and eighty thousand <idiom-start/>quarriers<idiom-end/><note>Literally “stone craftsmen”</note> in the hill country, and three thousand six hundred <supplied>men</supplied> to supervise them. <verse-number id="2 Ch 2:3">3</verse-number>And Solomon sent <supplied>word</supplied> to Huram<note>This is the spelling in Hebrew, though many translations have “Hiram”</note> king of Tyre, saying, “As you have dealt with David my father and sent cedar to him to build for himself a house in which to live, <supplied>please deal with me</supplied>. <verse-number id="2 Ch 2:4">4</verse-number>Look, I am building a house for the name of Yahweh my God to dedicate to him, to offer sweet spices of incense before him, and <supplied>for</supplied> the regular rows <supplied>of bread</supplied>, and burnt offerings for mornings, evenings, Sabbaths, and new moon festivals, and for appointed feasts of Yahweh our God which <supplied>are</supplied> everlasting for Israel. <verse-number id="2 Ch 2:5">5</verse-number>And the house that I am building <supplied>will be</supplied> great, for our God <supplied>is</supplied> greater than all gods. <verse-number id="2 Ch 2:6">6</verse-number>Now who indeed has adequate strength to build a house for him? For the heavens and <idiom-start/>the highest heavens<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the heavens of the heavens”</note> are not able to contain him. Now who <supplied>am</supplied> I that I would build a house for him, except to burn incense before him? <verse-number id="2 Ch 2:7">7</verse-number>So then, send to me skilled men to work with gold, silver, bronze, and iron, and with purple, crimson, and blue fabric, knowledgeable in engraving, with the skilled men who <supplied>are</supplied> with me in Judah and in Jerusalem, whom David my father has established. <verse-number id="2 Ch 2:8">8</verse-number>Send me trees of cedar, cypress, and algum from Lebanon, for I myself know that your servants <supplied>are</supplied> knowledgeable in cutting the trees of Lebanon. Now see, my servants <supplied>will be</supplied> with your servants <verse-number id="2 Ch 2:9">9</verse-number>to prepare trees in abundance for me, for the house that I am building <supplied>will be</supplied> great and wonderful. <verse-number id="2 Ch 2:10">10</verse-number>Now see, I will provide twenty thousand dry measures of crushed wheat, twenty thousand dry measures of barley, twenty thousand baths of wine, and twenty thousand baths of oil to the woodcarvers and those who cut timber.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 2:11">11</verse-number>Then Huram<note>This is the spelling in Hebrew, though many translations have “Hiram”</note> king of Tyre answered in a letter, and he sent <supplied>word</supplied> to Solomon: “Because Yahweh loves his people, he has made you king over them.” <verse-number id="2 Ch 2:12">12</verse-number>Then Huram<note>This is the spelling in Hebrew, though many translations have “Hiram”</note> said, “Blessed be Yahweh, the God of Israel, who has made the heavens and the earth, who has given to King David a wise son knowing discretion and understanding, who will build for Yahweh a house and a royal palace for himself. <verse-number id="2 Ch 2:13">13</verse-number>So now I have sent a skilled man, knowledgeable <supplied>and with</supplied> understanding: my master<note>Or “my father”</note> Huram, <verse-number id="2 Ch 2:14">14</verse-number>a son of a woman from the daughters of Dan, and his father <supplied>was</supplied> a man of Tyre, knowledgeable for working with gold, silver, bronze, iron, stone, and wood, and with purple, blue, and crimson fabric, and with fine linen, for engraving any engraving and devising any plan that is given to him, with your skilled men and the skilled men of my lord David your father. <verse-number id="2 Ch 2:15">15</verse-number>Now as for the wheat, barley, oil, and wine that my lord mentioned, let him send <supplied>that</supplied> to his servants. <verse-number id="2 Ch 2:16">16</verse-number>And we ourselves will cut trees from Lebanon according to all your need, and we will bring them to you on rafts over the sea to Joppa, so that you may bring them up to Jerusalem.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 2:17">17</verse-number>Then Solomon counted all the resident alien men who <supplied>were</supplied> in the land of Israel after the census that David his father had taken of them. And there were found one hundred and fifty-three thousand. <verse-number id="2 Ch 2:18">18</verse-number>And he appointed from them seventy thousand <idiom-start/>to bear burdens<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “carriers”</note> eighty thousand <idiom-start/>to quarry<idiom-end/><note>Literally “stone craftsmen”</note> in the hill country, and three thousand six hundred overseers to make the people work. </p>
		</chapter>