<chapter id="2 Ch 3">
			<pericope>Solomon Builds the Temple</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 3:1">1</verse-number>Then Solomon began to build the house of Yahweh in Jerusalem, on Mount Moriah, where Yahweh had appeared to David his father, at the place that David had established, on the threshing floor of Ornan the Jebusite. <verse-number id="2 Ch 3:2">2</verse-number>And he began to build in the second month of the fourth year of his reign. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 3:3">3</verse-number>Now these <supplied>were</supplied> the measurements of Solomon for building the house of God: the length in cubits by the former measurement <supplied>was</supplied> sixty cubits, and the width <supplied>was</supplied> twenty cubits. <verse-number id="2 Ch 3:4">4</verse-number><idiom-start/>The length of the portico that <supplied>was</supplied> in front was the same as the front of the width of the house<idiom-end/>:<note>Literally “The length at the front of the portico the front of the width of the house”</note> twenty cubits. And its height <supplied>was</supplied> one hundred and twenty cubits. And he overlaid it on the inside with pure gold. <verse-number id="2 Ch 3:5">5</verse-number>And the great house <supplied>itself</supplied> he covered with cypress wood, then he overlaid it with pure gold. And he put on it palm tree <supplied>images</supplied> and <supplied>ornate</supplied> chains. <verse-number id="2 Ch 3:6">6</verse-number>Then he overlaid the house with precious stone as decoration. (Now the gold <supplied>was</supplied> the gold of Parvaim.) <verse-number id="2 Ch 3:7">7</verse-number>And he overlaid the house with gold—the beams, the thresholds, the walls, and the doors. And he carved cherubim upon the walls. <verse-number id="2 Ch 3:8">8</verse-number>Then he made <idiom-start/>the most holy place<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the house of the holy of the holies”</note> Its length <idiom-start/>was equal to<idiom-end/><note>Literally “at the front of”</note> the width of the house: twenty cubits. And its breadth <supplied>was</supplied> twenty cubits. And he overlaid it with six hundred talents of fine gold. <verse-number id="2 Ch 3:9">9</verse-number>And the weight for the nails <supplied>was</supplied> fifty shekels of gold. And he overlaid its upper rooms with gold. <verse-number id="2 Ch 3:10">10</verse-number>And he made two sculpted wood cherubim in <idiom-start/>the most holy place<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the house of the holy of the holies”</note> and he overlaid them with gold. <verse-number id="2 Ch 3:11">11</verse-number>The length of the <supplied>outstretched</supplied> wings of the cherubim <supplied>were</supplied> twenty cubits; one wing of five cubits touched the wall of the house, and the other wing of five cubits <supplied>was</supplied> touching the <supplied>outstretched</supplied> wing of the other cherub. <verse-number id="2 Ch 3:12">12</verse-number>And the wing of five cubits of the other cherub <supplied>was</supplied> touching the wall of the house, and its other wing five cubits long touching the wing of the first<note>Or “other”</note> cherub. <verse-number id="2 Ch 3:13">13</verse-number>The wings of these cherubim extended twenty cubits, and they were standing on their feet, their faces toward the house. <verse-number id="2 Ch 3:14">14</verse-number>And he made the curtain of blue and purple and crimson and fine linen, and put cherubim on it. <verse-number id="2 Ch 3:15">15</verse-number>And at the front of the house he made two columns, thirty-five cubits high, and the capital on their top was five cubits. <verse-number id="2 Ch 3:16">16</verse-number>And he made <supplied>decorative</supplied> chains in the inner sanctuary and put <supplied>them</supplied> on top of the columns. And he made one hundred pomegranate <supplied>ornaments</supplied>, and put them on the chains. <verse-number id="2 Ch 3:17">17</verse-number>And he erected the columns in front of the temple, one on the south and one on the north. He called the name of the southern one Jakin, and the name of the northern one Boaz. </p>
		</chapter>