<chapter id="2 Ch 4">
			<pericope>The Furnishings of Solomon’s Temple</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 4:1">1</verse-number>And he made an altar of bronze, twenty cubits <supplied>was</supplied> its length, and twenty cubits <supplied>was</supplied> its width, and ten cubits <supplied>was</supplied> its height. <verse-number id="2 Ch 4:2">2</verse-number>Then he made the sea of molten metal, from brim to brim <supplied>it was</supplied> ten cubits, completely round. And <supplied>it was</supplied> five cubits in height, and <idiom-start/>its circumference measured<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and it measured a line all around it”</note> thirty cubits. <verse-number id="2 Ch 4:3">3</verse-number>Under it <supplied>were</supplied> figures of oxen all around it, ten cubits <supplied>high</supplied>, encircling the sea all around. The oxen <supplied>were</supplied> in two rows <idiom-start/>cast as one piece with it<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “molten with its casting”</note> <verse-number id="2 Ch 4:4">4</verse-number><supplied>It was</supplied> standing upon twelve oxen, three facing north, and three facing west, and three facing south, and three facing east. The sea <supplied>was set</supplied> upon them from above, and all their hindquarters <supplied>faced</supplied> <idiom-start/>inward<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “into the house”</note> <verse-number id="2 Ch 4:5">5</verse-number>And its thickness <supplied>was</supplied> a handbreadth, and its brim <supplied>was</supplied> like the working of the lip of a cup, the blossom of a lily. And it held three thousand baths. <verse-number id="2 Ch 4:6">6</verse-number>And he made ten basins. And he set five on the south and five on the north in which to wash; they washed off the work of the burnt offering in them, but the sea <supplied>was</supplied> for the priests to wash therein. <verse-number id="2 Ch 4:7">7</verse-number>And he made ten golden lampstands according to their custom, and he set <supplied>them</supplied> in the temple, five on the south and five on the north. <verse-number id="2 Ch 4:8">8</verse-number>And he made ten tables and placed them in the temple, five on the south and five on the north. And he made a hundred drinking bowls of gold. <verse-number id="2 Ch 4:9">9</verse-number>And he made the courtyard of the priests and the great outer courtyard and the doors for the outer court. And he overlaid their doors with bronze. <verse-number id="2 Ch 4:10">10</verse-number>And he set the sea at the southeast <supplied>corner of the temple</supplied>. <verse-number id="2 Ch 4:11">11</verse-number>And Huram<note>This is the spelling in Hebrew, though many translations have “Hiram”</note> made the pots, the shovels, and the drinking bowls. So Hiram<note>The spelling (“Hiram”) is different here than in the previous occurrences</note> finished making the work that he made on the house of God for King Solomon: <verse-number id="2 Ch 4:12">12</verse-number>the two columns, the bowls, and the two capitals on top of the columns, and the two latticeworks to cover the two bowls of the capitals that <supplied>were</supplied> on top of the columns, <verse-number id="2 Ch 4:13">13</verse-number>and the four hundred pomegranates for the two latticeworks, two rows of pomegranates for the latticework, to cover the two bowls of the capitals that <supplied>were</supplied> before the columns. <verse-number id="2 Ch 4:14">14</verse-number>And he made the water carts, and he made the basins on the water carts, <verse-number id="2 Ch 4:15">15</verse-number>and the one sea and the twelve oxen underneath it. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 4:16">16</verse-number>And Huram-abi made for King Solomon the pots, the shovels, the three-pronged meat forks, and all the utensils of polished bronze for the house of Yahweh. <verse-number id="2 Ch 4:17">17</verse-number>The king cast them in the plain of the Jordan, in the clay soil between Succoth and Zeredah. <verse-number id="2 Ch 4:18">18</verse-number>Solomon made all these utensils in great abundance, for the weight of the bronze could not be determined. <verse-number id="2 Ch 4:19">19</verse-number>So Solomon made all the objects that <supplied>were in</supplied> the house of God: the altar of gold; the tables upon which <supplied>was</supplied> the bread of the presence; <verse-number id="2 Ch 4:20">20</verse-number>the lampstands, and the lamps for burning according to the custom before the inner sanctuary, of solid gold; <verse-number id="2 Ch 4:21">21</verse-number>and the blossoms, the lamps, and the tongs that <supplied>were</supplied> of solid gold; <verse-number id="2 Ch 4:22">22</verse-number>and the snuffers, the drinking bowls, the dishes, and the firepans, of solid gold; and the entrance to the house, the inner doors to <idiom-start/>the most holy place<idiom-end/>, and the doors to the house of the temple <supplied>were</supplied> of gold. </p>
		</chapter>