<chapter id="2 Ch 5">
			<pericope>The Ark Installed in the Temple</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 5:1">1</verse-number>When all the work that Solomon did for the house of Yahweh was finished, Solomon brought the holy objects of David his father: the silver, the gold, and all the objects he had put into the storehouses of the house of God. <verse-number id="2 Ch 5:2">2</verse-number>Then Solomon assembled all the elders of Israel and all the heads of the tribes, the leaders of the <idiom-start/>families<idiom-end/><note>Literally “fathers”</note> for the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> to Jerusalem in order to bring up the ark of the covenant of Yahweh from the city of David, which <supplied>is</supplied> Zion. <verse-number id="2 Ch 5:3">3</verse-number>And all the men of Israel assembled before the king at the feast that <supplied>is in</supplied> the seventh month. <verse-number id="2 Ch 5:4">4</verse-number>And all the elders of Israel came, and the Levites took up the ark. <verse-number id="2 Ch 5:5">5</verse-number>And they brought up the ark, the tent of assembly,<note>Or “meeting”</note> and all the holy objects that <supplied>were</supplied> in the tent; the Levitical priests brought them up. <verse-number id="2 Ch 5:6">6</verse-number>And King Solomon and the whole community of Israel that was assembled before him <supplied>were</supplied> before the ark, sacrificing sheep and cattle that could not be counted nor numbered for abundance. <verse-number id="2 Ch 5:7">7</verse-number>Then the priests brought up the ark of the covenant of Yahweh to its place in the inner sanctuary of the house, into <idiom-start/>the most holy place<idiom-end/>, underneath the wings of the cherubim. <verse-number id="2 Ch 5:8">8</verse-number>The cherubim were spreading <supplied>their</supplied> wings over the place of the ark, so that the cherubim were covering the ark and over its poles <supplied>from</supplied> above. <verse-number id="2 Ch 5:9">9</verse-number>But the poles were <supplied>so</supplied> long that the ends of the poles from the ark were seen from before the inner sanctuary, but they could not be seen from the outside. And they are there until this day. <verse-number id="2 Ch 5:10">10</verse-number>There was nothing in the ark but the two stone tablets that Moses had put <supplied>inside</supplied> at Horeb <supplied>on</supplied> which Yahweh had <idiom-start/>made<idiom-end/><note>Literally “cut”</note> a covenant with the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> when they went out from Egypt. <verse-number id="2 Ch 5:11">11</verse-number>And when the priests came out of the sanctuary (for all the priests who were present<note>Or “who were found”</note> sanctified themselves without keeping their divisions) <verse-number id="2 Ch 5:12">12</verse-number>and all the Levitical singers—Asaph, Heman, Jeduthun, their sons, their brothers, dressed <supplied>in</supplied> fine linen, with cymbals, harps, and stringed instruments—<supplied>they</supplied> were standing to the east of the altar. And with them outside <supplied>were</supplied> one hundred and twenty priests <supplied>who were</supplied> trumpet blowers. <verse-number id="2 Ch 5:13">13</verse-number>And it was the primary <supplied>duty</supplied> of the trumpeters and singers to make themselves heard <supplied>with</supplied> one voice, to praise and give thanks to Yahweh. And when a sound from the trumpets, cymbals, and other instruments of song was raised to Yahweh—for he <supplied>is</supplied> good, because his loyal love <supplied>is</supplied> everlasting—then the house, the house of Yahweh, was filled with a cloud. <verse-number id="2 Ch 5:14">14</verse-number>And the priests were not able to stand to minister because of the cloud, for the glory of Yahweh filled the house of God. </p>
		</chapter>