<chapter id="2 Ch 9">
			<pericope>Solomon and the Queen of Sheba</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 9:1">1</verse-number>Now the queen of Sheba heard of the fame of Solomon, and she came to Jerusalem to test Solomon with hard questions, with much wealth and camels, bearing spices and much gold and precious stones. And she came to Solomon and told him all that <supplied>was</supplied> <idiom-start/>on her mind<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “in her heart”</note> <verse-number id="2 Ch 9:2">2</verse-number>And Solomon <idiom-start/>answered all her questions<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “made known to her all her words”</note> Not a word was hidden from Solomon that he did not answer for her. <verse-number id="2 Ch 9:3">3</verse-number>When the queen of Sheba saw the wisdom of Solomon and the house he had built, <verse-number id="2 Ch 9:4">4</verse-number>and the food of his table, and the position of his officers, the duty of his servants and their clothing, his cupbearers and their clothing, and his burnt offerings that he offered at the house of Yahweh, there was no longer any breath<note>Or “spirit”</note> in her. <verse-number id="2 Ch 9:5">5</verse-number>And she said to the king, “The word which I heard in my land concerning your words and your wisdom <supplied>is</supplied> true, <verse-number id="2 Ch 9:6">6</verse-number>but I did not believe their words until I came and saw with my own eyes. And behold, half the greatness of your wisdom was not reported to me; you surpass the rumors that I had heard. <verse-number id="2 Ch 9:7">7</verse-number>Blessed <supplied>are</supplied> your men, and blessed <supplied>are</supplied> these your servants who stand before you regularly and hear your wisdom! <verse-number id="2 Ch 9:8">8</verse-number>Blessed be Yahweh your God who took delight in you, to put you on his throne as king for Yahweh your God! Because your God loved Israel, he established him forever and has put you over them as king to do justice and righteousness!” <verse-number id="2 Ch 9:9">9</verse-number>And she gave to the king one hundred and twenty talents of gold and a very great amount of spices and precious stones. And there were no spices such as those that the queen of Sheba gave to King Solomon. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 9:10">10</verse-number>Moreover the servants of Hiram and the servants of Solomon who brought gold from Ophir brought algum wood and precious stones. <verse-number id="2 Ch 9:11">11</verse-number>And the king made steps for the house of Yahweh and the house of the king, and lyres and harps for the singers <supplied>from</supplied> the algum wood. And there was not seen <supplied>anything</supplied> like them before in the land of Judah. <verse-number id="2 Ch 9:12">12</verse-number>Now King Solomon gave to the queen of Sheba every desired thing she asked, besides what she had brought to the king. Then she turned and went to her land, she and her servants. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Solomon’s Great Wealth</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 9:13">13</verse-number>And it happened <supplied>that</supplied> the weight of the gold that came to Solomon in one year <supplied>was</supplied> six hundred and sixty-six talents of gold, <verse-number id="2 Ch 9:14">14</verse-number>besides the gold and silver the traders and merchants brought, and all the kings of Arabia and the governors of the land brought. <verse-number id="2 Ch 9:15">15</verse-number>And King Solomon made two hundred shields of beaten gold; six hundred <supplied>shekels</supplied> of beaten gold went into each shield. <verse-number id="2 Ch 9:16">16</verse-number>And <supplied>he made</supplied> three hundred small shields of beaten gold; three hundred <supplied>shekels</supplied> went into each small shield. And the king put them in the House of the Forest of Lebanon. <verse-number id="2 Ch 9:17">17</verse-number>And the king made a large ivory throne and overlaid it with pure gold. <verse-number id="2 Ch 9:18">18</verse-number>And the throne had six steps, and a footstool of gold <supplied>was</supplied> attached to the throne. And <supplied>there were</supplied> armrests <idiom-start/>on each side<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “from this and from that”</note> And by <idiom-start/>the seat<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the place of sitting”</note> <supplied>were</supplied> two lions standing beside the armrests. <verse-number id="2 Ch 9:19">19</verse-number>And twelve lions were standing there on <supplied>each</supplied> of the six steps <idiom-start/>on each end<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “from this and from that”</note> And there was nothing like <supplied>it</supplied> made in all the kingdom. <verse-number id="2 Ch 9:20">20</verse-number>And all the drinking vessels of King Solomon <supplied>were</supplied> of gold, and all the vessels of the House of the Forest of Lebanon <supplied>were</supplied> of pure gold. Silver was not valued as anything in the days of Solomon. <verse-number id="2 Ch 9:21">21</verse-number>For the ships of the king went to Tarshish with the servants of Huram.<note>This is the spelling in Hebrew, though many translations have “Hiram”</note> Once <idiom-start/>every three years<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for three years”</note> the ships of Tarshish came carrying gold, silver, ivory, apes, and peacocks. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 9:22">22</verse-number>Thus King Solomon was greater than all the kings of the earth in wealth and wisdom. <verse-number id="2 Ch 9:23">23</verse-number>And all the kings of the earth sought the face of Solomon to hear his wisdom that God put in his heart. <verse-number id="2 Ch 9:24">24</verse-number>And each of them brought his gifts, objects of silver, objects of gold, cloaks, myrrh, spices, horses, and mules, <supplied>as</supplied> an amount year by year. <verse-number id="2 Ch 9:25">25</verse-number>And Solomon had four thousand stalls for horses and chariots, and twelve thousand horsemen. And he stationed them in the chariot cities and with the king in Jerusalem. <verse-number id="2 Ch 9:26">26</verse-number>And he ruled over all the kings from the River<note>That is, the Euphrates</note> to the land of the Philistines, to the boundary of Egypt. <verse-number id="2 Ch 9:27">27</verse-number>And the king made silver in Jerusalem as stones, and he made cedar as the sycamore trees that <supplied>are</supplied> in the Shephelah for abundance. <verse-number id="2 Ch 9:28">28</verse-number>And the horses <supplied>were</supplied> imported from Egypt and from all lands for Solomon. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Death of Solomon</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 9:29">29</verse-number>As for the remainder of the words of Solomon <supplied>from</supplied> the first to the last, are they not written in the chronicles<note>Or “words”</note> of Nathan the prophet and in the prophecy of Ahijah the Shilonite, and in the visions of Iddo the seer, concerning Jeroboam the son of Nebat? <verse-number id="2 Ch 9:30">30</verse-number>And Solomon reigned in Jerusalem over all Israel forty years. <verse-number id="2 Ch 9:31">31</verse-number>And Solomon slept with his ancestors,<note>Or “fathers”</note> and they buried him in the city of David his father. And Rehoboam his son reigned in his place. </p>
		</chapter>