<chapter id="2 Ch 11">
			<pericope>Rehoboam’s Kingdom</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 11:1">1</verse-number>When Rehoboam came to Jerusalem he assembled the house of Judah and Benjamin, one hundred and eighty thousand <idiom-start/>chosen warriors<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “chosen makers of war”</note> to fight against Israel to restore the kingdom to Rehoboam. <verse-number id="2 Ch 11:2">2</verse-number>But the word of Yahweh came to Shemaiah, the man of God, saying, <verse-number id="2 Ch 11:3">3</verse-number>“Say to Rehoboam, son of Solomon, king of Judah, and to all Israel in Judah and Benjamin, <verse-number id="2 Ch 11:4">4</verse-number>‘Thus says Yahweh: “Do not go up, and do not fight against your brothers. Return, each man to his house, for this matter has come from me.” ’ ” So they obeyed the words of Yahweh and turned back from going against Jeroboam. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 11:5">5</verse-number>And Rehoboam lived in Jerusalem, and he built cities as strongholds in Judah. <verse-number id="2 Ch 11:6">6</verse-number>He built Bethlehem, Etah, Tekoa, <verse-number id="2 Ch 11:7">7</verse-number>Beth-Zur, Socoh, Adullam, <verse-number id="2 Ch 11:8">8</verse-number>Gath, Mareshah, Ziph, <verse-number id="2 Ch 11:9">9</verse-number>Adoraim, Lachish, Azekah, <verse-number id="2 Ch 11:10">10</verse-number>Zorah, Aijalon, and Hebron, fortified cities that <supplied>are</supplied> in Judah and in Benjamin. <verse-number id="2 Ch 11:11">11</verse-number>And he strengthened the fortifications and put commanders in them, <supplied>along with</supplied> stores of food, olive oil, and wine. <verse-number id="2 Ch 11:12">12</verse-number>And in all the cities <supplied>he put</supplied> shields and spears, and he greatly strengthened them. So he had Judah and Benjamin. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Priests and Levites Come to Jerusalem</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 11:13">13</verse-number>Now the priests and the Levites who <supplied>were</supplied> throughout all Israel took their stand with him<note>That is, Rehoboam</note> from all their territories. <verse-number id="2 Ch 11:14">14</verse-number>For the Levites left their pasturelands and their property and came to Judah and to Jerusalem, for Jeroboam and his sons had rejected them from serving as priests to Yahweh. <verse-number id="2 Ch 11:15">15</verse-number>And he appointed his own priests for the high places and for the goat idols and for the bull calves that he had made. <verse-number id="2 Ch 11:16">16</verse-number>Then after them, from all the tribes of Israel, those who set their heart to seek Yahweh, the God of Israel, came to Jerusalem to offer to Yahweh, the God of their ancestors.<note>Or “fathers”</note> <verse-number id="2 Ch 11:17">17</verse-number>And they strengthened the kingdom of Judah and made Rehoboam, the son of Solomon, secure for three years, for they walked in the way of David and Solomon for three years. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Rehoboam’s Harem and Family</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 11:18">18</verse-number>Then Rehoboam took to himself as a wife Mahalath, the daughter<note>This follows the reading tradition (<i>Qere)</i>; the <i>Kethib</i> reading has “son”</note> of Yerimot son of David, and of Abihail the daughter of Eliab the son of Jesse. <verse-number id="2 Ch 11:19">19</verse-number>And she bore to him sons: Jeush, Shemariah, and Zaham. <verse-number id="2 Ch 11:20">20</verse-number>And after her he took Maacah the daughter of Absalom, who bore to him Abijah, Attai, Ziza, and Shelomith. <verse-number id="2 Ch 11:21">21</verse-number>And Rehoboam loved Maacah the daughter of Absalom more than all his wives and concubines (for he took eighteen wives and sixty concubines, and he fathered twenty-eight sons and sixty daughters). <verse-number id="2 Ch 11:22">22</verse-number>And Rehoboam appointed Abijah the son of Maacah as chief and crown prince over his brothers, in order to make him king. <verse-number id="2 Ch 11:23">23</verse-number>And he dealt wisely and distributed some of his sons throughout all the land of Judah and Benjamin, through all the fortified cities, and gave abundant provisions to them and obtained many wives <supplied>for them</supplied>. </p>
		</chapter>