<chapter id="2 Ch 13">
			<pericope>Abijah and Civil War</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 13:1">1</verse-number>In the eighteenth year of King Jeroboam, Abijah reigned over Judah. <verse-number id="2 Ch 13:2">2</verse-number>He reigned for three years in Jerusalem. And the name of his mother <supplied>was</supplied> Micaiah the daughter of Uriel from Gibeah. </p>
			<p>Now there was war between Abijah and between Jeroboam. <verse-number id="2 Ch 13:3">3</verse-number>And Abijah joined in the battle with an army of four hundred thousand <idiom-start/>battle-hardened warriors<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “mighty warriors of battle”</note> chosen men, and Jeroboam put the battle in order against him with eight hundred thousand chosen men, an army of mighty warriors. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 13:4">4</verse-number>Then Abijah stood up on top of Mount Zemaraim that <supplied>is</supplied> in the hill country of Ephraim and said, “Hear me, O Jeroboam and all Israel! <verse-number id="2 Ch 13:5">5</verse-number>Do you not all know that Yahweh the God of Israel gave the kingdom to David over Israel forever, to him and to his sons <supplied>by</supplied> a covenant of salt? <verse-number id="2 Ch 13:6">6</verse-number>But Jeroboam the son of Nebat, a servant of Solomon the son of David, rose up and rebelled against his master, <verse-number id="2 Ch 13:7">7</verse-number>and worthless men, <idiom-start/>sons of wickedness<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons of Belial”</note> were gathered about him and became hostile against Rehoboam the son of Solomon, when Rehoboam was a boy and gentle of heart and was not strong enough <supplied>to stand</supplied> before them. <verse-number id="2 Ch 13:8">8</verse-number>So now you yourselves are considering <supplied>that you are</supplied> strong before the kingdom of Yahweh <supplied>which is</supplied> in the hand the sons of David, since you yourselves are a great multitude and you have bull calves of gold that Jeroboam has made for idols. <verse-number id="2 Ch 13:9">9</verse-number>Did you not drive out the priests of Yahweh, the sons of Aaron, the Levites? Have you <supplied>not</supplied> made for yourselves priests like all the peoples of the lands? All who come <idiom-start/>to be consecrated for priestly service<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to fill his hand” (a Hebrew idiom for ordination)</note> with a young bull or seven rams becomes a priest of <supplied>what is</supplied> not a god. <verse-number id="2 Ch 13:10">10</verse-number>But as for us, Yahweh <supplied>is</supplied> our God, and we have not forsaken him. The priests serving Yahweh <supplied>are</supplied> the sons of Aaron, the Levites, according to their service. <verse-number id="2 Ch 13:11">11</verse-number>They offer burnt offerings to Yahweh <idiom-start/>every morning<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the morning, in the morning”</note> and <idiom-start/>every evening<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “in the evening, in the evening”</note> sweet spices of incense, and the rows of bread upon the pure table. And the golden lampstand with its lamps <supplied>they</supplied> keep kindled <idiom-start/>every evening<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “in the evening, in the evening”</note> for we are keeping the requirement of Yahweh our God, but you yourselves have forsaken him. <verse-number id="2 Ch 13:12">12</verse-number>And look, God <supplied>is</supplied> with us at the head, and his priests <supplied>have</supplied> the trumpets for sounding blasts against you, O sons of Israel. Do not fight against Yahweh, the God of your ancestors,<note>Or “fathers”</note> for you will not succeed.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 13:13">13</verse-number>Then Jeroboam sent around an ambush to come behind them. So they were in front of Judah, but the ambush <supplied>was</supplied> behind them. <verse-number id="2 Ch 13:14">14</verse-number>When Judah turned, then behold, the battle against them <supplied>was</supplied> in front and behind, and they cried to Yahweh, and the priests blew on the trumpets. <verse-number id="2 Ch 13:15">15</verse-number>Then the men of Judah shouted, and it happened <supplied>that</supplied> when the men of Judah were shouting, then God defeated Jeroboam and all Israel before Abijah and Judah. <verse-number id="2 Ch 13:16">16</verse-number>And the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> fled from before Judah, and God gave them into their hand. <verse-number id="2 Ch 13:17">17</verse-number>And Abijah and his people struck a great blow against them, and the dead from Israel <supplied>that</supplied> fell <supplied>were</supplied> five hundred thousand chosen men. <verse-number id="2 Ch 13:18">18</verse-number>And the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> were subdued at that time, and the people<note>Or “sons”</note> of Judah were victorious, for they relied upon Yahweh the God of their ancestors.<note>Or “fathers”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 13:19">19</verse-number>And Abijah pursued after Jeroboam and took cities from him: Bethel with its villages, Jeshanah with its villages, and Ephron with its villages. <verse-number id="2 Ch 13:20">20</verse-number>And Jeroboam did not regain strength again in the days of Abijah. And Yahweh plagued him and he died. <verse-number id="2 Ch 13:21">21</verse-number>But Abijah became strong, and he took to himself fourteen wives and fathered twenty-two sons and sixteen daughters. <verse-number id="2 Ch 13:22">22</verse-number>Now the rest of the words of Abijah and his ways and his words are written in the story of the prophet Iddo. </p>
		</chapter>