<chapter id="2 Ch 14">
			<pericope>The Reign of Asa in Judah</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 14:1">1</verse-number><note><cite title="BibleLEB2: 2 Ch 14:1–15">2 Chronicles 14:1–15 </cite>in the English Bible is 13:23–14:14 in the Hebrew Bible</note> And Abijah slept with his ancestors,<note>Or “fathers”</note> and they buried him in the city of David. And Asa his son became king in his place. In his days the land was at rest ten years. <verse-number id="2 Ch 14:2">2</verse-number>Asa did that which <supplied>was</supplied> good and right in the eyes of Yahweh his God. <verse-number id="2 Ch 14:3">3</verse-number>He removed the foreign altars and high places, broke down the stone pillars, and cut down the Asherahs. <verse-number id="2 Ch 14:4">4</verse-number>And he commanded Judah to seek Yahweh, the God of their ancestors,<note>Or “fathers”</note> and to keep the law and the commandment. <verse-number id="2 Ch 14:5">5</verse-number>And he removed the high places and the incense stands from all the cities of Judah, and the kingdom had rest under<note>Or “before”</note> him. <verse-number id="2 Ch 14:6">6</verse-number>And he built fortified cities in Judah, for the land was at rest. Under<note>Or “With”</note> him there was no war in those years, for Yahweh had given rest to him. <verse-number id="2 Ch 14:7">7</verse-number>And he said to Judah, “Let us build these cities and surround <supplied>them with</supplied> walls, towers, gates, and bars while the land <supplied>is</supplied> before us, because we have sought Yahweh our God. We have sought and he has given rest to us on every side.” So they built and had success. <verse-number id="2 Ch 14:8">8</verse-number>And Asa had an army <supplied>of</supplied> three hundred thousand from Judah, bearing shields and spears, and two hundred and eighty thousand from Benjamin <supplied>who</supplied> carried shields and drew bows. All of these <supplied>were</supplied> mighty warriors of strength. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 14:9">9</verse-number>Zerah the Cushite came out against them with an army of a thousand thousands and three hundred chariots. And he came to Mareshah. <verse-number id="2 Ch 14:10">10</verse-number>And Asa went out before him, and a battle was put in order in the valley of Zepah at Mareshah. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 14:11">11</verse-number>Then Asa cried out to Yahweh his God. And he said, “O Yahweh, there is none with you to help between the great and the powerless. Help us, O Yahweh our God, for we rely upon you, and in your name we have come against this multitude. O Yahweh, you <supplied>are</supplied> our God! Let no man prevail against you!” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 14:12">12</verse-number>So Yahweh defeated the Cushites before Asa and before Judah, and the Cushites fled. <verse-number id="2 Ch 14:13">13</verse-number>Then Asa and the army<note>Or “people”</note> with him pursued them to Gerar. And <supplied>many</supplied> from the Cushites fell, for they had no deliverance, for they were shattered before Yahweh and before his army. And they carried away much war booty. <verse-number id="2 Ch 14:14">14</verse-number>And they struck all the cities around Gerar, for the fear of Yahweh was upon them. And they plundered all the cities, for there was much plunder in them. <verse-number id="2 Ch 14:15">15</verse-number>And they also struck the tents of the herdsmen and carried away many sheep and camels. Then they returned to Jerusalem. </p>
		</chapter>