<chapter id="2 Ch 16">
			<pericope>The End of Asa’s Reign</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 16:1">1</verse-number>In the thirty-sixth year of the reign of Asa, Baasha the king of Israel went up against Judah. And he built Ramah in order not to allow <supplied>anyone</supplied> to go out or come in to Asa, king of Judah. <verse-number id="2 Ch 16:2">2</verse-number>Then Asa brought out silver and gold from the storehouses of the house of Yahweh and the house of the king, and he sent <supplied>them</supplied> to Ben-Hadad, king of Aram,<note>Or “Syria”</note> who lived in Damascus, saying, <verse-number id="2 Ch 16:3">3</verse-number>“<supplied>There is</supplied> a covenant between me and you, <supplied>as there was</supplied> between my father and your father. Look, I am sending you silver and gold. Go, break your covenant with Baasha, king of Israel, that he might withdraw from me.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 16:4">4</verse-number>And Ben-Hadad listened to King Asa, and he sent commanders of his troops that <supplied>were</supplied> with him against the cities of Israel. And they struck Ijon, Dan, Abel-Maim, and all the storage cities of Naphtali. <verse-number id="2 Ch 16:5">5</verse-number>And it happened <supplied>that</supplied> when Baasha heard <supplied>this</supplied>, he stopped building Ramah and ceased his work. <verse-number id="2 Ch 16:6">6</verse-number>Then King Asa took all of Judah, and they carried away the stones of Ramah and its timber with which Baasha had been building, and he built Geba and Mizpah with them. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 16:7">7</verse-number>And at that time Hanani the seer came to Asa king of Judah and said to him, “On account of your reliance upon the king of Aram,<note>Or “Syria”</note> and <supplied>since</supplied> you did not rely on Yahweh your God, therefore the troops of the king of Aram<note>Or “Syria”</note> escaped from your hand. <verse-number id="2 Ch 16:8">8</verse-number>Were not the Cushites and Libyans a mighty army with very abundant chariots and horsemen? And because of your reliance on Yahweh he gave them into your hand. <verse-number id="2 Ch 16:9">9</verse-number>For the eyes of Yahweh roam throughout all the earth to strengthen those whose heart is fully devoted to him. You have been foolish in this, for from now on you will have wars.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 16:10">10</verse-number>Then Asa was angry with the seer and put him in <idiom-start/>the prison<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the house of the stocks”</note> for he was enraged with him concerning this. And Asa oppressed some of the people at that time. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 16:11">11</verse-number>Now behold, the words of Asa <supplied>from</supplied> the first to the last, behold, they are written in the scroll of the kings of Judah and Israel. <verse-number id="2 Ch 16:12">12</verse-number>And in the thirty-ninth year of his reign, he fell <idiom-start/>severely<idiom-end/><note>Literally “until his illness unto severity”</note> ill in his feet. But even in his illness he did not seek Yahweh, but <supplied>only</supplied> among the healers. <verse-number id="2 Ch 16:13">13</verse-number>And Asa slept with his ancestors.<note>Or “fathers”</note> And he died in the forty-first year of his reign. <verse-number id="2 Ch 16:14">14</verse-number>And they buried him in his burial site, which had been cut out for him in the city of David. And they laid him on the bier which they had filled with all kinds of spices made <supplied>by</supplied> the perfumers as a fragment ointment. And they made a great fire in his honor. </p>
		</chapter>