<chapter id="2 Ch 17">
			<pericope>Jehoshaphat Reigns in Judah</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 17:1">1</verse-number>And Jehoshaphat his son reigned in his place, and he strengthened himself against Israel. <verse-number id="2 Ch 17:2">2</verse-number>And he put troops in all the fortified cities of Judah, and put garrisons in the land of Judah and in the cities of Ephraim that Asa his father had taken. <verse-number id="2 Ch 17:3">3</verse-number>And Yahweh was with Jehoshaphat, because he walked in the former ways of David his father and did not seek after the Baals, <verse-number id="2 Ch 17:4">4</verse-number>but he sought after the God of his ancestors<note>Or “fathers”</note> and walked in his commandments and not according to the works of Israel. <verse-number id="2 Ch 17:5">5</verse-number>So Yahweh established the kingdom in his hand. And all Judah gave tribute to Jehoshaphat, and he had much wealth and honor. <verse-number id="2 Ch 17:6">6</verse-number>And his heart was courageous in the ways of Yahweh. Moreover, he removed the high places and the Asherahs from Judah. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 17:7">7</verse-number>In the third year of his reign he sent his officials, Ben-Hail, Obadiah, Zechariah, Nethanel, and Micaiah, to teach in the cities of Judah; <verse-number id="2 Ch 17:8">8</verse-number>and with them the Levites Shemaiah, Nethaniah, Zebadiah, Asahel, Shemiramoth, Jehonathan, Adonijah, Tobijah, and Tob-Adonijah; and with them the priests Elisham and Joram. <verse-number id="2 Ch 17:9">9</verse-number>And they taught in Judah, and the scroll of the law of Yahweh <supplied>was</supplied> with them when they went around in all the cities of Judah, and they taught the people. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 17:10">10</verse-number>And the fear of Yahweh was upon all the kingdoms of the lands surrounding Judah, and they did not make war against Jehoshaphat. <verse-number id="2 Ch 17:11">11</verse-number>And some of the Philistines brought a gift and silver to Jehoshaphat <supplied>as</supplied> tribute. The Arabians also brought him seven thousand seven hundred sheep and seven thousand seven hundred goats. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 17:12">12</verse-number>And Jehoshaphat <idiom-start/>grew greater and greater<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “was going and becoming great to the height”</note> and he built fortresses and storage cities in Judah. <verse-number id="2 Ch 17:13">13</verse-number>And he had many supplies in the cities of Judah and mighty warriors for battle in Jerusalem. <verse-number id="2 Ch 17:14">14</verse-number>Now these <supplied>were</supplied> their enrollment by the house of their ancestors:<note>Or “fathers”</note> of Judah, the commanders of thousands: Adnah, the commander, and with him <supplied>were</supplied> three hundred thousand mighty armed warriors; <verse-number id="2 Ch 17:15">15</verse-number>and at his side,<note>Or “hand”</note> Jehohanan the commander, and with him <supplied>were</supplied> two hundred and eighty thousand; <verse-number id="2 Ch 17:16">16</verse-number>and at his side,<note>Or “hand”</note> Amasiah the son of Zicri, who had made a freewill offering to Yahweh, and with him <supplied>were</supplied> two hundred thousand mighty armed warriors. <verse-number id="2 Ch 17:17">17</verse-number>And from Benjamin: Eliada, a powerful mighty warrior, and with him <supplied>were</supplied> two hundred thousand armed with bow and shield; <verse-number id="2 Ch 17:18">18</verse-number>and at his side,<note>Or “hand”</note> Jehozabad, and with him <supplied>were</supplied> one hundred and eighty thousand armed for war. <verse-number id="2 Ch 17:19">19</verse-number>These were serving the king, besides <supplied>those</supplied> whom the king had placed in the fortified cities throughout all Judah. </p>
		</chapter>