<chapter id="2 Ch 24">
			<pericope>Joash Repairs the Temple</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 24:1">1</verse-number>Joash <supplied>was</supplied> seven years old when he became king, and he reigned forty years in Jerusalem. And the name of his mother <supplied>was</supplied> Zibiah from Beersheba. <verse-number id="2 Ch 24:2">2</verse-number>And Joash did what was right in the eyes of Yahweh all the days of Jehoiada the priest. <verse-number id="2 Ch 24:3">3</verse-number>And Jehoiada took two wives for him, and he fathered sons and daughters. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 24:4">4</verse-number>And afterward it was in the heart of Joash to repair the house of Yahweh. <verse-number id="2 Ch 24:5">5</verse-number>So he gathered the priests and the Levites and said to them, “Go out to the cities of Judah and gather money from all Israel to strengthen the house of your God sufficiently year by year. Now you yourselves must hasten to the matter.” But the Levites did not act with haste. <verse-number id="2 Ch 24:6">6</verse-number>So the king called Jehoiada the chief, and he said to him, “Why have you not required the Levites to bring from Judah and Jerusalem the tax of Moses, the servant of Yahweh, and <supplied>of</supplied> the assembly of Israel for the tent of the testimony?” <verse-number id="2 Ch 24:7">7</verse-number>For the sons of the wicked Athaliah had broken into the house of God and had used all the holy vessels of the house of Yahweh for the Baals. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 24:8">8</verse-number>Then the king commanded, and they made a chest and put it at the gate outside the house of Yahweh. <verse-number id="2 Ch 24:9">9</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>they issued a proclamation<idiom-end/><note>Literally “they gave a voice”</note> in Judah and in Jerusalem to bring to Yahweh the tax <supplied>that</supplied> Moses the servant of God <supplied>had levied</supplied> upon Israel in the wilderness. <verse-number id="2 Ch 24:10">10</verse-number>And all the princes and all the people rejoiced, and they brought <supplied>their tax</supplied> and threw <supplied>it</supplied> into the chest until <supplied>it was</supplied> finished. <verse-number id="2 Ch 24:11">11</verse-number>And whenever he brought the chest to the appointee of the king by the hand of the Levites, and when they saw that <supplied>there was</supplied> much money <supplied>in it</supplied>, then the secretary of the king and the officer of the chief priest came and emptied the chest, then they took it and returned it to its place. Thus they did day by day and gathered money in abundance. <verse-number id="2 Ch 24:12">12</verse-number>And the king and Jehoiada gave it to those who did the work of the service of the house of Yahweh. And they hired stonemasons and skilled craftsmen to restore the house of Yahweh, and also workers in iron and bronze to repair the house of Yahweh. <verse-number id="2 Ch 24:13">13</verse-number>So those doing the work labored, and the restoration for the work made progress under their hand. And they restored the house of God to its position and strengthened it. <verse-number id="2 Ch 24:14">14</verse-number>And when they had finished, they brought the remainder of the money before the king and Jehoiada, and they used it <supplied>for</supplied> objects for the house of Yahweh, objects for the service and the burnt offerings, dishes, and objects of gold and silver. And they were offering burnt offerings in the house of Yahweh regularly, all the days of Jehoiada. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 24:15">15</verse-number>And Jehoiada grew old and full of days, and he died; <supplied>he was</supplied> one hundred and thirty years old at his death. <verse-number id="2 Ch 24:16">16</verse-number>And they buried him in the city of David with the kings, for he did good in Israel and with respect to God and his house. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 24:17">17</verse-number>Now after the death of Jehoiada, the princes of Judah came and bowed down to the king. Then the king listened to them. <verse-number id="2 Ch 24:18">18</verse-number>And they forsook the house of Yahweh, the God of their ancestors<note>Or “fathers”</note> and served the Asherahs and the idols. And wrath came upon Judah and Jerusalem on account of this guilt. <verse-number id="2 Ch 24:19">19</verse-number>But he sent prophets among them, to bring them back to Yahweh. And they testified against them, and they did not obey. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 24:20">20</verse-number>Then the Spirit of God clothed Zechariah the son of Jehoiada the priest, and he stood above the people and said to them, “Thus says God: ‘Why are you transgressing the commandments of Yahweh so that you will not succeed? For you have forsaken Yahweh, so he will forsake you.’ ” <verse-number id="2 Ch 24:21">21</verse-number>Then they conspired against him and stoned him <supplied>with</supplied> stones at the command of the king in the courtyard of the house of Yahweh. <verse-number id="2 Ch 24:22">22</verse-number>So King Joash did not remember the loyal love that Jehoiada had shown to him, and he killed his son. And as he was dying he said, “May Yahweh see and avenge!” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Death of Joash</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 24:23">23</verse-number>And it happened at the turn of the year <supplied>that</supplied> the army of Aram<note>Or “Syria”</note> went up against him, and they came to Judah and Jerusalem and destroyed all the commanders of the people from among the people, and all the war booty they sent to the king of Damascus. <verse-number id="2 Ch 24:24">24</verse-number>Though the army of Aram<note>Or “Syria”</note> came with few men, Yahweh gave a very large army into their hand, for they had forsaken Yahweh, the God of their ancestors.<note>Or “fathers”</note> And they inflicted punishment on Joash. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 24:25">25</verse-number>And when they were going away from him (for they had left him with many wounds), his servants conspired against him on account of the blood of the sons<note>The Septuagint reads “son”</note> of Jehoiada the priest. So they killed him on his bed and he died. And they buried him in the city of David, but they did not bury him at the burial sites of the kings. <verse-number id="2 Ch 24:26">26</verse-number>Now these <supplied>are</supplied> the ones who conspired against him: Zabad the son of Shimeath, the Ammonite, and Jehozabad the son of Shimrith, the Moabite. <verse-number id="2 Ch 24:27">27</verse-number>And <supplied>as for</supplied> his sons, the many oracles against him, and <supplied>his repair of</supplied> the foundation of the house of God, behold, they <supplied>are</supplied> written in the story of the scroll of the kings. And Amaziah his son reigned in his place. </p>
		</chapter>