<chapter id="2 Ch 25">
			<pericope>The Reign of Amaziah</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 25:1">1</verse-number>Amaziah was twenty-five years old <supplied>when</supplied> he became king. And he reigned twenty-nine years in Jerusalem, and the name of his mother <supplied>was</supplied> Jehoaddan from Jerusalem. <verse-number id="2 Ch 25:2">2</verse-number>And he did what was right in the eyes of Yahweh, only not with a fully-devoted heart. <verse-number id="2 Ch 25:3">3</verse-number>And it happened <supplied>that</supplied> as his reign was strengthened, he killed his servants who had killed his father the king. <verse-number id="2 Ch 25:4">4</verse-number>But he did not put their children to death, according to <supplied>what</supplied> is written in the law, in the scroll of Moses, where Yahweh commanded, saying, “Fathers shall not be put to death on account of the sons, and the sons shall not be put to death on account of the fathers, but each shall be put to death for his own sin.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 25:5">5</verse-number>Then Amaziah assembled <supplied>the men of</supplied> Judah and set them by <idiom-start/>families<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<supplied>the</supplied> house of the fathers”</note> under commanders of thousands and commanders of hundreds for all Judah and Benjamin. And he counted them from twenty years old and upward, and found them <supplied>to be</supplied> three hundred thousand chosen for going out to battle, able <supplied>with</supplied> spear and shield. <verse-number id="2 Ch 25:6">6</verse-number>And he hired from Israel one hundred thousand strong, mighty warriors for one hundred talents. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 25:7">7</verse-number>But a man of God came to him, saying, “O king, do not let the army of Israel go with you, for Yahweh is not with Israel, all the Ephraimites. <verse-number id="2 Ch 25:8">8</verse-number>But even still, you yourself go, do! Be strong for the battle <supplied>else</supplied> God will make you stumble before the enemy! For there is power with God to help and to cause stumbling.” <verse-number id="2 Ch 25:9">9</verse-number>And Amaziah said to the man of God, “Now what <supplied>should I</supplied> do with the one hundred talents that I have given to the troops of Israel?” And the man of God said, “<idiom-start/>Yahweh is able to give<idiom-end/><note>Literally “There is to Yahweh to give”</note> to you more than this.” <verse-number id="2 Ch 25:10">10</verse-number>Then Amaziah dismissed the troops that came to him from Ephraim to go to their home.<note>Or “their place”</note> And <idiom-start/>they became very angry<idiom-end/><note>Literally “their noses became very hot”</note> with Judah, and they returned to their home <idiom-start/>in great anger<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “in hotness of nose”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 25:11">11</verse-number>Then Amaziah strengthened himself, and leading his army, he went <supplied>to</supplied> the Valley of Salt. And he struck <supplied>down</supplied> ten thousand men<note>Or “sons”</note> of Seir. <verse-number id="2 Ch 25:12">12</verse-number>Now the <idiom-start/>troops<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the sons of the troop”</note> captured ten thousand <supplied>others</supplied> alive, and they brought them to the top of the rock and threw them from the top of the rock. So all of them were smashed <supplied>to pieces</supplied>. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 25:13">13</verse-number>As for the <idiom-start/>troops<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons of the troop”</note> Amaziah had sent back from going with him to war, they raided the cities of Judah from Samaria to Beth-Horon. And they struck <supplied>down</supplied> three thousand of them and plundered much booty. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 25:14">14</verse-number>And it happened <supplied>that</supplied> after Amaziah came <supplied>back</supplied> from killing the Edomites, he brought the gods of the sons of Seir, and he stood them up to himself as gods and bowed down before them and make smoke offerings for them. <verse-number id="2 Ch 25:15">15</verse-number>So <idiom-start/>Yahweh became very angry<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Yahweh’s nose became very hot”</note> with Amaziah and sent a prophet to him, and he said to him, “Why have you sought the gods of the people who could not deliver their own people from your hand?” <verse-number id="2 Ch 25:16">16</verse-number>And it happened <supplied>that</supplied> while he was speaking to him, he said to him, “Have we appointed you as a counselor to the king? Stop—<idiom-start/>why should you be killed<idiom-end/>?”<note>Literally “why shall he strike you?”</note> So the prophet stopped and said, “I know that God has determined to destroy you, because you have done this and have not listened to my advice.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 25:17">17</verse-number>Then Amaziah king of Judah took counsel, and he sent to Joash the son of Jehoahaz the son of Jehu, king of Israel, saying, “Come,<note>This translation follows the <i>Qere</i> reading</note> <idiom-start/>let us face one another<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “let us look at faces”</note> <verse-number id="2 Ch 25:18">18</verse-number>And Joash the king of Israel sent to Amaziah king of Judah, saying, “The thorn bush that <supplied>is</supplied> in Lebanon has sent to the cedar which <supplied>is</supplied> in Lebanon, saying, ‘Give your daughter to my son as wife.’ But a wild animal of the field that <supplied>was</supplied> in Lebanon passed by and trampled the thorn bush. <verse-number id="2 Ch 25:19">19</verse-number>Look, you say <supplied>that</supplied> you have struck Edom, and your heart has lifted you up to boast. Now remain at your home. Why stir up disaster that you fall, you and Judah with you?” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 25:20">20</verse-number>But Amaziah did not listen, for it <supplied>was</supplied> from God that he might give them into the hand <supplied>of enemies</supplied>, because they sought the gods of Edom. <verse-number id="2 Ch 25:21">21</verse-number>So Joash the king of Israel went up, and he and Amaziah the king of Judah <idiom-start/>faced one another<idiom-end/><note>Literally “looked at one another’s faces”</note> at Beth-Shemesh, which belongs to Judah. <verse-number id="2 Ch 25:22">22</verse-number>And Judah was defeated before Israel, and each <supplied>man</supplied> fled to his tent. <verse-number id="2 Ch 25:23">23</verse-number>And Joash the king of Israel captured Amaziah the king of Judah, the son of Joash, the son of Jehoahaz, at Beth-Shemesh. And they brought him <supplied>to</supplied> Jerusalem and broke down the wall of Jerusalem from the Gate of Ephraim to the Corner Gate, four hundred cubits. <verse-number id="2 Ch 25:24">24</verse-number>Then with all the gold and silver, all the objects found in the house of God with Obed-Edom, the storehouses of the house of the king, and <idiom-start/>the hostages<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the sons of the pledges”</note> he returned to Samaria. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 25:25">25</verse-number>And Amaziah the son of Joash, king of Judah, lived after the death of Joash the son of Jehoahaz, the king of Israel, fifteen years. <verse-number id="2 Ch 25:26">26</verse-number>Now the remainder of the words of Amaziah, <supplied>from</supplied> the first <supplied>to</supplied> the last, behold, are they not written in the scroll of the kings of Judah and Israel? <verse-number id="2 Ch 25:27">27</verse-number>And from the time that Amaziah turned away from Yahweh, they had plotted a conspiracy against him in Jerusalem. And he fled to Lachish, but they sent after him to Lachish and killed him there. <verse-number id="2 Ch 25:28">28</verse-number>And they carried him on the horses and buried him with his ancestors<note>Or “fathers”</note> in the city of Judah. </p>
		</chapter>