<chapter id="2 Ch 31">
			<pericope>Hezekiah Organizes the Priesthood</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 31:1">1</verse-number>And when all this was finished, all Israel who were found in the cities of Judah went out and shattered the stone pillars, cut down the Asherahs, and destroyed the high places and the altars from all Judah, Benjamin, Ephraim, and Manasseh <idiom-start/>to the very last one<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “until finishing”</note> Then all the Israelites returned, each to his own property <supplied>and</supplied> to their cities. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 31:2">2</verse-number>And Hezekiah appointed working groups of the priests and the Levites, each according to their divisions, <idiom-start/>according to the service for priests and Levites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “according to the mouth of his service, for priests and Levites”</note> for burnt offerings, for peace offerings, to serve, to give thanks, and to praise in the gates of the camps of Yahweh. <verse-number id="2 Ch 31:3">3</verse-number>And the gift of the king <supplied>was</supplied> out of his own possessions for the burnt offerings—the burnt offerings for the morning and the evening and for Sabbaths, new moon festivals, and appointed feasts, as is written in the law of Yahweh. <verse-number id="2 Ch 31:4">4</verse-number>Then he said to the people, to the inhabitants of Jerusalem, to give a gift for the priests and the Levites, so that they might be strong in the law of Yahweh. <verse-number id="2 Ch 31:5">5</verse-number>And the word spread. The Israelites gave abundantly <supplied>from</supplied> the firstfruits of grain, new wine, olive oil, honey, and all <supplied>kinds of</supplied> grains from the field. And they brought tithes of everything in abundance. <verse-number id="2 Ch 31:6">6</verse-number>Then the people of Israel and Judah who were living in the cities of Judah, they also brought a tithe of cattle and sheep and a tithe of consecrated objects to Yahweh their God. And they gave heaps <supplied>upon</supplied> heaps. <verse-number id="2 Ch 31:7">7</verse-number>In the third month the heaps began to pile up, and in the seventh month they ceased. <verse-number id="2 Ch 31:8">8</verse-number>When Hezekiah and the princes came and saw the heaps, they blessed Yahweh and his people Israel. <verse-number id="2 Ch 31:9">9</verse-number>And Hezekiah questioned<note>Or “sought”</note> the priests and the Levites concerning the heaps. <verse-number id="2 Ch 31:10">10</verse-number>And Azariah the chief priest of the house of Zadok answered him, saying, “Since the offerings began to be brought to the house of Yahweh, <supplied>we have</supplied> eaten and been satisfied, and have much to spare, for Yahweh has blessed his people. Now <supplied>see</supplied> this abundant remainder!” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 31:11">11</verse-number>And Hezekiah commanded to prepare chambers in the house of Yahweh, and they were prepared. <verse-number id="2 Ch 31:12">12</verse-number>Then they brought the offerings and tithes and holy objects faithfully. And over them <supplied>as</supplied> leader <supplied>was</supplied> Conaniah the Levite. And Shimei his brother <supplied>was</supplied> second <supplied>in rank</supplied>. <verse-number id="2 Ch 31:13">13</verse-number>And Jehiel, Azaziah, Nathan, Asahel, Jerimoth, Jozabad, Eliel, Ismachiah, Mahath, and Benaiah <supplied>were</supplied> chief officers under the hand of Conaniah and Shimei, his brother, by appointment of King Hezekiah. And Azaraiah <supplied>was</supplied> leader of the house of God. <verse-number id="2 Ch 31:14">14</verse-number>Now Kore the son of Imlah, the Levite, the gatekeeper of the east gate <supplied>was</supplied> over the freewill offerings of God, to give offerings to Yahweh and the most holy things. <verse-number id="2 Ch 31:15">15</verse-number>And at his hand <supplied>were</supplied> Eden, Miniamin, Jeshua, Shemaiah, Amariah, and Shecaniah in the cities of the priests <supplied>and</supplied> <idiom-start/>entrusted<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in faithfulness”</note> to give to their brothers by working groups, according to the eldest <supplied>to</supplied> the youngest, <verse-number id="2 Ch 31:16">16</verse-number>besides their enrollment by genealogy, to males from three years old and upward, to all who came into the house of Yahweh, <idiom-start/>as each day required<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for the word of the day by his day”</note> for their service in their posts according to their working groups. <verse-number id="2 Ch 31:17">17</verse-number>And the enrollment of the priests <supplied>was</supplied> according to the house of their fathers, and the Levites, from twenty years old and upward, according to their posts by their working groups. <verse-number id="2 Ch 31:18">18</verse-number>And <supplied>they were</supplied> enrolled with all their little ones, their wives, their sons, and their daughters for the whole assembly because of their faithfulness. And they sanctified themselves in holiness. <verse-number id="2 Ch 31:19">19</verse-number>And for the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Aaron, the priests, <supplied>who were</supplied> in the fields of the pasturelands of their cities, <idiom-start/>in each and every one of their cities<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in every city and the city”</note> <supplied>were</supplied> men who were designated by name to give shares to every male among the priests and to everyone enrolled among the Levites. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 31:20">20</verse-number>And Hezekiah did according to this throughout all Judah. And he did what <supplied>is</supplied> good and what <supplied>is</supplied> right and what <supplied>is</supplied> faithful before Yahweh his God. <verse-number id="2 Ch 31:21">21</verse-number>And in every work that he began in the service of the house of God or with respect to the law and the commandment to seek his God, he did with all his heart, and he prospered. </p>
		</chapter>