<chapter id="2 Ch 32">
			<pericope>Sennacherib’s Invasion of Judah</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 32:1">1</verse-number>After these things and these <supplied>acts of</supplied> faithfulness, Sennacherib the king of Assyria came, and he came against Judah. And he encamped against the fortified cities and planned to break them down for himself. <verse-number id="2 Ch 32:2">2</verse-number>When Hezekiah saw that Sennacherib had come and <supplied>that</supplied> his face <supplied>was set</supplied> for battle against Jerusalem, <verse-number id="2 Ch 32:3">3</verse-number>he took counsel with his commanders and his mighty warriors to block off the waters of the springs that <supplied>came</supplied> from outside the city, and they helped him. <verse-number id="2 Ch 32:4">4</verse-number>Then many people were gathered, and they blocked off all the springs and the river that flowed through the midst of the land, saying, “Why should the kings of Assyria come and find much water?” <verse-number id="2 Ch 32:5">5</verse-number>Then he strengthened himself and built up all the walls that were broken down, and raised towers upon <supplied>them</supplied> and another wall <idiom-start/>outside<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “toward the street”</note> And he strengthened the Millo of the city of David and made much weaponry and small shields. <verse-number id="2 Ch 32:6">6</verse-number>And he appointed commanders for battle over the people and gathered them to himself into the public square of the gate of the city. And he spoke to their hearts, saying, <verse-number id="2 Ch 32:7">7</verse-number>“Be strong! Be courageous! Do not fear and do not be dismayed before the king of Assyria and before all the crowd that <supplied>is</supplied> with him, for <supplied>there are</supplied> more with us than with him. <verse-number id="2 Ch 32:8">8</verse-number>With him <supplied>is</supplied> the arm of flesh, and with us <supplied>is</supplied> Yahweh our God, to help us and to fight our battles.” And the people took confidence with the words of Hezekiah, king of Judah. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 32:9">9</verse-number>After this Sennacherib the king of Assyria sent his servants to Jerusalem (now he and all his armies with him <supplied>were</supplied> against Lachish) to Hezekiah king of Judah and to all of Judah that <supplied>was</supplied> in Jerusalem, saying, <verse-number id="2 Ch 32:10">10</verse-number>“Thus says Sennacherib the king of Assyria: ‘On what <supplied>are</supplied> you relying that <supplied>you are</supplied> dwelling in siege works in Jerusalem? <verse-number id="2 Ch 32:11">11</verse-number>Is not Hezekiah urging you to give you <supplied>up</supplied> to die by starvation and thirst, saying, “Yahweh our God will save us from the hand of the king of Assyria”? <verse-number id="2 Ch 32:12">12</verse-number>Has not Hezekiah himself removed his high places and his altars and said to Judah and to Jerusalem, saying, “You must bow down before one altar and upon it you must make offerings”? <verse-number id="2 Ch 32:13">13</verse-number>Do you not know what I have done, I and my ancestors,<note>Or “fathers”</note> to all the peoples of the lands? Were the gods of the nations of all the lands at all able to save their land from my hand? <verse-number id="2 Ch 32:14">14</verse-number>Who among all the gods of those nations whom my ancestors<note>Or “fathers”</note> utterly destroyed was able to save his people from my hand, that your God will be able to save you from my hand? <verse-number id="2 Ch 32:15">15</verse-number>So now, do not let Hezekiah deceive you. Do not let him urge you according to this. Do not put trust in him, for no god of any nation and kingdom has been able to save his people from my hand and from the hand of my ancestors.<note>Or “fathers”</note> Surely then your God will not save you from my hand!’ ” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 32:16">16</verse-number>And still more his servants said against Yahweh God and against Hezekiah his servant. <verse-number id="2 Ch 32:17">17</verse-number>And he wrote letters to treat Yahweh the God of Israel with contempt and spoke against him, saying, “As the gods of the nations of the earth who did not save their people from my hand, so likewise the God of Hezekiah will not save his people from my hand.” <verse-number id="2 Ch 32:18">18</verse-number>Then they called with a great voice in Judean to the people of Jerusalem who <supplied>were</supplied> upon the wall to frighten them and terrify them, so that they could take the city captive. <verse-number id="2 Ch 32:19">19</verse-number>And they spoke about the God of Jerusalem as about the gods of the peoples of the earth, the works of the hands of humankind. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Yahweh’s Deliverance of Jerusalem</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 32:20">20</verse-number>Then King Hezekiah and Isaiah the son of Amoz, the prophet, prayed concerning this. And they cried to the heavens. <verse-number id="2 Ch 32:21">21</verse-number>Then Yahweh sent an angel, and he destroyed every mighty warrior of strength, commander, and officer in the camp of the king of Assyria. And he returned with shamed face to his land and went into the house of his god. And some of the offspring of his loins fell upon him there with the sword. <verse-number id="2 Ch 32:22">22</verse-number>So Yahweh saved Hezekiah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem from the hand of Sennacherib, king of Assyria, and from the all <supplied>their enemies</supplied>, and gave them rest all around. <verse-number id="2 Ch 32:23">23</verse-number>And many brought tribute to Yahweh, to Jerusalem, and precious things to Hezekiah king of Judah, so that he was exalted in the eyes of all the nations thereafter. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Rest of Hezekiah’s Reign</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 32:24">24</verse-number>In those days Hezekiah fell ill unto death, and he prayed to Yahweh. And he answered him and gave him a sign. <verse-number id="2 Ch 32:25">25</verse-number>But Hezekiah did not reciprocate according to the benefit <supplied>placed</supplied> upon him, because his heart became proud. So wrath was upon him and upon Judah and Jerusalem. <verse-number id="2 Ch 32:26">26</verse-number>But Hezekiah humbled himself with respect to the arrogance of his heart, he and the inhabitants of Jerusalem, so that the wrath of Yahweh did not come upon them in the days of Hezekiah. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 32:27">27</verse-number>And Hezekiah had very much wealth and honor, and he made storehouses for himself for silver, gold, precious stones, spices, small shields, and all <supplied>sorts of</supplied> desirable objects; <verse-number id="2 Ch 32:28">28</verse-number>and storage buildings for the yield of grain, new wine, and olive oil; and animal stalls for all <supplied>kinds of</supplied> animals, and animals and herds for animal stalls. <verse-number id="2 Ch 32:29">29</verse-number>And he made cities for himself, and livestock of sheep and abundant cattle, for God had given to him very abundant possessions. <verse-number id="2 Ch 32:30">30</verse-number>And this same Hezekiah blocked off the flow of the waters of the upper Gihon, and directed them down the west <supplied>side</supplied> of the city of David. And Hezekiah prospered in all his works. <verse-number id="2 Ch 32:31">31</verse-number>And thus <supplied>in the matter of</supplied> the envoys of the commanders of Babylon who had been sent to him to seek the sign that had happened in the land, God forsook him, to test him <supplied>and</supplied> to know all <supplied>that was</supplied> in his heart. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 32:32">32</verse-number>Now the remainder of the words of Hezekiah and his loyal love, behold, they are written in the visions of Isaiah the son of Amoz, the prophet, upon the scroll of the kings of Judah and Israel. <verse-number id="2 Ch 32:33">33</verse-number>And Hezekiah slept with his ancestors,<note>Or “fathers”</note> and they buried him in the upper <supplied>part</supplied> of the burial sites of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of David. And all Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem did him honor at his death. And Manasseh his son became king in his place. </p>
		</chapter>