<chapter id="2 Ch 35">
			<pericope>Josiah Observes the Passover</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 35:1">1</verse-number>Josiah kept<note>Or “made”</note> the Passover to Yahweh in Jerusalem. And they slaughtered the Passover <supplied>sacrifice</supplied> on the fourteenth day of the first month. <verse-number id="2 Ch 35:2">2</verse-number>And he set the priests at their posts and encouraged them in the service of the house of Yahweh. <verse-number id="2 Ch 35:3">3</verse-number>And he said to the Levites who <supplied>were</supplied> teaching all Israel, who were sanctified to Yahweh, “Put the holy ark in the house which Solomon the son of David, king of Israel, built. There is no <supplied>need</supplied> to carry it on <supplied>your</supplied> shoulders. Now serve Yahweh your God and his people Israel. <verse-number id="2 Ch 35:4">4</verse-number>And prepare yourselves according to <idiom-start/>your families<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the house of your fathers”</note> according to your working groups, according to the decree<note>Or “writing”</note> of David king of Israel and according to the decree<note>Or “writing”</note> of Solomon his son. <verse-number id="2 Ch 35:5">5</verse-number>And stand in the sanctuary according to the clans of <idiom-start/>your families<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the house of your fathers”</note> for your brothers, the <idiom-start/>lay people<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons of the people”</note> and a part of the <idiom-start/>family<idiom-end/><note>Literally “house of the father”</note> of the Levites. <verse-number id="2 Ch 35:6">6</verse-number>And slaughter the Passover <supplied>lamb</supplied> and consecrate yourself and prepare for your brothers to do according to the word of Yahweh by the hand of Moses. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 35:7">7</verse-number>Then Josiah provided for the <idiom-start/>lay people<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons of the people”</note> sheep, lambs, and young goats, all for the Passover for all who were found <supplied>there</supplied>, to the sum of thirty thousand, along with three thousand bulls. These <supplied>were</supplied> the possession of the king. <verse-number id="2 Ch 35:8">8</verse-number>And his officials contributed a freewill offering to the people, to the priests, and to the Levites. Hilkiah, Zechariah, and Jehiel, commanders of the house of God, gave to the priests two thousand six hundred Passover <supplied>lambs</supplied> and three hundred bulls. <verse-number id="2 Ch 35:9">9</verse-number>Conaniah also, and Shemaiah and Nethanel his brothers, and Hashabiah and Jeiel and Jehozabad, commanders of the Levites, contributed to the Levites five thousand Passover <supplied>lambs</supplied> and five hundred bulls. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 35:10">10</verse-number>And when the work had been completed, the priests stood at their positions and the Levites in their working groups according to the command of the king. <verse-number id="2 Ch 35:11">11</verse-number>And they slaughtered the Passover <supplied>lamb</supplied>, and the priests sprinkled <supplied>the blood</supplied> from their hand, and the Levites flayed <supplied>the sacrifices</supplied>. <verse-number id="2 Ch 35:12">12</verse-number>And they set aside the burnt offerings to give them to the clans of the <idiom-start/>families<idiom-end/><note>Literally “house of the fathers”</note> for the <idiom-start/>lay people<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons of the people”</note> to offer to Yahweh according to what is written in the scroll of Moses. And thus they did with the bulls. <verse-number id="2 Ch 35:13">13</verse-number>Then they roasted the Passover <supplied>lamb</supplied> in the fire according to the ordinance. And they boiled the holy offerings in pots, in kettles, and in dishes and brought it quickly to the <idiom-start/>lay people<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sons of the people”</note> <verse-number id="2 Ch 35:14">14</verse-number>And afterward they prepared for themselves and for the priests, since the priests, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Aaron, <supplied>were busy</supplied> with offering the burnt offerings and the fat until night. So the Levites prepared for themselves and for the priests, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Aaron. <verse-number id="2 Ch 35:15">15</verse-number>And the singers, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Asaph, <supplied>were</supplied> at their stations according to the decree<note>Or “command”</note> of David and Asaph and Heman and Jeduthun, the seer of the king. And the gatekeepers <supplied>were</supplied> at <idiom-start/>each gate<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “gate to gate”</note> They did not need to depart from their service, for their brothers the Levites had made preparations for them. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 35:16">16</verse-number>So all the service of Yahweh was prepared on that day to keep<note>Or “make”</note> the Passover and to sacrifice burnt offerings on the altar of Yahweh, according to the command of King Josiah. <verse-number id="2 Ch 35:17">17</verse-number>And the Israelites who were present kept<note>Or “made”</note> the Passover at that time, and the Feast of Unleavened Bread seven days. <verse-number id="2 Ch 35:18">18</verse-number>And there was no Passover like it kept<note>Or “made”</note> in Israel since the days of Samuel the prophet. And none of the kings of Israel kept<note>Or “made”</note> a Passover like that which Josiah and the priests and the Levites, and all of Judah and Israel who were present, and the inhabitants of Jerusalem, kept.<note>Or “made”</note> <verse-number id="2 Ch 35:19">19</verse-number>In the eighteenth year of the reign of Josiah this Passover was kept.<note>Or “made”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Death of Josiah</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 35:20">20</verse-number>After all of this that Josiah had prepared <supplied>for</supplied> the temple,<note>Or “house”</note> Neco the king of Egypt went up to make war at Carchemish on the Euphrates, and Josiah went up to meet him. <verse-number id="2 Ch 35:21">21</verse-number>And he<note>That is, Neco</note> sent messengers to him, saying, “<idiom-start/>What is there between us<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “What to me and to you”</note> O king of Judah? <supplied>I am</supplied> not against you yourself this day, but against the house making war against me. And God has commanded me to make haste. Stop <supplied>opposing</supplied> God, who <supplied>is</supplied> with me that he will not destroy you.” <verse-number id="2 Ch 35:22">22</verse-number>But Josiah did not turn his face from him, but he disguised himself to fight with him. He did not listen to the words of Neco from the mouth of God, and he went out to fight in the plain of Megiddo. <verse-number id="2 Ch 35:23">23</verse-number>And the archers shot King Josiah, and the king said to his servants, “Take me away, for I am badly wounded.” <verse-number id="2 Ch 35:24">24</verse-number>So his servants took him out of the chariot and transported him in his second chariot and brought him to Jerusalem. And he died and was buried in the burial sites of his ancestors.<note>Or “fathers”</note> And all Judah and Jerusalem mourned over Josiah. <verse-number id="2 Ch 35:25">25</verse-number>And Jeremiah uttered a lament for Josiah, and all the male and female singers have spoken in their laments about Josiah to this day. And they made them a requirement in Israel, and behold, they are written in the laments. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ch 35:26">26</verse-number>Now the remainder of the words of Josiah and his loyal love <supplied>for</supplied> what is written in the law of Yahweh <verse-number id="2 Ch 35:27">27</verse-number>and his words, <supplied>from</supplied> the first <supplied>to</supplied> the last, behold, they are written in the scroll of the kings of Israel and Judah. </p>
		</chapter>