<chapter id="Dt 1">
			<pericope>Preamble</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 1:1">1</verse-number>These <supplied>are</supplied> the words that Moses spoke to all <supplied>of</supplied> Israel <idiom-start/>on the other side of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the beyond <supplied>of</supplied>”</note> the Jordan in the desert,<note>Or “the wilderness”</note> in the desert plateau<note>Or “desert plain”; others render this as a named location, “Arabah”</note> opposite Suph, between Paran and between Tophel and Laban and Hazeroth and Dizahab. <verse-number id="Dt 1:2">2</verse-number>It is <supplied>a journey of</supplied> <idiom-start/>eleven days<idiom-end/><note>Literally “one and ten days”</note> from Herob <idiom-start/>by the way of Mount Seir<idiom-end/><note>Literally “by the mountain of Seir”</note> up to Kadesh Barnea. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 1:3">3</verse-number><idiom-start/>And it was<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and it happened” or “and then”</note> in the fortieth year, on the eleventh month, on <supplied>the</supplied> first <supplied>day</supplied> of the month, Moses spoke to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> according to all that Yahweh had instructed him <supplied>to speak</supplied> to them. <verse-number id="Dt 1:4">4</verse-number><supplied>This happened</supplied> <idiom-start/>after defeating<idiom-end/><note>Literally “after he had struck down”</note> Sihon king of the Amorites, who <supplied>was</supplied> reigning<note>Or “dwelling,” and in this context “reigning”</note> in Heshbon, and Og the king of Bashan, who <supplied>was</supplied> reigning<note>Or “dwelling,” and in this context “reigning”</note> in Ashtaroth in Edrei. <verse-number id="Dt 1:5">5</verse-number>On the other side of <note>Literally “in the beyond <supplied>of</supplied>”</note> the Jordan in the land of Moab Moses began to explain this law,<note>Hebrew <i>torah</i></note> <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>:<note>Literally “to say”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Historical Prologue</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 1:6">6</verse-number>“Yahweh our God spoke to us at Horeb, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> ‘You have stayed <idiom-start/>long enough<idiom-end/><note>Literally “much <supplied>time</supplied>”</note> at this mountain. <verse-number id="Dt 1:7">7</verse-number>Turn <supplied>now</supplied> and <idiom-start/>move on<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “journey on with respect to yourselves” or “move yourselves out”</note> and go <supplied>into</supplied> the hill of the Amorites<note>Hebrew “Amorite”</note> and to all <supplied>of</supplied> the neighboring regions<note>Or “peoples”</note> in the Jordan <idiom-start/>Valley<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Arabah,” arid stretches of land.</note> in the hill country and in the Negev and in the coastal area along the sea, <supplied>into</supplied> the land of the Canaanites<note>Hebrew “Canaanite”</note> and <supplied>into</supplied> the Lebanon, as far as the great river Euphrates. <verse-number id="Dt 1:8">8</verse-number>Look, I have set the land <idiom-start/>before you<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “before your face”</note> go and take possession of the land that Yahweh swore to your ancestors,<note>Or “fathers”</note> to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob, to give <supplied>it</supplied> to them and to their offspring after them.’ </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 1:9">9</verse-number>“And I spoke to them at that time, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> ‘I am not able to bear you alone. <verse-number id="Dt 1:10">10</verse-number>Yahweh your God has multiplied you, and look; you <supplied>are</supplied> today as the stars of the heaven <idiom-start/>in number<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “with respect to multitude/abundance”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 1:11">11</verse-number>Yahweh, the God of your ancestors,<note>Or “fathers”</note> may he add to you as you are <supplied>now</supplied> a thousand times, and may he bless you just as he <idiom-start/>promised you<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “spoke to you”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 1:12">12</verse-number>How can I bear you <idiom-start/>by myself<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to me alone”</note> your burden and your load and your strife? <verse-number id="Dt 1:13">13</verse-number>Choose for yourselves <idiom-start/>wise and discerning and knowledgeable men<idiom-end/><note>Literally “men wise and discerning and knowledgeable”</note> for <supplied>each of</supplied> your tribes, and I will appoint them as your leaders.’ </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 1:14">14</verse-number>“And you answered me, and you said, ‘The thing you have said to do is good.’ <verse-number id="Dt 1:15">15</verse-number>And so I took the leaders of your tribes, wise and knowledgeable men, and <supplied>then</supplied> I appointed them as leaders over you <supplied>as</supplied> commanders of <supplied>groups of</supplied> thousands and commanders of <supplied>groups of</supplied> hundreds and commanders of <supplied>groups of</supplied> fifties and commanders of <supplied>groups of</supplied> tens <supplied>as</supplied> officials for your tribes. <verse-number id="Dt 1:16">16</verse-number>And at that time I instructed your judges, saying, ‘<idiom-start/>hear out your fellow men<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “hear between your brothers,” with the idea of listening carefully in this context</note> and <supplied>then</supplied> judge fairly<note>Or “righteously”</note> between a man and between his brother and between <idiom-start/>his opponent who is a resident alien<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “between his resident alien/non-Israelite who dwells temporarily among Israel”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 1:17">17</verse-number>You must not <idiom-start/>be partial<idiom-end/><note>Literally “recognize faces”</note> <idiom-start/>in your judgment<idiom-end/>; <note>Literally “in the process of rendering a judgment”</note> hear <supplied>out</supplied> the small <supplied>person</supplied> as <supplied>also</supplied> the great <supplied>person</supplied>; <idiom-start/>do not be intimidated by any person<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “do not fear before the faces of <supplied>any</supplied> man”</note> because the judgment <supplied>is</supplied> God’s; and the case that is too difficult<note>Or “hard”</note> for you, bring <supplied>it</supplied> to me, and I will hear it <supplied>out</supplied>.’ <verse-number id="Dt 1:18">18</verse-number>And so I instructed you at that time <supplied>concerning</supplied> all <supplied>of</supplied> the things that you should do. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 1:19">19</verse-number>“Then we set out from Horeb, and we went <supplied>through</supplied> the whole <supplied>of</supplied> that great and terrible desert that you saw <supplied>on</supplied> the way <supplied>to</supplied> the hill country of the Amorites<note>Hebrew “Amorite”</note> as Yahweh our God had commanded us, and <supplied>so</supplied> we came up to Kadesh Barnea. <verse-number id="Dt 1:20">20</verse-number>I said to you, ‘<idiom-start/>You have reached<idiom-end/><note>Literally “You have come up to”</note> the hill country of the Amorites<note>Hebrew “Amorite”</note> that Yahweh our God <supplied>is</supplied> giving to us. <verse-number id="Dt 1:21">21</verse-number>See, Yahweh your God has set before you the land; go up and possess <supplied>it</supplied> as Yahweh the God of your ancestors<note>Or “fathers”</note> said to you; do not fear and do not be dismayed.’ </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 1:22">22</verse-number>“Then all of you approached me, and <supplied>you</supplied> said, ‘Let us send men <idiom-start/>before us<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “before our faces” or “ahead of us”</note> and let them explore the land for us, and let them bring back <idiom-start/>a report<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a word”</note> to us <supplied>concerning</supplied> the way that <idiom-start/>we should take<idiom-end/><note>Literally “we should go up by it”</note> <supplied>and concerning</supplied> the cities that we shall come to.’ <verse-number id="Dt 1:23">23</verse-number>The plan was good <idiom-start/>in my opinion<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “in my eyes”</note> and <supplied>so</supplied> I took from <supplied>among</supplied> you twelve men, <idiom-start/>one from each tribe<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “man one from the tribe”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 1:24">24</verse-number>And they <idiom-start/>set out<idiom-end/><note>Literally “turned”</note> and <idiom-start/>went up into the hill country<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “went up toward the hill <supplied>country</supplied> mountain”</note> and they went up to the wadi<note>A valley that is dry most of the year, but contains a stream during the rainy season</note> of Eschol, and they spied out <supplied>the land</supplied>. <verse-number id="Dt 1:25">25</verse-number>They took in their hands<note>Hebrew “hand”</note> <idiom-start/>some of the fruit<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from the fruit”</note> of the land, and they brought <supplied>it</supplied> down to us, and they brought to us back <idiom-start/>a report<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “a word”</note> and they said, ‘The land that Yahweh our God <supplied>is</supplied> giving to us <supplied>is</supplied> good.’ <verse-number id="Dt 1:26">26</verse-number>But you were not willing to go up, and you rebelled against the <idiom-start/>command<idiom-end/><note>Literally “mouth”</note> of Yahweh your God. <verse-number id="Dt 1:27">27</verse-number>And you grumbled in your tents, and you said, ‘Because of the hatred of Yahweh <supplied>toward</supplied> us he has brought us out from the land of Egypt to give us into the hand of the Amorites<note>Hebrew “Amorite”</note> to destroy us. <verse-number id="Dt 1:28">28</verse-number>Where <supplied>can</supplied> we go up? Our brothers have <idiom-start/>made our hearts melt<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “caused to melt our hearts”</note> <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> “The people are greater<note>Or “bigger”</note> and taller than we are,<note>Hebrew “than us”</note> <supplied>and there are</supplied> great fortified cities <supplied>reaching</supplied> up to heaven, and we saw the sons of the Anakites <supplied>living</supplied> there.” ’ </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 1:29">29</verse-number>“And so I said to you, ‘Do not be terrified, and do not fear them. <verse-number id="Dt 1:30">30</verse-number>Yahweh your God, who is going <idiom-start/>before you<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to your faces”</note> will himself<note>The Hebrew pronoun indicates emphasis</note> fight for you, <idiom-start/>just as<idiom-end/><note>Literally “like all that”</note> he did for you in Egypt before your eyes, <verse-number id="Dt 1:31">31</verse-number>and <supplied>just as he did</supplied> in the wilderness<note>Or “desert”</note> when<note>Or “where”</note> you saw that<note>Or “how”</note> Yahweh your God carried you, just as someone<note>Or “a man”</note> carries his son, all <supplied>along</supplied> the way <supplied>that</supplied> you traveled until <idiom-start/>you reached<idiom-end/><note>Literally “you came”</note> this place.’ <verse-number id="Dt 1:32">32</verse-number>But through all of this you did not trust in Yahweh your God, <verse-number id="Dt 1:33">33</verse-number><idiom-start/>who goes<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<supplied>is</supplied> the one going”</note> <idiom-start/>before you<idiom-end/><note>Literally “before your faces”</note> on your<note>Hebrew “the”</note> way, seeking a place for your encampment, in fire at night and in a cloud by day, to show you the way that <idiom-start/>you should go<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “you should go in it”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 1:34">34</verse-number>“Then Yahweh heard the sound of your words, and he was angry, and he swore, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 1:35">35</verse-number>‘No one of these men<note>The beginning of an oath in Hebrew; the text emphatically denies anyone of that evil generation the privilege of seeing the promised land</note> of this evil generation will see the good land that I swore to give to your ancestors,<note>Or “fathers”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 1:36">36</verse-number>except Caleb, the son of Jephunneh; he himself<note>Emphatic use of the pronoun</note> shall see it, and to him I will give the land upon which he has trodden and to his sons<note>Or “descendants”</note> because <idiom-start/>he followed Yahweh unreservedly<idiom-end/>.’<note>Literally “he filled <supplied>his hands</supplied> after Yahweh”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 1:37">37</verse-number>Even with me Yahweh was angry because of you, saying, ‘Not even you shall enter there. <verse-number id="Dt 1:38">38</verse-number>Joshua, the son of Nun, <idiom-start/>your assistant<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the one standing before you”</note> will go there; encourage him because he will cause Israel to inherit it. <verse-number id="Dt 1:39">39</verse-number>And your little children, who you thought shall become plunder, and your sons, who do not today know good or bad, shall themselves<note>The Hebrew pronoun is used for emphasis</note> go there, and I will give it to them, and they shall take possession of it. <verse-number id="Dt 1:40">40</verse-number>But you turn and set out <supplied>in the direction of</supplied> the wilderness by way of the <idiom-start/>Red Sea<idiom-end/>.’<note>Literally “sea of reeds”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 1:41">41</verse-number>“You replied and said to me, ‘We have sinned against Yahweh, <supplied>and now</supplied> we will go up and fight according to all that Yahweh our God commanded us’; and <supplied>so</supplied> each man fastened on <idiom-start/>his battle gear<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “his vessels of battle”</note> and you regarded <supplied>it</supplied> as easy to go up <supplied>into</supplied> the hill country. <verse-number id="Dt 1:42">42</verse-number>So Yahweh said to me, ‘Say to them, “You shall not go up, and you shall not fight because I am not in your midst; you will be defeated <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the faces of your enemies”</note> your enemies.” ’ <verse-number id="Dt 1:43">43</verse-number>So I spoke to you, but you did not listen; you rebelled against the <idiom-start/>command of Yahweh<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “mouth of Yahweh”</note> you behaved presumptuously, and you went up into the hill country. <verse-number id="Dt 1:44">44</verse-number>The Amorites living in the hill country went out <idiom-start/>to oppose you<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to meet you”</note> and chased you as <supplied>a swarm of</supplied> wild honey bees do; and <supplied>so</supplied> they <idiom-start/>beat<idiom-end/><note>Literally “cut”</note> you down in Seir as far as Hormah. <verse-number id="Dt 1:45">45</verse-number>So you returned and wept <idiom-start/>before Yahweh<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “before the faces of Yahweh”</note> but Yahweh did not listen to your voice and did not pay <supplied>any</supplied> attention to you. <verse-number id="Dt 1:46">46</verse-number>You stayed in Kadesh many days; such were the days that you stayed <supplied>there</supplied>. </p>
		</chapter>