<chapter id="Dt 2">
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 2">2</verse-number><verse-number id="Dt 2:1">1</verse-number> “<supplied>Then</supplied> we turned and set out <supplied>toward</supplied> the wilderness<note>Or “desert”</note> in the direction of the <idiom-start/>Red Sea<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sea of reeds”</note> as Yahweh told me, and we went around Mount Seir <supplied>for</supplied> many days. <verse-number id="Dt 2:2">2</verse-number>Yahweh spoke to me, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 2:3">3</verse-number>‘<supplied>Long</supplied> enough you have been skirting this mountain; turn yourselves north, <verse-number id="Dt 2:4">4</verse-number>and instruct<note>Or “command”</note> the people, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> “You <supplied>are</supplied> about to cross <supplied>through</supplied> the territory of your brothers, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Esau, who are living in Seir; they will be afraid of you, and <supplied>so</supplied> be very careful. <verse-number id="Dt 2:5">5</verse-number>Do not get involved in battle<note>Or “provoke”</note> with them, for I will not give you any of their land, not even <idiom-start/>a foot’s breadth<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a sole’s foot of space”</note> <supplied>of it</supplied>; since I have given Mount Seir <supplied>as</supplied> a possession for Esau. <verse-number id="Dt 2:6">6</verse-number>You shall buy food from them so that you may eat; and also you shall purchase water from them with money so that you may drink. <verse-number id="Dt 2:7">7</verse-number>The fact of the matter is, Yahweh your God has blessed you in <idiom-start/>all the work you have done<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “the work of your hand”</note> he knows <idiom-start/>your travels<idiom-end/><note>Literally “your journeying”</note> <supplied>with respect to</supplied> this great wilderness; forty years Yahweh your God <supplied>has been</supplied> with you; you have not lacked a thing.” ’ <verse-number id="Dt 2:8">8</verse-number>And so we passed by our brothers, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Esau, who live in Seir, past the road of the Arabah,<note>Or “Jordan Valley” since the Arabah is an extension of it</note> from Elath and Ezion Geber, and we turned and traveled along the route of the desert<note>Or “wilderness”</note> of Moab. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 2:9">9</verse-number>And Yahweh said to me, ‘You shall not attack Moab, and you shall not engage in war<note>Or “battle”</note> with them, for I will not give you any of his land <supplied>as</supplied> a possession; I have given Ar to the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Lot <supplied>as</supplied> a possession.’ <verse-number id="Dt 2:10">10</verse-number>(The Emim previously lived in it, a people large,<note>Or “great” in the sense of influential</note> numerous, and tall, like the Anakites. <verse-number id="Dt 2:11">11</verse-number>They were reckoned also <supplied>as</supplied> Rephaim as the Anakites <supplied>were</supplied>; but the Moabites called them Emim. <verse-number id="Dt 2:12">12</verse-number>The Horites previously lived in Seir, but the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Esau dispossessed them and destroyed them <idiom-start/>from among themselves<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from their presence”</note> as Israel did with respect to the land of their<note>Literally “its/his”</note> possession that Yahweh gave to them.) <verse-number id="Dt 2:13">13</verse-number>So <supplied>now</supplied> arise and cross over the wadi<note>A valley that is dry most of the year, but contains a stream during the rainy season</note> of Zered yourselves; and <supplied>so</supplied> we crossed the wadi<note>A valley that is dry most of the year, but contains a stream during the rainy season</note> of Zered. <verse-number id="Dt 2:14">14</verse-number>Now the <idiom-start/>length of time<idiom-end/><note>Literally “days”</note> that we had traveled from Kadesh Barnea until <supplied>the time when</supplied> we crossed the wadi<note>A valley that is dry most of the year, but contains a stream during the rainy season</note> of Zered <supplied>was</supplied> thirty-eight years, until the perishing of all of that generation; <supplied>that is</supplied>, the men of war from the midst of the camp as Yahweh had sworn to them. <verse-number id="Dt 2:15">15</verse-number>The hand of Yahweh was against them to root them out from the midst of the camp until they perished completely. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 2:16">16</verse-number>“<idiom-start/>And then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And it happened”</note> when all the men of war<note>Or “battle”</note> <idiom-start/>had died<idiom-end/><note>Literally “had finished/completed to die”</note> from among the people, <verse-number id="Dt 2:17">17</verse-number>Yahweh spoke to me, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 2:18">18</verse-number>‘You <supplied>are</supplied> about to cross over the boundary of Moab <idiom-start/>today<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the day”</note> at Ar. <verse-number id="Dt 2:19">19</verse-number>When you approach <idiom-start/>the border of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “opposite”</note> the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the sons/children of Ammon”</note> you shall not harass them, and you shall not get involved in battle with them, for I have not given the land of <idiom-start/>the Ammonites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the sons/children of Ammon”</note> to you as a possession; because I have given it to the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Lot <supplied>as</supplied> a possession. <verse-number id="Dt 2:20">20</verse-number>(It is also considered the land of Rephaim; Rephaim lived in it <idiom-start/>previously<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “before”</note> and the Ammonites called them Zamzummim, <verse-number id="Dt 2:21">21</verse-number>a people great and numerous and as tall as the Anakites; Yahweh destroyed them from before them,<note>That is, the Ammonites</note> and they dispossessed them and settled in place of them, <verse-number id="Dt 2:22">22</verse-number>just as he did for the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Esau, who live in Seir, when he destroyed the Horites from <idiom-start/>before them<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from the face/presence of them”</note> and dispossessed them, and <supplied>then</supplied> they settled in their<note>Hebrew “them”</note> place up to this day. <verse-number id="Dt 2:23">23</verse-number>And <supplied>also</supplied> the Avvites, who lived in villages as far as Gaza, <supplied>and the</supplied> Caphtorim, who came out from Caphtor, destroyed them and <supplied>then</supplied> settled in their place. <verse-number id="Dt 2:24">24</verse-number>Arise,<note>Or “Get up”</note> set out and cross <supplied>over</supplied> the wadi<note>A valley that is dry most of the year, but contains a stream during the rainy season</note> of Arnon. Look! I have given Sihon the Amorite, the king of Heshbon, and his land into your hand; begin to take possession of <supplied>it</supplied>, and engage with him in battle. <verse-number id="Dt 2:25">25</verse-number>This day I will begin to place <idiom-start/>the dread of you<idiom-end/><note>Literally “your dread”</note> and the fear of you <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “upon the faces of”</note> the peoples under all the heavens. <supplied>They</supplied> will hear <idiom-start/>the report about you<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “your report”</note> and <supplied>so</supplied> they will shake and tremble <idiom-start/>because of you<idiom-end/>.’ <note>Literally “from before you”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 2:26">26</verse-number>“So I sent messengers from the wilderness<note>Or “desert”</note> of Kedemoth to Sihon king of Heshbon; <supplied>I sent</supplied> terms of peace, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 2:27">27</verse-number>‘Let me cross through your land <supplied>and</supplied> <idiom-start/>only along the road<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the road, in the road”</note> I will go; I will not turn aside to the right or <supplied>to the</supplied> left. <verse-number id="Dt 2:28">28</verse-number>Food for money you shall sell me, so that I may eat, and water for money you will give to me, so that I may drink; just let me cross on foot. <verse-number id="Dt 2:29">29</verse-number><supplied>Just as</supplied> the descendants<note>Or “the children/sons of”</note> of Esau did for me, who live in Seir, and the Moabites, who live in Ar, until I cross the Jordan into the land that Yahweh our God is giving to us.’ <verse-number id="Dt 2:30">30</verse-number>But Sihon king of Heshbon was not willing to let us cross through his <supplied>territory</supplied> because Yahweh your God hardened his spirit and <idiom-start/>made him obstinate<idiom-end/><note>Literally “made firm his heart”</note> <idiom-start/>in order to give him<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to give him,” indicating purpose</note> into your hand, <idiom-start/>just as he has now done<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “as <supplied>it is</supplied> this day”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 2:31">31</verse-number>Yahweh said to me, ‘Look! I have begun to give <idiom-start/>over to you<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of you”</note> Sihon and his land; begin <idiom-start/>to take possession of his land<idiom-end/>.’<note>Literally, “take possession in order to possess his land”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 2:32">32</verse-number>Then Sihon and all his people came out to meet us for battle at Jahaz. <verse-number id="Dt 2:33">33</verse-number>And so Yahweh our God gave him over <idiom-start/>to us<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “before us”</note> and we struck him down, and his sons<note>Or “descendants”</note> and all of his people. <verse-number id="Dt 2:34">34</verse-number>So we captured all of his cities at that time, and we destroyed each town <supplied>of</supplied> males and the women and the children; we did not leave behind a survivor. <verse-number id="Dt 2:35">35</verse-number>We took only the livestock as spoil for ourselves,<note>Hebrew “us”</note> and <supplied>also</supplied> the booty of the cities that we had captured. <verse-number id="Dt 2:36">36</verse-number>From Aroer, which <supplied>is</supplied> on the edge of the wadi<note>A valley that is dry most of the year, but contains a stream during the rainy season</note> of Arnon and the city that <supplied>was</supplied> in the wadi<note>A valley that is dry most of the year, but contains a stream during the rainy season</note> on up to Gilead, <supplied>there</supplied> was not a city that was inaccessible to us; Yahweh our God gave <idiom-start/>everything<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the whole”</note> <idiom-start/>to us<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “before us”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 2:37">37</verse-number>Only the land of <idiom-start/>the Ammonites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “children/sons of Ammon”</note> you did not approach, <supplied>all along</supplied> the whole upper region of the Jabbok <idiom-start/>River<idiom-end/><note>Literally “wadi,” which here refers to a flowing river</note> and the towns of the hill country, <supplied>according to all</supplied> that Yahweh our God had instructed. </p>
		</chapter>