<chapter id="Dt 4">
			<pericope>Introduction to the Stipulations</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 4:1">1</verse-number>“Now, Israel, listen to the rules and to the regulations that I <supplied>am</supplied> teaching you to do, in order that you may live and you may go <supplied>in</supplied> and you may take possession of the land that Yahweh, the God of your ancestors,<note>Or “fathers”</note> <supplied>is</supplied> giving to you. <verse-number id="Dt 4:2">2</verse-number>You must not add to the word that I <supplied>am</supplied> commanding you, and you shall not take away from it <supplied>in order</supplied> to keep<note>Or “observe”</note> the commands of Yahweh your God that I <supplied>am</supplied> commanding you <supplied>to observe</supplied>. <verse-number id="Dt 4:3">3</verse-number>Your eyes have seen<note>Literally “your eyes the seeing what”</note> what Yahweh did with<note>Or “in”</note> <supplied>the case of</supplied> Baal Peor, for <idiom-start/>each<idiom-end/><note>Literally “every one <supplied>of</supplied>”</note> man that followed after Baal Peor Yahweh your God destroyed from your midst. <verse-number id="Dt 4:4">4</verse-number>But you, the <supplied>ones</supplied> holding fast to Yahweh your God, <supplied>are</supplied> all alive <idiom-start/>today<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the day”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 4:5">5</verse-number>See, I now teach<note>Or “I have taught” (compare NASB, NEB)</note> you rules and regulations <supplied>just</supplied> as Yahweh my God has commanded me, to observe <supplied>them</supplied> <supplied>just</supplied> so in the midst of the land where you <supplied>are</supplied> going, to take possession of it. <verse-number id="Dt 4:6">6</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>you must observe them diligently<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “you must observe and you must do”</note> for that <supplied>is</supplied> your wisdom and your insight before the eyes of the people, who will hear all <supplied>of</supplied> these rules, and they will say, ‘Surely this great nation <supplied>is</supplied> a wise and discerning people.’ <verse-number id="Dt 4:7">7</verse-number>For what great nation <supplied>has</supplied> for it a god near to it as Yahweh our God, whenever<note>Literally “in every matter/every time we call ”</note> we call <supplied>upon</supplied> him? <verse-number id="Dt 4:8">8</verse-number>And what <supplied>other</supplied> great nation has for it<note>Literally “which/that <supplied>is</supplied> for him <supplied>it</supplied>”</note> just rules and regulations just like<note>Literally “as”</note> <idiom-start/>this whole<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all <supplied>of</supplied>”</note> law that I <supplied>am</supplied> setting <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of”</note> you <idiom-start/>today<idiom-end/>?<note>Literally “the day”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 4:9">9</verse-number>“However, <idiom-start/>take care<idiom-end/><note>Literally “watch”</note> for yourself and watch your inner self<note>Or “soul”</note> closely, so that you do not forget the things that your eyes have seen, so that they do not slip from your mind all the days of your life; and you shall make them known to your children and to <idiom-start/>your grandchildren<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the children of your children”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 4:10">10</verse-number><supplied>Remember</supplied> the day that you stood <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of”</note> Yahweh your God at Horeb <idiom-start/>when Yahweh said to me<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “when to say Yahweh”</note> ‘Summon for me the people so that I can tell them my words, that they may learn to fear me all <supplied>of</supplied> the days they <supplied>are</supplied> alive on the earth and so <supplied>that</supplied> they may teach their children.’ <verse-number id="Dt 4:11">11</verse-number>And <supplied>so</supplied> you came near, and you stood under the mountain, and the mountain <supplied>was</supplied> burning with fire up to the heart of the heaven, <idiom-start/>dark with a very thick cloud<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “darkness, cloud, and very thick darkness”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 4:12">12</verse-number>And Yahweh spoke to you from the midst of the fire; <idiom-start/>you heard<idiom-end/><note>Literally “you <supplied>were</supplied> hearing”</note> a sound of words, but <idiom-start/>you did not see<idiom-end/><note>Literally “you were not seeing”</note> a form—only a voice. <verse-number id="Dt 4:13">13</verse-number>And he declared to you his covenant, <idiom-start/>the Ten Commandments<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the ten words”</note> which he charged you <idiom-start/>to observe<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to do”</note> and he wrote them on <supplied>the</supplied> two tablets of stone. <verse-number id="Dt 4:14">14</verse-number>And Yahweh charged me at that time to teach you rules and regulations <idiom-start/>for your observation of them<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for your doing them”</note> in the land that you <supplied>are</supplied> <idiom-start/>about to cross into<idiom-end/><note>Literally “about to cross into there”</note> to take possession of it. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 4:15">15</verse-number>“So <idiom-start/>you must be very careful for yourselves<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “watch yourselves diligently with respect to your souls”</note> because you did not see<note>Or “have not seen”</note> any form on the day Yahweh spoke to you at Horeb from the midst of the fire, <verse-number id="Dt 4:16">16</verse-number>so that you <supplied>do</supplied> not <idiom-start/>ruin yourselves<idiom-end/><note>Literally “corrupt yourselves”</note> and make for yourselves a divine image <supplied>in</supplied> a form of any image, a replica of male or female, <verse-number id="Dt 4:17">17</verse-number>a replica of any animal that <supplied>is</supplied> upon the earth, a replica of any winged bird that flies in the air, <verse-number id="Dt 4:18">18</verse-number>a replica of any creeping thing on the ground, a replica of any fish that <supplied>is</supplied> in the water <idiom-start/>below<idiom-end/><note>Literally “under”</note> the earth. <verse-number id="Dt 4:19">19</verse-number><idiom-start/>And do this so that you do not lift<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And lest you lift up”</note> your eyes <supplied>toward</supplied> heaven and <idiom-start/>observe<idiom-end/><note>Literally “see”</note> the sun and the moon and the stars, all the host of the heaven, and be led astray and bow down to them and serve them, things that Yahweh your God has allotted to all <supplied>of</supplied> the peoples under all <supplied>of</supplied> the heaven. <verse-number id="Dt 4:20">20</verse-number>But Yahweh has taken you and brought you out from the furnace of iron, from Egypt, to be a people of inheritance to<note>Or “for”; a people of inheritance = a people who is his very own possession</note> him, <idiom-start/>as it is this day<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “as the day the this” = as you are now</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 4:21">21</verse-number>“And Yahweh was angry with me <idiom-start/>because of you<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “because of your matter”</note> and he swore <idiom-start/>that I would not cross the Jordan<idiom-end/><note>Literally “not I to cross the Jordan”</note> and <idiom-start/>that I would not go to the good land<idiom-end/><note>Literally “not <supplied>I</supplied> going to the land”</note> that Yahweh your God is giving you as an inheritance. <verse-number id="Dt 4:22">22</verse-number>For I <supplied>am</supplied> going to die in this land; I am not going to cross the Jordan, but you <supplied>are</supplied> going to cross, and you are going to take possession of this good land. <verse-number id="Dt 4:23">23</verse-number>Watch <supplied>out</supplied> for yourselves so that you do not forget the covenant of Yahweh your God that he had <idiom-start/>made<idiom-end/><note>Literally “cut”</note> with you and make for yourselves a divine image <supplied>of</supplied> the form of anything that Yahweh your God <idiom-start/>has forbidden<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “has commanded you <supplied>about</supplied>”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 4:24">24</verse-number>for Yahweh your God <supplied>is</supplied> a devouring fire, a jealous<note>Or “zealous” or “impassioned”</note> God. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 4:25">25</verse-number>“When you have had children and <idiom-start/>grandchildren<idiom-end/><note>Literally “children of children”</note> and you have grown old in the land and you act corruptly and you make a divine image <supplied>of</supplied> the form of anything and you do evil in the eyes of Yahweh your God, <supplied>thus</supplied> provoking him to anger, <verse-number id="Dt 4:26">26</verse-number>I call<note>Or “I shall call to witness”</note> to witness against you today the heaven and the earth, that you will perish soon and completely from the land that you <supplied>are</supplied> crossing the Jordan into it to take possession of it; <idiom-start/>you will not live long on it<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “you will not extend days”</note> but you will be completely destroyed. <verse-number id="Dt 4:27">27</verse-number>And Yahweh will scatter you among the peoples, and you will be left <idiom-start/>few in number<idiom-end/><note>Literally “people of number,” as opposed to people without number</note> among the nations <idiom-start/>to where Yahweh will lead you<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “<supplied>he</supplied> will lead Yahweh you there”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 4:28">28</verse-number>And you will there serve gods <idiom-start/>made by human hands<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the work of the hands of human”</note> <supplied>of</supplied> wood and stone, <supplied>gods</supplied> that cannot see and cannot hear and cannot eat and cannot smell. <verse-number id="Dt 4:29">29</verse-number>But from there you shall seek Yahweh your God and will find him, if you seek him with all your heart and with all your soul.<note>Or “inner self”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 4:30">30</verse-number><idiom-start/>In your distress<idiom-end/><note>Literally “In <supplied>the</supplied> distress for you”</note> when<note>Hebrew “and”</note> all these things have found you in the <idiom-start/>latter days<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “in the last of the days”</note> then<note>Hebrew “and”</note> you will return to Yahweh your God, and you will listen to his voice. <verse-number id="Dt 4:31">31</verse-number>For Yahweh your God is a compassionate God; he <idiom-start/>will not abandon you<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “will not leave you alone”</note> and he will not destroy you, and he will not forget the covenant of your ancestors<note>Or “fathers”</note> that he swore to them. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 4:32">32</verse-number>“Yes, ask, please, about former days that <idiom-start/>preceded you<idiom-end/><note>Literally “that <supplied>they</supplied> were to the face of you”</note> from the day that God created humankind on the earth; <supplied>ask even</supplied> from <supplied>one</supplied> end of the heaven up to the <supplied>other</supplied> end of heaven <idiom-start/>whether anything ever happened<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was it <supplied>ever</supplied>”</note> like this great thing or <idiom-start/>whether anything like it was ever heard<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “was it <supplied>ever</supplied> heard as it”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 4:33">33</verse-number>Has a people <supplied>ever</supplied> heard the voice of God speaking from the midst of the fire, <supplied>just</supplied> as you heard <supplied>it</supplied>, and lived? <verse-number id="Dt 4:34">34</verse-number>Or has a god <supplied>ever</supplied> attempted to go to take for himself<note>Hebrew “for him”</note> a nation from the midst of a nation, <supplied>using</supplied> trials and signs and wonders and war, with an outstretched arm and with great and awesome deeds, like all that Yahweh your God did for you in Egypt before your eyes? <verse-number id="Dt 4:35">35</verse-number>You <supplied>yourselves</supplied><note>Emphatic use of pronoun; plural meaning implied</note> were shown <supplied>this wonder</supplied> in order <supplied>for you</supplied> to acknowledge that Yahweh <supplied>is</supplied> the God;<note>The definite article indicates that Israel’s God is alone the true God and the one who revealed himself to them</note> there is no other <supplied>God</supplied> <idiom-start/>besides him<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “except him” or “to him alone”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 4:36">36</verse-number>From heaven he made you hear his voice to teach you, and on the earth he showed you his great fire, and you heard his words from the midst of the fire. <verse-number id="Dt 4:37">37</verse-number>And because he loved your ancestors<note>Or “fathers”</note> he chose their <idiom-start/>descendants<idiom-end/><note>Literally “seed”</note> after them. And he brought you forth from Egypt <idiom-start/>with his own presence<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “with his faces”</note> by his great strength, <verse-number id="Dt 4:38">38</verse-number>to drive out nations greater and more numerous than you <idiom-start/>from before you<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from your face”</note> to bring you <supplied>and</supplied> to give to you their land <supplied>as</supplied> an inheritance, as <supplied>it is</supplied> this day. <verse-number id="Dt 4:39">39</verse-number>So you shall acknowledge <idiom-start/>today<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the day”</note> and <idiom-start/>you must call to mind<idiom-end/><note>Literally “you shall bring back to your heart”</note> that Yahweh <supplied>is</supplied> God in heaven above and on the earth beneath. There is no other <supplied>God</supplied>. <verse-number id="Dt 4:40">40</verse-number>And you shall keep his rules and his commandments that I am commanding you <idiom-start/>today<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the day”</note> <supplied>so</supplied> that <idiom-start/>it may go well<idiom-end/><note>Literally “he/it is good”</note> for you and for your children<note>Or “descendants”</note> after you, and so that <idiom-start/>you may remain a long time<idiom-end/><note>Literally “you may make long/prolong days”</note> on the land that Yahweh your God <supplied>is</supplied> giving to you <supplied>during</supplied> all <supplied>of</supplied> those days.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 4:41">41</verse-number>Then Moses set apart three cities <idiom-start/>on the other side of the Jordan<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “<supplied>in the</supplied> beyond <supplied>of</supplied> the Jordan”</note> <idiom-start/>toward the east<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “toward rising of the sun”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 4:42">42</verse-number><supplied>in order for</supplied> <idiom-start/>a manslayer<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a killer of a man”</note> to flee there <supplied>who</supplied> has killed his neighbor <idiom-start/>without intent<idiom-end/><note>Literally “without <supplied>previous</supplied> knowledge”</note> and was not hating him <idiom-start/>previously<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “<supplied>the</supplied> day before yesterday”</note> and <supplied>so</supplied> he could flee to one of these cities <idiom-start/>and be safe<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “and live”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 4:43">43</verse-number><supplied>He set apart</supplied> Bezer in the wilderness<note>Or “desert”</note> in the land of the plateau of the Reubenites;<note>Hebrew “Reubenite”</note> Ramoth in Gilead of the Gadites,<note>Hebrew “Gadite”</note> and Golan in Bashan of the Manassites.<note>Hebrew “Manassite”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 4:44">44</verse-number>Now this <supplied>is</supplied> the law<note>Hebrew “the <i>torah</i>” = teaching, instruction, law</note> that Moses set <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “before the faces of”</note> the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 4:45">45</verse-number>these are the legal provisions and the rules and the regulations that Moses spoke to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> <idiom-start/>when they left Egypt<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “at their going out from Egypt”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 4:46">46</verse-number>beyond the Jordan in the valley opposite Beth Peor in the land of Sihon the king of the Amorites,<note>Hebrew “Amorite”</note> who <supplied>was</supplied> reigning in Heshbon <supplied>and</supplied> whom Moses and the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> defeated <idiom-start/>when they came out of Egypt<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “at their going out from Egypt”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 4:47">47</verse-number>And <supplied>so</supplied> they took possession of his land and the land of Og king of Bashan, the two kings of the Amorites<note>Hebrew “Amorite”</note> who <supplied>were</supplied> beyond the Jordan, <idiom-start/>eastward<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “toward the rising of the sun”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 4:48">48</verse-number>from Aroer, which <supplied>is</supplied> on the bank of the wadi<note>A valley that is dry most of the year, but contains a stream during the rainy season</note> of Arnon and as far as Mount Sirion; that <supplied>is</supplied>, Hermon, <verse-number id="Dt 4:49">49</verse-number>and all <supplied>of</supplied> the Arabah<note>Or “valley” in this instance</note> beyond the Jordan, eastward, and as far as the Sea of the Arabah<note>Commonly known today as the Dead Sea</note> under the slopes of Pisgah. </p>
		</chapter>