<chapter id="Dt 5">
			<pericope>Basic Stipulations</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 5:1">1</verse-number>And <supplied>then</supplied> Moses summoned all <supplied>of</supplied> Israel and said to them, “Hear, Israel, the rules and the regulations that I <supplied>am</supplied> speaking in your ears <idiom-start/>today<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the day”</note> and you shall learn them, and <idiom-start/>you must observe them diligently<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “you shall observe them carefully to do them”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 5:2">2</verse-number>Yahweh our God made a covenant with us at Horeb. <verse-number id="Dt 5:3">3</verse-number><supplied>It was</supplied> not with our ancestors<note>Or “fathers”</note> <supplied>that</supplied> Yahweh made this covenant, <supplied>but with</supplied> these <supplied>of</supplied> us <supplied>who are</supplied> here alive today. <verse-number id="Dt 5:4">4</verse-number><idiom-start/>Face to face<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Faces to faces”</note> Yahweh spoke with you at the mountain from the midst of the fire. <verse-number id="Dt 5:5">5</verse-number>I was standing <idiom-start/>between Yahweh and you<idiom-end/><note>Literally “between Yahweh and between you”</note> at that time to report<note>Or “declare”</note> to you the word of Yahweh, for you were afraid because of <idiom-start/>the presence of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the faces of”</note> the fire, and <supplied>so</supplied> you <supplied>did</supplied> not go up the mountain. <idiom-start/>He said<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “To say”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 5:6">6</verse-number>‘I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh your God, who brought you out from the land of Egypt, from the house of slavery. <verse-number id="Dt 5:7">7</verse-number><supplied>There</supplied> shall not be for you other gods <idiom-start/>besides me<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “before my face”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 5:8">8</verse-number>‘You shall not make for yourself a divine image of any <supplied>type</supplied> of form that <supplied>is</supplied> in the heaven above or that <supplied>is</supplied> on the earth beneath or that <supplied>is</supplied> in the water under the earth. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 5:9">9</verse-number>‘You shall not bow down to them, and you shall not serve them, for I, Yahweh your God, <supplied>am</supplied> a jealous God, punishing the guilt of fathers upon <supplied>their</supplied> children and upon <supplied>the</supplied> third and upon <supplied>the</supplied> fourth generation of <supplied>those</supplied> hating me, <verse-number id="Dt 5:10">10</verse-number>but showing loyal love to thousands of <supplied>those who</supplied> love me and of <supplied>those who</supplied> keep my commandments. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 5:11">11</verse-number>‘You shall not take up the name of Yahweh your God for <supplied>a</supplied> worthless purpose, for Yahweh will not leave unpunished <supplied>anyone</supplied> who uses his name for <supplied>a</supplied> worthless purpose. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 5:12">12</verse-number>‘Observe the <idiom-start/>Sabbath day<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the day of the Sabbath”</note> to make it holy,<note>Or “to sanctify it”</note> <supplied>just</supplied> as Yahweh your God has commanded you. <verse-number id="Dt 5:13">13</verse-number>Six days you shall work, and you shall do all <supplied>of</supplied> your work, <verse-number id="Dt 5:14">14</verse-number>but the seventh day <supplied>is</supplied> <supplied>a</supplied> Sabbath unto Yahweh your God; you shall not do any work, or your son, or your daughter, or your slave, or your slave woman, or your ox, or your donkey, or any of your domestic animals, or your <supplied>resident</supplied> alien who <supplied>is</supplied> in your <idiom-start/>towns<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “gates”</note> so that your slave and your slave woman may rest as you <supplied>rest</supplied>. <verse-number id="Dt 5:15">15</verse-number>And you shall remember that you were a slave in the land of Egypt, and Yahweh your God brought you out with a strong hand and with an outstretched arm; therefore, Yahweh your God commanded you to keep <idiom-start/>the Sabbath<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the day of the Sabbath”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 5:16">16</verse-number>‘Honor your father and your mother, as Yahweh your God commanded you, so that it will be good for you<note>Or “it may go well for you”</note> <idiom-start/>in the land<idiom-end/><note>Literally “on the ground”</note> that Yahweh your God <supplied>is</supplied> giving to you. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 5:17">17</verse-number>‘You shall not murder. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 5:18">18</verse-number>‘And you shall not commit adultery. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 5:19">19</verse-number>‘And you shall not steal. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 5:20">20</verse-number>‘And you shall not falsely bear evidence against your neighbor. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 5:21">21</verse-number>‘And you shall not covet the wife of your neighbor, and you shall not crave the house of your neighbor, his field or his slave or his slave woman or his ox and his donkey or anything <idiom-start/>that belongs to your neighbor<idiom-end/>.’<note>Literally “that <supplied>is</supplied> for your neighbor”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 5:22">22</verse-number>“These words Yahweh spoke to your whole assembly at the mountain from the midst of the fire and the very thick cloud <supplied>with</supplied> a loud voice, and <idiom-start/>he did not add anything<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “and not he added”</note> and <supplied>then</supplied> he wrote them on two tablets of stone and gave them to me. <verse-number id="Dt 5:23">23</verse-number><idiom-start/>And then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And it happened”</note> <idiom-start/>when you heard<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and as/when you heard” or “<supplied>at</supplied> the moment of your hearing”</note> the voice from the midst of the darkness, and <supplied>as</supplied> the mountain <supplied>was</supplied> burning with fire, and <supplied>and</supplied> all the heads of your tribes and your elders approached me, <verse-number id="Dt 5:24">24</verse-number>you said, ‘Look, Yahweh our God has shown us his glory and his greatness, and we have heard his voice from the midst of the fire; this day we have seen<note>Or “saw”</note> that God can speak with a human being, <idiom-start/>yet he remains alive<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “and <supplied>he</supplied> lives”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 5:25">25</verse-number>And so then why shall we die, for this great fire will consume us if <idiom-start/>we continue<idiom-end/><note>Literally “we do again to hear”; or “we are doing again to hear”</note> to hear the voice of Yahweh our God <supplied>any</supplied> longer, and <supplied>so</supplied> we shall die? <verse-number id="Dt 5:26">26</verse-number>For who <supplied>is there of</supplied> all flesh who has heard the voice of the living God speaking from the midst of the fire as we <supplied>have heard it</supplied> <idiom-start/>and remained alive<idiom-end/>?<note>Literally “and lives”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 5:27">27</verse-number><supplied>You</supplied> go near and hear <idiom-start/>everything<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all of <supplied>that</supplied> which”</note> that Yahweh our God will say; and <supplied>then</supplied> you tell us all that Yahweh our God tells you, and we will listen, and we will do <supplied>it</supplied>.’ </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 5:28">28</verse-number>“And Yahweh heard the sound of your words <idiom-start/>when you spoke to me<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “in/at you to speak to me”</note> and Yahweh said to me, ‘I have heard the sound of the words of this people that they have spoken to you; <supplied>they</supplied> are right <supplied>with respect to</supplied> all that they have spoken. <verse-number id="Dt 5:29">29</verse-number><idiom-start/>If only<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Who gives/will give”</note> <idiom-start/>they had such a mind<idiom-end/>’;<note>Literally “<supplied>it</supplied> would be their heart this to them”</note> <supplied>that is</supplied>, to fear me and to keep all my commandments <idiom-start/>at all times<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “all the days”</note> so that <idiom-start/>it will go well<idiom-end/><note>Literally “he/it is good”</note> for them and for their children <idiom-start/>forever<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to eternity”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 5:30">30</verse-number>Go! Say to them, “Return to your tents.” <verse-number id="Dt 5:31">31</verse-number>But you stand here with me, and let me tell you all <supplied>of</supplied> the commandments and the rules and the regulations that you shall teach them, so that they may do <supplied>them</supplied> in the land that I <supplied>am</supplied> giving to them to take possession of it.’ </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 5:32">32</verse-number>“<supplied>So</supplied> you must be careful to do <supplied>just</supplied> as Yahweh your God commanded you; you shall not turn <supplied>to the</supplied> right or <supplied>to the</supplied> left. <verse-number id="Dt 5:33">33</verse-number><idiom-start/>In exactly the path<idiom-end/><note>Literally “In all the way/path”</note> that Yahweh your God has commanded, you must go, so that you may live and <idiom-start/>it will go well<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and good <supplied>it is</supplied>”</note> for you and <idiom-start/>you may live long<idiom-end/><note>Literally “you may make long”</note> in the land that you will take possession of.” </p>
		</chapter>