<chapter id="Dt 6">
			<pericope>Detailed Stipulations</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 6:1">1</verse-number>“Now this <supplied>is</supplied> the commandment, the rules and the regulations, that Yahweh your God charged to teach <supplied>to</supplied> you <supplied>for you</supplied> <idiom-start/>to observe<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to do”</note> in the land that you <supplied>are</supplied> about to cross <supplied>over</supplied> into<note>Or “there”</note> to take possession of it, <verse-number id="Dt 6:2">2</verse-number>so that you may revere Yahweh your God by keeping all his statutes and his commandments that I <supplied>am</supplied> commanding you, you and your children and <idiom-start/>grandchildren<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the children of your children”</note> all the days of your life and so you may live long<note>Literally “they may be long your days”</note> <supplied>lives</supplied>. <verse-number id="Dt 6:3">3</verse-number>And you shall hear, Israel, and be careful to observe <supplied>these instructions</supplied>, so that <idiom-start/>it may go well for you<idiom-end/><note>Literally “it/he may be good”</note> and that you may multiply greatly, <supplied>just</supplied> as Yahweh, the God of your ancestors,<note>Or “fathers”</note> <idiom-start/>promised<idiom-end/><note>Literally “spoke”</note> you, <supplied>in</supplied> a land with milk and honey. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 6:4">4</verse-number>“Hear, Israel, Yahweh our God, Yahweh is unique.<note>Or “one”; or possibly “one Lord”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 6:5">5</verse-number>And you shall love Yahweh your God with all of your heart<note>Or “mind”</note> and with all of your soul<note>Or “inner self”</note> and with all of your might. <verse-number id="Dt 6:6">6</verse-number>And these words that I am commanding you <idiom-start/>today<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the day”</note> shall be on<note>Or “in”</note> your heart.<note>Or “mind”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 6:7">7</verse-number>And you shall recite them to your children, and you shall talk about them at <supplied>the time of</supplied> your living in your house and at <supplied>the time of</supplied> your going on the road and at <supplied>the time of</supplied> your lying down and at <supplied>the time of</supplied> your rising <supplied>up</supplied>. <verse-number id="Dt 6:8">8</verse-number>And you shall bind them as a sign on your hand, and they shall be as an emblem between your eyes. <verse-number id="Dt 6:9">9</verse-number>And you shall write them on the doorframe of your house and on your gates. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 6:10">10</verse-number>“And then it will happen <supplied>that</supplied> when Yahweh your God will bring you to the land that he swore to your ancestors,<note>Or “fathers”</note> to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob, to give to you large and fine cities that you did not build, <verse-number id="Dt 6:11">11</verse-number>and houses full of all <supplied>sorts</supplied> of good things<note>Hebrew “thing”</note> that you did not fill, and hewn cisterns that you did not hew, vineyards and olive groves that you did not plant, and <idiom-start/>you have eaten your fill<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “you have eaten and you are satisfied”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 6:12">12</verse-number>then take care for yourself, so that you <supplied>do</supplied> not forget Yahweh, who brought you out from the land of Egypt from the house of slavery. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 6:13">13</verse-number>“You shall fear Yahweh your God, and you shall serve him, and by his name you shall swear. <verse-number id="Dt 6:14">14</verse-number>You shall not go after other gods from the gods of the peoples who <supplied>are</supplied> all around you, <verse-number id="Dt 6:15">15</verse-number>for Yahweh your God <supplied>is</supplied> a jealous god in your midst, <idiom-start/>so that the anger of Yahweh your God would be kindled<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “so that not/lest the nose of Yahweh your God would become hot”</note> and he would destroy you from the face of the earth. <verse-number id="Dt 6:16">16</verse-number>You shall not put Yahweh your God to <supplied>the</supplied> test, as you tested <supplied>him</supplied> at Massah. <verse-number id="Dt 6:17">17</verse-number>You shall diligently keep the commandments of Yahweh your God and his legal provisions and his rules that he has commanded you. <verse-number id="Dt 6:18">18</verse-number>And you shall do <supplied>what is</supplied> right and good in the eyes of Yahweh, so that <idiom-start/>it shall go well<idiom-end/><note>Literally “he/it shall be good”</note> for you and <supplied>so that</supplied> you may go and you may take possession of the good land that Yahweh swore for your ancestors,<note>Or “your fathers”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 6:19">19</verse-number>by driving out all <supplied>of</supplied> your enemies <idiom-start/>before you<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the face of you”</note> <supplied>just</supplied> as Yahweh <idiom-start/>has promised<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “had spoken”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 6:20">20</verse-number>“When your child<note>Or “son”</note> asks you in the future, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> ‘What <supplied>is the meaning of</supplied> the legal provisions and the rules and the regulations that Yahweh our God commanded for you?’ <verse-number id="Dt 6:21">21</verse-number>Then you shall say to your child,<note>Or “son”</note> ‘We were slaves of Pharaoh in Egypt, and Yahweh brought us out from Egypt with a strong hand. <verse-number id="Dt 6:22">22</verse-number>And Yahweh gave great and awesome signs and wonders in Egypt against Pharaoh and against his entire household <idiom-start/>in our presence<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “before our eyes”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 6:23">23</verse-number>But <supplied>he</supplied> brought us out from there in order to bring us <supplied>here</supplied> to give us the land that he swore to our ancestors.<note>Or “fathers”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 6:24">24</verse-number>And <supplied>so</supplied> Yahweh commanded us to observe all <supplied>of</supplied> these rules <supplied>and</supplied> to revere Yahweh our God <idiom-start/>for our benefit<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for good for us”</note> <idiom-start/>all the days that we live<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “all the days for our living”</note> <idiom-start/>as it is today<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “as the day the this”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 6:25">25</verse-number>And it shall be righteousness for us if we diligently observe <supplied>and</supplied> do all <supplied>of</supplied> this commandment <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the faces of”</note> Yahweh our God, as he has commanded us.’ </p>
		</chapter>