<chapter id="Dt 7">
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 7">7</verse-number><verse-number id="Dt 7:1">1</verse-number> “When Yahweh your God brings you into the land that you <supplied>are</supplied> about to enter <idiom-start/>into it<idiom-end/><note>Literally “there”</note> to take possession of it, and he drives<note>Or “he will drive out”</note> out many nations <idiom-start/>before you<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from your faces”</note> the Hittites<note>Hebrew “Hittite”</note> and the Girgashites<note>Hebrew “Girgashite”</note> and the Amorites<note>Hebrew “Amorite”</note> and the Canaanites<note>Hebrew “Canaanite”</note> and the Hivites<note>Hebrew “Hivite”</note> and the Jebusites,<note>Hebrew “Jebusite”</note> seven nations mightier and more numerous than you, <verse-number id="Dt 7:2">2</verse-number>and Yahweh your God will give them <idiom-start/>over to you<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to your faces” or “before you”</note> and you defeat them, you must <idiom-start/>utterly destroy them<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “set them aside for destruction”</note> you shall not make a covenant with them, and you shall not show mercy <supplied>to them</supplied>. <verse-number id="Dt 7:3">3</verse-number>And you shall not intermarry with them; you shall not give your daughter to their son; and you shall not take his daughter for your son.<note>Grammatically singular pronominal suffixes here can also be rendered “their”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 7:4">4</verse-number>For their<note>Or “his”</note> sons and daughters will cause your son<note>Or “sons”</note> to turn away <idiom-start/>from following me<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally from “behind/after me”</note> and <supplied>so</supplied> they will serve other gods, and <idiom-start/>the anger of Yahweh would be kindled<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and <supplied>it</supplied> would become hot the nose of Yahweh”</note> against you, and he would quickly destroy you. <verse-number id="Dt 7:5">5</verse-number>But this is what you must do to them: you shall break down their altars, and their stone pillars you shall smash, and their Asherah poles you shall hew down, and you shall burn their idols with fire. <verse-number id="Dt 7:6">6</verse-number>For you <supplied>are</supplied> a holy people for Yahweh your God; Yahweh your God has chosen you to be for him a people, a treasured possession from <supplied>among</supplied> all the peoples that <supplied>are</supplied> on the face<note>Or “surface”</note> of the earth. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 7:7">7</verse-number>“Yahweh loved you and chose you not <idiom-start/>because of your great number<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from your multitude/abundance”</note> exceeding all <supplied>other</supplied> peoples, for you <supplied>are</supplied> fewer than all of the peoples, <verse-number id="Dt 7:8">8</verse-number>but<note>Or “for”</note> <idiom-start/>because of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> the love of Yahweh <supplied>for</supplied> you and because of his keeping <supplied>of</supplied> the sworn oath that he swore to your ancestors,<note>Or “fathers”</note> Yahweh brought you <supplied>out</supplied> with a strong hand and redeemed you from the house of slavery, from the hand of Pharaoh, the king of Egypt. <verse-number id="Dt 7:9">9</verse-number><supplied>So</supplied> know that Yahweh your God, he <supplied>is</supplied> God, the trustworthy God, maintaining his<note>Hebrew “the”</note> covenant and his<note>Hebrew “the”</note> loyal love with those who love him and with those who keep his commandments to a thousand generations,<note>Hebrew “generation”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 7:10">10</verse-number>but repaying those<note>Hebrew “the one”</note> who hate him <idiom-start/>in their own person<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to their faces”</note> to destroy them;<note>Hebrew “him”; “them” in sense</note> he is not slow with those who hate him <idiom-start/>in their own person<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “to their faces”</note> he repays them.<note>Hebrew “him”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 7:11">11</verse-number>And <supplied>so</supplied> you shall keep the commandment and the rules and the regulations that I <supplied>am</supplied> commanding you <idiom-start/>today<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the day”</note> to observe them. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 7:12">12</verse-number>“<idiom-start/>And then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And it will happen”</note> because you listen <supplied>to</supplied> these regulations and you diligently keep and you do them, then Yahweh your God will maintain his<note>Hebrew “the”</note> covenant and his<note>Or “fathers”</note> loyal love that he swore to your ancestors.<note>Or “fathers”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 7:13">13</verse-number>And he will love you, and he will bless you, and he will multiply you, and he will bless the fruit of your womb and the fruit of your soil, your grain, your wine, and your olive oil, and <supplied>newborn</supplied> calves of your cattle, and the <supplied>newborn</supplied> lambs<note>Or “increase of”</note> of your flocks in the land that he swore to your ancestors<note>Or “fathers”</note> to give you. <verse-number id="Dt 7:14">14</verse-number>You shall be blessed more than all of the peoples; among you there shall not be sterility and bareness, even<note>Hebrew “and”</note> among domestic animals.<note>Hebrew “animal”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 7:15">15</verse-number>And Yahweh will turn away from you all the illness and all the harmful diseases of Egypt that you experienced; he will not lay them on you, but he will lay them on all <supplied>of</supplied> those who hate you. <verse-number id="Dt 7:16">16</verse-number>And you shall devour all of the peoples <supplied>that</supplied> Yahweh your God <supplied>is</supplied> giving to you; <idiom-start/>you shall not pity them<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “your eye shall not take pity on them”</note> and you shall not serve their gods, <supplied>which</supplied> will be a snare for you. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 7:17">17</verse-number>“If you think in your heart, ‘These nations <supplied>are</supplied> more numerous than I, so how can I dispossess them?’ <verse-number id="Dt 7:18">18</verse-number><supplied>then remember</supplied> you must not be afraid of them; you must well remember what Yahweh your God did to Pharaoh and to all <supplied>of</supplied> Egypt: <verse-number id="Dt 7:19">19</verse-number>the great trials that your eyes saw and the signs and the wonders and the <supplied>workings of</supplied> the strong hand and the outstretched arm <supplied>by</supplied> which Yahweh your God brought you out; so Yahweh your God will do to all <supplied>of</supplied> the peoples <idiom-start/>because of whom<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from them”</note> you <supplied>are</supplied> in fear <idiom-start/>before them<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “from their presence”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 7:20">20</verse-number>And, moreover, Yahweh your God will send the hornets<note>Hebrew “hornet”</note> among them until <supplied>both</supplied> the survivors and the fugitives <idiom-start/>are destroyed<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the destroying of”</note> <idiom-start/>before you<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “from your faces”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 7:21">21</verse-number>You must not <supplied>be in dread</supplied> from the presence of them, because Yahweh your God, <supplied>who is</supplied> in your midst, <supplied>is</supplied> a great and awesome God. <verse-number id="Dt 7:22">22</verse-number>And Yahweh your God will clear away these nations <idiom-start/>from before you<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from your faces”</note> little by little; you will not be able to finish them off quickly, <idiom-start/>lest<idiom-end/><note>Literally “so that not”</note> the <idiom-start/>wild animals<idiom-end/><note>Literally “animals of the field”</note> <idiom-start/>multiply<idiom-end/><note>Literally “will become numerous”</note> <idiom-start/>against you<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “on you”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 7:23">23</verse-number>But Yahweh your God will <idiom-start/>give them to you<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “give them to your face”</note> and he will throw them into great panic <idiom-start/>until they are destroyed<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “until their destroying”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 7:24">24</verse-number>And he will give their kings into your hand, and you shall blot out their names<note>Hebrew “name”</note> from under the heaven; anyone will not <supplied>be able to</supplied> stand <idiom-start/>against you<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in your faces”</note> <idiom-start/>until you destroy them<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “until your destroying them”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 7:25">25</verse-number>You shall burn the images of their gods with fire; you shall not covet <supplied>the</supplied> silver or gold <supplied>that is</supplied> on them, and <supplied>so</supplied> you take <supplied>it</supplied> for yourself, so that you are not ensnared by it, for it <supplied>is</supplied> a detestable thing to Yahweh your God. <verse-number id="Dt 7:26">26</verse-number>And you must not bring a detestable thing into your house, or you will become a thing devoted to destruction like it; you must utterly detest it, and you must utterly abhor it, for it <supplied>is</supplied> <supplied>an</supplied> object devoted to destruction. </p>
		</chapter>