<chapter id="Dt 8">
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 8">8</verse-number><verse-number id="Dt 8:1">1</verse-number> “All of the commandments<note>Or “every commandment”</note> that I <supplied>am</supplied> commanding you today you must diligently observe, so that you may live and multiply, and you may go and take possession of the land that Yahweh swore to your ancestors.<note>Or “your fathers”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 8:2">2</verse-number>And you shall remember all <supplied>of</supplied> the way that Yahweh your God led you <supplied>during</supplied> these forty years in the desert in order to humble you and to test you to know what <supplied>is</supplied> in your heart, whether you would <supplied>diligently</supplied> keep his commandments or not. <verse-number id="Dt 8:3">3</verse-number>And he humbled you and let you go hungry, and <supplied>then</supplied> he fed you with that which you did not know nor did your ancestors<note>Or “fathers”</note> know, in order to make you know that not by bread alone but by all <supplied>that</supplied> goes out<note>Or “by all <supplied>of</supplied> the going out of”</note> of the mouth of Yahweh humankind shall live. <verse-number id="Dt 8:4">4</verse-number>Your clothing did not wear out <idiom-start/>on you<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from on you”</note> and your feet did not swell <supplied>during</supplied> these forty years. <verse-number id="Dt 8:5">5</verse-number>And you should know with your heart that as a man disciplines his son, <supplied>so</supplied> Yahweh your God <supplied>is</supplied> disciplining you.<note>Or “has disciplined you”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 8:6">6</verse-number>So you must keep the commandments of Yahweh your God by walking in his ways and by fearing him. <verse-number id="Dt 8:7">7</verse-number>For Yahweh your God <supplied>is</supplied> bringing you to a good land <supplied>with</supplied> streams of water, springs and underground water, welling up in the valleys<note>Hebrew “valley”</note> and in the hills,<note>Hebrew “hill”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 8:8">8</verse-number><supplied>to</supplied> a land of wheat and barley and vines<note>Hebrew “vine”</note> and fig trees<note>Hebrew “fig tree”</note> and pomegranate trees,<note>Hebrew “pomegranate tree”</note> a land of olive trees,<note>Hebrew “olive tree”</note> olive oil and honey; <verse-number id="Dt 8:9">9</verse-number><supplied>to</supplied> a land where you may eat food in it <idiom-start/>without scarcity<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “not in scarcity”</note> you will not find anything lacking in it, a land where its stones <supplied>are</supplied> iron and from its mountains you can mine copper. <verse-number id="Dt 8:10">10</verse-number>And you will eat, and <idiom-start/>you will be satisfied<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “you will eat your fill”</note> and you will bless Yahweh your God because <supplied>of</supplied> the good land that he has given to you. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 8:11">11</verse-number>“Take care for yourself so that you not forget Yahweh your God <supplied>by</supplied> not keeping his commandments and his regulations and his statutes that I <supplied>am</supplied> commanding you <idiom-start/>today<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the day”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 8:12">12</verse-number>lest <supplied>when</supplied> you have eaten and you are satisfied and you have built good houses and you live <supplied>in them</supplied>, <verse-number id="Dt 8:13">13</verse-number>and your herds and your flocks have multiplied, and <idiom-start/>you have accumulated silver and gold<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “and silver and gold has multiplied for you”</note> and all that <idiom-start/>you have<idiom-end/><note>Literally “is for you”</note> has multiplied, <verse-number id="Dt 8:14">14</verse-number>then your heart <idiom-start/>becomes proud<idiom-end/><note>Literally “raises up”</note> and you forget Yahweh your God, <idiom-start/>the one who brought you out<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the one bringing you out”</note> from the land of Egypt, from the house of slavery, <verse-number id="Dt 8:15">15</verse-number>the one leading you in the great and terrible desert <supplied>infested</supplied> with <idiom-start/>dangerous<idiom-end/><note>Literally “burning”</note> snakes<note>Hebrew “snake”</note> and scorpions<note>Hebrew “scorpion”</note> and parched ground, where there is<note>Or “was”</note> no water, <supplied>and</supplied> the one bringing out water for you from flint rock, <verse-number id="Dt 8:16">16</verse-number>the one <idiom-start/>feeding you<idiom-end/><note>Literally “causing you to eat”</note> manna in the desert, <supplied>food</supplied> that your ancestors<note>Or “fathers”</note> did not know, in order to humble you and in order to test you <supplied>so that he could</supplied> do good to you <idiom-start/>in the future<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “in the end/later”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 8:17">17</verse-number>And you may think<note>Or “say”</note> in your heart, ‘My strength and the might of my hand <idiom-start/>acquired this wealth for<idiom-end/><note>Literally “gave this wealth to”</note> me.’ <verse-number id="Dt 8:18">18</verse-number>But you must remember Yahweh your God, for he <supplied>is</supplied> the <supplied>one</supplied> giving you strength to acquire wealth in order to confirm his covenant that he swore to your ancestors<note>Or “fathers”</note> <idiom-start/>as it is today<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “as the day the this”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 8:19">19</verse-number>And it will happen <supplied>that</supplied> if you indeed forget Yahweh your God and you go after other gods and you serve them and you bow down before them, I warn you today that you will surely perish. <verse-number id="Dt 8:20">20</verse-number>As <supplied>with</supplied> the nations that Yahweh <supplied>is</supplied> destroying <idiom-start/>before you<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from your faces”</note> so you shall perish because you would not obey the voice of Yahweh your God. </p>
		</chapter>