<chapter id="Dt 11">
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 11">11</verse-number><verse-number id="Dt 11:1">1</verse-number> “And you shall love Yahweh your God, and you shall keep his obligations and his statutes and his regulations and his commandments <idiom-start/>always<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “all <supplied>of</supplied> the days”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 11:2">2</verse-number>And you shall realize <idiom-start/>today<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the day”</note> that <supplied>it is</supplied> not <supplied>with</supplied> your children who have not known and who have not seen the discipline of Yahweh your God—his greatness, his strong hand, and his outstretched arm, <verse-number id="Dt 11:3">3</verse-number>and his signs and his deeds that he did in the midst of Egypt to Pharaoh, the king of Egypt, and to all <supplied>of</supplied> his land, <verse-number id="Dt 11:4">4</verse-number>and what he did to the army of Egypt and to their horses and to their chariots, <supplied>and</supplied> how he made the water of the <idiom-start/>Red Sea<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sea of reed”</note> flow over them, <idiom-start/>when they pursued after them<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “in/at their pursuing after them”</note> and so Yahweh has destroyed them, <idiom-start/>as is the case today<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “until the day the this”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 11:5">5</verse-number>and what he did to you in the desert until you came up to this place, <verse-number id="Dt 11:6">6</verse-number>and what he did to Dathan and to Abiram, the sons of Eliab, the son of Reuben, how the earth opened its mouth wide and swallowed them, their households and their tents, and all <supplied>of</supplied> the living creatures<note>Hebrew “creature”</note> that <supplied>were</supplied> in their possession <supplied>and that were</supplied> <idiom-start/>following along with them<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in their feet” = “living things traveling along with them”</note> in the midst of all <supplied>of</supplied> Israel. <verse-number id="Dt 11:7">7</verse-number>The fact of the matter is, <idiom-start/>your own eyes have seen<idiom-end/><note>Literally “your eyes that are seeing”</note> all <supplied>of</supplied> the great deeds<note>Hebrew “deed”</note> of Yahweh that he did. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 11:8">8</verse-number>“And you must keep all <supplied>of</supplied> the commandments<note>Hebrew “commandment”</note> that I <supplied>am</supplied> commanding you <idiom-start/>today<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the day”</note> so that you may have strength and <supplied>you may</supplied> go and <supplied>you may</supplied> take possession of that land <idiom-start/>to which you are crossing<idiom-end/><note>Literally “you are crossing there”</note> to take possession of it, <verse-number id="Dt 11:9">9</verse-number>so that <idiom-start/>you may live long<idiom-end/><note>Literally “you may make long days”</note> on the land that Yahweh swore to your ancestors,<note>Or “fathers”</note> to give <supplied>it</supplied> to them and to their offspring, a land flowing with milk and honey. <verse-number id="Dt 11:10">10</verse-number>For the fact is <supplied>that</supplied> the land <idiom-start/>that you are about to go into<idiom-end/><note>Literally “you are about to go there”</note> to take possession of it <supplied>is</supplied> not like the land of Egypt, <supplied>from</supplied> which you have <idiom-start/>come out of<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “come out from there”</note> where you sow your seed and you give water by <supplied>your</supplied> foot, <idiom-start/>as in a vegetable garden<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “as <supplied>the</supplied> garden of <supplied>the</supplied> vegetables”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 11:11">11</verse-number>But the land that you <supplied>are</supplied> about to cross into to take possession of it <supplied>is</supplied> a land of hills and valleys, <supplied>and</supplied> by the rain of the heaven it drinks water, <verse-number id="Dt 11:12">12</verse-number>a land that Yahweh your God <supplied>is</supplied> caring for it; continually the eyes of Yahweh your God <supplied>are</supplied> on it, from the beginning of the year up to the end of <supplied>the</supplied> year. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 11:13">13</verse-number>“And it will happen <supplied>that</supplied> if you listen carefully to my commandments that I <supplied>am</supplied> commanding you <idiom-start/>today<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the day”</note> to love Yahweh your God, and to serve him with all <supplied>of</supplied> your heart and with all <supplied>of</supplied> your soul,<note>Or “inner self”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 11:14">14</verse-number>then ‘I will send the rain for your land in its season, early rain and later rain, and you will gather your grain and your wine and your olive oil. <verse-number id="Dt 11:15">15</verse-number>And I will give vegetation in your field for your livestock, and <idiom-start/>you will eat your fill<idiom-end/>.’<note>Literally “you will eat and you will be satisfied”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 11:16">16</verse-number><idiom-start/>Take care<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Watch for yourself”</note> so that your heart is not easily deceived, and you turn away, and you serve other gods, and you bow down to them. <verse-number id="Dt 11:17">17</verse-number>And <supplied>then</supplied> <idiom-start/>the anger of Yahweh will be kindled against you<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the nose of Yahweh become hot against you”</note> and he will shut up the heavens,<note>Or “sky”</note> and there shall not be rain, and <supplied>so</supplied> the ground will not give its produce, and you will perish quickly from the good land that Yahweh <supplied>is</supplied> giving to you. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 11:18">18</verse-number>“And you shall put these, my words, on your heart and on your inner self,<note>Or “soul”</note> and you shall bind them as a sign on your hand and let them be as an emblem between your eyes. <verse-number id="Dt 11:19">19</verse-number>And you shall teach them to your children<note>Or “sons”</note> by talking about them when you sit in your house and when you travel on the road and when you lie down and when you get up. <verse-number id="Dt 11:20">20</verse-number>And you shall write them on the doorframes of your house and on your gates, <verse-number id="Dt 11:21">21</verse-number>so that <supplied>they</supplied> may multiply your days and the days of your children on the land that Yahweh swore to your ancestors<note>Or “fathers”</note> to give <supplied>it</supplied> to them <idiom-start/>as long as heaven endures over the earth<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “like the days of heaven above the earth”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 11:22">22</verse-number>Yes, if you diligently keep all<note>Or “every one of”</note> this commandment that I <supplied>am</supplied> commanding you <idiom-start/>to observe it<idiom-end/>, <note>Literally “to do it”</note> by loving Yahweh your God <idiom-start/>by walking in<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to walk in”</note> all his ways and by holding fast to him, <verse-number id="Dt 11:23">23</verse-number>then Yahweh will drive out all <supplied>of</supplied> these nations <idiom-start/>before you<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to the face of you”</note> and you will dispossess nations larger and more numerous than you. <verse-number id="Dt 11:24">24</verse-number>Every place on which the sole of your foot treads, it shall be yours; your boundary shall be from the desert and Lebanon from the river, the river Euphrates, on up to the western sea.<note>That is, the Mediterranean Sea</note> <verse-number id="Dt 11:25">25</verse-number>No one can take a stand <idiom-start/>against you<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “to your faces”</note> your dread and your fear Yahweh your God will put on the <idiom-start/>surface<idiom-end/><note>Literally “faces”</note> of all the land <idiom-start/>where you tread<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “which you tread in it”</note> <supplied>just</supplied> as he <idiom-start/>promised<idiom-end/><note>Literally “spoke”</note> to you. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 11:26">26</verse-number>“See, I am setting <idiom-start/>before you<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of you”</note> <idiom-start/>today<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the day”</note> a blessing and a curse: <verse-number id="Dt 11:27">27</verse-number>the blessing, if you listen to the commandments of Yahweh your God that I <supplied>am</supplied> commanding you <idiom-start/>today<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the day”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 11:28">28</verse-number>and the curse, if you <supplied>do</supplied> not listen to the commandments of Yahweh your God, but <supplied>rather</supplied> you turn from the way that I <supplied>am</supplied> commanding you <idiom-start/>today<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the day”</note> to go after other gods that you have not known. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 11:29">29</verse-number>“And it will happen <supplied>that</supplied> when Yahweh your God has brought you to <idiom-start/>the land that you are going to<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the land that you are going there”</note> to take possession of it, then<note>Hebrew “and”</note> you shall pronounce the blessing on Mount Gerizim and the curse on Mount Ebal. <verse-number id="Dt 11:30">30</verse-number>(Are they not beyond the Jordan, <idiom-start/>toward the west<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “after the way of the descent of the sun”</note> in the land of the Canaanites living in the Jordan Valley,<note>Hebrew “in the Arabah”</note> opposite Gilgal beside the terebinth<note>Or “oaks”</note> of Moreh?) <verse-number id="Dt 11:31">31</verse-number>For you are <supplied>now</supplied> about to cross the Jordan to go to take possession of the land that Yahweh, your God, <supplied>is</supplied> giving to you, and you will take possession of it and live in it, <verse-number id="Dt 11:32">32</verse-number>and you must diligently <idiom-start/>observe<idiom-end/><note>Literally “observe to do”</note> all the rules and the regulations that I <supplied>am</supplied> setting <idiom-start/>before you<idiom-end/><note>Literally “before your face”</note> <idiom-start/>today<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “the day”</note> </p>
		</chapter>