<chapter id="Dt 12">
			<pericope>Detailed Stipulations: Purity and Unity</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 12:1">1</verse-number>“These <supplied>are</supplied> the rules and the regulations <idiom-start/>that you must diligently observe<idiom-end/><note>Literally “that you must observe to do”</note> in the land that Yahweh, <supplied>the</supplied> God of your ancestors,<note>Or “fathers”</note> has given to you to take possession of it, <supplied>during</supplied> all the days that you <supplied>are</supplied> living on the land. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 12:2">2</verse-number>You must completely demolish all <supplied>of</supplied> the places there where <supplied>they</supplied> served their gods, <supplied>that is</supplied>, the nations whom you <supplied>are</supplied> about to dispossess, on the high mountains, and on the hills and under each leafy green tree.<note>Or “spreading tree”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 12:3">3</verse-number>And you shall break down their altars, and you shall smash their stone pillars, and their Asherah poles you must burn with fire, and the images of their gods you shall hew down, and you shall blot out their names from that place. <verse-number id="Dt 12:4">4</verse-number>You shall not worship Yahweh your God like this. <verse-number id="Dt 12:5">5</verse-number><idiom-start/>But only<idiom-end/><note>Literally “But if”</note> to the place that Yahweh your God will choose from all <supplied>of</supplied> your tribes to place his name there as his dwelling shall you seek, and there you shall go. <verse-number id="Dt 12:6">6</verse-number>And you shall bring there your burnt offerings and your sacrifices and your tithes and <idiom-start/>your donations<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the contributions of your hand”</note> and your votive gifts and your freewill offerings and the firstling of your herd and your flock. <verse-number id="Dt 12:7">7</verse-number>And you shall eat there <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “before the faces of”</note> Yahweh your God, and you shall rejoice <idiom-start/>in all your endeavors<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “in all <supplied>of</supplied> the sending of your hand”</note> you and your family <supplied>in</supplied> which Yahweh your God has blessed you. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 12:8">8</verse-number>“You must not do <supplied>just</supplied> as we <supplied>are</supplied> doing here <idiom-start/>today<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the day”</note> <idiom-start/>each according to all that is right in his eyes<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “each <supplied>man</supplied> all of the right in his eyes”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 12:9">9</verse-number>For you have not come up to now to the resting place and to the inheritance that Yahweh your God <supplied>is</supplied> giving to you. <verse-number id="Dt 12:10">10</verse-number>But you will cross the Jordan, and you will settle in the land that Yahweh your God <supplied>is</supplied> giving you as an inheritance, and he will give rest to you from all your enemies from all around, and you will live securely, <verse-number id="Dt 12:11">11</verse-number><idiom-start/>and then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and it will happen”</note> <supplied>at</supplied> the place that Yahweh your God will choose, to let his name dwell there, there you shall bring all <supplied>the things</supplied> I <supplied>am</supplied> commanding you, your burnt offerings and your sacrifices, your tithes and <idiom-start/>your donations<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the contribution of your hand”</note> and all <supplied>of</supplied> the choice <supplied>things</supplied>, your votive gifts that you vow to Yahweh. <verse-number id="Dt 12:12">12</verse-number>And you shall rejoice <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the face of”</note> Yahweh your God, you and your sons and your daughters and your slaves and your slave women and the Levite who <supplied>is</supplied> in your <idiom-start/>towns<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “gates”</note> because there is not for him a plot of ground and an inheritance with you. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 12:13">13</verse-number>“Take care for yourself so that you do not offer your burnt offerings at <supplied>just</supplied> any place that you happen to see, <verse-number id="Dt 12:14">14</verse-number><idiom-start/>but only<idiom-end/><note>Literally “but <supplied>only</supplied> if”</note> at the place that Yahweh will choose among one of your tribes; there you shall offer your burnt offerings, and there you shall do all <supplied>the things</supplied> that I <supplied>am</supplied> commanding you. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 12:15">15</verse-number>“But <idiom-start/>whenever you desire<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in all the wanting of your soul/inner self”</note> you may slaughter, and you may eat meat according to the blessing of Yahweh your God that he has given to you in all <supplied>of</supplied> your <idiom-start/>towns<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “gates”</note> the unclean and the clean may eat it <supplied>just</supplied> as <supplied>they would</supplied> the gazelle and as the deer. <verse-number id="Dt 12:16">16</verse-number>Only the blood you must not eat, <supplied>but</supplied> on the ground you must pour it like water. <verse-number id="Dt 12:17">17</verse-number>You are not allowed to eat in your <idiom-start/>towns<idiom-end/><note>Literally “gates”</note> the tithe of your grain and your wine and your olive oil and the firstborn of your herd and your flock and all <supplied>of</supplied> your votive gifts that you vowed and your freewill offering and <idiom-start/>your donations<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the contribution of your hand”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 12:18">18</verse-number>But only <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “before the face of”</note> Yahweh your God you shall eat it, at the place that Yahweh your God will choose,<note>Hebrew “choose it”</note> you and your son and your daughter and your slave and your slave woman and the Levite who <supplied>is</supplied> in your <idiom-start/>towns<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “gate”</note> and you must rejoice <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “before the face of”</note> your God <idiom-start/>in all your undertakings<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “in all <supplied>of</supplied> the sending of your hand”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 12:19">19</verse-number><idiom-start/>Take care<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Watch for yourself”</note> so that you do not neglect the Levite all <supplied>of</supplied> your days on your land. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 12:20">20</verse-number>“When Yahweh your God enlarges your territory <supplied>just</supplied> as he has <idiom-start/>promised<idiom-end/><note>Literally “spoken”</note> to you, and you say ‘I want to eat <supplied>some</supplied> meat,’ <idiom-start/>because you want it<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “because your soul/inner self desires it”</note> <idiom-start/>whenever you desire<idiom-end/><note>Literally “at/in all the wanting of your soul/inner self”</note> you may eat meat. <verse-number id="Dt 12:21">21</verse-number>If the place that<note>Or “where”</note> Yahweh your God will choose to put his name there is <supplied>too</supplied> far from you, and you slaughter any of your herd and any of your flock that Yahweh has given to you <supplied>just</supplied> as I have commanded you, then you may eat whenever you desire in your <idiom-start/>towns<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “gates”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 12:22">22</verse-number>Surely <supplied>just</supplied> as the gazelle and the deer is eaten, so <supplied>both</supplied> the unclean and the clean together may eat it. <verse-number id="Dt 12:23">23</verse-number>Only, be sure not to eat the blood, because the blood is the life, and you shall not eat the life with the meat. <verse-number id="Dt 12:24">24</verse-number>You shall not eat it, <supplied>but</supplied> on the ground you shall pour it out like water. <verse-number id="Dt 12:25">25</verse-number>You shall not eat it, so that <idiom-start/>it will go well<idiom-end/><note>Literally “it/he is good”</note> for you <supplied>and</supplied> your children after you, because <supplied>then</supplied> you will <supplied>be</supplied> doing what is<note>Hebrew “the”</note> right in the eyes of Yahweh. <verse-number id="Dt 12:26">26</verse-number>Only your holy objects <idiom-start/>that are yours<idiom-end/><note>Literally “that are for you”</note> and your votive gifts you must carry and you must bring to the place that Yahweh will choose. <verse-number id="Dt 12:27">27</verse-number>And you shall offer your burnt offerings, the flesh and the blood on the altar of Yahweh your God, and the blood of your sacrifices you shall pour out on the altar of Yahweh your God, but the meat you may eat. <verse-number id="Dt 12:28">28</verse-number><idiom-start/>Be careful to obey<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Watch carefully and listen”</note> all these things that I <supplied>am</supplied> commanding you, so that <idiom-start/>it will go well<idiom-end/><note>Literally “he/it is good”</note> for you and for your children after you <idiom-start/>forever<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “until ever”</note> because then you will <supplied>be</supplied> doing what is<note>Hebrew “the”</note> good and right<note>Hebrew “the right”</note> in the eyes of Yahweh your God. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 12:29">29</verse-number>“When Yahweh your God has cut off the nations whom you <supplied>are</supplied> <idiom-start/>about to go to<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “about to go to there”</note> to dispossess them <idiom-start/>before you<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from the face of you”</note> and you have dispossessed them, and you live in their land, <verse-number id="Dt 12:30">30</verse-number><idiom-start/>take care<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Watch for yourself”</note> so that you are not ensnared <idiom-start/>into imitating them<idiom-end/><note>Literally “after them”</note> after their being destroyed from <idiom-start/>before you<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from the face of you”</note> and so that you not enquire concerning their gods, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> ‘How did these nations serve their gods, and <supplied>thus</supplied> <idiom-start/>I myself<idiom-end/><note>Emphatic use of the pronoun</note> want to do also.’ <verse-number id="Dt 12:31">31</verse-number>You must not do so toward Yahweh your God, because of every detestable thing they have done for their gods Yahweh hates, for even their sons and their daughters they would burn in the fire to their gods. <verse-number id="Dt 12:32">32</verse-number><note><cite title="BibleLEB2: Dt 12:32–13:18">Deuteronomy 12:32–13:18 </cite>in the English Bible is 13:1–19 in the Hebrew Bible</note> All of the things<note>Hebrew “thing”</note> that I <supplied>am</supplied> commanding you, <idiom-start/>you must diligently observe<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “you must observe to do <supplied>it</supplied>”</note> you shall not add to it, and you shall not take away from it.” </p>
		</chapter>