<chapter id="Dt 13">
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 13">13</verse-number><verse-number id="Dt 13:1">1</verse-number> “If a prophet stands up in your midst or a dreamer of dreams<note>Hebrew “dream”</note> and he gives to you a sign or wonder, <verse-number id="Dt 13:2">2</verse-number>and the sign or<note>Hebrew “and”</note> the wonder comes <supplied>about</supplied> that he spoke<note>Or “promised/declared”</note> to you, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> ‘Let us go after other gods (those whom you have not known), and let us serve them,’ <verse-number id="Dt 13:3">3</verse-number>you must not listen to the words of that prophet or to that dreamer, for Yahweh your God <idiom-start/>is testing you to know whether you love<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a testing of Yahweh your God concerning you <supplied>in order</supplied> to know whether there is you loving”</note> Yahweh your God with all of your heart and with all <supplied>of</supplied> your inner self.<note>Or “soul”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 13:4">4</verse-number>You shall go after Yahweh your God, and him you shall revere, and his commandment you shall keep, and to his voice you shall listen, and him you shall serve, and to him you shall hold fast. <verse-number id="Dt 13:5">5</verse-number>But that prophet or the dreamer of that dream shall be executed, for he spoke falsely about Yahweh your God, the <supplied>one</supplied> bringing you out from the land of Egypt and the <supplied>one</supplied> redeeming you from the house of slavery, in order to seduce you from the way that Yahweh your God commanded you to go in it; so <supplied>in this way</supplied> you shall purge the evil from your midst. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 13:6">6</verse-number>“If your brother, the son of your mother or your son or your daughter <idiom-start/>or your wife whom you embrace<idiom-end/><note>Literally “or the wife of your embrace”</note> or <idiom-start/>your intimate friend<idiom-end/><note>Literally “your friend who is like your soul/inner self”</note> in secrecy <idiom-start/>says<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> ‘Let us go and let us serve other gods!’ <supplied>gods</supplied> that you and your ancestors<note>Or “fathers”</note> have not known, <verse-number id="Dt 13:7">7</verse-number>from <supplied>among</supplied> the gods of the people who are around you, <idiom-start/>those near you or those far from you<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the near ones to you or the distant ones from you”</note> from <supplied>one</supplied> end of the earth and up to the <supplied>other</supplied> end of the earth, <verse-number id="Dt 13:8">8</verse-number>you must not give in to him, and you shall not listen to him, and your eye shall not take pity on him, and you shall not have compassion, and you shall not cover <supplied>up</supplied><note>Or “conceal” him</note> for him. <verse-number id="Dt 13:9">9</verse-number>But you shall certainly kill him; your hand shall be first against him to kill him and next the hand of all <supplied>of</supplied> the people. <verse-number id="Dt 13:10">10</verse-number>And you shall stone him with stones and let him die, for he tried to seduce you from Yahweh your God, the <supplied>one</supplied> bringing you from <supplied>the</supplied> land of Egypt, from the house of slavery. <verse-number id="Dt 13:11">11</verse-number>And all <supplied>of</supplied> Israel shall hear, and they shall fear, and <idiom-start/>they shall not continue to act<idiom-end/><note>Literally “they shall not add to do”</note> according to this evil thing in your midst. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 13:12">12</verse-number>“If you hear in one of your towns which Yahweh your God <supplied>is</supplied> giving to you to live in, <supplied>someone</supplied> <idiom-start/>saying that<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 13:13">13</verse-number><idiom-start/>worthless men<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons of Belial”</note> have gone out from your midst and have seduced the inhabitants of their town, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> ‘Let us go and serve other gods!’ whom you have not known, <verse-number id="Dt 13:14">14</verse-number>then you shall inquire and examine and interrogate thoroughly, and, look! <supplied>It is</supplied> true; the thing has actually been done, this detestable thing in your midst, <verse-number id="Dt 13:15">15</verse-number><supplied>then</supplied> you shall certainly strike down the inhabitants of that town with the <idiom-start/>edge<idiom-end/><note>Literally “mouth”</note> of <supplied>the</supplied> sword; you shall destroy it and everything in it, its domestic animals with <supplied>the</supplied> <idiom-start/>edge<idiom-end/><note>Literally “mouth”</note> of <supplied>the</supplied> sword. <verse-number id="Dt 13:16">16</verse-number>And <supplied>then</supplied> you shall gather all of its booty into the middle of its public square, and you shall burn the town and all <supplied>of</supplied> its war-booty totally for Yahweh your God, and it shall be <idiom-start/>a pile of rubble forever<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “a tell/ruin forever”</note> it shall not be built again. <verse-number id="Dt 13:17">17</verse-number>And let not something cling to your hand from the things devoted to destruction, so that Yahweh may turn back <idiom-start/>from his burning anger<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from the burning of his nose”</note> and he may show compassion to you and he may <supplied>continue</supplied> to show compassion and <supplied>so</supplied> multiply you <idiom-start/>just as he swore<idiom-end/><note>Literally “as that he swore”</note> to your ancestors,<note>Or “fathers”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 13:18">18</verse-number>if you listen to the voice of Yahweh your God, to keep all <supplied>of</supplied> his commandments that I <supplied>am</supplied> commanding <supplied>to</supplied> you <idiom-start/>today<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the day”</note> <supplied>so as</supplied> to do the right <supplied>thing</supplied> in the eyes of Yahweh your God.” </p>
		</chapter>