<chapter id="Dt 14">
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 14">14</verse-number><verse-number id="Dt 14:1">1</verse-number> “You <supplied>are</supplied> children<note>Or “sons”</note> of Yahweh your God; <supplied>therefore</supplied> you must not gash<note>Or “cut”</note> yourself, and <idiom-start/>you must not make your forehead bald<idiom-end/><note>Literally “you shall not make/place baldness between your eyes”</note> for <supplied>the</supplied> dead. <verse-number id="Dt 14:2">2</verse-number>For you <supplied>are</supplied> a people holy to Yahweh your God, and you Yahweh has chosen to be a treasured possession from <supplied>among</supplied> all <supplied>of</supplied> the peoples that are on the surface<note>Or “face”</note> of the earth. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 14:3">3</verse-number>You shall not eat any detestable thing. <verse-number id="Dt 14:4">4</verse-number>These are the animals you may eat: ox, <idiom-start/>sheep, goats<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “small livestock of the sheep and a small livestock of the goats”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 14:5">5</verse-number>deer, gazelle, roebuck, wild goat, ibex, antelope, and mountain sheep. <verse-number id="Dt 14:6">6</verse-number>And any animal having a split hoof<note>Or “divides the hoof”</note> and <supplied>so</supplied> <idiom-start/>a dividing of the hoof into two parts<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a dividing cleft <supplied>creating</supplied> two hoofs”</note> <idiom-start/>and that chews the cud<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and that brings up the cud”</note> among the animals<note>Hebrew “animal”</note>—that <supplied>animal</supplied> you may eat. <verse-number id="Dt 14:7">7</verse-number>Only these you may not eat from <idiom-start/>those chewing the cud<idiom-end/><note>Literally “bringing up the cud”</note> and from <idiom-start/>those having a division of the hoof<idiom-end/>:<note>Literally “those having a division of the hoof divided”</note> the camel and the hare and the coney, because <idiom-start/>they chew the cud<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “they bringing up of the cud”</note> but they <supplied>do</supplied> not divide the hoof; they are <supplied>therefore</supplied> unclean for you. <verse-number id="Dt 14:8">8</verse-number>And <supplied>also</supplied> the pig <idiom-start/>because it has a division of the hoof<idiom-end/><note>Literally “because a division of the hoof”</note> <idiom-start/>but does not chew the cud<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “but not a <supplied>chewing</supplied> cud”</note> it <supplied>is</supplied> unclean for you; from their meat you shall not eat, and you shall not touch their <idiom-start/>carcasses<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “dead body”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 14:9">9</verse-number>“This <supplied>is what</supplied> you shall eat from all that <supplied>is</supplied> in the water: <idiom-start/>everything<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all <supplied>of</supplied> that”</note> <idiom-start/>that has fins and scales<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for it <supplied>is</supplied> fins and scales,” showing possession of these features</note> you may eat. <verse-number id="Dt 14:10">10</verse-number>But <idiom-start/>anything that does not have<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all <supplied>of</supplied> that there is not for it,” showing lack of possession of these features</note> fins and scales, you may not eat, <supplied>for</supplied> it <supplied>is</supplied> unclean for you. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 14:11">11</verse-number>“All <supplied>of</supplied> <supplied>the</supplied> birds <supplied>that</supplied> <supplied>are</supplied> clean you may eat. <verse-number id="Dt 14:12">12</verse-number>Now these <supplied>are</supplied> the ones you shall not eat <idiom-start/>any of them<idiom-end/>:<note>Literally “from them”</note> the eagle and the vulture and the short-toed eagle,<note>This list of birds is difficult to translate since the terms are not definitely known: e.g., some translations render the last bird as a “buzzard” (NASV); other translations give different names for all three: griffon vulture, black vulture, bearded vulture (NEB)</note> <verse-number id="Dt 14:13">13</verse-number>and the red kite<note>Various options are available: large bird, kite, red kite, glede, buzzard</note> and the black kite or <idiom-start/>any kind of falcon<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “or the falcon according to its kind”; other options for falcon: bird, falcon, kite (others as carrion-bird), vulture, crow or raven, buzzard</note> <verse-number id="Dt 14:14">14</verse-number>and any <supplied>kind</supplied> of crow<note>Or others translate as “raven”</note> according to its kind, <verse-number id="Dt 14:15">15</verse-number>and the <idiom-start/>ostrich<idiom-end/><note>Literally “daughter of the ostrich”; others “desert owl”</note> and the short-eared owl and the seagull<note>Or “long-eared owl”</note> and the hawk according to its kind, <verse-number id="Dt 14:16">16</verse-number>the little owl and the great owl and the barn owl,<note>Or “white owl”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 14:17">17</verse-number>and the desert owl<note>Or “large bird” or “horned-owl”</note> and the carrion vulture<note>Or “large bird”</note> and the cormorant,<note>Or “large bird,” or “fisher-owl”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 14:18">18</verse-number>and the stork and the heron according to its kind and the hoopoe and the bat. <verse-number id="Dt 14:19">19</verse-number>And <supplied>also</supplied> all <supplied>of</supplied> <idiom-start/>the winged insects<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “the swarmer<supplied>s</supplied> of the flyer<supplied>s</supplied>” or “all the swarms <supplied>of things</supplied> that fly”</note> they <supplied>are</supplied> unclean for you; you shall not eat <supplied>them</supplied>. <verse-number id="Dt 14:20">20</verse-number>You may eat any clean bird. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 14:21">21</verse-number>“You shall not eat any carcass;<note>Or “corpse”</note> you may give it to the alien who <supplied>is</supplied> in your <idiom-start/>towns<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “gates”</note> and he may eat it, or you may sell <supplied>it</supplied> to a foreigner, for you <supplied>are</supplied> a holy people for Yahweh your God; you may not boil a kid in its mother’s milk. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 14:22">22</verse-number>“Certainly you must give a tithe <supplied>of</supplied> all the yield of your seed, <idiom-start/>which comes forth from your field year after year<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the going forth of the field year <supplied>by</supplied> year”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 14:23">23</verse-number>And you shall eat <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “before the faces of”</note> Yahweh your God in the place that he will choose to make to dwell his name there the tithe of your grain, your wine and your olive oil and the firstling of your herd and your flock, so that you may learn to revere Yahweh your God <idiom-start/>always<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “all of the days”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 14:24">24</verse-number>But if <idiom-start/>the distance is too great for you<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “<supplied>it</supplied> is great from you the journey that”</note> <supplied>so</supplied> that you are not able to transport<note>Or “carry”</note> it, because the place that Yahweh your God will choose to set his name there, it is <supplied>too</supplied> far from you, when Yahweh your God will bless you, <verse-number id="Dt 14:25">25</verse-number>then <supplied>in that case</supplied> <idiom-start/>you may exchange for money<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “you may give it <supplied>in</supplied> for the money/silver”</note> and you shall take<note>Or “bind”</note> the money to your hand and go to the place that Yahweh your God will choose. <verse-number id="Dt 14:26">26</verse-number>You may spend the money for anything <idiom-start/>that you desire<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “that your soul/inner self desires”</note> for oxen or for sheep or for wine or for strong drink or for anything <idiom-start/>that you desire<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “that your soul/inner self desires”</note> and you shall eat <supplied>it</supplied> there <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of”</note> Yahweh your God, and you shall rejoice, you and your household. <verse-number id="Dt 14:27">27</verse-number>And <supplied>as to</supplied> the Levite who <supplied>is</supplied> in your <idiom-start/>towns<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “gates”</note> you shall not neglect him, because there is not a plot of ground for him and an inheritance <supplied>along</supplied> with you. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 14:28">28</verse-number>“At the end of three years you shall bring out all <supplied>of</supplied> the tithe of your yield for that year, and you shall store <supplied>it</supplied> in your <idiom-start/>towns<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “gates”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 14:29">29</verse-number>And <supplied>so</supplied> the Levite may come, because there is no plot of ground for him or an inheritance with you, and the alien <supplied>also may come</supplied> and the orphan and the widow that <supplied>are</supplied> in your <idiom-start/>towns<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “gates”</note> and <idiom-start/>they may eat their fill<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “they may eat and they may be satisfied”</note> so that Yahweh your God may bless you in all <supplied>of</supplied> the work of your hand that you undertake.” </p>
		</chapter>