<chapter id="Dt 15">
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 15">15</verse-number><verse-number id="Dt 15:1">1</verse-number> “At the end of seven years you shall grant <supplied>a</supplied> remission of debt. <verse-number id="Dt 15:2">2</verse-number>And this <supplied>is</supplied> the manner of the remission of debt: every <idiom-start/>creditor<idiom-end/><note>Literally “owner of the loan of his hand”</note> shall remit his claim that he holds against his neighbor, and he shall not exact payment <supplied>from</supplied> his brother because there<note>Hebrew “it”</note> <supplied>a</supplied> remission of debt has been proclaimed unto<note>Hebrew “for”</note> Yahweh. <verse-number id="Dt 15:3">3</verse-number><supplied>With respect to</supplied> the foreigner you may exact payment, but <idiom-start/>you must remit<idiom-end/><note>Literally “your hand shall remit”</note> what shall be <supplied>owed</supplied> to you <supplied>with respect to</supplied> your brother. <verse-number id="Dt 15:4">4</verse-number>Nevertheless, there<note>Hebrew “it”</note> shall not be among you a poor <supplied>person</supplied>, because Yahweh will certainly bless you in the land that Yahweh your God <supplied>is</supplied> giving to you <supplied>as</supplied> an inheritance, to take possession of it. <verse-number id="Dt 15:5">5</verse-number>If only you listen well to the voice of Yahweh your God <idiom-start/>by observing diligently<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to observe <supplied>so as</supplied> to do”</note> all of these commandments<note>Hebrew “commandment”</note> that I <supplied>am</supplied> commanding you <idiom-start/>today<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the day”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 15:6">6</verse-number>When Yahweh your God has blessed you, <supplied>just</supplied> as he <idiom-start/>promised<idiom-end/><note>Literally “spoke”</note> to you, then you will lend to many nations, but you will not borrow <supplied>from them</supplied>, and you will rule over many nations, but they will not rule over you. <verse-number id="Dt 15:7">7</verse-number>If <supplied>there</supplied> is a poor <supplied>person</supplied> among you from <supplied>among</supplied> one of your brothers in one of your <idiom-start/>towns<idiom-end/><note>Literally “gates”</note> that Yahweh your God <supplied>is</supplied> giving to you, you shall not harden your heart, and you shall not shut your hand toward <idiom-start/>your brother who is poor<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “from among your brothers, the poor one”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 15:8">8</verse-number>But you shall certainly open your hand for him, and <idiom-start/>you shall willingly lend<idiom-end/><note>Literally “lending you shall lend”</note> <supplied>to</supplied> him enough to meet his need, <idiom-start/>whatever it is<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “whatever is lacking for him”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 15:9">9</verse-number><idiom-start/>Take care<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Watch for yourself”</note> so that there<note>Hebrew “it”</note> will not be <idiom-start/>a thought of wickedness<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a thing in your heart wickedness”</note> in your heart, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> ‘The seventh year, the year of the remission of debt is near,’ <idiom-start/>and you view your needy neighbor with hostility<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “is bad your eye against your brother who is needy”</note> and <supplied>so</supplied> you <supplied>do</supplied> not give to him, and he might cry <supplied>out</supplied> against you to Yahweh, and <idiom-start/>you would incur guilt against yourself<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “it will be against you a sin”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 15:10">10</verse-number>By all means you must give to him, and <idiom-start/>you must not be discontented<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and not shall be bad/evil your heart at/when”</note> at your giving to him, because on account of this <supplied>very</supplied> thing, Yahweh your God will bless you in all your work and <idiom-start/>in all that you undertake<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “in all <supplied>of</supplied> the sending/putting forth of your hand”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 15:11">11</verse-number>For the poor<note>Or “the needy person”</note> will not cease to be <idiom-start/>among you<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from the midst of “</note> <supplied>in</supplied> the land; therefore I <supplied>am</supplied> commanding you, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> ‘You shall willingly open your hand to your brother, to your needy and to your poor <supplied>that are</supplied> in your land.’ </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 15:12">12</verse-number>If your relative<note>Or “brother”</note> who is a Hebrew man or a Hebrew woman is sold to you, and <supplied>he or she</supplied> has served you six years, then in the seventh year you shall send that person <supplied>out</supplied> <idiom-start/>free<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “free from with you”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 15:13">13</verse-number>And when you send him <supplied>out</supplied> free from you, you shall not send him <supplied>away</supplied> empty-handed. <verse-number id="Dt 15:14">14</verse-number>You shall generously supply him from <supplied>among</supplied> your flocks and from your threshing floor and from your press; <supplied>according to</supplied> that <supplied>with which</supplied> Yahweh your God has blessed you, you shall give to him. <verse-number id="Dt 15:15">15</verse-number>And remember that you were a slave in the land of Egypt, and Yahweh your God redeemed you; therefore I <supplied>am</supplied> commanding you thus <idiom-start/>today<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the day”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 15:16">16</verse-number>And then <supplied>if</supplied> it will happen <supplied>that</supplied> he says to you, ‘<idiom-start/>I do not want to go out<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I will not go out”</note> from you,’ because he loves you and your family, because it is good for him <supplied>to be</supplied> with you; <verse-number id="Dt 15:17">17</verse-number>then you shall take an awl, and you shall thrust <supplied>it</supplied> through his earlobe and into the door, and he shall be to you <idiom-start/>a slave forever<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “a slave of eternity”</note> and you shall also do likewise for your slave woman. <verse-number id="Dt 15:18">18</verse-number>It shall not be hard in your eyes <idiom-start/>when you send him forth free<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “in/at you to send him forth free from <supplied>being</supplied> with you”</note> because for six years he has served you <supplied>worth</supplied> twice the wage of a hired worker; and Yahweh your God will bless you <idiom-start/>in whatever you will do<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “in all <supplied>of</supplied> that you will do”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 15:19">19</verse-number>“Every firstling male that is born of your herd and of your flock you shall consecrate to Yahweh your God; you shall not do work with the firstling of your ox, and you shall not shear the firstling of your flock. <verse-number id="Dt 15:20">20</verse-number><supplied>Rather</supplied> <idiom-start/>before Yahweh<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the face of Yahweh”</note> your God you shall eat it year by year at the place Yahweh will choose, you and your household. <verse-number id="Dt 15:21">21</verse-number>But if there is a physical defect in it, <supplied>such as</supplied> lameness or blindness, any serious defect, you shall not sacrifice it to Yahweh your God. <verse-number id="Dt 15:22">22</verse-number>In your <idiom-start/>towns<idiom-end/><note>Literally “gates”</note> you shall eat it, the unclean and the clean together <supplied>may eat it</supplied>, <supplied>just</supplied> as <supplied>they eat</supplied> the gazelle and as <supplied>they eat</supplied> the deer. <verse-number id="Dt 15:23">23</verse-number>But you shall not eat its blood; you shall pour it on the ground like water.” </p>
		</chapter>