<chapter id="Dt 16">
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 16">16</verse-number><verse-number id="Dt 16:1">1</verse-number> “Observe the month of Abib, and you shall keep <supplied>the</supplied> Passover to Yahweh your God, for in the month of Abib Yahweh your God brought you out from Egypt <supplied>by</supplied> night. <verse-number id="Dt 16:2">2</verse-number>And you shall offer the Passover sacrifice to Yahweh your God <supplied>from among</supplied> <supplied>your</supplied> flock and herd at the place that Yahweh will choose, to let his name dwell there. <verse-number id="Dt 16:3">3</verse-number>You shall not eat <idiom-start/>with it<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in addition to” or “upon it”</note> anything leavened; seven days you shall eat <idiom-start/>with it<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in addition to” or “upon it”</note> unleavened bread of affliction, because in haste you went out from the land of Egypt, so that you will remember the day of your going out from the land of Egypt all the days of your life. <verse-number id="Dt 16:4">4</verse-number>And leaven shall not be seen with<note>Or “for”</note> you in any of your territory<note>Or “all <supplied>of</supplied>” your territory</note> for seven days, and none of the meat that you will slaughter on the evening on the first day shall remain overnight until morning. <verse-number id="Dt 16:5">5</verse-number>You are not allowed to offer the Passover sacrifice in one of your <idiom-start/>towns<idiom-end/><note>Literally “gates”</note> that Yahweh your God is giving to you, <verse-number id="Dt 16:6">6</verse-number>but only at the place that Yahweh your God will choose, to let his name dwell there; you shall offer the Passover sacrifice <idiom-start/>in the evening at sunset<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “in the evening as the sun goes/sets”</note> <supplied>at the</supplied> designated time<note>The Hebrew word here indicates the specific time that God had chosen to bring Israel out of Egypt</note> of your going out from Egypt. <verse-number id="Dt 16:7">7</verse-number>And you shall cook, and you shall eat <supplied>it</supplied> at the place that Yahweh your God will choose; and you may turn in the morning and go to your tents. <verse-number id="Dt 16:8">8</verse-number>Six days you shall eat unleavened bread, and on the seventh day <supplied>there shall be</supplied> an assembly for Yahweh your God; you shall not do work. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 16:9">9</verse-number>“You shall count <supplied>off</supplied> seven weeks for you; <idiom-start/>from the time you begin to harvest the standing grain<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from the beginning of <supplied>the</supplied> sickle against the standing grain”</note> you shall begin to count seven weeks. <verse-number id="Dt 16:10">10</verse-number>And <supplied>then</supplied> you shall celebrate the Feast of Weeks for Yahweh your God with the measure of the freewill offering of your hand that you shall give <supplied>just</supplied> as Yahweh your God has blessed you. <verse-number id="Dt 16:11">11</verse-number>And you shall rejoice before Yahweh your God, you and your son and your daughter and your slave and your slave woman and the Levite that <supplied>is</supplied> in your <idiom-start/>towns<idiom-end/><note>Literally “gates”</note> and the alien and the orphan and the widow who are in your midst in the place that Yahweh your God will choose to let his name dwell there. <verse-number id="Dt 16:12">12</verse-number>And you shall remember that you were a slave in Egypt, and <supplied>so</supplied> <idiom-start/>you shall diligently observe<idiom-end/><note>Literally “you shall observe and do”</note> these rules. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 16:13">13</verse-number>“You shall celebrate the Feast of Booths for yourselves<note>Hebrew “for you”</note> seven days <idiom-start/>at the gathering in of the produce<idiom-end/><note>Literally “at your gathering <supplied>of the produce</supplied>”</note> from your threshing floor and from your press; <verse-number id="Dt 16:14">14</verse-number>and you shall rejoice at your feast, you and your son and your daughter and your slave and your slave woman and the Levite and the orphan and the widow that <supplied>are</supplied> in your <idiom-start/>towns<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “gates”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 16:15">15</verse-number>Seven days you shall celebrate <supplied>your</supplied> feast to Yahweh your God at the place Yahweh will choose, for Yahweh your God shall bless you in all of your produce<note>Or “increase”</note> and in all <supplied>of</supplied> the work of your hand, and you shall surely <supplied>be</supplied> rejoicing.<note>Or “joyful”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 16:16">16</verse-number>Three times in the year all <supplied>of</supplied> your males shall appear <idiom-start/>before <idiom-end/><note>Literally “with the face of”</note> Yahweh your God at the place that he will choose, at the Feast of Unleavened Bread and at the Feast of Weeks and at the Feast of Booths, and they shall not appear <idiom-start/>before Yahweh<idiom-end/><note>Literally “with the face of Yahweh”</note> empty-handed. <verse-number id="Dt 16:17">17</verse-number>Each <supplied>person</supplied> <idiom-start/>shall give as he is able<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “according to the gift of his hand”</note> <supplied>that is</supplied>, according to the blessing of Yahweh your God that he has given to you. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 16:18">18</verse-number>“You shall appoint judges and officials for you in all your <idiom-start/>towns<idiom-end/><note>Literally “gates”</note> that Yahweh your God <supplied>is</supplied> giving to you throughout your tribes, and you shall render <supplied>for</supplied> the people <idiom-start/>righteous judgments<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “a judgment <supplied>based on</supplied> righteousness”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 16:19">19</verse-number>You shall not subvert<note>Or “distort/pervert”</note> justice; you shall not <idiom-start/>show partiality<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “recognize faces”</note> and you shall not take a bribe, for the bribe makes blind <supplied>the</supplied> eyes of <supplied>the</supplied> wise and misrepresents <supplied>the</supplied> words of <supplied>the</supplied> righteous. <verse-number id="Dt 16:20">20</verse-number><idiom-start/>Justice, only justice<idiom-end/><note>Literally “justice justice”</note> you shall pursue, so that you may live, and you shall take possession of the land that Yahweh your God <supplied>is</supplied> giving to you. <verse-number id="Dt 16:21">21</verse-number>You shall not plant for yourselves<note>Hebrew “for/to you” but with collective meaning</note> <idiom-start/>an Asherah pole<idiom-end/><note>Literally “an Asherah of any wood/tree”</note> beside the altar of Yahweh your God that you make for yourselves.<note>Hebrew “for/to you” but with collective meaning</note> <verse-number id="Dt 16:22">22</verse-number>And you shall not set up for yourselves a stone pillar, <supplied>a thing</supplied> that Yahweh your God hates. </p>
		</chapter>