<chapter id="Dt 17">
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 17">17</verse-number><verse-number id="Dt 17:1">1</verse-number> “You shall not sacrifice to Yahweh your God an ox or sheep <idiom-start/>that has a physical defect<idiom-end/><note>Literally “that is on it a physical defect”</note> <idiom-start/>of anything seriously wrong<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “of any thing bad/evil”</note> for that <supplied>is</supplied> a detestable thing to Yahweh your God. <verse-number id="Dt 17:2">2</verse-number>If <supplied>there</supplied> is found in one of your <idiom-start/>towns<idiom-end/><note>Literally “gates”</note> that Yahweh your God <supplied>is</supplied> giving to you a man or a woman that does evil in the eyes of Yahweh your God to transgress his covenant <verse-number id="Dt 17:3">3</verse-number>and by going and serving other gods and <supplied>so</supplied> he bows down to them and to the sun or to the moon or to any <supplied>of</supplied> the host of heaven <idiom-start/>which I have forbidden<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “which not I <supplied>have</supplied> commanded”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 17:4">4</verse-number>and it is reported to you or you hear <supplied>about it</supplied> and you enquire <supplied>about it</supplied> thoroughly and, indeed,<note>Or “look!”</note> <supplied>the</supplied> trustworthiness of the deed<note>Hebrew “the thing”</note> <supplied>has</supplied> been established, it <idiom-start/>has occurred<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “has been done”</note> this detestable thing, in Israel, <verse-number id="Dt 17:5">5</verse-number>then you shall bring out that man or that woman who has<note>Hebrew “have”</note> done this evil thing to your gates; that is, the man or the woman, and you shall stone them with stones <idiom-start/>to death<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “and <supplied>so</supplied> they die”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 17:6">6</verse-number><idiom-start/>On the evidence of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “By the mouth of”</note> two or three witnesses <idiom-start/>the person shall be put to death<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “he/she shall be put to death, the dead person”</note> The person<note>Hebrew “he/she”</note> shall not be put to death by the mouth of one witness. <verse-number id="Dt 17:7">7</verse-number>The hand of the witnesses shall be first against the person<note>Hebrew “him”</note> to kill the person,<note>Hebrew “him”</note> and afterward the hands<note>Hebrew “hand”</note> <supplied>of</supplied> all the people, and <supplied>so</supplied> you shall purge the evil from your midst. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 17:8">8</verse-number>“<idiom-start/>If a matter is too difficult for you<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “If is difficult/wonderful from you a thing for judgment”</note> <supplied>for example disputes</supplied> between blood and blood,<note>Or “between one homicide and another”</note> between legal claim and legal claim<note>Or “one kind of lawsuit and another”</note> and between assault and assault<note>Or “one kind of abuse and another”</note> <supplied>and between</supplied> matters of discernment in your <idiom-start/>towns<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “gates”</note> then you shall get up and you shall go to the place that Yahweh your God will choose; <verse-number id="Dt 17:9">9</verse-number>then you shall go to the priests and the Levites and to the judge who will be <supplied>in office</supplied> in those days, and you shall enquire, and they shall announce to you <idiom-start/>the verdict<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the word of the decision”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 17:10">10</verse-number>“And <idiom-start/>you shall carry out exactly the decision<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and you shall do according to the mouth of the word”</note> that they announced to you from that place that Yahweh will choose, and <idiom-start/>you shall diligently observe<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and you shall observe and do”</note> according to all that they instruct you. <verse-number id="Dt 17:11">11</verse-number><supplied>And so</supplied> according to <idiom-start/>the instruction of the law<idiom-end/><note>Literally “mouth of the law”</note> that they teach you and according to the decisions that they say to you, you shall do; you shall not turn from the word that they tell you to the right or <supplied>to the</supplied> left. <verse-number id="Dt 17:12">12</verse-number>And the man who treats with contempt<note>Or “acts presumptuously”</note> <supplied>so as</supplied> not to listen to the priest <supplied>who</supplied> <supplied>is</supplied> standing to minister on behalf of Yahweh your God or to the judge, that man shall die; so you shall purge the evil from Israel. <verse-number id="Dt 17:13">13</verse-number>And all the people will hear and will be afraid, and they will not behave presumptuously again. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 17:14">14</verse-number>“When you have come to that land that Yahweh your God <supplied>is</supplied> giving to you and you have taken possession of it and you have settled in it, and you say, ‘I will set over me a king like all the nations that <supplied>are</supplied> around me,’ <verse-number id="Dt 17:15">15</verse-number>indeed, you may set a king over you whom Yahweh your God will choose, from the midst of your countrymen<note>Or “brothers”</note> you must set a king over you; you are not allowed to appoint over you a man, a foreigner, who <supplied>is</supplied> not your countryman.<note>Or “brother”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 17:16">16</verse-number>Except, he may <idiom-start/>not make numerous<idiom-end/><note>Literally “not multiply”</note> for himself horses, and he may not allow the people to <supplied>to go</supplied> to Egypt <idiom-start/>in order to increase horses<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “in order to make numerous horse”</note> for Yahweh has said to you that <idiom-start/>you may never return<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “not you may do again to return”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 17:17">17</verse-number>And he must not <idiom-start/>acquire many<idiom-end/><note>Or “make numerous”</note> wives for himself, so that his heart <supplied>would</supplied> turn aside; and <idiom-start/>he must not accumulate silver and gold for himself excessively<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “gold and silver not he must make numerous for him very”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 17:18">18</verse-number>“<idiom-start/>And then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And it shall happen”</note> <idiom-start/>when he is sitting<idiom-end/><note>Literally “as/when his sitting”</note> on the throne of his kingdom, then he shall write for himself a copy of this law on a scroll <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of”</note> the Levitical priests. <verse-number id="Dt 17:19">19</verse-number>And it shall be with him, and he shall read it<note>Hebrew “in it”</note> all the days of his life, so that he may learn to revere Yahweh your God by <idiom-start/>diligently observing<idiom-end/><note>Literally “by keeping ... to do them”</note> all the word of this law and these rules, <verse-number id="Dt 17:20">20</verse-number><supplied>so as</supplied> not to exalt his heart above his countrymen<note>Or “brothers”</note> and not to turn aside from the commandment to the right or to the left, so that <idiom-start/>he may reign long over his kingdom<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “he may make long <supplied>his</supplied> days over his kingdom”</note> he and his children in the midst of Israel.” </p>
		</chapter>