<chapter id="Dt 18">
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 18">18</verse-number><verse-number id="Dt 18:1">1</verse-number> “And there shall not be for the Levitical priests, the whole tribe of Levi, a plot of ground and an inheritance with Israel, <supplied>rather</supplied> they may eat an offering made by fire <supplied>as</supplied> their inheritance,<note>The meaning of the Hebrew text here is uncertain; possibly it reads: “<supplied>rather</supplied> an offering by fire then they will eat as <supplied>their</supplied> inheritance/patrimony”</note> for Yahweh. <verse-number id="Dt 18:2">2</verse-number>And there shall not be for them<note>Hebrew “him”</note> an inheritance <supplied>of land</supplied> in the midst of his brothers; <supplied>rather</supplied> Yahweh is his inheritance, <supplied>just</supplied> as he <idiom-start/>promised<idiom-end/><note>Literally “spoke”</note> to them.<note>Hebrew “him”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 18:3">3</verse-number>Now this shall be the share of the priest from the people, from <idiom-start/>those who sacrifice the sacrifice<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the sacrificers of the sacrifice”</note> <supplied>whether it is</supplied> an ox, sheep, or goat, and they shall give the priest the shoulder and the jawbones and the stomach. <verse-number id="Dt 18:4">4</verse-number>The firstfruits<note>Hebrew “firstfruit”</note> of your grain, your wine, and your olive oil and the firstfruits<note>Hebrew “firstfruit”</note> of the fleece of your sheep you shall give to him. <verse-number id="Dt 18:5">5</verse-number>For Yahweh your God has chosen him from <supplied>among</supplied> all your tribes to stand to minister in the name of Yahweh, he and his sons <idiom-start/>forever<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “all <supplied>of</supplied> the days”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 18:6">6</verse-number>And if a<note>Hebrew “the”</note> Levite comes from one of your <idiom-start/>towns<idiom-end/><note>Literally “gates”</note> from <idiom-start/>anywhere in Israel<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all <supplied>of</supplied> Israel”</note> where he is residing, <idiom-start/>he may come whenever he desires<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “he may come in all the desire of his soul/inner self”</note> to the place that Yahweh will choose, <verse-number id="Dt 18:7">7</verse-number>and he may minister in the name of Yahweh his God, <supplied>just</supplied> like all his brothers, <idiom-start/>the Levites who stand there<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the Levites the ones standing there”</note> <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of”</note> Yahweh. <verse-number id="Dt 18:8">8</verse-number>They shall eat <idiom-start/>equal portions<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “a portion like a portion”</note> apart from what he may receive from the sale of his patrimony.<note>Hebrew meaning of these phrases/words is not certain; also could translate as “except <supplied>what they receive</supplied> from the sale of their fathers’ <supplied>estates</supplied>” (NASB); or “what he may inherit from his father’s family”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 18:9">9</verse-number>“When you come to the land that Yahweh your God <supplied>is</supplied> giving to you, you must not learn to do like the detestable practices of those nations. <verse-number id="Dt 18:10">10</verse-number><supplied>There</supplied> shall not be found among you one who makes his son or his daughter go through the fire, <supplied>or</supplied> <idiom-start/>one who practices divination<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “a diviner of divination”</note> <supplied>or</supplied> an interpreter of signs,<note>Or “soothsayer”</note> or an augur,<note>Or “an interpreter of omens”</note> or sorcerer, <verse-number id="Dt 18:11">11</verse-number>or one who casts magic spells, or one who consults <supplied>a</supplied> spirit of the dead,<note>Or “medium”</note> or spiritist, or one who inquires of the dead.<note>Or “necromancer”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 18:12">12</verse-number>For everyone doing these <supplied>things</supplied> <supplied>is</supplied> detestable to Yahweh, and because of these detestable things Yahweh your God <supplied>is</supplied> driving them out from <idiom-start/>before you<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the face of you”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 18:13">13</verse-number>You must be blameless before Yahweh your God. <verse-number id="Dt 18:14">14</verse-number>For these nations that you <supplied>are</supplied> about to dispossess listen to interpreters of signs<note>Or “practice witchcraft”</note> and to diviners, but Yahweh your God has not allowed you to do the same. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 18:15">15</verse-number>“Yahweh your God will raise up for you a prophet like me from your midst, from your countrymen,<note>Or “your brothers”</note> <supplied>and</supplied> to him you shall listen. <verse-number id="Dt 18:16">16</verse-number><supplied>This is</supplied> <idiom-start/>according to all that you asked<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<supplied>just</supplied> as all <supplied>of</supplied> that you asked”</note> from Yahweh your God at Horeb, on the day of the assembly, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> ‘<idiom-start/>I do not want again to hear<idiom-end/><note>Literally “not I want to do again to hear”</note> the voice of Yahweh my God, <supplied>and</supplied> I do not want to see again this great fire, so that I may not die!’ <verse-number id="Dt 18:17">17</verse-number>And Yahweh said to me, ‘They are right <supplied>in</supplied> what they have said. <verse-number id="Dt 18:18">18</verse-number>I will raise up a prophet for them <idiom-start/>from among their countrymen<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from the midst of their brothers”</note> like you, and I will place<note>Or “give”</note> my words into his mouth, and he shall speak to them <idiom-start/>everything that I command him<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “all <supplied>of</supplied> what I command him”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 18:19">19</verse-number><idiom-start/>And then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And it will happen”</note> the man that will not listen to my words that he shall speak in my name, I will hold accountable. <verse-number id="Dt 18:20">20</verse-number>However, the prophet that behaves presumptuously by speaking a word in my name that I have not commanded him to speak, and who speaks in the name of other gods, then that prophet shall die.’ <verse-number id="Dt 18:21">21</verse-number>And if you say <idiom-start/>to yourself<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “in your heart”</note> ‘How can we know the word that Yahweh has not spoken to him?’ <verse-number id="Dt 18:22">22</verse-number><supplied>Whenever</supplied> what the prophet spoke in the name of Yahweh, the thing does not take place and <supplied>does</supplied> not come <supplied>about</supplied>, that <supplied>is</supplied> the thing that Yahweh has not spoken to him.<note>Or “that Yahweh has not spoken it”</note> Presumptuously the prophet spoke it; you shall not fear that<note>Hebrew “the”</note> prophet.” </p>
		</chapter>