<chapter id="Dt 19">
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 19">19</verse-number><verse-number id="Dt 19:1">1</verse-number> “When Yahweh your God has <idiom-start/>exterminated<idiom-end/><note>Literally “cut off”</note> the nations <supplied>concerning whom</supplied> Yahweh your God <supplied>is</supplied> giving to you their land, and you have dispossessed them, and you have settled in their towns and in their houses, <verse-number id="Dt 19:2">2</verse-number>you shall set apart three cities for you in the midst of your land that Yahweh your God <supplied>is</supplied> giving to you to take possession of it. <verse-number id="Dt 19:3">3</verse-number>You shall prepare the roads<note>Hebrew “road”</note> for yourselves, and you shall divide the regions of your land into thirds that Yahweh your God gives you as a possession, so that <idiom-start/>it will be available for any manslayer to flee there<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “it shall be to flee there all/anyone killing”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 19:4">4</verse-number>“Now this <supplied>is</supplied> the case of the manslayer who may flee there and live <supplied>there</supplied> who has killed his neighbor <idiom-start/>unintentionally<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “with no knowledge”</note> and he did not hate him <idiom-start/>previously<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “from yesterday <supplied>and the</supplied> day before”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 19:5">5</verse-number><idiom-start/>For example<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “And as”</note> when somebody goes with his neighbor into the forest to cut wood, and the iron <supplied>head</supplied> slips from the handle <supplied>of the tool</supplied> and strikes his neighbor and he dies, <supplied>then</supplied> he may flee to one of these cities, and <supplied>so</supplied> he may live. <verse-number id="Dt 19:6">6</verse-number><supplied>He does this</supplied> lest the avenger of blood might pursue after the killer, because <idiom-start/>he is hot with anger<idiom-end/><note>Literally “is hot his heart”</note> and he overtakes him, because it is a long distance <supplied>to the city of refuge</supplied>, and <supplied>so</supplied> <idiom-start/>he kills him<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “he strikes him down as to his life/soul”</note> but <idiom-start/>he did not deserve a death sentence<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “for him there was not a judgment of death”</note> because he <supplied>was</supplied> not hating him <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “from yesterday <supplied>and the</supplied> day before”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 19:7">7</verse-number>Therefore I <supplied>am</supplied> commanding you, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> ‘You shall set apart three cities.’ <verse-number id="Dt 19:8">8</verse-number>Then if Yahweh your God enlarges your territory <supplied>just</supplied> as he swore to your ancestors<note>Or “fathers”</note> and gives<note>Hebrew “will give”</note> to you all the land that he <idiom-start/>promised<idiom-end/><note>Literally “spoke”</note> to give to your ancestors,<note>Or “fathers”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 19:9">9</verse-number><supplied>then</supplied> <idiom-start/>if you diligently observe this entire commandment<idiom-end/><note>Literally “if you observe all <supplied>of</supplied> the commandment the this to do it”</note> that I <supplied>am</supplied> commanding you <idiom-start/>today<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the day”</note> by loving Yahweh your God and by going<note>Or “walking”</note> in his ways <idiom-start/>at all times<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “all <supplied>of</supplied> the days”</note> then you shall add three more cities for yourselves to these three. <verse-number id="Dt 19:10">10</verse-number><supplied>Do this</supplied> so that innocent blood will not be shed<note>Hebrew “is not shed”</note> in the midst of your land that Yahweh your God <supplied>is</supplied> giving to you <supplied>as an</supplied> inheritance and <supplied>thereby</supplied> bloodguilt would be on you.<note>Hebrew “shall be on you,” but conditional sense of imperfect is clear</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 19:11">11</verse-number>But if someone hates<note>Hebrew “<supplied>is</supplied> hating”</note> his neighbor and lies in wait for him and rises up<note>Or “gets up”</note> against him <idiom-start/>and murders him<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “and strikes him mortally <supplied>with regard to his life</supplied> and he dies”</note> and <supplied>the murderer</supplied> flees to one of these cities, <verse-number id="Dt 19:12">12</verse-number>then the elders of his city shall send and take him from there, and they shall give him into the hand of the avenger of blood, and he shall be put to death. <verse-number id="Dt 19:13">13</verse-number>Your eye shall not take pity on him, and you shall purge the guilt of innocent blood from Israel, <idiom-start/>so that good will be directed toward you<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “and good shall be for you” or “it shall be good for you”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 19:14">14</verse-number>“You shall not move the boundary <supplied>marker</supplied> of your neighbor that <idiom-start/>former generations<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the first settlers/ancestors”</note> set up on your property in the land that Yahweh your God <supplied>is</supplied> giving to you to take possession of it. <verse-number id="Dt 19:15">15</verse-number><idiom-start/>The testimony of a single witness may not be used to convict<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Not shall get up <supplied>only</supplied> a single witness against a man”</note> <supplied>with respect to</supplied> any crime and for any wrongdoing in any offense that a person<note>Hebrew “he”</note> committed; on the <idiom-start/>evidence<idiom-end/><note>Literally “mouth”</note> of two witnesses or on the <idiom-start/>evidence<idiom-end/><note>Literally “mouth”</note> of three witnesses <idiom-start/>a charge shall be sustained<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “shall be established a case/charge”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 19:16">16</verse-number>If <idiom-start/>a malicious witness<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a witness of violence”</note> gets up <idiom-start/>to accuse<idiom-end/><note>Literally “against”</note> anyone to testify against him falsely, <verse-number id="Dt 19:17">17</verse-number>then the two men <idiom-start/>to whom the legal dispute pertains<idiom-end/><note>Literally “who for them <supplied>are</supplied> the legal dispute”</note> shall stand <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of”</note> Yahweh, <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of”</note> the priests and the judges who are <supplied>in office</supplied> in those days. <verse-number id="Dt 19:18">18</verse-number>Then judges shall make a thorough inquiry, and <supplied>if</supplied> it turns out<note>Or “in fact”</note> that the witness is a false witness <supplied>and</supplied> he testified falsely against his brother, <verse-number id="Dt 19:19">19</verse-number>then you shall do to him as he meant<note>Or “planned”</note> to do to his brother, and so you shall purge the evil from your midst. <verse-number id="Dt 19:20">20</verse-number><idiom-start/>And the rest<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and those remaining”</note> shall hear and shall fear, and <idiom-start/>they shall not continue to do such a thing again<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and they shall not do again to do again”</note> as this evil thing in your midst. <verse-number id="Dt 19:21">21</verse-number><idiom-start/>You must show no pity<idiom-end/>:<note>Literally “And not take pity your eye”</note> life for life, eye for eye, tooth for tooth, hand for hand, foot for foot.” </p>
		</chapter>