<chapter id="Dt 20">
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 20">20</verse-number><verse-number id="Dt 20:1">1</verse-number> “If you go out to war against your enemies and you see a horse and a chariot, <idiom-start/>an army<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a people”</note> larger that you, you shall not be afraid because of them; for Yahweh your God <supplied>is</supplied> with you, the one who brought you from the land of Egypt. <verse-number id="Dt 20:2">2</verse-number><idiom-start/>And then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And it will happen”</note> when you approach the battle, then the priest shall come near and speak to the troops. <verse-number id="Dt 20:3">3</verse-number>And he shall say to them, ‘Hear, Israel, you are near <idiom-start/>today<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the day”</note> to the battle against your enemies; <idiom-start/>do not lose heart<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “do not be faint/tender-hearted”</note> you shall not be afraid, and you shall not panic, and you shall not be terrified <idiom-start/>because of them<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from their faces”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 20:4">4</verse-number>for Yahweh your God <supplied>is</supplied> going with you to fight for you against your enemies to help you.’ <verse-number id="Dt 20:5">5</verse-number>And the officials shall speak to the troops, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> ‘Who <supplied>is</supplied> the man who has built a new house and has not dedicated it? Let him go and return to this house, so that he does not die in battle and <idiom-start/>another man<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a man other”</note> dedicates it. <verse-number id="Dt 20:6">6</verse-number>And who <supplied>is</supplied> the man that has planted a vineyard and has not enjoyed it? Let him go and let him return to his house, so that he does not die in battle and <idiom-start/>another man<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a man other”</note> enjoys it. <verse-number id="Dt 20:7">7</verse-number>And who <supplied>is</supplied> the man who got engaged to a woman and <supplied>has</supplied> not married her? Let him go and let him return to his house, so that he does not die in battle and <idiom-start/>another man<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a man other”</note> marries her.’ <verse-number id="Dt 20:8">8</verse-number>And the officials shall continue to speak to the troops, and they shall say, ‘<idiom-start/>What man<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Who is the man”</note> is afraid <idiom-start/>and disheartened<idiom-end/>?<note>Literally “and soft/weak of the heart”</note> Let him go, and let him return to his house, and let him not cause the heart of his brothers to melt<note>The verb has a causal meaning here</note> like his.’ <verse-number id="Dt 20:9">9</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>when the officials have finished speaking<idiom-end/><note>Literally “it will happen as to finish the officials to speak”</note> to the army troops, then they shall appoint commanders of divisions at the head of the troops. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 20:10">10</verse-number>“When you approach a city to fight against it, <idiom-start/>you must offer it peace<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “you should call it for peace”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 20:11">11</verse-number><idiom-start/>And then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And it will happen”</note> if <idiom-start/>they accept your terms of peace<idiom-end/><note>Literally “if peace they reply to you”</note> and <idiom-start/>they surrender to you<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “they open to you”</note> <idiom-start/>and then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and it will happen”</note> all the people <idiom-start/>inhabiting it<idiom-end/><note>Literally “being found in it”</note> shall be forced labor for you, and they shall serve you. <verse-number id="Dt 20:12">12</verse-number>But if they <idiom-start/>do not accept your terms of peace<idiom-end/><note>Literally “not they make peace with you”</note> and they want to make war with you, then you shall lay siege against it.<note>That is, the city</note> <verse-number id="Dt 20:13">13</verse-number>And Yahweh your God will give it into your hand, and you shall kill all its males with the <idiom-start/>edge<idiom-end/><note>Literally “mouth”</note> of <supplied>the</supplied> sword. <verse-number id="Dt 20:14">14</verse-number>Only the women and the little children and the domestic animals<note>Hebrew “animal”</note> and all that shall be in the city, all of its spoil you may loot for yourselves, and you may enjoy the spoil of your enemies that Yahweh you God has given to you. <verse-number id="Dt 20:15">15</verse-number>Thus you shall do to all the far<note>Or “distant”</note> cities from you, which <supplied>are</supplied> not from the cities of these nations located <idiom-start/>nearby<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “here”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 20:16">16</verse-number>But from the cities of these peoples that Yahweh your God <supplied>is</supplied> giving to you as an inheritance, you shall not let anything live that breathes.<note>Or “is alive”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 20:17">17</verse-number>Rather, you shall utterly destroy them, the Hittites<note>Hebrew “Hittite”</note> and the Amorites,<note>Hebrew “Amorite”</note> the Canaanites<note>Hebrew “Canaanite”</note> and the Perizzites,<note>Hebrew “Perizzite”</note> the Hivites,<note>Hebrew “Hivite”</note> and the Jebusites,<note>Hebrew “Jebusite”</note> <supplied>just</supplied> as Yahweh your God has commanded you, <verse-number id="Dt 20:18">18</verse-number>so that they may not teach you to do like all their detestable things that they do for their gods and <supplied>thereby</supplied> you sin against Yahweh your God. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 20:19">19</verse-number>“If<note>Or “when”</note> you besiege a town <supplied>for</supplied> many days to make war against it <supplied>in order to</supplied> seize it, you shall not destroy its trees by wielding an ax against them,<note>Hebrew “it”</note> for you may eat from them,<note>Hebrew “it”</note> and <supplied>so</supplied> you must not cut them<note>Hebrew “it”</note> down. Are the trees of the field humans that they should come in siege <idiom-start/>against you<idiom-end/>?<note>Literally “from your face”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 20:20">20</verse-number>Only<note>Or “But”</note> the trees<note>Hebrew “tree”</note> that you know <idiom-start/>are not fruit trees<idiom-end/><note>Literally “not a tree of food”</note> you may destroy and you may cut down, and you may build siege works against that city that is making war with you <idiom-start/>until it falls<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “it to fall”</note> </p>
		</chapter>