<chapter id="Dt 22">
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 22">22</verse-number><verse-number id="Dt 22:1">1</verse-number> “You shall not watch the ox of your neighbor or his sheep or goat straying and ignore them; certainly you shall return them to your neighbor. <verse-number id="Dt 22:2">2</verse-number>And if your countryman<note>Or “brother”</note> <supplied>is</supplied> not near you or you do not know <idiom-start/>who he is<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “him”</note> then you shall bring it <idiom-start/>to your household<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to the midst of your house”</note> and it shall be<note>Or “remain”</note> with you <idiom-start/>until your countryman seeks after it<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the seeking of your countryman after it”</note> and you shall return it to him. <verse-number id="Dt 22:3">3</verse-number>And thus <supplied>also</supplied> you shall do regarding<note>Or “to”</note> his donkey, and thus you shall do concerning<note>Or “to”</note> his garment, and so you shall do with respect to<note>Or “to”</note> all <supplied>of</supplied> the lost property of your countryman<note>Or “brother”</note> that is lost from him and you find it; you are not allowed to withhold help. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 22:4">4</verse-number>“You shall not see the donkey of your neighbor or his ox fallen on the road and you ignore them; certainly you must help them <supplied>get</supplied> up <supplied>along</supplied> with him. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 22:5">5</verse-number>“The apparel of a man shall not be <supplied>put</supplied> on<note>Literally “on”</note> a woman, and a man shall not wear the clothing of a woman, because everyone who does these things is detestable to Yahweh your God. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 22:6">6</verse-number>“If a bird’s nest is found <idiom-start/>before you<idiom-end/><note>Literally “before your face”</note> on the road in any tree or on the ground, <supplied>and there are</supplied> chicks or eggs, and the mother <supplied>is</supplied> lying down on the chicks or the eggs, you shall not take the mother along with the young; <verse-number id="Dt 22:7">7</verse-number>you shall certainly let the mother go, but you may take the young for yourselves;<note>Hebrew “for you”</note> <supplied>do this</supplied> <idiom-start/>so that it may go well<idiom-end/><note>Literally “he/it is good”</note> for you and <idiom-start/>you may live long in the land<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “and you may make long/extend days”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 22:8">8</verse-number>“When you build a new house then<note>Hebrew “and”</note> you shall make a parapet wall<note>Or “fence/rail”</note> for your roof, so that you will not bring bloodguilt on your house <idiom-start/>if anyone should fall from it<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “if should fall the falling from it”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 22:9">9</verse-number>“You shall not sow your vineyard <supplied>with</supplied> differing kinds <supplied>of seed</supplied>, so that you shall not forfeit <idiom-start/>the whole harvest<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the entire fullness”</note> <supplied>both</supplied> the seed that you sowed and the yield of the vineyard. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 22:10">10</verse-number>“You shall not plow with an ox and with a donkey <supplied>yoked</supplied> together. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 22:11">11</verse-number>“You shall not wear woven material <supplied>made of</supplied> wool and linen <supplied>mixed</supplied> together. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 22:12">12</verse-number>“You shall make tassels for yourselves<note>Hebrew “for you”</note> on the four corners of your clothing with which you cover <supplied>yourself</supplied>. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 22:13">13</verse-number>“If a man takes a woman and <idiom-start/>he has sex with her<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “and he goes unto her”</note> but <supplied>he</supplied> then <idiom-start/>dislikes her<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “hates her”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 22:14">14</verse-number>and <idiom-start/>he accuses her falsely<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “he puts to her deeds of words”</note> and <idiom-start/>he defames her<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “he brings forth against her a bad name”</note> and he says ‘This woman I took and I lay with her and <idiom-start/>I discovered that she was not a virgin<idiom-end/>,’<note>Literally “I found not with her virginity”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 22:15">15</verse-number>then <supplied>in defense</supplied> the father of the young woman shall take, along with her mother, and <supplied>together</supplied> they must bring out the <supplied>evidence of</supplied> the virginity of the young woman <supplied>to display it</supplied> to the elders of the city <idiom-start/>at the city gate<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “toward the city gate”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 22:16">16</verse-number>And <supplied>then</supplied> the father of the young woman shall say to the elders, ‘I gave my daughter to this man as wife, but he <supplied>now</supplied> <idiom-start/>dislikes<idiom-end/><note>Literally “hates”</note> her, <verse-number id="Dt 22:17">17</verse-number>and now look <idiom-start/>he has accused her falsely<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “he put deeds of words”</note> saying, “I did not find <idiom-start/>your daughter a virgin<idiom-end/>,”<note>Literally “to your daughter virginity”</note> but here <supplied>is</supplied> <supplied>evidence of</supplied> the virginity of my daughter’; and they shall spread the cloth <supplied>out</supplied> <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of”</note> the elders of the city. <verse-number id="Dt 22:18">18</verse-number>Then the elders of that city shall take the man, and they shall discipline him. <verse-number id="Dt 22:19">19</verse-number>Then they shall fine him <supplied>a</supplied> hundred <supplied>shekels of</supplied> silver, and they shall give <supplied>them</supplied> to the father of the young woman, for <idiom-start/>he defamed an Israelite young woman<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “for he brought out a bad name against the virgin of Israel”</note> and <idiom-start/>she shall become his wife<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “and for him she shall become as wife”</note> he will not be allowed <idiom-start/>to divorce her<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to send her out”</note> all his days. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 22:20">20</verse-number>“But if <idiom-start/>this charge<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the thing”</note> was true, <idiom-start/>and the signs of virginity were not found<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and they were not found <supplied>evidence of</supplied> virginity”</note> for the young woman, <verse-number id="Dt 22:21">21</verse-number>and <supplied>then</supplied> they shall bring out the young woman to the doorway of the house of her father, and the men of her city shall stone her with stones, and she shall die, because she did a disgraceful thing in Israel <idiom-start/>by playing the harlot<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to play the harlot/to prostitute <supplied>herself</supplied>”</note> <supplied>in</supplied> the house of her father, and so you shall purge the evil from your midst. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 22:22">22</verse-number>“If a man is found lying <idiom-start/>with a married woman<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “with a woman, a young woman of a husband”</note> then they shall both die; <idiom-start/>both of them<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “also/even the two of them”</note> the man who lay with the woman and the woman <supplied>also</supplied>, so you shall purge the evil from Israel. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 22:23">23</verse-number>“If it happens <supplied>that</supplied> a young woman, a virgin, <supplied>is</supplied> engaged to a man, <supplied>and</supplied> a man finds her in the town and lies with her, <verse-number id="Dt 22:24">24</verse-number>then you shall bring out <idiom-start/>both of them<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the two of them”</note> to the gate of that city, and you shall stone them with stones so that they shall die, the young woman because she did not cry out in the town, and the man because<note>Literally “because of the fact that”</note> he violated his neighbor’s wife; and so you shall purge the evil from your midst. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 22:25">25</verse-number>“But if the man finds the young engaged woman in the field and the man overpowers her and <idiom-start/>he has sex with her<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “he lies down with her”</note> then the man only<note>Or “alone”</note> must die who lay<note>Or “slept”</note> with her. <verse-number id="Dt 22:26">26</verse-number>But you shall not do anything<note>Hebrew “a thing”</note> to the young woman, <supplied>for</supplied> there is not <supplied>reckoned</supplied> against<note>Hebrew “to”</note> the young woman <idiom-start/>a sin deserving death<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “a sin of death”</note> <idiom-start/>it is similar to when<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for as that”</note> a man rises up against his neighbor and murders him, <idiom-start/>a fellow human being<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “a soul/individual person”</note> <supplied>just</supplied> so <supplied>is</supplied> this <idiom-start/>case<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “thing/matter”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 22:27">27</verse-number>for he found her in the field, the engaged young woman cried out, but there was no<note>Hebrew “there was not”</note> rescuer <idiom-start/>to help her<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “for her”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 22:28">28</verse-number>“If a man finds a young woman, a virgin <supplied>who</supplied> is not engaged, and he seizes her and <idiom-start/>he has sex with her<idiom-end/><note>Literally “he lies with her”</note> and they are caught, <verse-number id="Dt 22:29">29</verse-number>then <idiom-start/>the man who lay with her<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the man the <supplied>one</supplied> lying with her”</note> shall give to the father of the young woman fifty <supplied>shekels</supplied> of silver, and she shall become <idiom-start/>his wife<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for/as a wife”</note> <idiom-start/>because<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in place of”</note> he violated her, and he is not allowed to divorce her <idiom-start/>during his lifetime<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “all <supplied>of</supplied> his days”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 22:30">30</verse-number><note><cite title="BibleLEB2: Dt 22:30–23:25">Deuteronomy 22:30–23:25 </cite>in the English Bible is 23:1–26 in the Hebrew Bible</note> A man may not take the wife of his father, and <supplied>so</supplied> <idiom-start/>he may not dishonor his father<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “not he may reveal the skirt of the garment of his father”</note> </p>
		</chapter>