<chapter id="Dt 23">
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 23">23</verse-number><verse-number id="Dt 23:1">1</verse-number> “No man <idiom-start/>with crushed testicles<idiom-end/><note>Literally “bruised of crushing”</note> or <supplied>whose</supplied> <idiom-start/>male organ is cut off<idiom-end/><note>Literally “cut off of male organ”</note> may come into the assembly of Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 23:2">2</verse-number>An illegitimate child may not come into the assembly of Yahweh; even <supplied>to</supplied> the tenth generation none <idiom-start/>of his descendants<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to him”</note> may come into the assembly of Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 23:3">3</verse-number>An Ammonite or a Moabite may not come into the assembly of Yahweh; even <supplied>to</supplied> the tenth generation none <idiom-start/>of his descendants<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to him”</note> may come into the assembly of Yahweh <idiom-start/>forever<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “until eternity”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 23:4">4</verse-number><idiom-start/>because<idiom-end/><note>Literally “because of the event when”</note> they did not come to meet you with food and with water <idiom-start/>when you came out of Egypt<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “at your going out of Egypt”</note> and <supplied>also</supplied> <idiom-start/>because<idiom-end/><note>Literally “because of the event when”</note> they<note>Hebrew “he,” but with plural meaning</note> hired Balaam, son of Beor, from Pethor, in Aram Naharaim<note>Or “Mesopotamia” = “between the rivers”</note> <supplied>to act</supplied> against you to curse you. <verse-number id="Dt 23:5">5</verse-number>But Yahweh your God was not willing to listen to Balaam, and Yahweh your God turned the curse into a blessing for you, because Yahweh your God loved you. <verse-number id="Dt 23:6">6</verse-number>You shall not promote their welfare or their prosperity all your days <idiom-start/>forever<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “until eternity”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 23:7">7</verse-number>“You shall not abhor an Edomite, because he <supplied>is</supplied> your brother; you shall not abhor an Egyptian because you were an alien in his land. <verse-number id="Dt 23:8">8</verse-number>The children<note>Or “sons”</note> <supplied>that</supplied> are born to them <supplied>in</supplied> the third generation may come <idiom-start/>representing them<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for them” or possibly “become members of”</note> in the assembly of Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 23:9">9</verse-number>“If<note>Or “when”</note> you go out to encamp against your enemies, then you shall guard against <supplied>doing</supplied> anything evil. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 23:10">10</verse-number>“If <supplied>there</supplied> is among you a man that is not clean because of a seminal emission <idiom-start/>during the night<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “of the night”</note> he shall go outside the camp; he shall not come within the camp. <verse-number id="Dt 23:11">11</verse-number><idiom-start/>And then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And it will happen/come about that”</note> toward the <idiom-start/>coming<idiom-end/><note>Literally “turning”</note> of the evening, he shall bathe with<note>Hebrew “in” but this is instrumental use of this preposition</note> water, and at the going down<note>The verb can mean “coming/going” and here it means “going”</note> of the sun, he may come to the midst of the camp. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 23:12">12</verse-number>“And there shall be for you a designated place outside the camp; <idiom-start/>and you shall go there to relieve yourself<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “and you shall go out there, outside <supplied>to relieve yourself</supplied>”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 23:13">13</verse-number>and a digging tool<note>Or “spade”</note> shall <supplied>be included</supplied> in addition to your <supplied>other</supplied> utensils<note>Hebrew “utensil”</note> for yourself; <idiom-start/>and then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and it will happen”</note> <idiom-start/>when you relieve yourself<idiom-end/><note>Literally “at your sitting”</note> outside <supplied>the camp</supplied> you shall dig with it, and <supplied>then</supplied> you shall turn, and you shall cover your excrement. <verse-number id="Dt 23:14">14</verse-number>For Yahweh your God <supplied>is</supplied> walking about in the midst of your camp to deliver you and <idiom-start/>to hand your enemies over to you before you<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to give your enemies to the face of you”</note> and so let your camp be holy, so that he shall not see in it <idiom-start/>anything indecent<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “nakedness of a thing”</note> and he shall turn away <idiom-start/>from going with you<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “from behind/after you”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 23:15">15</verse-number>“And you shall not hand over a slave to his master who has escaped <supplied>and fled</supplied> to you from his master. <verse-number id="Dt 23:16">16</verse-number>He shall reside with you in your midst in the place that he chooses in one of <idiom-start/>your towns wherever he pleases<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “in your gates good for him”</note> you shall not oppress him. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 23:17">17</verse-number>“No woman <idiom-start/>of Israel<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from the daughters of Israel”</note> shall be a temple prostitute, and no man <idiom-start/>of Israel<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from the sons of Israel”</note> shall be a male shrine prostitute. <verse-number id="Dt 23:18">18</verse-number>You may not bring the <idiom-start/>hire<idiom-end/><note>Literally “gift”</note> of a prostitute or <idiom-start/>the earnings of a male prostitute<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the earnings of a dog”</note> <supplied>into</supplied> the house of Yahweh your God, for any vow offerings, because <idiom-start/>both<idiom-end/><note>Literally “both, the two of them”</note> are a detestable thing to Yahweh your God. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 23:19">19</verse-number>“<idiom-start/>You shall not charge your brother interest on money<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “You shall not lend on interest to your brother, interest of money”</note> interest on<note>Hebrew “of”</note> food, or interest on<note>Hebrew “of”</note> anything that one could lend<note>Or “can lend”</note> on interest. <verse-number id="Dt 23:20">20</verse-number>You may lend on interest to the foreigner, but to your countryman<note>Or “brother”</note> you may not lend on interest, so that Yahweh your God may bless you <idiom-start/>in all your undertakings<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in all the sending<supplied>s</supplied> out of your hand”</note> in <idiom-start/>the land where you are going<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the land that you <supplied>are</supplied> going there”</note> <idiom-start/>in order to take possession of it<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to take possession”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 23:21">21</verse-number>“<idiom-start/>When you make a vow<idiom-end/><note>Literally “When/if you vow a vow”</note> to Yahweh your God, you shall not postpone <idiom-start/>fulfillment of it<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to fulfill it”</note> <supplied>for</supplied> certainly Yahweh your God shall require it from you and <supplied>if postponed</supplied> <idiom-start/>you will incur guilt<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “it shall become against you <supplied>as</supplied> sin”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 23:22">22</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>if you refrain from vowing<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “if you refrain to make a vow”</note> <idiom-start/>you shall not incur guilt<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “it shall not become against you <supplied>as</supplied> sin”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 23:23">23</verse-number>The utterance of your lips <idiom-start/>you must perform diligently<idiom-end/><note>Literally “you must observe and you shall do”</note> <supplied>just</supplied> as you have vowed freely to Yahweh your God whatever <supplied>it was</supplied> that you promised<note>Or “spoke”</note> with your mouth. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 23:24">24</verse-number>“When<note>Or “If”</note> you come into the vineyard of your neighbor, then you may eat grapes <idiom-start/>as you please<idiom-end/><note>Literally “according to your desire”</note> and <idiom-start/>until you are full<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to your satiation”</note> but you shall not put <supplied>any</supplied> into your container. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 23:25">25</verse-number>“When<note>Or “If”</note> you come into the standing grain of your neighbor, then you may pluck ears with your hand, but you may not <idiom-start/>swing<idiom-end/><note>Literally “wave”</note> a sickle among the standing grain of your neighbor.” </p>
		</chapter>