<chapter id="Dt 24">
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 24">24</verse-number><verse-number id="Dt 24:1">1</verse-number> “When<note>Or “If”</note> a man takes a wife and he marries her <idiom-start/>and then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and it will happen”</note> <idiom-start/>she does not please him<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “if not she finds favor in his eyes”</note> because he found <idiom-start/>something objectionable<idiom-end/><note>Literally “shameful/repulsive thing”</note> and writes her a letter of divorce and puts <supplied>it</supplied> in her hand and sends her <supplied>away</supplied> from his house, <verse-number id="Dt 24:2">2</verse-number>and she goes from his house, and she goes <supplied>out</supplied> and becomes <supplied>a wife</supplied> <idiom-start/>for another man<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “for a man other”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 24:3">3</verse-number>and <supplied>then</supplied> the second man dislikes her and he writes her a letter of divorce and places <supplied>it</supplied> into her hand and sends her from his house, or if the second man dies who took her <idiom-start/>to himself<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to for him”</note> as a wife, <verse-number id="Dt 24:4">4</verse-number>her first husband who sent her <supplied>away</supplied> is not allowed <idiom-start/>to take her again<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to return to take her”</note> to become a wife to him after she has <idiom-start/>been defiled<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “become unclean”</note> for that <supplied>is</supplied> a detestable thing <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of”</note> Yahweh, and <supplied>so</supplied> you shall not mislead into sin the land that Yahweh your God <supplied>is</supplied> giving to you <supplied>as an</supplied> inheritance. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 24:5">5</verse-number>“When<note>Or “If”</note> a man takes a new wife he shall not go out with the army, and <idiom-start/>he shall not be obligated with anything<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “he shall not come across <supplied>come over</supplied> upon him to anything”</note> he shall be free from obligation, <idiom-start/>to stay at home<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for his house”</note> for one year, and he shall bring joy <supplied>to</supplied> his wife that he took. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 24:6">6</verse-number>“A person<note>Hebrew “he”</note> shall not take<note>Or “require”</note> a pair of millstones or an upper millstone, for <idiom-start/>he is taking necessities of life as a pledge<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “for a life <supplied>he</supplied> is taking as a pledge”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 24:7">7</verse-number>“If a man is <idiom-start/>caught<idiom-end/><note>Literally “found”</note> kidnapping somebody from <supplied>among</supplied> his countrymen,<note>Or “brothers”</note> the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and he treats him as a slave or he sells him, then that kidnapper shall die, and <supplied>so</supplied> you shall purge the evil <idiom-start/>from among you<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “from your midst”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 24:8">8</verse-number>Be watchful<note>Or “Be careful”</note> <idiom-start/>with respect to<idiom-end/><note>Literally “against”</note> <supplied>an</supplied> outbreak of <supplied>any</supplied> infectious skin disease, by being very careful and by acting<note>Or “doing”</note> according to all that the priests and the Levites have instructed you, <supplied>just</supplied> as I have commanded them, <idiom-start/>so you shall diligently observe<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “<supplied>so</supplied> you shall observe to do”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 24:9">9</verse-number><supplied>So</supplied> remember what Yahweh your God did to Miriam on the journey <idiom-start/>when you went out from Egypt<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “in you to go out from Egypt”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 24:10">10</verse-number>“When you make a loan to your neighbor, a loan of any kind, you shall not go into his house <idiom-start/>to take his pledge<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to pledge <supplied>with respect to</supplied> his pledge”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 24:11">11</verse-number>You shall wait outside, and the man <supplied>to</supplied> whom you <supplied>are</supplied> lending, he shall bring the pledge outside to you. <verse-number id="Dt 24:12">12</verse-number>And if <supplied>he is</supplied> a needy man, you shall not sleep in his pledge.<note>“His pledge” refers to “a garment given as pledge”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 24:13">13</verse-number>You shall certainly return the pledge to him <idiom-start/>as the sun sets<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “as/at the moment of the going <supplied>out</supplied> of the sun”</note> so that he may sleep in his cloak and may bless you, and it shall be <supplied>considered</supplied> righteousness <idiom-start/>on your behalf<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to you”</note> <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of”</note> Yahweh your God. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 24:14">14</verse-number>“You shall not exploit a hired worker, <supplied>who is</supplied> needy and poor, from among your fellow men or from <supplied>among</supplied> your aliens<note>Hebrew “alien”</note> who are in your land <supplied>and</supplied> in your <idiom-start/>towns<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “gates”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 24:15">15</verse-number>On his day you shall give his wage, and the sun shall not go <idiom-start/>down<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “over him”</note> because <supplied>he is</supplied> poor and <idiom-start/>his life depends on it<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “and to him it is a lifting up with respect to his life/soul”</note> <supplied>do this</supplied> so that he does not cry out against you to Yahweh, <idiom-start/>and you incur guilt<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “and it becomes against you <supplied>as</supplied> sin</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 24:16">16</verse-number>“Fathers shall not be put to death because of <supplied>their</supplied> children, and children shall not be put to death because of <supplied>their</supplied> fathers; each one shall be put to death for his <supplied>own</supplied> sin. <verse-number id="Dt 24:17">17</verse-number>You shall not subvert the rights of an alien <supplied>or</supplied> an orphan, and you shall not take as pledge <supplied>the</supplied> garment of a widow. <verse-number id="Dt 24:18">18</verse-number>And you shall remember that you were a slave in Egypt and <supplied>that</supplied> Yahweh your God redeemed you from there; therefore I <supplied>am</supplied> commanding you to do this commandment. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 24:19">19</verse-number>“When<note>Or “If”</note> you reap your harvest in your field and you forget a sheaf in the field, you shall not return to get it, for it shall be for the alien, for the orphan, and for the widow, so that Yahweh your God may bless you in all the work of your hands. <verse-number id="Dt 24:20">20</verse-number>When you beat off the fruit of your olive trees you shall not search through the branches afterward, for it<note>That is, what is left</note> shall be for the alien, for the orphan, and for the widow. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 24:21">21</verse-number>When you harvest <supplied>grapes</supplied>, you shall not glean your vineyards <idiom-start/>again<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “behind/after you”</note> it<note>That is, what is left</note> shall be for the alien, for the orphan, and for the widow. <verse-number id="Dt 24:22">22</verse-number>And you shall remember that you were a slave in the land of Egypt, therefore I <supplied>am</supplied> commanding you to do this thing.” </p>
		</chapter>