<chapter id="Dt 25">
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 25">25</verse-number><verse-number id="Dt 25:1">1</verse-number> “When a legal dispute <idiom-start/>takes place<idiom-end/><note>Literally “shall be”</note> between men and they come near to the court, and <supplied>the judges</supplied> judge <supplied>with respect to</supplied> them, then they shall declare the righteous <supplied>to be</supplied> in the right and they shall condemn the wicked, <verse-number id="Dt 25:2">2</verse-number>then it will happen if the guilty <supplied>one</supplied> <idiom-start/>deserves beating<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “<supplied>is</supplied> a son <supplied>of</supplied> beating”</note> then the judge shall make him lie, and he shall beat him <idiom-start/>before him<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to the face of him”</note> <idiom-start/>according to<idiom-end/><note>Literally “as”</note> <idiom-start/>the prescribed number of lashes proportionate to the offense<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “as is sufficient/necessary, with respect to number, for his wickedness/wicked behavior”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 25:3">3</verse-number>He may beat him <supplied>with</supplied> forty lashes, and he shall not do more <supplied>than these</supplied>, so that he <supplied>will</supplied> not beat more in addition to these many blows,<note>Hebrew “blow”</note> and your countryman<note>Or “brother”</note> would be<note>Hebrew “is”</note> degraded before your eyes. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 25:4">4</verse-number>“You shall not muzzle an ox <idiom-start/>when he is threshing<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “at his threshing”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 25:5">5</verse-number>“When brothers dwell together and one of them dies and has no son, the wife of the deceased shall not become the wife of a <idiom-start/>man of another family<idiom-end/>;<note>Others: “strange man,” “man outside the family” (NEB)</note> her brother-in-law <idiom-start/>shall have sex with her<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “shall go to her”</note> and he shall take her <idiom-start/>to himself<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to/for him”</note> as <supplied>a</supplied> wife, and he shall perform his duty as <supplied>a</supplied> brother-in-law <supplied>with respect to</supplied> her. <verse-number id="Dt 25:6">6</verse-number>And then the firstborn that she bears <idiom-start/>shall represent his dead brother<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “he shall stand upon the name of his brother the deceased”</note> so that his name is not blotted out from Israel. <verse-number id="Dt 25:7">7</verse-number>But if the man <supplied>does</supplied> not want to take his sister-in-law, then his sister-in-law shall go up to the gate, to the elders, and she shall say, ‘My brother-in-law refused <idiom-start/>to perpetuate his brother’s name<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to cause a name to stand for his brother”</note> in Israel, <supplied>for</supplied> he is not willing <idiom-start/>to marry me<idiom-end/>.’<note>Literally “to consummate the marriage with the widow of a <supplied>his</supplied> brother”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 25:8">8</verse-number>Then the elders of his town shall summon him and speak to him, and <supplied>if</supplied> he persists and says, ‘<idiom-start/>I do not desire to<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I do not delight in”</note> marry her’ <verse-number id="Dt 25:9">9</verse-number><supplied>then</supplied> his sister-in-law shall go near him before the eyes of the elders, and she shall pull off his sandal from his foot, and she shall spit in his face, and she shall <idiom-start/>declare<idiom-end/><note>Literally “respond/answer”</note> and she shall say, ‘This is how it is done to the man who does not build the house of his brother.’ <verse-number id="Dt 25:10">10</verse-number>And his <idiom-start/>family<idiom-end/><note>Literally “name”</note> shall be called in Israel, ‘The house where the sandal was pulled off.’<note>Or “the house <supplied>of the man whose</supplied> sandal was pulled off”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 25:11">11</verse-number>“If a man and his brother fight each other and the wife of the one <supplied>man</supplied> comes near to rescue her husband from the hand of his attacker and she stretches <supplied>out</supplied> her hand and she seizes his genitals, <verse-number id="Dt 25:12">12</verse-number>then you shall cut off her hand; your eye shall not take pity. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 25:13">13</verse-number>“There shall not be <idiom-start/>for your use<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to you”</note> in your bag <idiom-start/>two kinds of stone weights, a large one and a small one<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “stone and stone large and small”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 25:14">14</verse-number>There shall not be in your house <idiom-start/>for your use<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for you”</note> <idiom-start/>two kinds of measures<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “ephah and ephah large and small”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 25:15">15</verse-number><supplied>Rather</supplied> a full and honest weight shall be <idiom-start/>for your use<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “for you”</note> there shall be for you a full and honest <idiom-start/>measure<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “an ephah”</note> so that your days on the land that Yahweh your God <supplied>is</supplied> giving to you may be long. <verse-number id="Dt 25:16">16</verse-number>For detestable to<note>Or “for”</note> Yahweh your God <supplied>is</supplied> everyone who <supplied>is</supplied> doing such things,<note>Or “<supplied>are</supplied> all <supplied>who</supplied><supplied>are</supplied> doing”</note> everyone who <supplied>is</supplied> acting<note>Or “all <supplied>who</supplied><supplied>are</supplied> acting”</note> dishonestly. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 25:17">17</verse-number>“Remember what Amalek did to you on the journey when<note>Or “at/in”</note> you went out from Egypt, <verse-number id="Dt 25:18">18</verse-number>that he met you on the journey and attacked you, all those lagging behind you and <supplied>when</supplied> you were weary and worn out, and he did not fear God. <verse-number id="Dt 25:19">19</verse-number><idiom-start/>And when<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And it will happen when”</note> Yahweh your God gives rest to you from all your enemies from around <supplied>about you</supplied> in the land that Yahweh your God <supplied>is</supplied> giving to you <supplied>as an</supplied> inheritance to take possession of it, you shall blot out the remembrance of Amalek from under the heavens; you shall not forget!” </p>
		</chapter>