<chapter id="Dt 27">
			<pericope>Ceremonies</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 27:1">1</verse-number>Then Moses and the elders of Israel charged the people, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> “Keep all of the commandment that I <supplied>am</supplied> commanding you <idiom-start/>today<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the day”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 27:2">2</verse-number>And then on the day that you cross the Jordan to the land that Yahweh your God <supplied>is</supplied> giving to you, then you shall set up <idiom-start/>for yourselves<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for you”</note> large stones, and you shall paint<note>Or “coat/cover them”</note> them with lime, <verse-number id="Dt 27:3">3</verse-number>and you shall write on them all the words of this law at your crossing, so that you may come into the land that Yahweh your God <supplied>is</supplied> giving to you, a land flowing with milk and honey, as Yahweh, the God of your ancestors,<note>Or “fathers”</note> <idiom-start/>promised<idiom-end/><note>Literally “spoke”</note> to you. <verse-number id="Dt 27:4">4</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>when you cross the Jordan<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “at/in your crossing the Jordan”</note> you shall set up these stones that I <supplied>am</supplied> commanding you <supplied>about</supplied> <idiom-start/>today<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the day”</note> on Mount Ebal, and you shall paint<note>Or “coat/cover”</note> them with lime. <verse-number id="Dt 27:5">5</verse-number>And you shall build an altar there for Yahweh your God, an altar of stone, but<note>Or “and”</note> <idiom-start/>you shall not use an iron tool to shape the stones<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “and you shall not wave to and fro over them an iron tool”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 27:6">6</verse-number>You must build the altar of your God <supplied>with</supplied> unhewn stones, and you shall sacrifice on it burnt offerings to Yahweh your God. <verse-number id="Dt 27:7">7</verse-number>And you shall sacrifice fellowship offerings, and you shall eat <supplied>them</supplied> there, and you shall rejoice <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of”</note> Yahweh your God. <verse-number id="Dt 27:8">8</verse-number>You shall write on the stone all of the words of this law very clearly.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 27:9">9</verse-number>Then Moses and the priests, the Levites, spoke to all Israel, saying,<note>Literally “to say”</note> “Be silent and hear, Israel, <supplied>for</supplied> this day you have become <idiom-start/>a people<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for a people”</note> for Yahweh your God. <verse-number id="Dt 27:10">10</verse-number>And listen to the voice of Yahweh your God, and observe his commandments and his rules that I <supplied>am</supplied> commanding you <idiom-start/>today<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “the day”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Blessings and Curses</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 27:11">11</verse-number>And Moses charged the people on that day, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 27:12">12</verse-number>“These <supplied>tribes</supplied> shall stand on Mount Gerizim to bless the people <idiom-start/>when you cross<idiom-end/><note>Literally “at/in crossing your”</note> the Jordan: Simeon and Levi and Judah and Issachar and Joseph and Benjamin. <verse-number id="Dt 27:13">13</verse-number>And these shall stand on Mount Ebal for <supplied>delivering</supplied> the curse: Reuben, Gad and Asher and Zebulun, Dan and Naphtali. <verse-number id="Dt 27:14">14</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>the Levites shall declare<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “they shall answer the Levites”</note> and they shall say to each man of Israel <supplied>with</supplied> a loud voice, <verse-number id="Dt 27:15">15</verse-number>‘Cursed be the man that makes a divine image or a cast image, <supplied>which is</supplied> a detestable thing for Yahweh, the work of the hand of a skilled craftsman, and <supplied>then</supplied> sets <supplied>it</supplied> in a hiding place.’<note>Or “a secret place”</note> And <idiom-start/>all the people shall respond<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “and they shall answer all of the people”</note> ‘Amen.’ </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 27:16">16</verse-number>‘Cursed be the one who dishonors his father or his mother.’ And all of the people shall say, ‘Amen.’ </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 27:17">17</verse-number>‘Cursed be the one who moves the boundary <supplied>marker</supplied> of his neighbor.’ And all the people shall say, ‘Amen.’ </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 27:18">18</verse-number>‘Cursed be the one who misleads a blind person on the road.’ And all the people shall say, ‘Amen.’ </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 27:19">19</verse-number>‘Cursed be the one who deprives <supplied>the</supplied> alien, <supplied>the</supplied> orphan, and <supplied>the</supplied> widow of justice.’ And all the people shall say, ‘Amen.’ </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 27:20">20</verse-number>‘Cursed be the one who lies with the wife of his father, because <idiom-start/>he has dishonored his father’s bed<idiom-end/>.’<note>Literally “because he uncovered the hem of his father”</note> And all the people shall say, ‘Amen.’ </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 27:21">21</verse-number>‘Cursed be the one who lies with any <supplied>kind</supplied> of animal.’ And all the people shall say, ‘Amen.’ </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 27:22">22</verse-number>‘Cursed be the one who lies with his sister, the daughter of his father or the daughter of his mother.’ And all the people shall say, ‘Amen.’ </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 27:23">23</verse-number>‘Cursed be the one who lies with his mother-in-law.’ And all the people shall say, ‘Amen.’ </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 27:24">24</verse-number>‘Cursed be the one who strikes down his neighbor in secret.’ And all the people shall say, ‘Amen.’ </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 27:25">25</verse-number>‘Cursed be the one who takes a bribe <idiom-start/>to murder an innocent person<idiom-end/>.’<note>Literally “to strike down an individual person in blood”</note> And all the people shall say, ‘Amen.’ </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 27:26">26</verse-number>‘Cursed be <supplied>the one</supplied> <idiom-start/>who does not keep<idiom-end/><note>Literally “who not keeps”</note> the words of this law, to observe them.’ And all the people shall say, ‘Amen.’ ” </p>
		</chapter>