<chapter id="Dt 28">
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 28">28</verse-number><verse-number id="Dt 28:1">1</verse-number> “And it will happen <supplied>that</supplied> if you indeed listen to the voice of Yahweh your God, <idiom-start/>to diligently observe<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to observe to do”</note> all his commandments that I <supplied>am</supplied> commanding you <idiom-start/>today<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the day”</note> then Yahweh your God will set you above all the nations of the earth. <verse-number id="Dt 28:2">2</verse-number>And all of these blessings shall come upon you, and <idiom-start/>they shall have an effect on you<idiom-end/><note>Literally “they shall overtake you”</note> if you listen to the voice of Yahweh your God: </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 28:3">3</verse-number>“You will be blessed in the city, and you will be blessed in the field. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 28:4">4</verse-number>“Blessed will be the fruit of your womb and the fruit of your ground and the fruit of your livestock, <idiom-start/>the calf of your cattle and the lambs of your flock<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “<supplied>what</supplied> is dropped of your cattle and the offspring of your flocks”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 28:5">5</verse-number>“Blessed will be your basket and your kneading trough. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 28:6">6</verse-number>“Blessed will you be <idiom-start/>when you come in and blessed will you be when you go out<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “in/at your coming and you will be blessed in/at your going out”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 28:7">7</verse-number>“Yahweh will cause your enemies <idiom-start/>who rise up against you to be defeated before you<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “the ones rising against you being defeated to the face of you”</note> on one road<note>Or “way”</note> they shall come out <supplied>against</supplied> you, but on seven roads<note>Or “ways”</note> they shall flee <idiom-start/>before you<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to the face of you”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 28:8">8</verse-number>Yahweh will command <idiom-start/>concerning you<idiom-end/><note>Literally “with you”</note> the blessing <supplied>to be</supplied> in your barns and <idiom-start/>in all your endeavors<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “in all of the sending <supplied>forth</supplied> of your hand”</note> and he will bless you in the land that Yahweh your God <supplied>is</supplied> giving to you. <verse-number id="Dt 28:9">9</verse-number>Yahweh will establish you for <idiom-start/>himself<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to/for him”</note> as a holy people as he has sworn to you, if you keep the commandments of Yahweh your God and you walk in his ways. <verse-number id="Dt 28:10">10</verse-number>And all of the peoples of the earth shall see that <idiom-start/>by the name of Yahweh you are called<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “that the name of Yahweh is called/assigned upon you”</note> and <idiom-start/>they shall fear you<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “they shall be afraid/fearful from you”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 28:11">11</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>Yahweh will make you successful and prosperous<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “Yahweh will cause for you goodness”</note> in the fruit of your womb and on the land that Yahweh swore to your ancestors<note>Or “fathers”</note> to give to you. <verse-number id="Dt 28:12">12</verse-number>Yahweh shall open for you his <idiom-start/>rich<idiom-end/><note>Literally “good”</note> storehouse, <supplied>even</supplied> the heavens, to give the rain for<note>Hebrew “of”</note> your land in its time and to bless all of the work of your hand, and you will lend to many nations; you will not borrow <supplied>from them</supplied>. <verse-number id="Dt 28:13">13</verse-number>And Yahweh shall make you<note>Literally “place/set you up”</note> as head and not the tail, and you shall be only at the top <supplied>of the nations</supplied>, and you shall not be at the bottom, if you listen to the commandments of Yahweh your God that I <supplied>am</supplied> commanding you <idiom-start/>today<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the day”</note> <idiom-start/>and diligently observe them<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to observe them and to do them”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 28:14">14</verse-number>And you <supplied>shall</supplied> not turn aside from <idiom-start/>any of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all of”</note> the words that I <supplied>am</supplied> commanding you <idiom-start/>today<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the day”</note> <supplied>to the</supplied> right or left by going after other gods to serve them. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 28:15">15</verse-number>“<idiom-start/>And then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and it will happen”</note> if you do not listen to the voice of Yahweh your God <idiom-start/>by diligently observing<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to observe and to do”</note> all of his commandments and his statutes that I <supplied>am</supplied> commanding you <idiom-start/>today<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the day”</note> then all of these curses shall come upon you, and they shall overtake you: </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 28:16">16</verse-number>“You <supplied>shall</supplied><note>All of these curses have a future orientation that points to Israel in the land of Canaan</note> be cursed in the city, and <supplied>you shall</supplied> be cursed in the field. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 28:17">17</verse-number>“Your basket <supplied>shall</supplied> be cursed and your kneading trough. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 28:18">18</verse-number>“The fruit of your womb <supplied>shall</supplied> be cursed and the fruit of you ground, the calves of your cattle and the lambs of your flock. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 28:19">19</verse-number>“You shall be cursed <idiom-start/>when you come in<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “at/in your coming”</note> and you <supplied>shall</supplied> be cursed <idiom-start/>when you go out<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “at/in your going out”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 28:20">20</verse-number>“Yahweh will send upon you<note>Others translate as a wish: “may Yahweh send upon you …”</note> the curse,<note>These words are translated variously, e.g., “starvation,” “thirst,” “rebuke/dysentery” (NEB) or “curses,” “confusion,” “frustration” (NLT)</note> the panic,<note>Or “confusion”</note> and the threat<note>Or “rebuke”</note> <idiom-start/>in everything that you undertake<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “in all the sending out of your hand that you do”</note> <idiom-start/>until you are destroyed and until you perish quickly<idiom-end/><note>Literally “until your to be destroyed and until your to perish quickly”</note> <idiom-start/>because of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from the face of the evil of your deeds”</note> the evil of your deeds in that<note>Literally “which”</note> you have forsaken me. <verse-number id="Dt 28:21">21</verse-number>Yahweh will cause the plague to cling to you <idiom-start/>until it consumes you<idiom-end/><note>Literally “it to consume to”</note> from the land that you <supplied>are</supplied> going to,<note>Hebrew “to there”</note> to take possession of it. <verse-number id="Dt 28:22">22</verse-number>Yahweh will afflict you with the wasting diseases and with the fever and with the inflammation and with the scorching heat and with the sword<note>Others translate “drought” (NLT, NEB)</note> and with the blight and with the mildew, and they shall pursue you <idiom-start/>until you perish<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “until your/you to perish”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 28:23">23</verse-number>And your heavens that <supplied>are</supplied> over your heads shall be <supplied>like</supplied> bronze, and the earth that <supplied>is</supplied> under you <supplied>shall be like</supplied> iron. <verse-number id="Dt 28:24">24</verse-number>Yahweh will change the rain of your land <supplied>to</supplied> fine dust and <supplied>to</supplied> sand; from the heaven it shall come down upon you <idiom-start/>until you are destroyed<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “until your being destroyed”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 28:25">25</verse-number>“Yahweh shall cause you to be defeated <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of”</note> your enemies; on one road you shall go <idiom-start/>against<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to/toward”</note> them,<note>Hebrew “him”</note> but you will flee on seven roads <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of”</note> them,<note>Hebrew “him”</note> and you shall become a thing of horror to all of the kingdoms of the earth. <verse-number id="Dt 28:26">26</verse-number>And your dead bodies shall be as food for all of the birds of the heaven and to the animals of the earth, and there shall not be <idiom-start/>anyone to frighten them away<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “one causing fright <supplied>to them</supplied>”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 28:27">27</verse-number>“Yahweh shall afflict you with the boils of Egypt and with tumors and with the scurvy and with <idiom-start/>the skin rash that cannot be healed<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the skin rash that not it is able it to be healed”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 28:28">28</verse-number>Yahweh shall afflict you with madness and with blindness and with confusion of heart. <verse-number id="Dt 28:29">29</verse-number>And you shall be groping at noon just as the blind person gropes in the dark, and you shall not succeed <supplied>in finding</supplied> your way, and you shall only be abused and robbed <idiom-start/>all the time<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “all the days”</note> and there will not be <idiom-start/>anyone who will rescue you<idiom-end/>. <note>Literally “one who delivers/rescues <supplied>you</supplied>”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 28:30">30</verse-number>You shall become engaged to a woman, but another man shall sleep<note>Or “ravish/violate”</note> with her; you shall build a house, but you shall not live in it; a vineyard you shall plant, but you shall not enjoy it. <verse-number id="Dt 28:31">31</verse-number>Your ox <supplied>shall</supplied> <supplied>be</supplied> slaughtered before your eyes, and you shall not eat it; your donkey <supplied>shall be</supplied> stolen <supplied>right</supplied> <idiom-start/>before you<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to the face of you”</note> and it shall not be returned to you; your sheep and your goats <supplied>shall</supplied> be given to your enemies, and <idiom-start/>there shall not be anyone who rescues you<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “there shall not be for you one who rescues”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 28:32">32</verse-number>Your sons and your daughters <supplied>shall be</supplied> given to other people, and <idiom-start/>you will be looking on<idiom-end/><note>Literally “your eyes <supplied>will</supplied> see/look”</note> <idiom-start/>longingly<idiom-end/><note>Literally “wearing out”</note> for<note>Hebrew “to”</note> them all day, <idiom-start/>but you will be powerless to do anything<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “but there will not be for power of your hand”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 28:33">33</verse-number>A people that you do not know shall consume the harvest of your land and all your labor, and you will be only oppressed and crushed <idiom-start/>for the rest of your lives<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “all of the days”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 28:34">34</verse-number>You shall become mad <idiom-start/>because of what your eyes shall see<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “from/by the sight of your eyes”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 28:35">35</verse-number>Yahweh shall strike you with grievous boils on the knees and on the upper thighs <supplied>from which</supplied> <idiom-start/>you will not be able to be healed<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “which not you are able to heal”</note> from the sole of your foot and up to your crown. <verse-number id="Dt 28:36">36</verse-number>Yahweh will bring you and your king whom you set up over you to a nation that you or your ancestors<note>Or “fathers”</note> have not known, and there you will serve other gods <supplied>of</supplied> wood and stone. <verse-number id="Dt 28:37">37</verse-number>And you will become a horror and a proverb and ridicule among all the peoples where Yahweh drives you there. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 28:38">38</verse-number>“You shall carry out much seed to the field, but you shall gather little <supplied>produce</supplied>, for the locust shall devour it. <verse-number id="Dt 28:39">39</verse-number>You shall plant vineyards and you shall dress<note>Or “cultivate”</note> <supplied>them</supplied>, but you shall not drink wine and you shall not gather grapes, for the worm shall eat it.<note>That is, the produce</note> <verse-number id="Dt 28:40">40</verse-number>There shall be olive trees for you in all of your territory, but you shall not anoint <supplied>yourself</supplied>, for your olives<note>Hebrew “olive”</note> shall drop off. <verse-number id="Dt 28:41">41</verse-number>You shall bear sons and daughters, but they shall not be <idiom-start/>yours<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “for you”</note> for they shall go into captivity. <verse-number id="Dt 28:42">42</verse-number>The cricket shall take possession of all your trees and the fruit of your ground. <verse-number id="Dt 28:43">43</verse-number>The alien that <supplied>is</supplied> in your midst shall ascend over you, higher <supplied>and</supplied> higher, but you shall go down lower <supplied>and</supplied> lower. <verse-number id="Dt 28:44">44</verse-number>He shall lend to you, but you shall not lend to him; he shall be <supplied>the</supplied> head, but you shall be <supplied>the</supplied> tail. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 28:45">45</verse-number>“And all of these curses shall come over you, and they shall pursue you, and they shall overtake you <idiom-start/>until you are destroyed<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “until you to be destroyed”</note> because <idiom-start/>you did not listen<idiom-end/><note>Literally “not you listened”</note> to the voice of Yahweh your God, <idiom-start/>by observing<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to observe”</note> his commandments and his statutes that he commanded you. <verse-number id="Dt 28:46">46</verse-number>And they shall be among you as a sign and as a wonder and among your offspring <idiom-start/>forever<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “until eternity,” but not in a timeless, philosophic sense</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 28:47">47</verse-number>“<idiom-start/>Because<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Under”</note> <supplied>of the fact</supplied> that you did not serve Yahweh your God with joy and with gladness of heart for the abundance of everything, <verse-number id="Dt 28:48">48</verse-number>then you shall serve your enemies, whom Yahweh will send against you <supplied>under conditions of</supplied> famine, in thirst, in nakedness, and in <supplied>a</supplied> lack of everything; and he shall place<note>Literally “give”</note> a yoke of iron on your neck <idiom-start/>until he has destroyed you<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “until his destroying of you”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 28:49">49</verse-number>Yahweh will raise <supplied>up</supplied> against you a nation from far <supplied>off</supplied>, from the end of the earth, <supplied>attacking</supplied> as the eagle swoops <supplied>down</supplied>, <idiom-start/>a nation whose language you will not understand<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “a nation who not you will understand its language”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 28:50">50</verse-number><idiom-start/>a grim-faced nation<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a nation fierce/determined of face”</note> <idiom-start/>who does not show respect<idiom-end/><note>Literally “who not lifts up face<supplied>s</supplied>”</note> to <supplied>the</supplied> old and <supplied>the</supplied> young <supplied>and</supplied> does not show pity. <verse-number id="Dt 28:51">51</verse-number>And it<note>That is, the invading nation</note> shall consume the fruit of your livestock and the fruit of your ground <idiom-start/>until you are destroyed<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “until your destroying”</note> <supplied>and</supplied> who will not leave for you <supplied>any</supplied> grain, wine, and olive oil, <idiom-start/>calves of your herds<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “what is dropped of your herds”</note> and <idiom-start/>lambs of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the offspring of small animals”</note> your flock <idiom-start/>until it has destroyed you<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “until his to destroy you”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 28:52">52</verse-number>And it shall besiege you in all your towns <idiom-start/>until your high and fortified walls fall<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “until the coming down of your walls, high and fortified”</note> which you <supplied>are</supplied> trusting in<note>Hebrew “in them,” which is redundant</note> <idiom-start/>throughout your land<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “in all of your land”</note> and it shall besiege you in all of your towns in all of your land that Yahweh your God has given to you. <verse-number id="Dt 28:53">53</verse-number>And you shall eat the fruit of your womb, the flesh of your sons and your daughters, whom Yahweh your God gave to you, <idiom-start/>during the siege and during the distress<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in siege and in distress”</note> your enemy inflicts upon you. <verse-number id="Dt 28:54">54</verse-number>The most refined and the very sensitive<note>Or “kindly disposed”</note> man among you <idiom-start/>shall be mean with his brother<idiom-end/><note>Literally “shall be bad/evil his eye against his brother”</note> and <idiom-start/>against his beloved wife<idiom-end/><note>Literally “against the wife of his lap”</note> and against the rest<note>Or “remainder”</note> of his children that he has left over, <verse-number id="Dt 28:55">55</verse-number><idiom-start/>by refraining from giving<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from giving”</note> to <supplied>even</supplied> one of them any of the meat of his children that he eats, because <supplied>there is</supplied> not anything <supplied>that is</supplied> left over for him <idiom-start/>during the siege and distress<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the siege and distress”</note> that your enemy inflicts upon you. <verse-number id="Dt 28:56">56</verse-number>The most refined and the <supplied>most</supplied> delicate <supplied>woman</supplied> among you, who shall<note>Or “would”</note> not venture to put the sole of her foot on the ground from being <supplied>so</supplied> delicate and from <supplied>such</supplied> gentleness, <idiom-start/>shall be mean to her beloved husband<idiom-end/><note>Literally “shall be bad her eye against the husband of her lap”</note> and against her son and against her daughter, <verse-number id="Dt 28:57">57</verse-number>and <supplied>even</supplied> concerning her afterbirth <idiom-start/>that goes out<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the going out”</note> from between her feet and <supplied>also</supplied> concerning her children that she bears, because she eats them for lack of anything in secret <idiom-start/>during the siege and during the distress<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the siege and in the distress”</note> that your enemy inflicts upon her in your <idiom-start/>towns<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “gates”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 28:58">58</verse-number>“If <idiom-start/>you do not diligently observe<idiom-end/><note>Literally “you observe to do”</note> all the words of this law written in this scroll by revering this glorious and awesome name, Yahweh your God, <verse-number id="Dt 28:59">59</verse-number>then Yahweh shall overwhelm <supplied>you</supplied> with your plagues and the plagues of your offspring, severe plagues and lasting illnesses, grievous and enduring. <verse-number id="Dt 28:60">60</verse-number>And he shall bring back upon you all the diseases of Egypt <supplied>concerning</supplied> which <idiom-start/>you were in dread<idiom-end/><note>Literally “you dreaded”</note> <idiom-start/>because of them<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “from their presence”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 28:61">61</verse-number>Also any illness and any plague<note>Or “each illness and each plague”</note> that <supplied>is</supplied> not written in the scroll of this law, he shall bring them, Yahweh, upon you until you are destroyed. <verse-number id="Dt 28:62">62</verse-number>And you shall remain <idiom-start/>only a few people<idiom-end/><note>Literally “with people of few”</note> in place of <supplied>the fact</supplied> you were <supplied>formerly</supplied> as the stars of heaven as far as number <supplied>is concerned</supplied>, because you did not listen to the voice of Yahweh your God. <verse-number id="Dt 28:63">63</verse-number><idiom-start/>And then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And it will happen”</note> as Yahweh delighted over you <idiom-start/>to make you prosperous<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to do good with you”</note> to make you numerous, so Yahweh shall delight over you to exterminate you<note>Or “to cause you to perish”</note> and to destroy you, and <supplied>so</supplied> you shall be plucked from the land that you <supplied>are</supplied> going there to take possession of it. <verse-number id="Dt 28:64">64</verse-number>And Yahweh shall scatter you among all the nations from <supplied>one</supplied> end of the earth up to the <supplied>other</supplied> end of the earth, and there you shall serve other gods that you have not known nor<note>Hebrew “and”</note> your ancestors,<note>Or “your fathers”</note> <supplied>gods of</supplied> wood and stone. <verse-number id="Dt 28:65">65</verse-number>And among these nations you shall not find rest, and <supplied>there</supplied> shall not be a resting place for the sole of your foot, and Yahweh shall give you there an anxious heart and a weakening of eyes<note>Or “a failure of eyes”</note> and a languishing of <supplied>your</supplied> inner self.<note>Or “soul”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 28:66">66</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>your life shall hang in doubt before you<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “they shall be your life hanging for you in front”</note> and you shall be startled<note>Or “in fear”</note> night and day, and you shall not be confident of your life. <verse-number id="Dt 28:67">67</verse-number>In the morning you shall say, ‘<idiom-start/>If only it was evening<idiom-end/>!’<note>Literally “Who shall give evening?”</note> and in the evening you shall say ‘<idiom-start/>If only it was morning<idiom-end/>!’<note>Literally “Who shall give morning?”</note> because of the dread of your heart that you shall feel, and because of the sight of your eyes that you shall see. <verse-number id="Dt 28:68">68</verse-number>And Yahweh shall bring you back <supplied>to</supplied> Egypt in ships by the route that I <idiom-start/>promised<idiom-end/><note>Literally “spoke”</note> to you <supplied>that</supplied> ‘<idiom-start/>You shall not see it again<idiom-end/>!’<note>Literally “you shall not do again further to see it/her”</note> And you shall sell yourself there to your enemies as slaves and as female slaves, but there will not be a buyer.” </p>
		</chapter>