<chapter id="Dt 29">
			<pericope>Covenant Renewal, Oaths, Restoration, Charges to the Nation</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 29:1">1</verse-number><note><cite title="BibleLEB2: Dt 29:1–29">Deuteronomy 29:1–29 </cite>in the English Bible is 28.69–29:28 in the Hebrew Bible</note> These <supplied>are</supplied> the words of the covenant that Yahweh commanded Moses to make with the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> in the land of Moab <idiom-start/>besides<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from to alone”</note> the covenant that he made with them at Horeb. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 29:2">2</verse-number>And Moses summoned all of Israel and said to them, “You saw all that Yahweh did before your eyes in the land of Egypt and to Pharaoh and to all his servants and to all his land; <verse-number id="Dt 29:3">3</verse-number><supplied>that is</supplied>, the great trials that your eyes saw, <supplied>and</supplied> those great signs and wonders. <verse-number id="Dt 29:4">4</verse-number>But Yahweh has not given to you a heart to understand, or eyes to see, or ears to hear, <supplied>even</supplied> <idiom-start/>to this day<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “until the day the this”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 29:5">5</verse-number>And I have led you forty years<note>Hebrew “year”</note> in the desert; your clothes <supplied>have</supplied> not worn out <idiom-start/>on you<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from on you”</note> and your sandal has not worn out <idiom-start/>on your foot<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “from on your foot”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 29:6">6</verse-number>You have not eaten bread, and you have not drunk wine and strong drink, so that you may know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh your God. <verse-number id="Dt 29:7">7</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied> you came to this place <supplied>then</supplied> Sihon the king of Heshbon, and Og the king of Bashan, came out to meet you for battle, and we defeated them. <verse-number id="Dt 29:8">8</verse-number>And we took their land and gave it as <supplied>an</supplied> inheritance to the Reubenites<note>Hebrew “Reubenite”</note> and to the Gadites<note>Hebrew “Gadite”</note> and to <supplied>the</supplied> half-tribe of Manasseh. <verse-number id="Dt 29:9">9</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>you must diligently observe the words of this covenant<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “you must keep the words of the covenant the this and you must do them”</note> so that you may succeed in all that you do. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 29:10">10</verse-number>“You <supplied>are</supplied> standing <idiom-start/>today<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the day”</note> all of you, <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of”</note> Yahweh your God, your leaders, your tribes, your elders, and your officials, all the men of Israel, <verse-number id="Dt 29:11">11</verse-number>your little children, your women and your aliens<note>Hebrew “alien”</note> who <supplied>are</supplied> in the midst of your camp, from the choppers<note>Hebrew “chopper”</note> of your wood to the drawers<note>Hebrew “drawer”</note> of your water, <verse-number id="Dt 29:12">12</verse-number><idiom-start/>in order for you to enter into the covenant of Yahweh your God<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “for you to go over into the covenant of Yahweh your God”</note> and into<note>Or “with”</note> his oath that Yahweh your God <supplied>is</supplied> <idiom-start/>making with you<idiom-end/><note>Literally “cutting with you”</note> <idiom-start/>today<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the day”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 29:13">13</verse-number>in order to establish you <idiom-start/>today<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the day”</note> <idiom-start/>to himself<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for him”</note> as a people and <supplied>so that</supplied> he may be for you <supplied>as</supplied> God, <supplied>just</supplied> as he <idiom-start/>promised<idiom-end/><note>Literally “spoke”</note> to you and <idiom-start/>just as<idiom-end/><note>Literally “according to that which”</note> he swore to your ancestors,<note>Or “your fathers”</note> to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 29:14">14</verse-number>“Now I am not <idiom-start/>making this covenant<idiom-end/><note>Literally “cutting this covenant”</note> and this oath <idiom-start/>with you alone<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “with you to alone you”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 29:15">15</verse-number>But with <idiom-start/>whoever is standing here<idiom-end/><note>Literally “with who he is here with us standing”</note> with us <idiom-start/>today<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the day”</note> <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of”</note> Yahweh our God, and with <idiom-start/>whoever is not standing here<idiom-end/><note>Literally “with who he is not standing here with us”</note> with us <idiom-start/>today<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the day”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 29:16">16</verse-number>For you know how we lived in the land of Egypt and how we traveled through the midst of the nations that you traveled<note>Or “journeyed”</note> through. <verse-number id="Dt 29:17">17</verse-number>And you have seen their detestable things and their idols of wood and stone, silver, and gold that <supplied>were</supplied> among them, <verse-number id="Dt 29:18">18</verse-number>so that <idiom-start/>there is not<idiom-end/><note>Literally “lest there be/develop”</note> among you a man or a woman or a clan or a tribe <idiom-start/>whose heart<idiom-end/><note>Literally “his heart”</note> turns <idiom-start/>today<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the day”</note> from <supplied>being</supplied> with Yahweh our God to go to serve the gods of these nations, so that there is not among you a root sprouting poison and wormwood. <verse-number id="Dt 29:19">19</verse-number>And then when he hears the words of this oath, then<note>Or “and”</note> <idiom-start/>he will assure himself<idiom-end/><note>Literally “he will bless himself”; HALOT 160 suggests “to consider oneself fortunate”</note> in his heart, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> ‘<idiom-start/>Safety shall be mine even though I go in the stubbornness of my heart<idiom-end/>,’<note>Literally “Peace shall happen/be for me, although/even if in the stubbornness of my heart I go”</note> thereby destroying the well-watered <supplied>land</supplied> <supplied>along</supplied> with the parched.<note>Some translators prefer to include the last clause as a part of the words of the wicked man (NASV vs. NEB)</note> <verse-number id="Dt 29:20">20</verse-number>Yahweh will not be willing to forgive him, for <supplied>by then</supplied> the anger of Yahweh will smoke, and his passion against that man and all the curses written in this scroll will descend on him, and Yahweh will blot out his name from under heaven. <verse-number id="Dt 29:21">21</verse-number>And Yahweh will single him out for calamity out of all the tribes of Israel, according to all the curses of the covenant written in the scroll of this law. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 29:22">22</verse-number>“And the next generation, <supplied>that is</supplied>, your children who will rise <supplied>up</supplied> after you, and the foreigner who will come from a distant land, when<note>Hebrew “and”</note> they will see the plagues of that land and its diseases that Yahweh has inflicted upon it, will say, <verse-number id="Dt 29:23">23</verse-number>‘All its land is brimstone and salt left by fire, <idiom-start/>none of its land will be sown<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “all of its land will not be sown”</note> and it will not make plants sprout out and it will not grow any vegetation; <supplied>it is</supplied> as the destruction of Sodom and Gomorrah, Adman and Zeboiim, which Yahweh overturned in his anger and in his wrath.’ <verse-number id="Dt 29:24">24</verse-number>And all the nations will say, ‘<idiom-start/>Why<idiom-end/><note>Literally “On what <supplied>basis</supplied>”</note> has Yahweh done <idiom-start/>such a thing<idiom-end/><note>Literally “so”</note> to this land? What <supplied>caused</supplied> the fierceness of this great anger?’ <verse-number id="Dt 29:25">25</verse-number>And they will say,<note>Or “answer/respond”</note> ‘<supplied>It is</supplied> because they abandoned the covenant of Yahweh, the God of their ancestors,<note>Or “fathers”</note> which he <idiom-start/>made<idiom-end/><note>Literally “cut”</note> with them <idiom-start/>when he brought them out<idiom-end/><note>Literally “at/in his to bring them out from the land of Egypt”</note> from the land of Egypt. <verse-number id="Dt 29:26">26</verse-number>And they went and served other gods and bowed down to them, gods whom they did not know them and he<note>That is, Yahweh</note> had not allotted to them. <verse-number id="Dt 29:27">27</verse-number>So <idiom-start/>the anger of Yahweh was kindled<idiom-end/><note>Literally “became hot the nose of Yahweh”</note> against that land to bring upon it all the curses written in this scroll, <verse-number id="Dt 29:28">28</verse-number>and Yahweh uprooted them from their land in anger and in wrath and in great fury, and he cast them into another land, <idiom-start/>just as it is today<idiom-end/>.’<note>Literally “as the day the this”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 29:29">29</verse-number>“The hidden <supplied>things</supplied> <idiom-start/>belong to Yahweh<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<supplied>are</supplied> for Yahweh”</note> our God, but the revealed <supplied>things</supplied> <idiom-start/>belong to us<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<supplied>are</supplied> for us”</note> <supplied>to know</supplied> and to our children <idiom-start/>forever<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “until eternity”</note> <supplied>in order</supplied> to do all the words of this law.” </p>
		</chapter>