<chapter id="Dt 34">
			<pericope>The Death of Moses and the Commissioning of Joshua</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 34:1">1</verse-number>Then Moses went up from the desert plateau<note>Or “plains/lowlands”</note> of Moab to Mount Nebo, to the top of Pisgah, <idiom-start/>which is opposite<idiom-end/><note>Literally “which is on the face of”</note> Jericho, and Yahweh showed him all of the land, Gilead <supplied>all the way</supplied> up to Dan, <verse-number id="Dt 34:2">2</verse-number>and all of Naphtali and the land of Ephraim and Manasseh and all of the land of Judah, up to the western sea,<note>That is, the Mediterranean Sea</note> <verse-number id="Dt 34:3">3</verse-number>and the Negev and the plain of the valley of Jericho, the city of palms, <supplied>on</supplied> up to Zoar. <verse-number id="Dt 34:4">4</verse-number>And Yahweh said to him, “This <supplied>is</supplied> the land that I swore to Abraham to Isaac and to Jacob, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> ‘To your offspring I will give it.’ I have let you see <supplied>it</supplied> with your eyes, but you shall not cross <idiom-start/>into it<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “to there”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 34:5">5</verse-number>Then Moses, the servant of Yahweh, died there in the land of Moab <idiom-start/>according to the command of Yahweh<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “at the mouth of Yahweh”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 34:6">6</verse-number>And he<note>That is, Yahweh</note> buried him in the valley in the land of Moab opposite Beth Peor. But until this day no one knows his burial site. <verse-number id="Dt 34:7">7</verse-number><idiom-start/>Now Moses was a hundred and twenty years old<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and Moses <supplied>was</supplied> a son of <supplied>a</supplied> hundred and twenty year”</note> <idiom-start/>when he died<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “at/in his dying”</note> <idiom-start/>his sight was not impaired and his vigor had not abated<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “not faded his eyes and not had fled away his vitality”</note> <verse-number id="Dt 34:8">8</verse-number>And the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> wept <supplied>concerning</supplied> Moses thirty days; <supplied>finally</supplied> the days of weeping and mourning for Moses were completed. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Dt 34:9">9</verse-number>Now<note>Or “And”</note> Joshua the son of Nun was full of the spirit of wisdom because Moses had placed his hands on him, and the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> listened to him, and they did as Yahweh had commanded Moses. <verse-number id="Dt 34:10">10</verse-number>And not again<note>Or “since then”</note> has a prophet arisen in Israel like Moses, whom Yahweh knew<note>Hebrew “knew him”</note> face to face, <verse-number id="Dt 34:11">11</verse-number>as far as all the signs and the wonders Yahweh sent him to do in the land of Egypt, against<note>Hebrew “to”</note> Pharaoh and all of his servants and against<note>Hebrew “to”</note> all of his land, <verse-number id="Dt 34:12">12</verse-number>and as far as all of <idiom-start/>the mighty deeds<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the hand the strong”</note> and as far as <idiom-start/>the great awesome wonders<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the terrifying the great <supplied>actions</supplied>”</note> Moses did before the eyes of all Israel. </p>
		</chapter>