<chapter id="Php 1">
			<pericope>Greeting</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Php 1:1">1</verse-number> Paul and Timothy, slaves of Christ Jesus, to all the saints in Christ Jesus who are in Philippi, together with the overseers and deacons. <verse-number id="Php 1:2">2</verse-number>Grace to you and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Thanksgiving</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Php 1:3">3</verse-number>I give thanks to my God upon my every remembrance of you,<note>Or “upon your every remembrance <supplied>of me</supplied>”</note> <verse-number id="Php 1:4">4</verse-number>always in my every prayer for all of you, making the prayer with joy, <verse-number id="Php 1:5">5</verse-number>because of your participation in the gospel from the first day until now, <verse-number id="Php 1:6">6</verse-number>convinced of this same <supplied>thing</supplied>, that the one who began a good work in you will finish <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> until the day of Christ Jesus, <verse-number id="Php 1:7">7</verse-number>just as it is right for me to think this about all of you, because I have you in my heart, <supplied>since</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “since” is supplied as a component of the participle (“are”) which is understood as causal</note> both in my imprisonment and in the defense and confirmation of the gospel all of you are sharers of grace with me. <verse-number id="Php 1:8">8</verse-number>For God <supplied>is</supplied> my witness, that I long for all of you with the affection of Christ Jesus. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Prayer for Spiritual Maturity</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Php 1:9">9</verse-number>And this I pray: that your love may abound still more and more in knowledge and all discernment, <verse-number id="Php 1:10">10</verse-number>so that you may approve what is superior, in order that you may be sincere and blameless in<note>Or “for,” or “until”</note> the day of Christ, <verse-number id="Php 1:11">11</verse-number>having been filled <supplied>with the</supplied> fruit of righteousness which <supplied>comes</supplied> through Jesus Christ to the glory and praise of God. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Progress of the Gospel</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Php 1:12">12</verse-number>Now I want you to know, brothers, that <idiom-start/>my circumstances<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the things with me”</note> have happened instead for the progress of the gospel, <verse-number id="Php 1:13">13</verse-number>so that my imprisonment in Christ has become known in the whole praetorium<note>Or “praetorian guard,” or “imperial guard”</note> and to all the rest, <verse-number id="Php 1:14">14</verse-number>and most of the brothers, trusting in the Lord because of my imprisonment, dare <supplied>even</supplied> more to speak the word without fear. <verse-number id="Php 1:15">15</verse-number>Some even because of envy and strife preach Christ, but some also because of good will. <verse-number id="Php 1:16">16</verse-number>The latter <supplied>do so</supplied> from love, knowing that I am appointed for the defense of the gospel. <verse-number id="Php 1:17">17</verse-number>The former proclaim Christ from selfish ambition, not sincerely, thinking to raise up affliction in my imprisonment. <verse-number id="Php 1:18">18</verse-number><idiom-start/>What is the result?<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for what”</note> Only that in every way, whether in pretense or in truth, Christ is proclaimed, and in this I rejoice. But also I will rejoice, <verse-number id="Php 1:19">19</verse-number>for I know that this will turn out to me for deliverance through your prayer and the support of the Spirit of Jesus Christ, <verse-number id="Php 1:20">20</verse-number>according to my eager expectation and hope, that I will be put to shame in nothing, but with all boldness, even now as always Christ will be exalted in my body, whether through life or through death. <verse-number id="Php 1:21">21</verse-number>For to me to live <supplied>is</supplied> Christ and to die <supplied>is</supplied> gain. <verse-number id="Php 1:22">22</verse-number>But if <supplied>it is</supplied> to live in the flesh, this <supplied>is</supplied> fruitful work for me, and which I will prefer <supplied>I do</supplied> not know. <verse-number id="Php 1:23">23</verse-number>But I am hard pressed <idiom-start/>between the two options<idiom-end/><note>Literally “by the two”</note>, having the desire to depart and to be with Christ, <idiom-start/>for this is very much better<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for <supplied>this is</supplied> more better by much”</note>. <verse-number id="Php 1:24">24</verse-number>But to stay on in the flesh <supplied>is</supplied> more necessary for your sake. <verse-number id="Php 1:25">25</verse-number>And because I am<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “because” is supplied as a component of the participle (“convinced”) which is understood as causal</note> convinced of this, I know that I will remain and continue with all of you for your progress and joy in the faith, <verse-number id="Php 1:26">26</verse-number>so that <supplied>what</supplied> you can be proud of may increase in Christ Jesus because of me through my return again to you. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Stand Firm for the Gospel</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Php 1:27">27</verse-number>Only lead your lives in a manner worthy of the gospel of Christ, so that whether I come and see you or am absent I hear <idiom-start/>your circumstances<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the things concerning you”</note>, that you are standing firm in one spirit, with one soul contending side by side for the faith of the gospel, <verse-number id="Php 1:28">28</verse-number>and not letting yourselves be intimidated in anything by your opponents, which is a sign of destruction to them, but of your salvation, and this from God, <verse-number id="Php 1:29">29</verse-number>because to you has been graciously granted on behalf of Christ not only to believe in him, but also to suffer on behalf of him, <verse-number id="Php 1:30">30</verse-number>having the same struggle which you saw in me and now hear about in me. </p>
		</chapter>