<chapter id="Php 2">
			<pericope>Humility and Unity</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Php 2:1">1</verse-number> Therefore, if <supplied>there is</supplied> any encouragement in Christ, if any consolation of love, if any fellowship of the Spirit, if any affection and compassion, <verse-number id="Php 2:2">2</verse-number>complete my joy, so that <idiom-start/>you are in agreement<idiom-end/><note>Literally “you think the same <supplied>thing</supplied></note>, having the same love, united in spirit, <idiom-start/>having one purpose<idiom-end/><note>Literally “thinking the one <supplied>thing</supplied>”</note>. <verse-number id="Php 2:3">3</verse-number><supplied>Do</supplied> nothing according to selfish ambition or according to empty conceit, but in humility considering one another better than yourselves, <verse-number id="Php 2:4">4</verse-number>each of you<note>Some manuscripts have “each one of you”</note> not looking out for <idiom-start/>your own interests<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the things of yourselves”</note>, but also each of you <supplied>for</supplied> <idiom-start/>the interests<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the things”</note> of others. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Christ’s Humiliation and Exaltation</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Php 2:5">5</verse-number>Think this in<note>Or “among”</note> yourselves which <supplied>was</supplied> also in Christ Jesus, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Php 2:6">6</verse-number>who, existing in the form of God, </li1>
				<li2>did not consider being equal with God something to be grasped, </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Php 2:7">7</verse-number>but emptied himself </li1>
				<li2><supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “by” is supplied as a component of the participle (“taking”) which is understood as means</note> taking the form of a slave, </li2>
				<li2><supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “by” is supplied as a component of the participle (“becoming”) which is understood as means</note> becoming in the likeness of people. </li2>
				<li1>And being found in appearance like a man, </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Php 2:8">8</verse-number>he humbled himself </li1>
				<li2><supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “by” is supplied as a component of the participle (“becoming”) which is understood as means</note> becoming obedient to the point of death, </li2>
				<li3>that is, death on a cross. </li3>
				<li1><verse-number id="Php 2:9">9</verse-number>Therefore also God exalted him </li1>
				<li2>and graciously granted him the name above every name, </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Php 2:10">10</verse-number>so that at the name of Jesus </li1>
				<li1>every knee should bow, </li1>
				<li2>of <supplied>those</supplied> in heaven and of <supplied>those</supplied> on earth and of <supplied>those</supplied> under the earth, </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Php 2:11">11</verse-number>and every tongue confess </li1>
				<li1>that Jesus Christ <supplied>is</supplied> Lord, </li1>
				<li2>to the glory of God the Father. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Holding Fast to the Word of Life</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Php 2:12">12</verse-number>Therefore my dear friends, just as you have always obeyed, not as in my presence only but now much more in my absence, work out your own salvation with fear and trembling. <verse-number id="Php 2:13">13</verse-number>For the one at work in you, both to will and to work for his good pleasure, is God. <verse-number id="Php 2:14">14</verse-number>Do all <supplied>things</supplied> without grumbling and disputing, <verse-number id="Php 2:15">15</verse-number>in order that you may become blameless and innocent, children of God without fault<note>Or “blameless”</note> in the midst of a crooked and perverted generation, among whom you shine as stars in the world,<note>Or possibly “in the universe”</note> <verse-number id="Php 2:16">16</verse-number>holding fast to the word of life, for a source of pride<note>Or “for a cause of boasting”</note> to me in the day of Christ, that I did not run in vain or labor in vain. <verse-number id="Php 2:17">17</verse-number>But even if I am being poured out as a drink offering on the sacrifice and service of your faith, I rejoice and rejoice with all of you. <verse-number id="Php 2:18">18</verse-number>And <supplied>in</supplied> the same <supplied>way</supplied> also you rejoice and rejoice with me. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Timothy’s Proven Character</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Php 2:19">19</verse-number>But I hope in the Lord Jesus to send Timothy to you soon, so that I also may be encouraged <supplied>when I</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “when” is supplied as a component of the participle (“know”) which is understood as temporal</note> know <idiom-start/>your circumstances<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the things concerning you”</note>. <verse-number id="Php 2:20">20</verse-number>For I have no one like-minded who <supplied>will</supplied> sincerely be concerned about <idiom-start/>your circumstances<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the things concerning you”</note>. <verse-number id="Php 2:21">21</verse-number>For they all seek <idiom-start/>their own interests<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the things of themselves”</note>, not those of Jesus Christ. <verse-number id="Php 2:22">22</verse-number>But you know his proven character, that like a child with a father he served with me for the gospel. <verse-number id="Php 2:23">23</verse-number>Therefore I hope to send him at once, as soon as I see <idiom-start/>my circumstances<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the things concerning me”</note>. <verse-number id="Php 2:24">24</verse-number>And I am convinced in the Lord that I myself will arrive shortly also. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Epaphroditus’ Mission</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Php 2:25">25</verse-number>But I considered <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> necessary to send to you Epaphroditus, my brother and fellow worker and fellow soldier, but your messenger and servant of my need, <verse-number id="Php 2:26">26</verse-number>because he was longing for all of you and was distressed because you had heard that he was sick. <verse-number id="Php 2:27">27</verse-number>For indeed he was sick, coming near to death, but God had mercy on him and not <supplied>on</supplied> him only, but also <supplied>on</supplied> me, so that I would not have grief upon grief. <verse-number id="Php 2:28">28</verse-number>Therefore I am sending him with special urgency, in order that <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “when” is supplied as a component of the participle (“see”) which is understood as temporal</note> you see him again you may rejoice, and I may be less anxious. <verse-number id="Php 2:29">29</verse-number>Therefore welcome him in the Lord with all joy, and consider such <supplied>people</supplied> highly honored, <verse-number id="Php 2:30">30</verse-number>because on account of the work of Christ he came near to the point of death, risking his life in order that <idiom-start/>he might make up for your inability to serve me<idiom-end/><note>Literally “he might fill up your lack of service to me”</note>. </p>
		</chapter>