<chapter id="Php 4">
			<pericope>Appeal for Unity</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Php 4:1">1</verse-number> So then, my beloved and greatly desired brothers, my joy and crown, thus stand firm in the Lord, dear friends. <verse-number id="Php 4:2">2</verse-number>I appeal to Euodia and I appeal to Syntyche <idiom-start/>to be in agreement<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to think the same <supplied>thing</supplied>”</note> in the Lord. <verse-number id="Php 4:3">3</verse-number>Yes, I ask also you, true yokefellow, help them, who struggled along with me in the gospel with both Clement and the rest of my fellow workers whose names <supplied>are</supplied> in the book of life. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Be Anxious for Nothing</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Php 4:4">4</verse-number>Rejoice in the Lord always; again I say, rejoice. <verse-number id="Php 4:5">5</verse-number>Let your gentleness be made known to all people. The Lord <supplied>is</supplied> near. <verse-number id="Php 4:6">6</verse-number>Be anxious for nothing, but in everything by prayer and supplication with thanksgiving let your requests be made known to God. <verse-number id="Php 4:7">7</verse-number>And the peace of God that surpasses all understanding will guard your hearts and your minds<note>Or “thoughts”</note> in Christ Jesus. <verse-number id="Php 4:8">8</verse-number>Finally, brothers, whatever <supplied>things</supplied> are true, whatever <supplied>things are</supplied> honorable, whatever <supplied>things are</supplied> right, whatever <supplied>things are</supplied> pure, whatever <supplied>things are</supplied> pleasing, whatever <supplied>things are</supplied> commendable, if <supplied>there is</supplied> any excellence of character and if anything praiseworthy, think about these <supplied>things</supplied>. <verse-number id="Php 4:9">9</verse-number>And <supplied>the things</supplied> which you have learned and received and heard about and seen in me, practice these <supplied>things</supplied>, and the God of peace will be with you. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Support for Paul’s Ministry</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Php 4:10">10</verse-number>But I rejoiced in the Lord greatly that now at last <idiom-start/>you have renewed your concern for me<idiom-end/><note>Literally “you have revived to think on behalf of me”</note>, for whom also you were thinking, but you had no opportunity <supplied>to express it</supplied>. <verse-number id="Php 4:11">11</verse-number>Not that I speak from need, for I have learned to be content in whatever <supplied>circumstances</supplied> I am. <verse-number id="Php 4:12">12</verse-number>I know <supplied>how</supplied> both <idiom-start/>to make do with little<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to be humbled”</note> and I know <supplied>how</supplied> <idiom-start/>to have an abundance<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to abound”</note>. In everything and in all <supplied>things</supplied> I have learned the secret both to be filled and to be hungry, both <idiom-start/>to have an abundance<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to abound”</note> and to go without. <verse-number id="Php 4:13">13</verse-number>I am able <supplied>to do</supplied> all <supplied>things</supplied> by the one who strengthens me. <verse-number id="Php 4:14">14</verse-number>Nevertheless you have done well by sharing<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “by” is supplied as a component of the participle (“sharing”) which is understood as means</note> with me in my affliction. <verse-number id="Php 4:15">15</verse-number>Now you also know, Philippians, that at the beginning of the gospel, when I departed from Macedonia, no church shared with me in the matter of giving and receiving except you alone, <verse-number id="Php 4:16">16</verse-number>because even in Thessalonica <idiom-start/>on more than one occasion<idiom-end/><note>Literally “both once and twice”</note> you sent for my need. <verse-number id="Php 4:17">17</verse-number>Not that I seek the gift, but I seek for the profit that increases to your account. <verse-number id="Php 4:18">18</verse-number>But I have received everything <supplied>in full</supplied> and have an abundance; <idiom-start/>I am well supplied<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I have been made full”</note> <supplied>because</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “because” is supplied as a component of the participle (“received”) which is understood as causal</note> I received from Epaphroditus <idiom-start/>what you had sent<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the things from you”</note>, a fragrant offering, an acceptable sacrifice, well-pleasing to God. <verse-number id="Php 4:19">19</verse-number>And my God will fulfill your every need according to his riches in glory in Christ Jesus. <verse-number id="Php 4:20">20</verse-number>Now to our God and Father <supplied>be</supplied> the glory <idiom-start/>forever and ever<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the ages of the ages”</note>. Amen. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Final Greetings and Benediction</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Php 4:21">21</verse-number>Greet every saint in Christ Jesus. The brothers with me greet you. <verse-number id="Php 4:22">22</verse-number>All the saints greet you, and especially those of Caesar’s household. <verse-number id="Php 4:23">23</verse-number>The grace of the Lord Jesus Christ <supplied>be</supplied> with your spirit. </p>
		</chapter>