<chapter id="1 Ki 2">
			<pericope>David’s Instructions for Solomon</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 2:1">1</verse-number>The days of David came near <supplied>for him</supplied> to die, and he charged Solomon his son, saying, <verse-number id="1 Ki 2:2">2</verse-number>“I <supplied>am about to</supplied> go the way of all the world. Be strong and be <idiom-start/>courageous<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “as a man”</note> <verse-number id="1 Ki 2:3">3</verse-number>You shall keep the charge of Yahweh your God, to walk in his ways, to keep his statutes, his commandments, his judgments, and his testimonies, as are written in the law of Moses, so that you may prosper in all that you do and everywhere you turn, <verse-number id="1 Ki 2:4">4</verse-number>so that Yahweh may establish his word which he spoke concerning me, saying, ‘If your sons take heed of their way, to walk before me in faithfulness, with all their heart and with all their soul, no man of yours will be cut off from the throne of Israel.’ ” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 2:5">5</verse-number>“Moreover, you also know what Joab the son of Zeruiah did to me when he dealt with the two commanders of the armies of Israel, to Abner son of Ner and to Amasa son of Jether, and he murdered them and put the blood of war in <supplied>a time of</supplied> peace. He put the blood of war on the leather belt that was on his waist and on the sandals which were on his feet. <verse-number id="1 Ki 2:6">6</verse-number>You must act according to your wisdom, but you must not let his gray hair go down to Sheol in peace. <verse-number id="1 Ki 2:7">7</verse-number>Regarding the sons of Barzillai the Gileadite, you shall do loyal love and let them be among those who eat at your table, because they met me when I fled from Absalom your brother. <verse-number id="1 Ki 2:8">8</verse-number>And look, Shimei the son of Gera the son of the Benjaminite from Bahurim is with you. Now he <idiom-start/>cursed me severely<idiom-end/><note>Literally “cursed me <supplied>with</supplied> a curse”</note> when I went to Mahanaim, but he came down to meet me at the Jordan, so I swore to him by Yahweh, ‘I surely will not kill you with the sword.’ <verse-number id="1 Ki 2:9">9</verse-number>So then, do not leave him unpunished, for you <supplied>are</supplied> a wise man, and you will know what you must do to him. You must bring his grey hair down to Sheol with blood.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 2:10">10</verse-number>Then David slept with his ancestors<note>Or “fathers”</note> and was buried in the city of David. <verse-number id="1 Ki 2:11">11</verse-number>The days that David reigned over Israel <supplied>were</supplied> forty years; he reigned seven years in Hebron and thirty-three years in Jerusalem. <verse-number id="1 Ki 2:12">12</verse-number>Then Solomon sat on the throne of David his father, and his kingdom was firmly established. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Adonijah’s Persistence</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 2:13">13</verse-number>Adonijah the son of Haggith came to Bathsheba the mother of Solomon, and she said, “<idiom-start/>Are you coming in peace<idiom-end/>?”<note>Literally “<supplied>Is</supplied> peace your coming?”</note> He said, “Peace.” <verse-number id="1 Ki 2:14">14</verse-number>Then he said, “<idiom-start/>May I have a word with you<idiom-end/>?”<note>Literally “A word is for me to you”</note> Then she said, “Go on.” <verse-number id="1 Ki 2:15">15</verse-number>He said, “You know that the kingship was mine and that all Israel had set their face toward me as king, but the kingship turned around and became my brother’s, for it was from Yahweh for him <supplied>to have it</supplied>. <verse-number id="1 Ki 2:16">16</verse-number>Now one request I am asking from you, and you must <idiom-start/>not refuse me<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “not turn my face”</note> Then she said to him, “Go on.” <verse-number id="1 Ki 2:17">17</verse-number>He said, “Please speak to King Solomon, for he will not refuse you, so that he will give to me Abishag the Shunnamite as wife.” <verse-number id="1 Ki 2:18">18</verse-number>Then Bathsheba said, “Very well, I will speak to the king concerning you.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Solomon’s Responses to Adonijah, Joab, and Shimei</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 2:19">19</verse-number>Bathsheba came to King Solomon to speak to him concerning Adonijah, and the king got up to meet her, bowed down to her, and then sat on his throne. Then he set up a throne for the king’s mother, and she sat on his right. <verse-number id="1 Ki 2:20">20</verse-number>She said, “I have one small request I am asking from you. Do <idiom-start/>not refuse me<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “not turn my face”</note> The king said to her, “Ask, my mother, for I will <idiom-start/>not refuse you<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “not turn your face”</note> <verse-number id="1 Ki 2:21">21</verse-number>Then she said, “Let Abishag the Shunnamite be given to Adonijah your brother as wife.” <verse-number id="1 Ki 2:22">22</verse-number>King Solomon answered and said to his mother, “Why are you asking Abishag the Shunnamite for Adonijah? Ask for him also the kingdom, for he is my brother, older than I; and <supplied>ask</supplied> for him also Abiathar the priest, and for Joab the son of Zeruiah.” <verse-number id="1 Ki 2:23">23</verse-number>Then King Solomon swore by Yahweh, saying, “Thus may God do to me and thus may he add, if Adonijah hasn’t spoken this thing at the expense of his life. <verse-number id="1 Ki 2:24">24</verse-number>So then, <idiom-start/>as Yahweh lives<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the life of Yahweh”</note> who has established me and seated me on the throne of my father David and who has established for me a dynasty as he promised, then surely Adonijah will be put to death today.” <verse-number id="1 Ki 2:25">25</verse-number>King Solomon sent through the hand of Benaiah the son of Jehoiada, so he struck him, and he died. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 2:26">26</verse-number>To Abiathar the priest, the king said, “Go to Anathoth, to your field, for <idiom-start/>you deserve to die<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “you are a man of death”</note> but on this day I will not kill you, for you carried the ark of the Lord Yahweh before David my father, and because you endured hardship in all the hardship that my father endured.” <verse-number id="1 Ki 2:27">27</verse-number>So Solomon banished Abiathar from being priest to Yahweh, thus fulfilling the word which Yahweh had spoken concerning the house of Eli in Shiloh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 2:28">28</verse-number>When the message came to Joab (now Joab <idiom-start/>had supported<idiom-end/><note>Literally “had turned after”</note> Adonijah but <idiom-start/>had not supported<idiom-end/><note>Literally “had not turned after”</note> Absalom), he fled to the tent of Yahweh and grasped the horns of the altar. <verse-number id="1 Ki 2:29">29</verse-number>It was told to King Solomon that Joab had fled to the tent of Yahweh and was beside the altar. So Solomon sent <supplied>word</supplied> to Benaiah son of Jehoiada, saying, “Go and fall upon him.” <verse-number id="1 Ki 2:30">30</verse-number>So Benaiah went to the tent of Yahweh, and he said to him, “Thus says the king: ‘Come out.’ ” And he said, “No, for I want to die here.” So Benaiah returned a word to the king, saying, “Thus Joab spoke, and thus he answered me.” <verse-number id="1 Ki 2:31">31</verse-number>Then the king said to him, “Do as he spoke; fall upon him and bury him, and so you shall remove the innocent blood that Joab shed from on me and from on the house of my father. <verse-number id="1 Ki 2:32">32</verse-number>Yahweh will return his blood on his head, because he fell upon two men, more righteous and better than he, and he killed them with the sword, even though my father did not know it; <supplied>namely</supplied> Abner son of Ner, commander of the army of Israel, and Amasa son of Jether, commander of the army of Judah. <verse-number id="1 Ki 2:33">33</verse-number>And their blood will return on the head of Joab and on the head of his descendants forever, but for David and his descendants and for his house and his throne, <supplied>there</supplied> will be peace forever from Yahweh.” <verse-number id="1 Ki 2:34">34</verse-number>So Benaiah son of Jehoiada went up, and he fell on him and killed him, and he was buried in his house in the wilderness. <verse-number id="1 Ki 2:35">35</verse-number>Then the king appointed Benaiah the son of Jehoiada in his place over the army, and the king appointed Zadok the priest in place of Abiathar. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 2:36">36</verse-number>Then the king sent and summoned Shimei, and he said to him, “Build yourself a house in Jerusalem and live there, but you must not go out <idiom-start/>anywhere whatsoever<idiom-end/><note>Literally “where and where”</note> from there. <verse-number id="1 Ki 2:37">37</verse-number>It shall happen that on the day you go out and cross over the Wadi<note>A valley that is dry most of the year, but contains a stream during the rainy season</note> Kidron, know for certain that <idiom-start/>you will surely die<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “dying you will die”</note> Your blood will be on your head.” <verse-number id="1 Ki 2:38">38</verse-number>Shimei said to the king, “The word is good that my lord the king has spoken to me; thus will your servant do.” So Shimei lived in Jerusalem many days. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 2:39">39</verse-number>It happened that at the end of three years, two of Shimei’s slaves fled to Achish, son of Maacah, the king of Gath. They told Shimei, saying, “Your slaves <supplied>are</supplied> here in Gath.” <verse-number id="1 Ki 2:40">40</verse-number>So Shimei got up and saddled his donkey, and he went to Gath, to Achish, to search for his slaves. So Shimei went and brought his slaves from Gath. <verse-number id="1 Ki 2:41">41</verse-number>When Solomon was told that Shimei had gone from Jerusalem to Gath and had returned, <verse-number id="1 Ki 2:42">42</verse-number>the king sent and summoned Shimei, and he said to him, “Did I not make you swear by Yahweh? I warned you, saying, ‘On the day you go out and you go <idiom-start/>anywhere whatsoever<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “where and where”</note> know for certain that <idiom-start/>you will surely die<idiom-end/>.’<note>Literally “dying you will die”</note> And you said to me, ‘The word is good; I accept.’ <verse-number id="1 Ki 2:43">43</verse-number>Why have you not kept the oath of Yahweh and the command which I commanded you?” <verse-number id="1 Ki 2:44">44</verse-number>Then the king said to Shimei, “You know all the evil which your heart knows, what you did to David my father. Now Yahweh will return the evil on your head, <verse-number id="1 Ki 2:45">45</verse-number>but King Solomon will be blessed and the throne of David will be established before Yahweh forever.” <verse-number id="1 Ki 2:46">46</verse-number>Then the king commanded Benaiah son of Jehoiada, and he went out and fell upon him, and he died. So the kingdom was established in the hand of Solomon. </p>
		</chapter>