<chapter id="1 Ki 3">
			<pericope>Solomon’s Walk with Yahweh</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 3:1">1</verse-number>Solomon intermarried with Pharaoh the king of Egypt, and he took the daughter of Pharaoh and brought her to the city of David until he finished building his house, the house of Yahweh, and the walls of Jerusalem all around. <verse-number id="1 Ki 3:2">2</verse-number>But the people <supplied>were</supplied> sacrificing on the high places, for the house for the name of Yahweh had not <supplied>yet</supplied> been built in those days. <verse-number id="1 Ki 3:3">3</verse-number>Solomon loved Yahweh, by walking in the statutes of David his father; only he <supplied>was</supplied> sacrificing and offering incense on the high places. <verse-number id="1 Ki 3:4">4</verse-number>So the king went to Gibeon to sacrifice, for the great high place <supplied>was</supplied> there. Solomon used to offer a thousand burnt offerings on that altar. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Solomon’s Request for Wisdom</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 3:5">5</verse-number>Yahweh appeared to Solomon at Gibeon in a dream at night, and God said, “Ask what I should give to you.” <verse-number id="1 Ki 3:6">6</verse-number>Then Solomon said, “You have shown great loyal love with your servant David my father, as he walked before you in faithfulness and in righteousness and in uprightness of heart with you. You have shown for him this great loyal love, and you have given a son to him who is sitting on his throne as <supplied>it is</supplied> this day. <verse-number id="1 Ki 3:7">7</verse-number>So then, O Yahweh, you are my God. You have made your servant king in place of David my father <supplied>though</supplied> I <supplied>am</supplied> a young boy. I do not know going out or coming in. <verse-number id="1 Ki 3:8">8</verse-number>Your servant <supplied>is</supplied> in the middle of your people whom you have chosen; a great people who cannot be counted or numbered because of abundance. <verse-number id="1 Ki 3:9">9</verse-number>Give to your servant a listening heart to judge your people, to discern between good and bad, because who is able to judge this, your difficult people?” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 3:10">10</verse-number>The word was good in the eyes of <supplied>the</supplied> Lord that Solomon had asked this thing. <verse-number id="1 Ki 3:11">11</verse-number>And God said to him, “Because you have asked this thing and you did not ask for yourself <idiom-start/>a long life<idiom-end/><note>Literally “many days”</note> and you did not ask riches for yourself and you did not ask for the life of your enemies, but you have asked for yourself <idiom-start/>the ability to make wise judgments<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “understanding to hear judgment”</note> <verse-number id="1 Ki 3:12">12</verse-number>behold, I do hereby do according to your word. I hereby give you a wise and discerning heart; there was no one like you before you, nor afterwards will one like you arise. <verse-number id="1 Ki 3:13">13</verse-number>Too, what you have not asked I give to you: both riches and honor, <supplied>so that</supplied> no man among the kings will be like you all of your days. <verse-number id="1 Ki 3:14">14</verse-number>If you will walk in my ways by keeping my statutes and my commandments, as David your father walked, then I will lengthen your days.” <verse-number id="1 Ki 3:15">15</verse-number>Then Solomon awoke, and look, <supplied>it was</supplied> a dream, and he came <supplied>to</supplied> Jerusalem and stood before the ark of the covenant of <supplied>the</supplied> Lord, and he offered burnt offerings and presented fellowship offerings, and he held a feast for all of his servants. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Solomon’s Wisdom Tested: The Two Prostitutes</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 3:16">16</verse-number>Then two prostitutes came to the king, and they stood before him. <verse-number id="1 Ki 3:17">17</verse-number>The one woman said, “Please my lord, I and this woman are living in one house, and I gave birth, with her in the house. <verse-number id="1 Ki 3:18">18</verse-number>It happened on the third day <supplied>after</supplied> my giving birth, this woman also gave birth, and we <supplied>were</supplied> together. There was not anyone with us in the house, only the two of us <supplied>were</supplied> in the house. <verse-number id="1 Ki 3:19">19</verse-number>Then the son of this woman died <supplied>in the</supplied> night because she laid on him. <verse-number id="1 Ki 3:20">20</verse-number>So she got up in the middle of the night, and she took my son from beside me while your servant was asleep, and she put him in her lap, and she put her dead son in my lap. <verse-number id="1 Ki 3:21">21</verse-number>When I got up in the morning to nurse my son, behold, he was dead! When I looked closely at him in the morning, behold, it was not my son whom I had borne.” <verse-number id="1 Ki 3:22">22</verse-number>Then the other woman said, “No, for my son <supplied>is</supplied> the living one, and your son <supplied>is</supplied> the dead one.” The other kept on saying, “No, for your son <supplied>is</supplied> the dead one, and my son <supplied>is</supplied> the living one,” and so they argued in front of the king. <verse-number id="1 Ki 3:23">23</verse-number>Then the king said, “This one <supplied>is</supplied> saying, ‘This <supplied>is</supplied> my son, the living one, but your son <supplied>is</supplied> the dead one,’ and the other one keeps saying, ‘But no! Your son <supplied>is</supplied> the dead one, and my son <supplied>is</supplied> living!’ ” <verse-number id="1 Ki 3:24">24</verse-number>So the king said, “Bring me a sword,” and they brought the sword before the king. <verse-number id="1 Ki 3:25">25</verse-number>Then the king said, “Divide the living child into two, and give half to the one and half to the other.” <verse-number id="1 Ki 3:26">26</verse-number>Then the woman whose son <supplied>was</supplied> the living one spoke to the king because her compassion was aroused for her son, and she said, “Please, my lord, give her the living child, but certainly do not kill him!” The other one <supplied>was</supplied> saying, “As for me, so for you! Divide <supplied>him</supplied>!” <verse-number id="1 Ki 3:27">27</verse-number>Then the king answered and said, “Give the living child to her, and do not kill him; she <supplied>is</supplied> his mother.” <verse-number id="1 Ki 3:28">28</verse-number>When all of Israel heard the judgment that the king had rendered, they <idiom-start/>stood in awe<idiom-end/><note>Literally “feared the face”</note> of the king, because they realized that the wisdom of God was in him to execute justice. </p>
		</chapter>