<chapter id="1 Ki 4">
			<pericope>Solomon’s Wisdom: Political Administration</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 4:1">1</verse-number>King Solomon was king over all Israel. <verse-number id="1 Ki 4:2">2</verse-number>Now these are the officials who were his: Azariah the son of Zadok <supplied>was</supplied> the priest. <verse-number id="1 Ki 4:3">3</verse-number>Elihoreph and Ahijah, the sons of Shisha, <supplied>were</supplied> the secretaries; Jehoshaphat the son of Ahilud <supplied>was</supplied> the recorder. <verse-number id="1 Ki 4:4">4</verse-number>Benaiah the son of Jehoiada <supplied>was</supplied> over the army, and Zadok and Abiathar were priests. <verse-number id="1 Ki 4:5">5</verse-number>Azariah the son of Nathan <supplied>was</supplied> over the governors, and Zabud the son of Nathan was a priest, an advisor to the king. <verse-number id="1 Ki 4:6">6</verse-number>Ahishar <supplied>was</supplied> over the palace, and Adoniram the son of Abda <supplied>was</supplied> over the forced labor. <verse-number id="1 Ki 4:7">7</verse-number>Solomon had twelve governors over all Israel, and they sustained the king and his palace, <idiom-start/>each one was to sustain for each month of the year<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “a month in the year he was over one to sustain”</note> <verse-number id="1 Ki 4:8">8</verse-number>These <supplied>are</supplied> their names: Ben-Hur <supplied>was</supplied> in the hill country of Ephraim. <verse-number id="1 Ki 4:9">9</verse-number>Ben-Deker <supplied>was</supplied> in Makaz and in Shaalbim and in Beth-Shemesh and Elon of Beth-Hanan. <verse-number id="1 Ki 4:10">10</verse-number>Ben-Hesed <supplied>was</supplied> in the Arubbot; Socoh and all the land of Hepher <supplied>were</supplied> his. <verse-number id="1 Ki 4:11">11</verse-number>Ben-Abinadab <supplied>was</supplied> in all of Naphat of Dor; Taphath the daughter of Solomon was his wife. <verse-number id="1 Ki 4:12">12</verse-number>Baanah the son of Ahilud <supplied>was</supplied> in Taanach and Megiddo and all Beth-Shean which <supplied>is</supplied> beside Zarethan below Jezreel, of Beth-Shean up to Abel-Meholah up to the other side of Jokmeam. <verse-number id="1 Ki 4:13">13</verse-number>Ben-Geber <supplied>was</supplied> in Ramoth-Gilead; the villages of Jair, the son of Manasseh which are in the Gilead <supplied>were</supplied> his, and the region of Argob which <supplied>is</supplied> in the Bashan, sixty great cities, with walls <supplied>having</supplied> crossbars of bronze, <supplied>were</supplied> his. <verse-number id="1 Ki 4:14">14</verse-number>Ahinadab the son of Iddo <supplied>was in</supplied> Mahanaim. <verse-number id="1 Ki 4:15">15</verse-number>Ahimaaz <supplied>was</supplied> in Naphtali; he moreover also had taken Basemath the daughter of Solomon as wife. <verse-number id="1 Ki 4:16">16</verse-number>Baanah the son of Hushai <supplied>was</supplied> in Asher and Bealoth. <verse-number id="1 Ki 4:17">17</verse-number>Jehoshaphat the son of Paruah <supplied>was</supplied> in Issachar. <verse-number id="1 Ki 4:18">18</verse-number>Shimei the son of Ela <supplied>was</supplied> in Benjamin. <verse-number id="1 Ki 4:19">19</verse-number>Geber the son of Uri <supplied>was</supplied> in the land of Gilead, the land of Sihon, the king of the Amorites, and of Og, the king of Bashan; one governor which <supplied>was</supplied> over the land. <verse-number id="1 Ki 4:20">20</verse-number>Judah and Israel <supplied>were</supplied> as many as the sand which is on the seashore in abundance, eating and drinking and rejoicing! </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Solomon’s Wisdom: Prosperity</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 4:21">21</verse-number><note><cite title="BibleLEB2: 1 Ki 4:21–5:18">1 Kings 4:21–5:18 </cite>in the English Bible is 5:1–32 in the Hebrew Bible</note> Now Solomon was ruling over all the kingdoms from the River<note>That is, the Euphrates</note> <supplied>to</supplied> the land of <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines, and up to the border of Egypt, who <supplied>were</supplied> bringing tribute and <supplied>were</supplied> serving Solomon all the days of his life. <verse-number id="1 Ki 4:22">22</verse-number>The food of Solomon for one day was thirty dry measures of choice meal and sixty dry measures of flour; <verse-number id="1 Ki 4:23">23</verse-number>ten stall-fed oxen and twenty pasture-fed oxen and a hundred sheep, besides deer and buck gazelles and roebucks and well-fed fowls. <verse-number id="1 Ki 4:24">24</verse-number>For he <supplied>was</supplied> ruling over all the west of the River<note>That is, the Euphrates</note> from Tiphsah up to Gaza, over all the kings west of the River;<note>That is, the Euphrates</note> and he had peace from every side all around. <verse-number id="1 Ki 4:25">25</verse-number>Judah and Israel lived in security, each man under his vine and under his fig tree, from Dan as far as Beersheba, all the days of Solomon. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 4:26">26</verse-number>Now Solomon had forty thousand stalls of horses for his war chariots and twelve thousand horsemen. <verse-number id="1 Ki 4:27">27</verse-number>These governors sustained King Solomon and all who came near to the table of King Solomon, each <supplied>in</supplied> his month; they did not omit anything. <verse-number id="1 Ki 4:28">28</verse-number>The barley and the straw for the horses and for packhorses they brought to the place where they were, each according to his share. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Solomon’s Wisdom: Literature, Zoology, Biology, Dendrology</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 4:29">29</verse-number>God gave wisdom to Solomon and very great discernment, as well as <idiom-start/>breadth of understanding<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “width of heart”</note> as the sand which is on the edge of the seashore. <verse-number id="1 Ki 4:30">30</verse-number>The wisdom of Solomon was greater than the wisdom of all the people<note>Or “sons/children”</note> of <supplied>the</supplied> east and more than all the wisdom of Egypt. <verse-number id="1 Ki 4:31">31</verse-number>He was wiser than all the men: Ethan the Ezrahite; Heman, Calcol, and Darda the children of Mahol; and <idiom-start/>he was very well known<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “his name was among all the peoples around”</note> <verse-number id="1 Ki 4:32">32</verse-number>He spoke three thousand proverbs, and his songs were one thousand and five. <verse-number id="1 Ki 4:33">33</verse-number>He spoke concerning the trees, from the cedar which <supplied>is</supplied> in Lebanon up to the hyssop which grows on the wall; he also spoke concerning the animals, concerning the birds, concerning the creeping things, and concerning the fish. <verse-number id="1 Ki 4:34">34</verse-number>They came from all the nations to hear the wisdom of Solomon; from all the kings of the earth who had heard <supplied>of</supplied> his wisdom. </p>
		</chapter>