<chapter id="1 Ki 5">
			<pericope>Solomon’s Wisdom: Architecture</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 5:1">1</verse-number>Hiram king of Tyre sent his servants to Solomon when he heard that they had anointed him as king in place of his father, for Hiram had always been a friend for David. <verse-number id="1 Ki 5:2">2</verse-number>Then Solomon sent to Hiram, saying, <verse-number id="1 Ki 5:3">3</verse-number>“You knew David my father, that he was not able to build a house for the name of Yahweh his God, <idiom-start/>in view of the warfare<idiom-end/><note>Literally “because of the face of the warfare”</note> which surrounded him, until Yahweh placed them<note>That is, David’s enemies</note> under the soles of his feet. <verse-number id="1 Ki 5:4">4</verse-number>But now Yahweh my God has given me rest all around me. There is no adversary, and there is no bad occurrence. <verse-number id="1 Ki 5:5">5</verse-number>Here I am, intending to build a house for the name of Yahweh my God, as Yahweh promised to my father David, saying, ‘Your son, whom I will set in your place on your throne, shall build the house for my name.’ <verse-number id="1 Ki 5:6">6</verse-number>So then, command that they may cut cedars for me from Lebanon, and let my servants be with your servants. The wage of your servants I will give to you according to all that you say, for you know that there is no one among us who knows <supplied>how</supplied> to cut timber like the Sidonians.” <verse-number id="1 Ki 5:7">7</verse-number>When Hiram heard the words of Solomon, he rejoiced greatly, and he said, “Blessed be Yahweh this day, who has given to David a wise son over this great people.” <verse-number id="1 Ki 5:8">8</verse-number>Hiram sent to Solomon, saying, “I have heard what you have sent to me; I will do all of your desire concerning the timber of cedars and concerning the timber of cypresses. <verse-number id="1 Ki 5:9">9</verse-number>My servants will bring <supplied>them</supplied> down from Lebanon to the sea, and I will make them <supplied>into</supplied> rafts in the sea <supplied>to float to</supplied> the place which you indicated to me. Then I shall break them up there, and you may carry <supplied>them further</supplied>, and <idiom-start/>you shall meet my needs<idiom-end/><note>Literally “you shall do my desire”</note> by giving food for my house.” <verse-number id="1 Ki 5:10">10</verse-number>So Hiram was giving to Solomon the cedar timbers and the cypress timbers, <idiom-start/>everything he needed<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “all of his desire”</note> <verse-number id="1 Ki 5:11">11</verse-number>Then Solomon gave to Hiram twenty thousand dry measures of wheat <supplied>as</supplied> food for his household, and twenty dry measures of <idiom-start/>specially prepared olive oil<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “beaten olive oil”</note> thus Solomon gave to Hiram year by year. <verse-number id="1 Ki 5:12">12</verse-number>Yahweh gave wisdom to Solomon as he promised to him, and there was peace between Hiram and Solomon, and the two of them <idiom-start/>made<idiom-end/><note>Literally “cut”</note> a covenant. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 5:13">13</verse-number>Then King Solomon conscripted a forced labor from all Israel, and the forced labor <supplied>numbered</supplied> thirty thousand men. <verse-number id="1 Ki 5:14">14</verse-number>He sent them to Lebanon, ten thousand <idiom-start/>every month<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “in the month”</note> the work groups were a month in Lebanon and two months at home; now Adoniram was over the forced labor. <verse-number id="1 Ki 5:15">15</verse-number>Solomon had seventy thousand <idiom-start/>common laborers<idiom-end/><note>Literally “carrying burden”</note> and eighty thousand stone craftsmen in the hill country. <verse-number id="1 Ki 5:16">16</verse-number>Besides the chiefs of the officers Solomon had, there were three thousand three hundred having charge over the people who were doing the work. <verse-number id="1 Ki 5:17">17</verse-number>When the king commanded, they quarried great stones <supplied>and</supplied> precious stones to lay <supplied>the</supplied> foundation of the house <supplied>with</supplied> hewn stones. <verse-number id="1 Ki 5:18">18</verse-number>So Solomon’s builders and Hiram’s builders and the Gebalites hewed <supplied>stones</supplied>, and they prepared the timber and the stone to build the house. </p>
		</chapter>