<chapter id="1 Ki 6">
			<pericope>Solomon Builds the Temple for Yahweh</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 6:1">1</verse-number>It happened in the four hundred and eightieth year <supplied>after</supplied> the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> went out from the land of Egypt, in the fourth year <idiom-start/>of Solomon’s rule<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Solomon to rule”</note> over Israel, the month of Ziv (that <supplied>is</supplied> the second month), that he began to build the house for Yahweh. <verse-number id="1 Ki 6:2">2</verse-number>Now the house that King Solomon built for Yahweh <supplied>was</supplied> sixty cubits <supplied>in</supplied> its length and twenty cubits <supplied>in</supplied> its width and thirty cubits <supplied>in</supplied> its height. <verse-number id="1 Ki 6:3">3</verse-number>The vestibule on the face of the main hall of the temple<note>Or “house”</note> <supplied>was</supplied> twenty cubits <supplied>in</supplied> its length, and the width of the temple<note>Or “house”</note> <supplied>was</supplied> ten cubits wide on the face of the temple.<note>Or “house”</note> <verse-number id="1 Ki 6:4">4</verse-number>And he made for the temple<note>Or “house”</note> specially designed framed windows, <verse-number id="1 Ki 6:5">5</verse-number>and he built a structure against the wall of the temple<note>Or “house”</note> <supplied>running</supplied> all along the walls of the house, for the outer sanctuary and for the inner sanctuary, and made side rooms all around. <verse-number id="1 Ki 6:6">6</verse-number>The lower structure <supplied>was</supplied> five cubits in its width and the middle <supplied>was</supplied> six cubits in its width and the third <supplied>was</supplied> seven cubits in its width, for he made niches for the temple<note>Or “house”</note> all around to the outside, <supplied>so that</supplied> beams <supplied>would</supplied> not attach to the walls of the temple.<note>Or “house”</note> <verse-number id="1 Ki 6:7">7</verse-number>Now while the temple<note>Or “house”</note> was being built, it was built <supplied>with</supplied> stones finished <supplied>at the</supplied> quarry, <supplied>so that</supplied> no hammer or stone shaping tool or any instrument of iron was heard in the temple<note>Or “house”</note> as it was being built. <verse-number id="1 Ki 6:8">8</verse-number>The doorway of the side room in the middle of the side of the temple<note>Or “house”</note> <supplied>was</supplied> on the south; they went up with a stairway to the middle and from the middle to the third <supplied>floor</supplied>. <verse-number id="1 Ki 6:9">9</verse-number>So he built the house and finished it. He covered the temple<note>Or “house”</note> <supplied>with</supplied> rafters and wood planks and with the cedars. <verse-number id="1 Ki 6:10">10</verse-number>He also built the structure against all of the temple<note>Or “house”</note> five cubits in height and fastened it to the temple<note>Or “house”</note> with beams of cedar. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 6:11">11</verse-number>Then the word of Yahweh came to Solomon, saying, <verse-number id="1 Ki 6:12">12</verse-number>“<supplied>Regarding</supplied> this temple<note>Or “house”</note> that you are building: if you walk in my ordinances and if you do my judgments and you keep all my commandments to walk in them, then I will establish my promise with you which I made to David your father. <verse-number id="1 Ki 6:13">13</verse-number>And I will dwell <idiom-start/>among<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the middle of”</note> the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and I will not forsake my people Israel.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 6:14">14</verse-number>So Solomon built the temple<note>Or “house”</note> and finished it. <verse-number id="1 Ki 6:15">15</verse-number>He lined the walls <idiom-start/>of the inside of the house<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the house from house”</note> with boards of cedar; from the floor of the temple<note>Or “house”</note> up to the rafters of the ceiling he covered <supplied>them with</supplied> wood <idiom-start/>on the inside<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “from house”</note> He also covered the floor of the temple<note>Or “house”</note> with cypress boards. <verse-number id="1 Ki 6:16">16</verse-number>He built twenty cubits from the rear of the house with boards of cedar from the floor up to the ceiling, and he built for it an inner sanctuary on the inside, as the <idiom-start/>most holy place<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “as the holy place of the holy places.” Often referred to as the Holy of Holies</note> <verse-number id="1 Ki 6:17">17</verse-number>The main hall of the temple<note>Or “house”</note> was forty cubits <idiom-start/>in front of the inner sanctuary<idiom-end/>,<note>So LXX supported by the Vulgate. MT has “before me”</note> <verse-number id="1 Ki 6:18">18</verse-number>with the cedar within the inner house <supplied>having</supplied> carvings of gourds and buds of flowers. It <supplied>was</supplied> entirely of cedar; there was not a stone visible. <verse-number id="1 Ki 6:19">19</verse-number>Now <supplied>in</supplied> the inner sanctuary in the middle of the temple<note>Or “house”</note> he prepared the inside to place the ark of the covenant of Yahweh there. <verse-number id="1 Ki 6:20">20</verse-number>In front, the inner sanctuary <supplied>was</supplied> twenty cubits long and twenty cubits wide and twenty cubits high, and he overlaid it <supplied>with</supplied> pure gold and covered the altar <supplied>with</supplied> cedar. <verse-number id="1 Ki 6:21">21</verse-number>Solomon overlaid the temple<note>Or “house”</note> on the inside <supplied>with</supplied> pure gold, and he drew across it with golden chains in front of the inner sanctuary, which he overlaid with gold. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 6:22">22</verse-number>All of the temple<note>Or “house”</note> he overlaid with gold until all of the temple<note>Or “house”</note> <supplied>was</supplied> finished; all of the altar which belonged to the inner sanctuary he overlaid with gold. <verse-number id="1 Ki 6:23">23</verse-number>He made two cherubim of olive wood for the inner sanctuary, ten cubits high. <verse-number id="1 Ki 6:24">24</verse-number>Five cubits <supplied>was</supplied> the first wing of the cherub, and five cubits the second wing of the cherub, from the tip of his <supplied>one</supplied> wing up to the tip of his <supplied>other</supplied> wing. <verse-number id="1 Ki 6:25">25</verse-number>The second cherub <supplied>was</supplied> ten cubits <supplied>according to</supplied> <idiom-start/>the same<idiom-end/><note>Literally “one”</note> measurement, and <supplied>there</supplied> was one shape for the two cherubim. <verse-number id="1 Ki 6:26">26</verse-number>The height of the first cherub <supplied>was</supplied> ten cubits and so <supplied>was</supplied> the second cherub. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 6:27">27</verse-number>He placed the cherubim in the middle of the inner house, and they spread out the wings of the cherubim; the wing of the first cherub touched against the wall and the wing of the second cherub <supplied>was</supplied> touching against the second wall; their wings <supplied>spread</supplied> to the middle of the house <supplied>and were</supplied> touching wing to wing. <verse-number id="1 Ki 6:28">28</verse-number>He also overlaid the cherubim with gold. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 6:29">29</verse-number>On all of the walls around the house, he carved engravings of cherubim and palm tree images and budding flowers both inside and out. <verse-number id="1 Ki 6:30">30</verse-number>He overlaid the floor of the house with gold both inside and out. <verse-number id="1 Ki 6:31">31</verse-number>He made doors of olive wood for the doorway of the inner sanctuary, <supplied>as well as for</supplied> the doorpost of the fifth doorframe. <verse-number id="1 Ki 6:32">32</verse-number><supplied>On</supplied> the two doors of olive wood he made carvings of cherubim and palm tree images and budding flowers, and he overlaid them with gold <idiom-start/>by beating<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and he beat out”</note> out the gold on the cherubim and the palm tree images. <verse-number id="1 Ki 6:33">33</verse-number>Thus he made doorframes of olive wood on four sides for the doorway of the main hall <verse-number id="1 Ki 6:34">34</verse-number>and two doors of cypress wood; one door <supplied>with</supplied> two folding panels and the second door <supplied>with</supplied> two folding panels. <verse-number id="1 Ki 6:35">35</verse-number>He carved cherubim and palm tree images and budding flowers and overlaid them with gold evenly applied on the carved work. <verse-number id="1 Ki 6:36">36</verse-number>Then he built the inner courtyard <supplied>with</supplied> three rows of dressed stone and a row of cedar beams. <verse-number id="1 Ki 6:37">37</verse-number>In the fourth year,<note>That is, the fourth year of Solomon’s reign</note> the house of Yahweh was founded in the month of Ziv. <verse-number id="1 Ki 6:38">38</verse-number>In the eleventh year in the month of Bul, that is, the eighth month, the house was finished <supplied>according</supplied> to all his specifications and <supplied>according</supplied> to all his plans. He had built it in seven years. </p>
		</chapter>