<chapter id="1 Ki 7">
			<pericope>Solomon Continues to Build</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 7:1">1</verse-number>Solomon built his house <supplied>over</supplied> thirteen years, and he finished all of his house. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 7:2">2</verse-number>He built the House of the Forest of Lebanon; one hundred cubits its length, fifty cubits its width, and thirty cubits its height, on four rows of cedar pillars and cedar beams atop the pillars. <verse-number id="1 Ki 7:3">3</verse-number>It was covered with cedar above, and the supporting beams which <supplied>were</supplied> on the forty-five pillars, fifteen <supplied>to</supplied> the row. <verse-number id="1 Ki 7:4">4</verse-number><supplied>There were</supplied> three rows of specially designed windows; <supplied>with</supplied> window to window three times. <verse-number id="1 Ki 7:5">5</verse-number>All of the doorways and the doorframes <supplied>had</supplied> four-sided casings, with opening to opposite opening three times. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 7:6">6</verse-number>The hall of pillars he made fifty cubits <supplied>in</supplied> its length and thirty cubits <supplied>in</supplied> its width, and a porch <supplied>was</supplied> <idiom-start/>in front of them<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “on their face”</note> with pillars and an overhang <idiom-start/>in front of them<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “on their face”</note> <verse-number id="1 Ki 7:7">7</verse-number>He made the hall of the throne where he <supplied>would</supplied> pronounce judgment, the hall of justice, and <supplied>it was</supplied> covered with cedar from the floor to the rafters.<note>Hebrew “floor,” but other ancient versions have “rafters”</note> <verse-number id="1 Ki 7:8">8</verse-number>His house where he would live in the next courtyard on the inside of the porch was like this work, and he would make a house like this porch for the daughter of Pharaoh whom Solomon had taken <supplied>as wife</supplied>. <verse-number id="1 Ki 7:9">9</verse-number>All of these <supplied>were</supplied> of precious stones, according to the measurement of dressed stone, sawn with a saw <idiom-start/>on all sides<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “on <supplied>the</supplied> inside and on <supplied>the</supplied> outside”</note> from <supplied>the</supplied> foundation up to the eaves and from <supplied>the</supplied> outside up to the great courtyard. <verse-number id="1 Ki 7:10">10</verse-number><supplied>The</supplied> foundation <supplied>was of</supplied> precious stones, <supplied>and</supplied> large stones of ten cubits and stones of eight cubits <verse-number id="1 Ki 7:11">11</verse-number>with precious stones above, <idiom-start/>just the right size<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “according to <supplied>the</supplied> measurement of dressed stones”</note> and cedar. <verse-number id="1 Ki 7:12">12</verse-number>The great courtyard all around had three rows of dressed stones and a row of cedar beams; for <supplied>both</supplied> the courtyard of the inner house<note>Or “temple”</note> of Yahweh and for the porch of the house. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 7:13">13</verse-number>King Solomon invited and received Hiram from Tyre. <verse-number id="1 Ki 7:14">14</verse-number>He <supplied>was</supplied> the son of a widow woman from the tribe of Naphtali, and his father <supplied>was</supplied> a man of Tyre, an artisan of bronze. He was filled with wisdom and with ability and with the knowledge to do all the work with the bronze. And he came to King Solomon, and he did all of his work. <verse-number id="1 Ki 7:15">15</verse-number>He cast the two pillars <supplied>out of</supplied> bronze; eighteen cubits <supplied>was</supplied> the height of the first, and a cord of twelve cubits would encircle the second pillar. <verse-number id="1 Ki 7:16">16</verse-number>He made two capitals to place on the tops of the pillars <supplied>out of</supplied> molten bronze; the first capital <supplied>was</supplied> five cubits <supplied>in</supplied> height, and the second capital <supplied>was</supplied> five cubits <supplied>in</supplied> height. <verse-number id="1 Ki 7:17">17</verse-number>A network of latticework <supplied>and</supplied> wreaths of chainwork with small chains <supplied>were</supplied> for the capitals which <supplied>were</supplied> on top of the pillars; seven for the first capital and seven for the second capital. <verse-number id="1 Ki 7:18">18</verse-number>He also made the pillars with two rows around on the lattice, each to cover the capitals which <supplied>were</supplied> on top, <supplied>out of</supplied> the pomegranate-shaped ornaments, and thus he did for the second capital <supplied>as well</supplied>. <verse-number id="1 Ki 7:19">19</verse-number>And <supplied>on</supplied> the capitals which <supplied>were</supplied> on top of the pillars in the porch <supplied>were</supplied> works of lilies four cubits <supplied>high</supplied>. <verse-number id="1 Ki 7:20">20</verse-number>And capitals <supplied>were</supplied> on the two pillars above near the bulging section which was beside the lattice, and two hundred pomegranate-shaped ornaments <supplied>were</supplied> in rows all around on the second capital. <verse-number id="1 Ki 7:21">21</verse-number>He set up the pillars for the porch of the main hall; he erected the pillar on the right and called its name Jakin, and he set up the pillar on the left and called its name Boaz. <verse-number id="1 Ki 7:22">22</verse-number>On the top of the pillars <supplied>was</supplied> a work of lilies; and so the work of the pillars <supplied>was</supplied> finished. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 7:23">23</verse-number>He also made the molten<note>That is, cast from molten bronze</note> sea, ten cubits <idiom-start/>in diameter<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from its edge up to its edge, round all around”</note> and five cubits <supplied>was</supplied> its height. A measuring line of thirty cubits would encircle it all around. <verse-number id="1 Ki 7:24">24</verse-number>Gourds <supplied>were</supplied> under its rim surrounding it all around; ten to the cubit, surrounding the sea all around with two rows of gourds, <supplied>which</supplied> were cast when he cast the metal. <verse-number id="1 Ki 7:25">25</verse-number><supplied>The sea</supplied> was standing on twelve oxen, with three facing to the north, three facing to the west, three facing to the south, and three facing to the east. The sea <supplied>was</supplied> on top of them, with all of their hindquarters <supplied>turned</supplied> to the inside. <verse-number id="1 Ki 7:26">26</verse-number>Its thickness <supplied>was</supplied> a handbreadth, but its rim <supplied>was</supplied> as the work on the brim of a cup, <supplied>like the</supplied> bud of a lily; it held two thousand baths. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 7:27">27</verse-number>He made the ten stands of bronze; each stand <supplied>was</supplied> four cubits long, four cubits wide, and three cubits in height. <verse-number id="1 Ki 7:28">28</verse-number>Now this <supplied>was</supplied> the construction of the stands: there <supplied>were</supplied> frames for them and frames between the crossbars, <verse-number id="1 Ki 7:29">29</verse-number>and on the frames which <supplied>were</supplied> between the crossbars <supplied>were</supplied> lions, oxen, and cherubim. On the crossbars both above and beneath the lions and oxen <supplied>were</supplied> works of cascading wreaths. <verse-number id="1 Ki 7:30">30</verse-number><supplied>There were</supplied> four bronze wheels for each of the stands, with bronze axles; the four support pedestals for these <supplied>were</supplied> under the basin, and the supports <supplied>were</supplied> decorated on each side <supplied>with</supplied> wreaths. <verse-number id="1 Ki 7:31">31</verse-number>Its opening from <supplied>the</supplied> inside of the capital and above <supplied>was</supplied> a cubit; its pedestal <supplied>was</supplied> a round work of a cubit and a half; moreover, on its opening <supplied>were</supplied> the carvings with four-sided frames, not circular. <verse-number id="1 Ki 7:32">32</verse-number>Four of the wheels <supplied>were</supplied> underneath the frames, and the axles of the wheels <supplied>were</supplied> on the stands. The height of each wheel <supplied>was</supplied> a cubit and a half. <verse-number id="1 Ki 7:33">33</verse-number>The construction of the wheel <supplied>was</supplied> like the construction of the wheel of the chariot; their axles, their rims, their spokes, and their naves <supplied>were</supplied> all cast. <verse-number id="1 Ki 7:34">34</verse-number>The four supports <supplied>were</supplied> the four corners of each stand, with the stand supporting it. <verse-number id="1 Ki 7:35">35</verse-number>On top of the stand <supplied>was</supplied> half a cubit deep, circular all around, and on the top of the stand <supplied>were</supplied> its supports and its frames. <verse-number id="1 Ki 7:36">36</verse-number>He engraved on the plates, on its supports, and on its frame cherubim, lions and images of a palm tree, according to the space for each, with wreaths all around. <verse-number id="1 Ki 7:37">37</verse-number>He made the ten stands like this in one cast, with the same measurement and shape for each of them. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 7:38">38</verse-number>He also made ten bronze basins, <supplied>each</supplied> holding forty baths; each basin <supplied>was</supplied> four cubits, one basin on each of the ten stands. <verse-number id="1 Ki 7:39">39</verse-number>He placed five of the stands on the south side of the house and five on the north side of the house, and the sea he set on the southeast side of the house. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 7:40">40</verse-number>Hiram also made the basins and the shovels and the bowls for drinking wine; and so Hiram finished doing all of the work <idiom-start/>that he was to do<idiom-end/><note>Literally “that he did”</note> for King Solomon in the house of Yahweh: <verse-number id="1 Ki 7:41">41</verse-number>the two pillars and the bowls of the capitals which <supplied>were</supplied> atop the two pillars, and the two lattice works to cover the two bowls of the capitals which <supplied>were</supplied> atop the pillars; <verse-number id="1 Ki 7:42">42</verse-number>and the four hundred pomegranate-shaped ornaments for the two lattice works, the two rows of pomegranate-shaped ornaments for each latticework to cover the two bowls of the capitals which <supplied>were</supplied> on the surface of the pillars; <verse-number id="1 Ki 7:43">43</verse-number>and the ten stands and the ten basins on the stands; <verse-number id="1 Ki 7:44">44</verse-number>and the one sea and the twelve oxen under the sea; <verse-number id="1 Ki 7:45">45</verse-number>and the pots, the shovels, and the bowls for drinking wine. All the vessels of the tent which Hiram had made for King Solomon <supplied>for</supplied> the house of Yahweh <supplied>were</supplied> polished bronze. <verse-number id="1 Ki 7:46">46</verse-number>The king had cast them in the plain of the Jordan with the casting mold <supplied>set in</supplied> the ground between Succoth and Zarethan. <verse-number id="1 Ki 7:47">47</verse-number>Solomon left all of the vessels <supplied>unweighed</supplied> because of their very great abundance, so the weight of the bronze could not be determined. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 7:48">48</verse-number>Solomon also made all of the vessels which <supplied>were</supplied> in the house of Yahweh: the golden altar and the golden table on which <supplied>was</supplied> the bread of the presence; <verse-number id="1 Ki 7:49">49</verse-number>as well as the five lampstands of beaten gold at the south and five lampstands at the north before the presence of the inner sanctuary, with the flower-shaped ornaments, the lamps, and the pair of tongs <supplied>all of gold</supplied>. <verse-number id="1 Ki 7:50">50</verse-number>The cups, the snuffers, the bowls for drinking wine, the bowls for the incense, and the firepans <supplied>were made from</supplied> beaten gold; the facades for the doors of the inner house, for the <idiom-start/>most holy place<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “holy of the holiest”</note> for the doors of the main hall of the temple <supplied>were of</supplied> gold. <verse-number id="1 Ki 7:51">51</verse-number><supplied>When</supplied> all of the work which king Solomon did on the house of Yahweh was completed, Solomon brought out the holy objects of his father David, the silver and the gold and the vessels, <supplied>which</supplied> he put in the treasury rooms of the house of Yahweh. </p>
		</chapter>