<chapter id="1 Ki 9">
			<pericope>Yahweh’s Challenge to Solomon</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 9:1">1</verse-number>It happened that as Solomon finished the building of the house of Yahweh, the king’s house, and all the things Solomon desired to do, <verse-number id="1 Ki 9:2">2</verse-number>Yahweh appeared to Solomon a second time, as he had appeared to him in Gibeon. <verse-number id="1 Ki 9:3">3</verse-number>Yahweh said to him, “I have heard your prayer and your plea which you have made before me. I have consecrated this house which you have built, by putting my name there forever. My eyes and my heart will always be there. <verse-number id="1 Ki 9:4">4</verse-number>As for you, if you walk before me as David your father walked, with <idiom-start/>integrity of heart<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in blamelessness of heart”</note> and with uprightness, to do according to all that I have commanded you, <supplied>and if</supplied> you keep my ordinances and my judgments, <verse-number id="1 Ki 9:5">5</verse-number>then I will establish the throne of your kingdom over Israel forever, as I promised David your father, saying, ‘A man will not be cut off for you from upon the throne of Israel.’ </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 9:6">6</verse-number>“If ever you or any of your descendants<note>Or “children”</note> turn from <supplied>following</supplied> me and do not keep my commandments <supplied>and</supplied> my ordinances that I have set before you and you go and serve other gods and bow down to them, <verse-number id="1 Ki 9:7">7</verse-number>then I will cut Israel off from the face of the land that I have given to them, <supplied>even</supplied> the house which I have consecrated for my name I will cast away from my face; and Israel shall become a proverb and an object of taunting among all the peoples. <verse-number id="1 Ki 9:8">8</verse-number>This house shall become a heap of ruins; all those passing by will be appalled by it and hiss, and they will say, ‘On what account did Yahweh do this to this land and to this house?’ <verse-number id="1 Ki 9:9">9</verse-number>And they will say, ‘Because they have forsaken Yahweh their God who brought their ancestors<note>Or “fathers”</note> out from the land of Egypt and they embraced other gods and bowed down to them and served them. Therefore, Yahweh brought on them all of this disaster.’ ” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Solomon and Hiram Complete Their Agreement</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 9:10">10</verse-number>It happened at the end of twenty years <supplied>in</supplied> which Solomon had built the two houses, the house of Yahweh and the house of the king, <verse-number id="1 Ki 9:11">11</verse-number><supplied>since</supplied> Hiram king of Tyre had supplied Solomon with wood of cedar and with wood of cypresses and with the gold according to all his desire, then King Solomon gave twenty cities in the land of the Galilee to Hiram. <verse-number id="1 Ki 9:12">12</verse-number>So Hiram went out from Tyre to see the cities that Solomon had given him, but they were not right in his eyes. <verse-number id="1 Ki 9:13">13</verse-number>So he said, “What <supplied>are</supplied> these cities that you have given to me, my brother?” <idiom-start/>So they are called the land of Cabul until this day<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “So he called them the land of Cabul up to this day”</note> <verse-number id="1 Ki 9:14">14</verse-number>Then Hiram sent to the king a hundred and twenty talents of gold. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Solomon’s Accomplishments</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 9:15">15</verse-number>This <supplied>is</supplied> the account of the forced labor that King Solomon conscripted to build the house of Yahweh and his house, the Millo, the walls of Jerusalem, Hazor, Megiddo, and Gezer. <verse-number id="1 Ki 9:16">16</verse-number>Pharaoh, the king of Egypt, had gone up and captured Gezer and burnt it with fire. He had also killed the Canaanites who were living in the city and had given it as a dowry to his daughter, the wife of Solomon. <verse-number id="1 Ki 9:17">17</verse-number>Solomon rebuilt Gezer and Lower Beth-Horon, <verse-number id="1 Ki 9:18">18</verse-number><supplied>as well as</supplied> Baalath and Tamar in the wilderness in the land; <verse-number id="1 Ki 9:19">19</verse-number>and <supplied>he also built</supplied> all of the storage cities which were Solomon’s, the cities <supplied>for</supplied> the chariots, the cities <supplied>for</supplied> the cavalry, and all of Solomon’s desire that he wanted<note>Or “desired”</note> to build in Jerusalem and in Lebanon and in all the land of his dominion. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 9:20">20</verse-number>All of the people who were remaining from the Amorites, the Hittites, the Perizzites, the Hivites, and the Jebusites who <supplied>were</supplied> not of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> <verse-number id="1 Ki 9:21">21</verse-number>their children who remained after them in the land, whom the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> were not able to completely destroy, Solomon conscripted them for forced labor, until this very day. <verse-number id="1 Ki 9:22">22</verse-number>But from the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> Solomon did not make a slave, but they <supplied>were</supplied> the men of war, his officers, his commanders, his captains, and the commanders of his chariots and his cavalry. <verse-number id="1 Ki 9:23">23</verse-number>These <supplied>were</supplied> the commanders of the overseers who <supplied>were</supplied> over the work for Solomon, five hundred and fifty, ruling over the people doing the work. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 9:24">24</verse-number>As soon as the daughter of Pharaoh went up from the city of David to her house which he<note>That is, Solomon</note> built for her, then he built the Millo. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 9:25">25</verse-number>Solomon sacrificed three times a year: burnt offerings and fellowship offerings on the altar that he had built to Yahweh, and he offered incense with it before Yahweh; and so he completed the house. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 9:26">26</verse-number>King Solomon also built a fleet of ships at Ezion-Geber which <supplied>is</supplied> near Elath on the shore of the <idiom-start/>Red Sea<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sea of reed”</note> in the land of Edom. <verse-number id="1 Ki 9:27">27</verse-number>Hiram sent his servants with the fleet of ships, <idiom-start/>sailors<idiom-end/><note>Literally “men of ships”</note> who knew the sea, with the servants of Solomon. <verse-number id="1 Ki 9:28">28</verse-number>They went to Ophir and imported from there four hundred and twenty talents of gold, and they brought it to King Solomon. </p>
		</chapter>