<chapter id="1 Ki 18">
			<pericope>War between Elijah and the Prophets of Baal</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 18:1">1</verse-number>It happened many days <supplied>later</supplied> that the word of Yahweh came to Elijah in the third year, saying, “Go, present yourself to Ahab so that I may give rain on the surface of the earth.” <verse-number id="1 Ki 18:2">2</verse-number>So Elijah went to present himself to Ahab. Now the famine <supplied>was</supplied> severe in Samaria. <verse-number id="1 Ki 18:3">3</verse-number>Ahab summoned Obadiah who <supplied>was</supplied> over the house. (Now Obadiah was fearing Yahweh greatly. <verse-number id="1 Ki 18:4">4</verse-number>It had happened that when Jezebel killed the prophets of Yahweh, Obadiah took a hundred prophets and hid them <idiom-start/>by fifties<idiom-end/><note>Literally “fifty men”</note> in the cave and sustained them <supplied>with</supplied> food and water.) <verse-number id="1 Ki 18:5">5</verse-number>Ahab said to Obadiah, “Go through the land to all the springs of water and to all the wadis.<note>A valley that is dry most of the year, but contains a stream during the rainy season</note> Perhaps we may find green grass that we may keep horses and mules alive and that we might not lose any of the animals.” <verse-number id="1 Ki 18:6">6</verse-number>So they divided the land for themselves in order to pass through it; Ahab went one way by himself, and Obadiah went another way by himself. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 18:7">7</verse-number>It happened that Obadiah <supplied>was</supplied> on the way, and suddenly Elijah was there to meet him. When he recognized him, he fell on his face and said, “<supplied>Is</supplied> this you, my lord Elijah?” <verse-number id="1 Ki 18:8">8</verse-number>He said to him, “I <supplied>am</supplied>. Go, say to your lord, ‘Elijah <supplied>is</supplied> here.’ ” <verse-number id="1 Ki 18:9">9</verse-number>He said, “How have I sinned that you <supplied>are</supplied> giving your servant into the hand of Ahab to kill me? <verse-number id="1 Ki 18:10">10</verse-number><idiom-start/>As Yahweh your God lives<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “The life of Yahweh your God”</note> surely there is not a nation or a kingdom to which my lord has not sent me to seek you. <supplied>If</supplied> they would say, ‘He is not here,’ then he would make the kingdom or the nation swear that it could not find you. <verse-number id="1 Ki 18:11">11</verse-number>Now you <supplied>are</supplied> saying, ‘Go, say to your lord: “Elijah <supplied>is</supplied> here.” ’ <verse-number id="1 Ki 18:12">12</verse-number>And it will happen that I will go from you and the Spirit of Yahweh will carry you up to where I do not know. Then I will come to tell Ahab, but he will not find you, and then he will kill me, <supplied>even though</supplied> your servant has feared Yahweh from my youth. <verse-number id="1 Ki 18:13">13</verse-number>Has it not been told to my lord what I did when Jezebel killed the prophets of Yahweh? I hid a hundred men of the prophets of Yahweh <idiom-start/>by fifties<idiom-end/><note>Literally “fifty fifty men”</note> in the cave, and I sustained them <supplied>with</supplied> food and water. <verse-number id="1 Ki 18:14">14</verse-number>Now you <supplied>are</supplied> saying, ‘Go, say to your lord: “Elijah <supplied>is</supplied> here,” ’ and he will kill me.” <verse-number id="1 Ki 18:15">15</verse-number>Elijah said, “<idiom-start/>As Yahweh of hosts lives<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “The life of Yahweh of hosts”</note> before whom I stand, I will certainly show myself to him today.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 18:16">16</verse-number>So Obadiah went to meet Ahab, and he told him, so Ahab went to meet Elijah. <verse-number id="1 Ki 18:17">17</verse-number>When Ahab saw Elijah, Ahab said to him, “<supplied>Is</supplied> this you <supplied>who</supplied> throws Israel into confusion?” <verse-number id="1 Ki 18:18">18</verse-number>He said, “I did not throw Israel into confusion; rather you and the house of your father <supplied>have</supplied> by forsaking the commands of Yahweh when you went after the Baals! <verse-number id="1 Ki 18:19">19</verse-number>So then, send <supplied>word</supplied> and assemble all of Israel to me on Mount Carmel, with the four hundred and fifty prophets of Baal and the four hundred prophets of Asherah, who eat at the table of Jezebel.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 18:20">20</verse-number>So Ahab sent <supplied>word</supplied> among the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and he assembled the prophets to Mount Carmel. <verse-number id="1 Ki 18:21">21</verse-number>Elijah approached to all the people and said, “How long <supplied>will</supplied> you <supplied>go</supplied> limping over two opinions? If Yahweh <supplied>is</supplied> God, go after him; but if Baal, go after him.” But the people did not answer him a word. <verse-number id="1 Ki 18:22">22</verse-number>Then Elijah said to the people, “I alone <supplied>am</supplied> left a prophet of Yahweh, but the prophets of Baal <supplied>are</supplied> four hundred and fifty men. <verse-number id="1 Ki 18:23">23</verse-number>Let them give us two bulls, and let them choose for themselves one bull, cut him in pieces, and put it on the wood, but don’t let them start a fire on it. I will prepare the other bull and set it on the wood, but I will put no fire <supplied>on it</supplied>. <verse-number id="1 Ki 18:24">24</verse-number>Then you call on the name of your god, and I will call on the name of Yahweh, and it shall be that the god who answers by fire, he <supplied>is</supplied> God.”<note>Baal is known in Canaanite texts as being the god in control of lightning and fire</note> Then all the people answered and said, “The word <supplied>is</supplied> good!” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 18:25">25</verse-number>Then Elijah said to the prophets of Baal, “Choose for yourselves one bull and prepare it first, for you <supplied>are</supplied> the majority, and call on the name of your god, but don’t set fire <supplied>under it</supplied>.” <verse-number id="1 Ki 18:26">26</verse-number>So they took the bull that he allowed to them, prepared it, and called upon the name of Baal from morning until noon, saying, “O Baal, answer us!” But there was no voice and there was no answer, so they limped<note>That is, moved about the altar in a cultic dance step</note> about the altar which they had made. <verse-number id="1 Ki 18:27">27</verse-number>It happened at noon that Elijah mocked them and said, “Call out with a loud voice, for he <supplied>is</supplied> a god! Perhaps he is meditating, or <idiom-start/>is using the bathroom<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “has backed off for himself”</note> or <supplied>is</supplied> on a journey. Perhaps he <supplied>is</supplied> asleep and must wake up!” <verse-number id="1 Ki 18:28">28</verse-number>So they called out with a loud voice, and they cut themselves with swords and with spears as was their custom, until the blood poured out over them. <verse-number id="1 Ki 18:29">29</verse-number>It happened as noon passed, they raged until the <supplied>time of</supplied> the evening offering, but there was no voice, there was no answer, and no <supplied>one</supplied> paid attention. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 18:30">30</verse-number>Then Elijah said to all the people, “Come near to me,” so all the people came closer to him. He repaired the altar of Yahweh <supplied>that had been</supplied> destroyed. <verse-number id="1 Ki 18:31">31</verse-number>Elijah took twelve stones according to the number of the tribes of the sons of Jacob, to whom the word of God came, saying, “Israel shall be your name.” <verse-number id="1 Ki 18:32">32</verse-number>With them, he built an altar in the name of Yahweh, and he made a trench <idiom-start/>which would have held<idiom-end/><note>Literally “as the house of”</note> about two seahs of seed, all around the altar. <verse-number id="1 Ki 18:33">33</verse-number>And he arranged the wood, cut the bull into pieces, and placed <supplied>it</supplied> on the wood.<note>in the Hebrew Bible, <cite title="BibleLEB2: 1 Ki 18:34">1 Kings 18:34 </cite>begins here</note> Then he said, “Fill four jars <supplied>with</supplied> water, and pour it on the burnt offering and on the wood.” <verse-number id="1 Ki 18:34">34</verse-number>He said, “Do <supplied>it</supplied> again!” They did <supplied>it</supplied> again. He said, “Do <supplied>it</supplied> a third time!” So they did <supplied>it</supplied> a third time. <verse-number id="1 Ki 18:35">35</verse-number>The water went all around the altar, and the trench also was filled <supplied>with</supplied> water. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 18:36">36</verse-number>It happened at the offering of the <supplied>evening</supplied> oblation, Elijah the prophet went near, and he said, “O Yahweh, God of Abraham, Isaac, and Israel; let it be known today that you <supplied>are</supplied> God in Israel and <supplied>that</supplied> I <supplied>am</supplied> your servant and <supplied>that</supplied> I have done all of these things by your words. <verse-number id="1 Ki 18:37">37</verse-number>Answer me, O Yahweh, answer me; that this people may know that you, O Yahweh, <supplied>are</supplied> God and that you have turned their hearts back again.” <verse-number id="1 Ki 18:38">38</verse-number>Then the fire of Yahweh fell, and it consumed the burnt offering, and the wood, and the stones, and the dust; and the water which <supplied>was</supplied> in the trench it licked up! <verse-number id="1 Ki 18:39">39</verse-number>When all the people saw, they fell on their faces and said, “Yahweh, he <supplied>is</supplied> God! Yahweh, he <supplied>is</supplied> God!” <verse-number id="1 Ki 18:40">40</verse-number>Then Elijah said to them, “Seize the prophets of Baal; don’t let any man of them escape!” So they seized them, and Elijah brought them down to the wadi<note>A valley that is dry most of the year, but contains a stream during the rainy season</note> of Kishon and killed them there. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Ki 18:41">41</verse-number>Then Elijah said to Ahab, “Go up, eat and drink, for <supplied>there is</supplied> the sound of the noise of rain.” <verse-number id="1 Ki 18:42">42</verse-number>So Ahab went up to eat and to drink while Elijah went to the top of Carmel, bent down to the earth, and put his face between his knees. <verse-number id="1 Ki 18:43">43</verse-number>Then he said to his servant, “Please go <supplied>and</supplied> look in the direction of <supplied>the</supplied> sea.” So he went up and looked; then he said, “There is nothing.” Then he said, “Go back,” seven times. <verse-number id="1 Ki 18:44">44</verse-number>It happened that at the seventh time, he said, “Look, there is a small cloud, as <supplied>the</supplied> hand of a man, coming up from the sea.” Then <supplied>Elijah</supplied> said, “Go up, say to Ahab, ‘Harness <supplied>your horses</supplied> and go down, lest the rain stop you.’ ” <verse-number id="1 Ki 18:45">45</verse-number><idiom-start/>In no time<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Until here and until here”</note> the heavens grew black <supplied>with</supplied> clouds and wind, and there was heavy rain. Ahab rode and he went to Jezreel, <verse-number id="1 Ki 18:46">46</verse-number>but the hand of Yahweh was on Elijah; he girded up his loins and ran before Ahab as one comes to Jezreel. </p>
		</chapter>