<chapter id="1 Jn 3">
			<p><verse-number id="1 Jn 3">3</verse-number><verse-number id="1 Jn 3:1">1</verse-number> See what sort of love the Father has given to us: that we should be called children of God, and we are! Because of this the world does not know us: because it did not know him. <verse-number id="1 Jn 3:2">2</verse-number>Dear friends, now we are children of God, and what we will be has not yet been revealed. We know that whenever he is revealed we will be like him, because we will see him just as he is. <verse-number id="1 Jn 3:3">3</verse-number>And everyone who has this hope in him purifies himself, just as that one is pure. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Jn 3:4">4</verse-number>Everyone who practices sin also practices lawlessness, and sin is lawlessness. <verse-number id="1 Jn 3:5">5</verse-number>And you know that that one was revealed in order that he might take away sins, and in him <supplied>there</supplied> is no sin. <verse-number id="1 Jn 3:6">6</verse-number>Everyone who resides in him does not sin. Everyone who sins has neither seen him nor known him. <verse-number id="1 Jn 3:7">7</verse-number>Little children, let no one deceive you: the one who practices righteousness is righteous, just as that one is righteous. <verse-number id="1 Jn 3:8">8</verse-number>The one who practices sin is of the devil, because the devil has been sinning from the beginning. For this <supplied>reason</supplied> the Son of God was revealed: in order to destroy the works of the devil. <verse-number id="1 Jn 3:9">9</verse-number>Everyone who is fathered by God does not practice sin, because his seed resides in him, and <supplied>he is</supplied> not able to sin, because he has been fathered by God. <verse-number id="1 Jn 3:10">10</verse-number>By this the children of God and the children of the devil are evident: everyone who does not practice righteousness is not of God, namely, the one who does not love his brother. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>God is Love, so Love One Another</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Jn 3:11">11</verse-number>For this is the message that you have heard from the beginning: that we should love one another, <verse-number id="1 Jn 3:12">12</verse-number>not as Cain, who was of the evil one and violently murdered his brother. And <idiom-start/>for what reason<idiom-end/><note>Literally “on account of what”</note> did he violently murder him? Because his deeds were evil and the <supplied>deeds</supplied> of his brother <supplied>were</supplied> righteous. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Jn 3:13">13</verse-number>Do not marvel,<note>Some manuscripts have “And do not marvel”</note> brothers, if the world hates you. <verse-number id="1 Jn 3:14">14</verse-number>We know that we have passed over from death to life because we love the brothers. The one who does not love remains in death. <verse-number id="1 Jn 3:15">15</verse-number>Everyone who hates his brother is a murderer, and you know that every murderer does not have eternal life residing in him. <verse-number id="1 Jn 3:16">16</verse-number>We have come to know love by this: that <idiom-start/>he<idiom-end/><note>Literally “that one” (referring to Jesus Christ)</note> laid down his life on behalf of us, and we ought to lay down our lives on behalf of the brothers. <verse-number id="1 Jn 3:17">17</verse-number>But whoever has the world’s material possessions and observes his brother <idiom-start/>in need<idiom-end/><note>Literally “having need”</note> and shuts his heart against him, how does the love of God reside in him? </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Jn 3:18">18</verse-number>Little children, let us not love with word or with tongue, but in deed and truth. <verse-number id="1 Jn 3:19">19</verse-number>By this<note>Some manuscripts have “And by this”</note> we know that we are of the truth and will convince our heart before him, <verse-number id="1 Jn 3:20">20</verse-number>that<note>Or “because”</note> if our heart condemns us, that God is greater than our heart and knows all <supplied>things</supplied>. <verse-number id="1 Jn 3:21">21</verse-number>Dear friends, if our heart does not condemn <supplied>us</supplied>, we have confidence before God, <verse-number id="1 Jn 3:22">22</verse-number>and whatever we ask we receive from him, because we keep his commandments and do <supplied>what is</supplied> pleasing <idiom-start/>in his sight<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the sight of him”</note>. <verse-number id="1 Jn 3:23">23</verse-number>And this is his commandment: that we believe in the name of his Son Jesus Christ and love one another, just as <idiom-start/>he commanded us<idiom-end/><note>Literally “he gave us commandment”</note>. <verse-number id="1 Jn 3:24">24</verse-number>And the one who keeps his commandments resides in him, and he in him. And by this we know that he resides in us: by the Spirit whom he has given to us. </p>
		</chapter>