<chapter id="1 Jn 5">
			<p><verse-number id="1 Jn 5">5</verse-number><verse-number id="1 Jn 5:1">1</verse-number> Everyone who believes that Jesus is the Christ has been fathered by God, and everyone who loves <idiom-start/>the father<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the one who fathers”</note> also loves the <supplied>child</supplied> fathered by him. <verse-number id="1 Jn 5:2">2</verse-number>By this we know that we love the children of God: whenever we love God and keep his commandments. <verse-number id="1 Jn 5:3">3</verse-number>For this is the love of God: that we keep his commandments. And his commandments are not burdensome, <verse-number id="1 Jn 5:4">4</verse-number>because everyone who is fathered by God conquers the world. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>God Has Given Us Eternal Life in the Son</pericope>
			<p>And this is the victory which has conquered the world: our faith. <verse-number id="1 Jn 5:5">5</verse-number>Now who is the one who conquers the world except the one who believes that Jesus is the Son of God? <verse-number id="1 Jn 5:6">6</verse-number>This is the one who came by water and blood—Jesus Christ, not with the water only, but with the water and with the blood. And the Spirit is the one who testifies, because the Spirit is the truth. <verse-number id="1 Jn 5:7">7</verse-number>For <supplied>there</supplied> are three that testify,<note>Later Latin manuscripts add the following words to v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:1 Jn 5:7">7</cite> and v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:1 Jn 5:8">8</cite>: “in heaven, the Father, the Word, and the Holy Spirit, and these three are one. <b>8</b> And there are three that testify on earth”</note> <verse-number id="1 Jn 5:8">8</verse-number>the Spirit and the water and the blood, and the three are <idiom-start/>in agreement<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for the one”</note>. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Jn 5:9">9</verse-number>If we receive the testimony of people, the testimony of God is greater, because this is the testimony of God that he has testified concerning his Son. <verse-number id="1 Jn 5:10">10</verse-number>(The one who believes in the Son of God has the testimony in himself. The one who does not believe God has made him a liar, because he has not believed in the testimony that God has testified concerning his Son.) <verse-number id="1 Jn 5:11">11</verse-number>And this is the testimony: that God has given us eternal life, and this life is in his Son. <verse-number id="1 Jn 5:12">12</verse-number>The one who has the Son has the life; the one who does not have the Son of God does not have the life. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Our Assurance of Eternal Life</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Jn 5:13">13</verse-number>These <supplied>things</supplied> I have written to you who believe in the name of the Son of God, in order that you may know that you have eternal life. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Jn 5:14">14</verse-number>And this is the confidence that we have before him: that if we ask anything according to his will, he hears us. <verse-number id="1 Jn 5:15">15</verse-number>And if we know that he hears us <supplied>in</supplied> whatever we ask, we know that we have the requests that we have asked from him. <verse-number id="1 Jn 5:16">16</verse-number>If anyone should see his brother sinning a sin not <supplied>leading</supplied> to death, he should ask, and he will grant life to him, to those who sin not <supplied>leading</supplied> to death. (<supplied>There</supplied> is a sin <supplied>leading</supplied> to death; I do not say that he should ask about that. <verse-number id="1 Jn 5:17">17</verse-number>All unrighteousness is sin, and <supplied>there</supplied> is a sin not <supplied>leading</supplied> to death.) </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Jn 5:18">18</verse-number>We know that everyone who is fathered by God does not sin, but the one fathered by God, he protects him, and the evil one does not touch him. <verse-number id="1 Jn 5:19">19</verse-number>We know that we are from God, and the whole world lies in <supplied>the power of</supplied> the evil one. <verse-number id="1 Jn 5:20">20</verse-number>And we know that the Son of God has come and has given us understanding, in order that we may know the one who is true, and we are in the one who is true, in his Son Jesus Christ. This one is the true God and eternal life. <verse-number id="1 Jn 5:21">21</verse-number>Little children, guard yourselves from idols. </p>
		</chapter>