<chapter id="2 Pe 1">
			<pericope>Greeting</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Pe 1:1">1</verse-number> Simeon Peter, a slave and apostle of Jesus Christ, to those who have obtained a faith equal in value to ours by the righteousness of our God and Savior Jesus Christ. <verse-number id="2 Pe 1:2">2</verse-number>May grace and peace be multiplied to you in the knowledge of God and of Jesus our Lord, <verse-number id="2 Pe 1:3">3</verse-number>because his divine power has bestowed on us all <supplied>things</supplied> <supplied>that are</supplied> necessary for life and godliness, through the knowledge of the one who called us by his own glory and excellence of character, <verse-number id="2 Pe 1:4">4</verse-number>through which things he has bestowed on us his precious and very great promises, so that through these you may become sharers of the divine nature <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“escaping from”) which is understood as temporal</note> escaping from the corruption <supplied>that is</supplied> in the world because of evil desire, <verse-number id="2 Pe 1:5">5</verse-number>and <supplied>for</supplied> this same <supplied>reason</supplied>, and <supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“applying”) which is understood as means</note> applying all diligence, supply with your faith excellence of character, and with excellence of character, knowledge, <verse-number id="2 Pe 1:6">6</verse-number>and with knowledge, self-control, and with self-control, patient endurance, and with patient endurance, godliness, <verse-number id="2 Pe 1:7">7</verse-number>and with godliness, brotherly love, and with brotherly love, love. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Make Your Calling and Election Secure</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Pe 1:8">8</verse-number>For <supplied>if</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>if</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“are”) which is understood as conditional</note> these <supplied>things</supplied> are yours and are increasing, this does not make <supplied>you</supplied> useless or unproductive in the knowledge of our Lord Jesus Christ. <verse-number id="2 Pe 1:9">9</verse-number>For <supplied>the one</supplied> for whom these <supplied>things</supplied> <supplied>are</supplied> not present is blind, being nearsighted, <idiom-start/>having forgotten the cleansing<idiom-end/><note>Literally “receiving forgetfulness of the cleansing”</note> of his former sins. <verse-number id="2 Pe 1:10">10</verse-number>Therefore, brothers, be zealous even more to make your calling and election secure, because <supplied>if you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>if</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“do”) which is understood as conditional</note> do these <supplied>things</supplied>, you will never ever stumble. <verse-number id="2 Pe 1:11">11</verse-number>For in this way entrance into the eternal kingdom of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ will be richly supplied for you. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Pe 1:12">12</verse-number>Therefore I intend to remind you continually concerning these <supplied>things</supplied>, although <supplied>you</supplied> know <supplied>them</supplied> and are established in the truth that you have. <verse-number id="2 Pe 1:13">13</verse-number>But I consider <supplied>it</supplied> right, for as long as I am in this habitation, to stir you up by a reminder, <verse-number id="2 Pe 1:14">14</verse-number><supplied>because I</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“know”) which is understood as causal</note> know that the removal of my habitation is imminent, as indeed our Lord Jesus Christ made clear to me. <verse-number id="2 Pe 1:15">15</verse-number>And I will also make every effort <supplied>that</supplied> you are able at any time, after my departure, <idiom-start/>to recall these things to mind<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to make recollection of these”</note>. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Reliable Prophetic Word of Testimony</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Pe 1:16">16</verse-number>For we did not make known to you the power and coming of our Lord Jesus Christ <supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“following”) which is understood as means</note> following ingeniously concocted myths, but <supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“being”) which is understood as means</note> being eyewitnesses of that one’s majesty. <verse-number id="2 Pe 1:17">17</verse-number>For <supplied>he</supplied> received honor and glory from God the Father <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was brought”)</note> a voice such as this was brought to him by the Majestic Glory, “This is my beloved Son, in whom I am well pleased.” <verse-number id="2 Pe 1:18">18</verse-number>And <supplied>we</supplied> ourselves heard this voice brought from heaven <supplied>when we</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“were”) which is understood as temporal</note> were with him on the holy mountain, <verse-number id="2 Pe 1:19">19</verse-number>and we possess <supplied>as</supplied> more reliable the prophetic word, to which you do well <supplied>if you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>if</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“pay attention to”) which is understood as conditional</note> pay attention to <supplied>it</supplied> as to a lamp shining in a dark place, until the day dawns and the morning star rises in your hearts, <verse-number id="2 Pe 1:20">20</verse-number>recognizing this above all, that every prophecy of scripture does not come about from one’s own interpretation, <verse-number id="2 Pe 1:21">21</verse-number>for no prophecy was ever produced by the will of man, but men carried along by the Holy Spirit spoke from God. </p>
		</chapter>