<chapter id="2 Pe 2">
			<pericope>The Rise and Fall of the False Teachers</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Pe 2:1">1</verse-number> But there were also false prophets among the people, as there will be false teachers among you also, who will bring in <idiom-start/>destructive heresies<idiom-end/><note>Literally “heresies of destruction”</note>, even denying the Master who bought them, <supplied>thus</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>thus</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“bringing on”) which is understood as result</note> bringing on themselves swift destruction. <verse-number id="2 Pe 2:2">2</verse-number>And many will follow their licentious ways, because of whom the way of truth will be reviled. <verse-number id="2 Pe 2:3">3</verse-number>And in greediness they will exploit you with false words, whose condemnation <supplied>from</supplied> long ago is not idle, and their destruction is not asleep. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Pe 2:4">4</verse-number>For if God did not spare the angels who sinned, but held <supplied>them</supplied> captive in Tartarus with chains of darkness <supplied>and</supplied> handed <supplied>them</supplied> over to be kept for judgment, <verse-number id="2 Pe 2:5">5</verse-number>and did not spare the ancient world, but preserved Noah, a proclaimer of righteousness, <idiom-start/>and seven others<idiom-end/><note>Literally “eighth”</note> <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“brought”) which is understood as temporal</note> brought a flood on the world of the ungodly, <verse-number id="2 Pe 2:6">6</verse-number>and condemned the cities of Sodom and Gomorrah to destruction, reducing them to ashes, having appointed <supplied>them</supplied> <supplied>as</supplied> an example for those who are going to be ungodly, <verse-number id="2 Pe 2:7">7</verse-number>and rescued righteous Lot, worn down by the way of life of lawless persons in licentiousness <verse-number id="2 Pe 2:8">8</verse-number>(for that righteous man, <supplied>as he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“lived”) which is understood as temporal</note> lived among them day after day, was tormenting <supplied>his</supplied> righteous soul by the lawless deeds <supplied>he was</supplied> seeing and hearing), <verse-number id="2 Pe 2:9">9</verse-number><supplied>then</supplied> the Lord knows how to rescue the godly from trials and to reserve the unrighteous to be punished at<note>Or “until”</note> the day of judgment, <verse-number id="2 Pe 2:10">10</verse-number>and especially those who go after the flesh in defiling lust<note>Literally “in lust of defilement,” translated here as an attributive genitive</note> and who despise authority. </p>
			<p>Bold <supplied>and</supplied> arrogant, they do not tremble in awe <supplied>as they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“blaspheme”) which is understood as temporal</note> blaspheme majestic beings, <verse-number id="2 Pe 2:11">11</verse-number>whereas angels, who are greater in strength and power, do not bring against them a demeaning judgment.<note>Some manuscripts have “a demeaning judgment from the Lord”</note> <verse-number id="2 Pe 2:12">12</verse-number>But these persons, like irrational animals born <supplied>only with</supplied> natural <supplied>instincts</supplied> for capture and killing, blaspheming <idiom-start/>about things<idiom-end/><note>Literally “with reference to which”</note> they do not understand, in their destruction will also be destroyed, <verse-number id="2 Pe 2:13">13</verse-number>being harmed <supplied>as the</supplied> wages of unrighteousness. Considering reveling in the daytime a pleasure, <supplied>they are</supplied> stains and blemishes, carousing in their deceitful pleasures <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“feast together”) which is understood as temporal</note> feast together with you, <verse-number id="2 Pe 2:14">14</verse-number>having eyes full of <supplied>desire for</supplied> an adulteress and unceasing from sin, enticing unstable persons, <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied in keeping with English style</note> having hearts trained for greediness. Accursed children! <verse-number id="2 Pe 2:15">15</verse-number><supplied>By</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“leaving”) which is understood as means</note> leaving the straight path, they have gone astray, <supplied>because they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“followed”) which is understood as causal</note> followed the way of Balaam the <supplied>son of</supplied> Bosor,<note>Although some English versions use “Beor” here, this is due to harmonization with the Old Testament; the vast majority of Greek manuscripts read “Bosor” here</note> who loved the wages of unrighteousness, <verse-number id="2 Pe 2:16">16</verse-number>but received a rebuke for his own lawlessness: a speechless donkey, speaking with a human voice, restrained <idiom-start/>the prophet’s madness<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the of the prophet madness”</note>. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Pe 2:17">17</verse-number>These <supplied>people</supplied> are waterless springs and mists driven by a hurricane, for whom the gloom of darkness has been reserved. <verse-number id="2 Pe 2:18">18</verse-number><idiom-start/>For by speaking high-sounding but empty words<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for speaking pompous <supplied>words</supplied> of emptiness”</note>, they entice with desires of the flesh <supplied>and</supplied> with licentiousness those who are scarcely escaping from those who live in error, <verse-number id="2 Pe 2:19">19</verse-number>promising them freedom <supplied>although they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>although</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“are”) which is understood as concessive</note> themselves are slaves of depravity. For to whatever someone succumbs, by this he is also<note>Some manuscripts omit “also”</note> enslaved. <verse-number id="2 Pe 2:20">20</verse-number>For if, <supplied>after they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“have escaped from”) which is understood as temporal</note> have escaped from the defilements of the world through the knowledge of the Lord<note>Some manuscripts have “of our Lord”</note> and Savior Jesus Christ, and they are again entangled in these <supplied>things</supplied> <supplied>and</supplied> succumb to <supplied>them</supplied>, the last <supplied>state</supplied> has become worse for them than the first. <verse-number id="2 Pe 2:21">21</verse-number>For it would have been better for them not to have known the way of righteousness than having known <supplied>it</supplied>, to turn back from the holy commandment that had been delivered to them. <verse-number id="2 Pe 2:22">22</verse-number>The <supplied>statement</supplied> of the true proverb has happened to them, “A dog returns to its own vomit,”<note>A paraphrased quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Pr 26:11">Prov 26:11</cite></note> and “A sow, <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“washing herself”) which is understood as temporal</note> washing herself, <supplied>returns</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The verb “<supplied>returns</supplied>” is not in the Greek text, but is an understood repetition from the previous clause</note> to wallowing in the mud.”<note>The source of this quotation is uncertain</note> </p>
		</chapter>