<chapter id="2 Pe 3">
			<pericope>The Coming Day of the Lord</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Pe 3:1">1</verse-number> Dear friends, this <supplied>is</supplied> already the second letter I am writing to you, in <supplied>both of</supplied> which I am attempting to stir up your sincere mind by a reminder, <verse-number id="2 Pe 3:2">2</verse-number>to remember the words proclaimed beforehand by the holy prophets and the commandment of the Lord and Savior through your apostles, <verse-number id="2 Pe 3:3">3</verse-number>above all knowing this, that in the last days scoffers will come with scoffing, following according to their own desires <verse-number id="2 Pe 3:4">4</verse-number>and saying, “Where is the promise of his coming? For <idiom-start/>ever since<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from which <supplied>time</supplied>”</note> the fathers fell asleep, all <supplied>things</supplied> have continued just as they have been from the beginning of creation.” <verse-number id="2 Pe 3:5">5</verse-number>For <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“maintain”) which is understood as temporal</note> they maintain this, it escapes <supplied>their</supplied> notice that the heavens existed long ago and the earth held together out of water and through water by the word of God, <verse-number id="2 Pe 3:6">6</verse-number>by means of which things the world that existed at that time was destroyed <supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“being inundated”) which is understood as means</note> being inundated with water. <verse-number id="2 Pe 3:7">7</verse-number>But by the same word the present heavens and earth are reserved for fire, being kept for the day of judgment and destruction of ungodly people. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Pe 3:8">8</verse-number>Now, dear friends, do not let this one thing escape your <supplied>notice</supplied>, that one day with the Lord <supplied>is</supplied> like a thousand years, and a thousand years <supplied>is</supplied> like one day. <verse-number id="2 Pe 3:9">9</verse-number>The Lord is not delaying the promise, as some consider slowness, but is being patient toward you, <supplied>because he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“want”) which is understood as causal</note> does not want any to perish, but all to come to repentance. <verse-number id="2 Pe 3:10">10</verse-number>But the day of the Lord will come like a thief, in which the heavens will disappear with a rushing noise, and the celestial bodies will be destroyed <supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“being burned up”) which is understood as means</note> being burned up, and the earth and the deeds <supplied>done</supplied> on it will be disclosed. <verse-number id="2 Pe 3:11">11</verse-number><supplied>Because</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“are being destroyed”) which is understood as causal</note> all these things are being destroyed in this way, what sort of <supplied>people</supplied> must you be in holy behavior and godliness, <verse-number id="2 Pe 3:12">12</verse-number><supplied>while</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“waiting for”) which is understood as temporal</note> waiting for and hastening the coming of the day of God, because of which the heavens will be destroyed <supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“being burned up”) which is understood as means</note> being burned up and the celestial bodies will melt <supplied>as they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“are consumed by heat”) which is understood as temporal</note> are consumed by heat! <verse-number id="2 Pe 3:13">13</verse-number>But according to his promise, we are waiting for new heavens and a new earth in which righteousness resides. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Final Exhortations and Conclusion</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Pe 3:14">14</verse-number>Therefore, dear friends, <supplied>because you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“are waiting for”) which is understood as causal</note> are waiting for these <supplied>things</supplied>, make every effort to be found at peace, spotless and unblemished in him. <verse-number id="2 Pe 3:15">15</verse-number>And regard the patience of our Lord as salvation, just as also our dear brother Paul wrote to you, according to the wisdom that was given to him, <verse-number id="2 Pe 3:16">16</verse-number>as <supplied>he does</supplied> also in all his<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note>﻿<note>Some manuscripts do not explicitly state “his”</note> letters, speaking in them about these <supplied>things</supplied>, in which there are some <supplied>things</supplied> hard to understand, which the ignorant and unstable distort to their own destruction, as <supplied>they</supplied> also <supplied>do</supplied> the rest of the scriptures. <verse-number id="2 Pe 3:17">17</verse-number>Therefore, dear friends, <supplied>because you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“know beforehand”) which is understood as causal</note> know <supplied>this</supplied> beforehand, guard yourselves so that you do not lose your own safe position <supplied>because you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“have been led away”) which is understood as causal</note> have been led away by the error of lawless persons. <verse-number id="2 Pe 3:18">18</verse-number>But grow in the grace and knowledge of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ. To him <supplied>be</supplied> the glory, both now and to the day of eternity. Amen. </p>
		</chapter>