<chapter id="Mic 6">
			<pericope>Yahweh Brings a Charge against Israel</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Mic 6:1">1</verse-number>Hear now what Yahweh says: </li1>
				<li1>“Arise! Plead <supplied>your case</supplied> with the mountains, </li1>
				<li2>and let the hills hear your voice.” </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Mic 6:2">2</verse-number>Hear, O mountains, the indictment of Yahweh, </li1>
				<li2>and you eternal foundations of the earth, </li2>
				<li1>for Yahweh has an indictment against his people, </li1>
				<li2>and against Israel he contends. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Mic 6:3">3</verse-number>“O my people, what have I done to you, </li1>
				<li2>and how have I wearied you? Answer me! </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Mic 6:4">4</verse-number>For I brought you up from the land of Egypt, </li1>
				<li2>and from the house of slavery I redeemed you. </li2>
				<li2>And I sent Moses, Aaron, and Miriam before you. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Mic 6:5">5</verse-number>O my people, remember what Balak the king of Moab devised, </li1>
				<li2>and what Balaam the son of Beor answered him, </li2>
				<li1>and <supplied>what happened from</supplied> Shittim to Gilgal, </li1>
				<li2>so that you might know the righteous acts of Yahweh.” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>What Does Yahweh Require?</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Mic 6:6">6</verse-number>With what shall I approach Yahweh, </li1>
				<li2>and bow down to God on high? </li2>
				<li1>Shall I approach him with burnt offerings, </li1>
				<li2>with bull calves a year old? </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Mic 6:7">7</verse-number>Will Yahweh be pleased with thousands of rams, </li1>
				<li2>with myriads of rivers of oil? </li2>
				<li1>Shall I give my firstborn for my transgression, </li1>
				<li2>the fruit of my body <supplied>for the</supplied> sin of my soul? </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Mic 6:8">8</verse-number>He has told you, O mortal, what <supplied>is</supplied> good, </li1>
				<li2>and what does Yahweh ask from you </li2>
				<li1>but to do justice, and to love kindness, </li1>
				<li2>and to walk humbly with your God? </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Destruction of the Wicked</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Mic 6:9">9</verse-number>The voice of Yahweh calls to the city </li1>
				<li2>(<supplied>it is</supplied> sound judgment to fear your name): </li2>
				<li2>“Hear, <supplied>O</supplied> staff!<note>Or “tribe”</note> Now who has appointed it? </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Mic 6:10">10</verse-number>Is there any longer a man <supplied>in</supplied> the house of the wicked </li1>
				<li2>treasures of wickedness, </li2>
				<li2>and the ephah of scarcity <supplied>which is</supplied> accursed?<note>The meaning of the Hebrew text is uncertain</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Mic 6:11">11</verse-number>Shall I regard as pure <supplied>the one</supplied> with scales of wickedness, </li1>
				<li2>and with a bag of deceitful weights? </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Mic 6:12">12</verse-number>Because her rich are full of violence, </li1>
				<li2>and her inhabitants speak lies, </li2>
				<li2>and their tongue <supplied>is</supplied> deceitful in their mouth. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Mic 6:13">13</verse-number>And I also <idiom-start/>have made you sick by striking you down<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “I have made sick to strike you down”</note> </li1>
				<li2>making <supplied>you</supplied> desolate because of your sins. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Mic 6:14">14</verse-number>You yourself will eat but not be satisfied; </li1>
				<li2>your hunger <supplied>will be</supplied> in your midst, </li2>
				<li1>and you will put away, but you will not save, </li1>
				<li2>and what you save I will hand over to the sword. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Mic 6:15">15</verse-number>You yourself will sow, but you will not reap; </li1>
				<li2>you will tread olives, but you will not anoint yourself with oil; </li2>
				<li2><supplied>you will tread</supplied> grapes, but you will not drink wine. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Mic 6:16">16</verse-number>For you have observed the regulations of Omri </li1>
				<li2>and all the works of the house of Ahab. </li2>
				<li1>And you have walked in their counsels, </li1>
				<li2>so that I am making you a desolation </li2>
				<li1>and your inhabitants an object of scorn. </li1>
				<li2>So you will bear the scorn of my people. </li2>
			</ul>
		</chapter>