<chapter id="Hag 2">
			<pericope>A Promise to Rebuild</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Hag 2:1">1</verse-number>In the seventh <supplied>month</supplied> on the twenty-first day, the word of Yahweh <idiom-start/>came through<idiom-end/><note>Literally “came through the hand of”</note> Haggai the prophet, saying, <verse-number id="Hag 2:2">2</verse-number>“Speak now to Zerubbabel son of Shealtiel, governor of Judah, and to Joshua son of Jehozadak, the high priest, and to the remnant of the people, saying, <verse-number id="Hag 2:3">3</verse-number>‘Who among you <supplied>is</supplied> left that saw this house in its former glory? And how do you see it now? Does it seem like nothing <idiom-start/>to you<idiom-end/>?<note>Literally “in your eyes”</note> <verse-number id="Hag 2:4">4</verse-number>‘But now take courage,<note>Or “be strong”</note> Zerubbabel,’ <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh. ‘Take courage,<note>Or “Be strong”</note> Joshua son of Jehozadak, the high priest, and take courage,<note>Or “be strong”</note> all the people of the land,’ <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh. ‘Do the work, because I <supplied>am</supplied> with you,’ <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh of hosts, <verse-number id="Hag 2:5">5</verse-number>‘according to <idiom-start/>the promise<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the word”</note> that <idiom-start/>I covenanted<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I cut”</note> with you when you came out of Egypt. My spirit <idiom-start/>is with you<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “<supplied>is</supplied> standing in your midst”</note> do not be afraid.’ <verse-number id="Hag 2:6">6</verse-number>For thus says Yahweh of hosts: ‘Once again, in a little while, I will shake the heavens and the earth and the sea and dry land. <verse-number id="Hag 2:7">7</verse-number>I will shake all the nations so that the treasure of all the nations will come, and I will fill this house<note>That is, the temple</note> <supplied>with</supplied> glory,’ says Yahweh of hosts. <verse-number id="Hag 2:8">8</verse-number>‘The silver <supplied>is</supplied> mine and the gold <supplied>is</supplied> mine,’ <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh of hosts. <verse-number id="Hag 2:9">9</verse-number>‘The latter glory of this house will be greater than the former,’ says Yahweh of hosts, ‘and in this place I will give peace’ <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh of hosts.’ ” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Hag 2:10">10</verse-number>On <supplied>the</supplied> twenty-fourth <supplied>day</supplied> of the ninth <supplied>month</supplied>, in the second year of Darius, the word of Yahweh came to the prophet Haggai, saying, <verse-number id="Hag 2:11">11</verse-number>“Thus says Yahweh of hosts: ‘Ask now the priests <supplied>for</supplied> a ruling:<note>Or “a torah,” or “a law”</note> <verse-number id="Hag 2:12">12</verse-number>If a man carries<note>Literally “lifts”</note> consecrated meat in the hem of his garment, and his hem touches bread, or stew, or wine, or olive oil, or any kind of food, will it become holy?’ ” The priests answered, “No.” <verse-number id="Hag 2:13">13</verse-number>Then Haggai said, “If one who is unclean from contact with a corpse touches any of these, will it become unclean?” The priests answered, “Yes, it will be become unclean.” <verse-number id="Hag 2:14">14</verse-number>And Haggai answered and said, “ ‘So <supplied>it is with</supplied> this people, and <supplied>with</supplied> this nation before me,’ <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh, ‘and so <supplied>it is with</supplied> every kind of work of their hands; and what they offer there <supplied>is</supplied> unclean. <verse-number id="Hag 2:15">15</verse-number>But now, please <idiom-start/>consider<idiom-end/><note>Literally “set your heart”</note> from this day forward, before one stone was placed on another in the temple of Yahweh, <verse-number id="Hag 2:16">16</verse-number><idiom-start/>from that time when<idiom-end/><note>Or “from their being,” or “from the time they were then”</note> one came to a heap of twenty <supplied>measures</supplied>, there were <supplied>only</supplied> ten, and <supplied>when</supplied> one came to the wine vat to draw out fifty measures,<note>Hebrew “measure”</note> there were <supplied>only</supplied> twenty. <verse-number id="Hag 2:17">17</verse-number>I struck you with blight, and with plant mildew, and hail, all the work of your hands. But <idiom-start/>you did not come back to me<idiom-end/>,’<note>Literally “there were none of you to me”</note> <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh. <verse-number id="Hag 2:18">18</verse-number>‘<idiom-start/>Please consider<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Please set your heart”</note> from this day forward, from the twenty-fourth day of the ninth <supplied>month</supplied>, from the day that the foundation of Yahweh’s temple was laid,<note>Or “placed,” or “set”</note> <idiom-start/>consider<idiom-end/>:<note>Literally “set your heart”</note> <verse-number id="Hag 2:19">19</verse-number><supplied>Is there</supplied> still seed in the store chamber? Do the vine, the fig tree, the pomegranate, and the olive tree still produce nothing? From this day <supplied>forward</supplied> I will bless <supplied>you</supplied>.’ ” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Coming Kingdom</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Hag 2:20">20</verse-number>And the word of Yahweh came to Haggai a second time on the twenty-fourth <supplied>day</supplied> of the month saying, <verse-number id="Hag 2:21">21</verse-number>“Say to Zerubbabel, governor of Judah: I <supplied>am</supplied> going to shake the heavens and the earth, <verse-number id="Hag 2:22">22</verse-number>and I will overthrow the thrones of kingdoms and destroy the military strength of the kingdoms of the nations. I will overthrow chariots and their drivers; horses and their riders will fall, every one by the sword of another! <verse-number id="Hag 2:23">23</verse-number>‘On that day,’ <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh of hosts, ‘I will take you, Zerubbabel son of Shealtiel, my servant,’ <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh, ‘and I will make you a signet ring, for I have chosen you,’ <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh of hosts.” </p>
		</chapter>