<chapter id="Jn 1">
			<pericope>The Prologue to John’s Gospel</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 1:1">1</verse-number> In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God. <verse-number id="Jn 1:2">2</verse-number>This one was in the beginning with God. <verse-number id="Jn 1:3">3</verse-number>All <supplied>things</supplied> came into being through him, and apart from him not one <supplied>thing</supplied> came into being that<note>Or “came into being. What …,” beginning a new sentence connected with the following verse. A major punctuation problem is involved, since the earliest manuscripts have no punctuation, but some important later ones place the punctuation before this phrase, effectively connecting it to v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Jn 1:4">4</cite>: “What has come into being was life in him”</note> has come into being. <verse-number id="Jn 1:4">4</verse-number>In him was life, and the life was the light of humanity.<note>Or “humankind”</note> <verse-number id="Jn 1:5">5</verse-number>And the light shines in the darkness, and the darkness did not overcome<note>Or “comprehend” (if primarily referring to people in the world)</note> it. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 1:6">6</verse-number>A man came, sent from God, <idiom-start/>whose name was<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the name to him”</note> John. <verse-number id="Jn 1:7">7</verse-number>This one came for a witness, in order that he could testify about the light, so that all would believe through him. <verse-number id="Jn 1:8">8</verse-number>That one was not the light, but <supplied>came</supplied><note>The verb is implied from the previous verse, and must be supplied in the English translation</note> in order that he could testify about the light. <verse-number id="Jn 1:9">9</verse-number>The true light, who gives light to every person, was coming into the world. <verse-number id="Jn 1:10">10</verse-number>He was in the world, and the world came into being through him, and the world did not recognize<note>Or “acknowledge”</note> him. <verse-number id="Jn 1:11">11</verse-number>He came to his own <supplied>things</supplied>, and his own <supplied>people</supplied> did not receive him. <verse-number id="Jn 1:12">12</verse-number>But as many as received him—to those who believe in his name—he gave to them authority to become children of God, <verse-number id="Jn 1:13">13</verse-number>who were born not of blood, nor of the will of the flesh, nor of the will of a husband, but of God. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 1:14">14</verse-number>And the Word became flesh and took up residence among us, and we saw his glory, glory as of the one and only from the Father, full of grace and truth. <verse-number id="Jn 1:15">15</verse-number>John testified about him and cried out, saying, “This one was <supplied>he about</supplied> whom I said, ‘The one who comes after me is ahead of me, because he existed before me.’ ” <verse-number id="Jn 1:16">16</verse-number>For from his fullness we have all received, and grace after grace. <verse-number id="Jn 1:17">17</verse-number>For the law was given through Moses; grace and truth came about through Jesus Christ. <verse-number id="Jn 1:18">18</verse-number>No one has seen God at any time; the one and only, God, the one who is in the bosom of the Father—that one has made <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> known. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>John the Baptist Testifies to Jesus</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 1:19">19</verse-number>And this is the testimony of John, when the Jews sent<note>Some manuscripts have “sent to him”</note> priests and Levites from Jerusalem so that they could ask him, “Who are you?” <verse-number id="Jn 1:20">20</verse-number>And he confessed—and he did not deny, and confessed—“I am not the Christ!” <verse-number id="Jn 1:21">21</verse-number>And they asked him, “Then who <supplied>are</supplied> you? Are you Elijah?” And he said, “I am not!” “Are you the Prophet?”<note>A reference to the “Prophet like Moses” of <cite title="BibleLEB2: Dt 18:15">Deut 18:15 </cite>(see <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ac 3:22">Acts 3:22</cite>)</note> And he answered, “No!” <verse-number id="Jn 1:22">22</verse-number>Then they said to him, “Who are you, so that we can give an answer to those who sent us? What do you say about yourself?” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 1:23">23</verse-number>He said, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“I <supplied>am</supplied> ‘the voice of one crying out in the wilderness, </li1>
				<li2>“Make straight the way of the Lord,” ’<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 40:3">Isa 40:3</cite></note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p>just as Isaiah the prophet said.” <verse-number id="Jn 1:24">24</verse-number>(And they had been sent from the Pharisees.) <verse-number id="Jn 1:25">25</verse-number>And they asked him and said to him, “Why then are you baptizing, if you are not the Christ, nor Elijah, nor the Prophet?” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 1:26">26</verse-number>John answered them, saying, “I baptize with water. In your midst stands <supplied>one</supplied> whom you do not know—<verse-number id="Jn 1:27">27</verse-number>the one who comes after me, of whom I am not worthy <idiom-start/>to untie<idiom-end/><note>Literally “that I might untie”</note> the strap of his sandal!” <verse-number id="Jn 1:28">28</verse-number>These <supplied>things</supplied> took place in Bethany on the other side of the Jordan, where John was baptizing. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 1:29">29</verse-number>On the next day he saw Jesus coming to him and said, “Look! The Lamb of God who takes away the sin of the world! <verse-number id="Jn 1:30">30</verse-number>This one is <supplied>the one</supplied> about whom I said, ‘After me is coming a man who is ahead of me, because he existed before me.’ <verse-number id="Jn 1:31">31</verse-number>And I did not know him, but in order that he could be revealed to Israel, because of this I came baptizing with water.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 1:32">32</verse-number>And John testified, saying, “I have seen the Spirit descending like a dove from heaven and remaining upon him. <verse-number id="Jn 1:33">33</verse-number>And I did not know him, but the one who sent me to baptize with water, that one said to me, ‘<supplied>The one</supplied> upon whom you see the Spirit descending and remaining upon him—this one is the one who baptizes with the Holy Spirit.’ <verse-number id="Jn 1:34">34</verse-number>And I have seen and testify that this one is the Chosen One<note>Some manuscripts have “the Son of God”</note> of God. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Two of John’s Disciples Follow Jesus</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 1:35">35</verse-number>On the next day again John was standing <supplied>there</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The word “<supplied>there</supplied>” is not in the Greek text but is implied</note> and two of his disciples, <verse-number id="Jn 1:36">36</verse-number>and looking at Jesus <supplied>as he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“walking by”) which is understood as temporal</note> was walking by, he said, “Look! The Lamb of God!” <verse-number id="Jn 1:37">37</verse-number>And the two disciples heard him speaking, and they followed Jesus. <verse-number id="Jn 1:38">38</verse-number>And Jesus, turning around and seeing them following <supplied>him</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> said to them, “What do you seek?” And they said to him, “Rabbi” (which means <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“translated”) which is understood as temporal</note> translated “Teacher”), “where are you staying?” <verse-number id="Jn 1:39">39</verse-number>He said to them, “Come and you will see!” So they came and saw where he was staying, and they stayed with him that day (it was about the tenth hour). </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Andrew Declares Jesus to be the Messiah</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 1:40">40</verse-number>Andrew, the brother of Simon Peter, was one of the two who heard John and followed him. <verse-number id="Jn 1:41">41</verse-number>This one first found his own brother Simon and said to him, “We have found the Messiah!” (which is translated “Christ”). <verse-number id="Jn 1:42">42</verse-number>He brought him to Jesus. Looking at him, Jesus said, “You are Simon the son of John. You will be called Cephas” (which is interpreted “Peter”). </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus Calls Philip and Nathanael</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 1:43">43</verse-number>On the next day he wanted to depart for Galilee, and he found Philip. And Jesus said to him, “Follow me!” <verse-number id="Jn 1:44">44</verse-number>(Now Philip was from Bethsaida, the town of Andrew and Peter.) <verse-number id="Jn 1:45">45</verse-number>Philip found Nathanael and said to him, “We have found <supplied>the one</supplied> whom Moses wrote <supplied>about</supplied> in the law, and the prophets wrote <supplied>about</supplied>—Jesus son of Joseph from Nazareth!” <verse-number id="Jn 1:46">46</verse-number>And Nathanael said to him, “Can anything good come out of Nazareth?” Philip said to him, “Come and see!” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 1:47">47</verse-number>Jesus saw Nathanael coming toward him and said about him, “Look! <idiom-start/>A true Israelite<idiom-end/><note>Literally “truly an Israelite”</note> in whom is no deceit!” <verse-number id="Jn 1:48">48</verse-number>Nathanael said to him, “From where do you know me?” Jesus answered and said to him, “Before Philip called you, <supplied>when you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“were”) which is understood as temporal</note> were under the fig tree, I saw you.” <verse-number id="Jn 1:49">49</verse-number>Nathanael answered him, “Rabbi, you are the Son of God! You are the king of Israel!” <verse-number id="Jn 1:50">50</verse-number>Jesus answered and said to him, “Because I said to you that I saw you under the fig tree, do you believe? You will see greater <supplied>things</supplied> than these!” <verse-number id="Jn 1:51">51</verse-number>And he said to him, “Truly, truly I say to all of you, you will see heaven opened and the angels of God ascending and descending upon the Son of Man.” </p>
		</chapter>