<chapter id="Jn 4">
			<pericope>The Samaritan Woman at Jacob’s Well</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 4:1">1</verse-number> Now when Jesus knew that the Pharisees had heard that Jesus was making and baptizing more disciples than John <verse-number id="Jn 4:2">2</verse-number>(although Jesus himself was not baptizing, but his disciples), <verse-number id="Jn 4:3">3</verse-number>he left Judea and departed again for Galilee. <verse-number id="Jn 4:4">4</verse-number>And it was necessary <supplied>for</supplied> him to go through Samaria. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 4:5">5</verse-number>Now he came to a town of Samaria called Sychar, near the piece of land that Jacob had given to his son Joseph. <verse-number id="Jn 4:6">6</verse-number>And Jacob’s well was there, so Jesus, <supplied>because he</supplied> had become tired from the journey, simply sat down at the well. It was about the sixth hour. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 4:7">7</verse-number>A woman of Samaria came to draw water. Jesus said to her, “Give me <supplied>water</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “water” is supplied in the translation as the understood direct object of the verb “give”</note> to drink.” <verse-number id="Jn 4:8">8</verse-number>(For his disciples had gone away into the town so that they could buy food.) <verse-number id="Jn 4:9">9</verse-number>So the Samaritan woman said to him, “How do you, being a Jew, ask from me <supplied>water</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “water” is supplied in the translation as the understood direct object of the verb “ask”</note> to drink, <supplied>since I</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>since</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“am”) which is understood as causal</note> am a Samaritan woman?” (For Jews have no dealings with Samaritans.) </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 4:10">10</verse-number>Jesus answered and said to her, “If you had known the gift of God and who it is who says to you, ‘Give me <supplied>water</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “water” is supplied in the translation as the understood direct object of the verb “give”</note> to drink,’ you would have asked him, and he would have given you living water.” <verse-number id="Jn 4:11">11</verse-number>The woman said to him, “Sir, you have no bucket and the well is deep! From where then do you get this living water? <verse-number id="Jn 4:12">12</verse-number>You are not greater than our father Jacob, <supplied>are you</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here, indicated by the supplied phrase “<supplied>are you</supplied>” in the translation</note> who gave us the well and drank from it himself, and his sons and his livestock?” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 4:13">13</verse-number>Jesus answered and said to her, “Everyone who drinks of this water will be thirsty again. <verse-number id="Jn 4:14">14</verse-number>But whoever drinks of this water which I will give to him will never be thirsty for eternity, but the water which I will give to him will become in him a well of water springing up to eternal life.” <verse-number id="Jn 4:15">15</verse-number>The woman said to him, “Sir, give me this water, so that I will not be thirsty or come here to draw <supplied>water</supplied>!”<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <verse-number id="Jn 4:16">16</verse-number>He said to her, “Go, call your husband and come here.” <verse-number id="Jn 4:17">17</verse-number>The woman answered and said to him, “I do not have a husband.” Jesus said to her, “You have said rightly, ‘I do not have a husband,’ <verse-number id="Jn 4:18">18</verse-number>for you have had five husbands, and <supplied>the one</supplied> whom you have now is not your husband; this you have said truthfully!” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 4:19">19</verse-number>The woman said to him, “Sir, I see that you are a prophet. <verse-number id="Jn 4:20">20</verse-number>Our fathers worshiped on this mountain, and you <supplied>people</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>people</supplied>” is supplied in the translation because the Greek pronoun is plural</note> say that in Jerusalem is the place where it is necessary to worship.” <verse-number id="Jn 4:21">21</verse-number>Jesus said to her, “Believe me, woman, that an hour is coming when neither on this mountain nor in Jerusalem will you worship the Father. <verse-number id="Jn 4:22">22</verse-number>You worship what you do not know. We worship what we know, because salvation is from the Jews. <verse-number id="Jn 4:23">23</verse-number>But an hour is coming—and now is <supplied>here</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The word “<supplied>here</supplied>” is not in the Greek text but is implied</note>—when the true worshipers will worship the Father in spirit and truth, for indeed the Father seeks such <supplied>people</supplied> <supplied>to be</supplied> his worshipers. <verse-number id="Jn 4:24">24</verse-number>God <supplied>is</supplied> spirit, and the ones who worship him must worship in spirit and truth.” <verse-number id="Jn 4:25">25</verse-number>The woman said to him, “I know that Messiah is coming” (the one called Christ); “whenever that one comes, he will proclaim all <supplied>things</supplied> to us.” <verse-number id="Jn 4:26">26</verse-number>Jesus said to her, “I, the one speaking to you, am <supplied>he</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the predicate nominative is supplied from context in the English translation</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Disciples and the Harvest</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 4:27">27</verse-number>And at this <supplied>point</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The word “<supplied>point</supplied>” is not in the Greek text but is implied</note> his disciples came, and they were astonished that he was speaking with a woman. However, no one said, “What do you seek?” or “Why are you speaking with her?” <verse-number id="Jn 4:28">28</verse-number>So the woman left her water jar and went away into the town and said to the people,<note>Assuming the term is used here in a generic sense to refer to persons of either gender, it should be translated “people”; if instead the term here refers only to the town leaders or elders who met at the town gate, then “men” would be appropriate</note> <verse-number id="Jn 4:29">29</verse-number>“Come, see a man who told me everything I have ever done! Perhaps this one is the Christ?” <verse-number id="Jn 4:30">30</verse-number>They went out from the town and were coming to him. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 4:31">31</verse-number>In the meanwhile the disciples were asking him, saying, “Rabbi, eat <supplied>something</supplied>!”<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <verse-number id="Jn 4:32">32</verse-number>But he said to them, “I have food to eat that you do not know about.” <verse-number id="Jn 4:33">33</verse-number>So the disciples began to say<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to say”)</note> to one another, “No one brought him <supplied>anything</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to eat, <supplied>did they</supplied>?”<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here, indicated by the supplied phrase “<supplied>did they</supplied>” in the translation</note> <verse-number id="Jn 4:34">34</verse-number>Jesus said to them, “My food is that I do the will of the one who sent me and complete his work. <verse-number id="Jn 4:35">35</verse-number>Do you not say, ‘There are yet four months and the harvest comes’? Behold, I say to you, lift up your eyes and look at the fields, that they are white for harvest already.<note>Some interpreters and Bible translations place the word “already” at the beginning of the next verse: “Already the one who reaps receives wages …”</note> <verse-number id="Jn 4:36">36</verse-number>The one who reaps receives wages and gathers fruit for eternal life, in order that the one who sows and the one who reaps can rejoice together. <verse-number id="Jn 4:37">37</verse-number>For in this <supplied>instance</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The word “<supplied>point</supplied>” is not in the Greek text but is implied</note> the saying is true, ‘It is one who sows and another who reaps.’ <verse-number id="Jn 4:38">38</verse-number>I sent you to reap what you did not work for; others have worked, and you have entered into their work.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Samaritans and the Savior of the World</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 4:39">39</verse-number>Now from that town many of the Samaritans believed in him because of the word of the woman who testified, “He told me everything that I have done.” <verse-number id="Jn 4:40">40</verse-number>So when the Samaritans came to him, they began asking<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began asking”)</note> him to stay with them. And he stayed there two days. <verse-number id="Jn 4:41">41</verse-number>And many more believed because of his word, <verse-number id="Jn 4:42">42</verse-number>And they were saying to the woman, “No longer because of <idiom-start/>what you said<idiom-end/><note>Literally “your speaking”</note> do we believe, for we ourselves have heard, and we know that this one is truly the Savior of the world!” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Return to Galilee</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 4:43">43</verse-number>And after the two days he departed from there into Galilee. <verse-number id="Jn 4:44">44</verse-number>For Jesus himself testified that a prophet has no honor in his own homeland. <verse-number id="Jn 4:45">45</verse-number>So when he came to Galilee, the Galileans welcomed him, <supplied>because they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had seen”) which is understood as causal</note> had seen all <supplied>the things</supplied> he had done in Jerusalem at the feast (for they themselves had also come to the feast). </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A Royal Official’s Son Is Healed</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 4:46">46</verse-number>Now he came again to Cana in Galilee, where he had made the water wine. And <supplied>there</supplied> was at Capernaum a certain royal official whose son was sick. <verse-number id="Jn 4:47">47</verse-number>This man, <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> heard that Jesus had come from Judea into Galilee, went to him and asked that he come down and heal his son, for he was about to die. <verse-number id="Jn 4:48">48</verse-number>So Jesus said to him, “Unless you <supplied>people</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>people</supplied>” is supplied in the translation because the Greek verb (“see”) is plural</note> see signs and wonders, you will never believe!” <verse-number id="Jn 4:49">49</verse-number>The royal official said to him, “Sir, come down before my child dies!” <verse-number id="Jn 4:50">50</verse-number>Jesus said to him, “Go, your son will live.” The man believed the word that Jesus spoke to him, and he departed. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 4:51">51</verse-number>Now <supplied>as</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was going down”)</note> he was going down, his slaves met him, saying that his child was alive. <verse-number id="Jn 4:52">52</verse-number>So he inquired from them the hour at which he had gotten better. Then they said to him, “Yesterday at the seventh hour the fever left him.” <verse-number id="Jn 4:53">53</verse-number>So the father knew that <supplied>it was</supplied> that<note>Some manuscripts have “that <supplied>it was</supplied> at that same hour”</note> same hour at which Jesus said to him, “Your son will live,” and he himself believed, and his whole household. <verse-number id="Jn 4:54">54</verse-number>Now this <supplied>is</supplied> again a second sign Jesus performed <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“came”) which is understood as temporal</note> came from Judea into Galilee. </p>
		</chapter>