<chapter id="Jn 5">
			<pericope>A Paralytic Is Healed</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 5:1">1</verse-number> After these <supplied>things</supplied> <supplied>there</supplied> was a feast of the Jews, and Jesus went up to Jerusalem. <verse-number id="Jn 5:2">2</verse-number>Now there is in Jerusalem near the Sheep Gate a pool called in Aramaic <i>Bethzatha</i>,<note>The majority of later manuscripts read “Bethesda,” while other early manuscripts read “Bethsaida”</note> which has five porticoes. <verse-number id="Jn 5:3">3</verse-number>In these were lying a large number of those who were sick, blind, lame, paralyzed.<note>The majority of later manuscripts add the following words: “waiting for the moving of the water. <b>4</b> For an angel of the Lord from time to time went down in the pool and stirred up the water. So the one who went in first after the stirring of the water was healed of whatever disease he suffered.”</note> <verse-number id="Jn 5:5">5</verse-number>And a certain man was there who had <supplied>been</supplied> thirty-eight years in his sickness. <verse-number id="Jn 5:6">6</verse-number>Jesus, <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> saw this one lying <supplied>there</supplied> and knew that he had <supplied>been sick</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The phrase “<supplied>been sick</supplied>” is not in the Greek text, but is supplied from the context</note> a long time already, said to him, “Do you want to become well?” <verse-number id="Jn 5:7">7</verse-number>The one who was sick answered him, “Sir, I do not have anyone that, whenever the water is stirred up, could put me into the pool. But <idiom-start/>while<idiom-end/><note>Literally “during which <supplied>time</supplied>”</note> I am coming, another goes down before me.” <verse-number id="Jn 5:8">8</verse-number>Jesus said to him, “Get up! Pick up your mat and walk!” <verse-number id="Jn 5:9">9</verse-number>And immediately the man became well and picked up his mat and began to walk.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to walk”)</note> (Now it was the Sabbath on that day.) </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 5:10">10</verse-number>So the Jews were saying to the one who had been healed, “It is the Sabbath, and it is not permitted for you to pick up the mat!”<note>Some manuscripts have “your mat”</note> <verse-number id="Jn 5:11">11</verse-number>But he answered them, “The one who made me well—that one said to me, ‘Pick up your mat and walk!’ ” <verse-number id="Jn 5:12">12</verse-number>So they asked him,<note>Some manuscripts have “They asked him”</note> “Who is the man who said to you, ‘Pick up <supplied>your mat</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*In Greek the direct object (“<supplied>your mat</supplied>”) is not in the Greek text but the repetition is implied from the previous verse</note> and walk?’ ” <verse-number id="Jn 5:13">13</verse-number>But the one who was healed did not know who it was, for Jesus had withdrawn <supplied>while</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was”)</note> a crowd was in the place. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Equal with God</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 5:14">14</verse-number>After these <supplied>things</supplied> Jesus found him at the temple and said to him, “Look, you have become well! Sin no longer, lest something worse happen to you.” <verse-number id="Jn 5:15">15</verse-number>The man went and reported to the Jews that Jesus was the one who made him well. <verse-number id="Jn 5:16">16</verse-number>And on account of this the Jews began to persecute<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to persecute”)</note> Jesus, because he was doing these <supplied>things</supplied> on the Sabbath. <verse-number id="Jn 5:17">17</verse-number>But he answered<note>Some manuscripts have “Jesus answered”</note> them, “My Father is working until now, and I am working.” <verse-number id="Jn 5:18">18</verse-number>So on account of this the Jews were seeking even more to kill him, because he not only was breaking the Sabbath, but also was calling God his own Father, <supplied>thus</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>thus</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“making”) which is understood as result</note> making himself equal with God. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Authority of the Son</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 5:19">19</verse-number>So Jesus answered and said to them, “Truly, truly I say to you, the Son can do nothing from himself except what he sees the Father doing. For whatever that one does, these <supplied>things</supplied> also the Son does likewise. <verse-number id="Jn 5:20">20</verse-number>For the Father loves the Son and shows him everything that he himself is doing. And greater works than these he will show him, so that you will be astonished. <verse-number id="Jn 5:21">21</verse-number>For just as the Father raises the dead and makes <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> alive, thus also the Son makes alive whomever he wishes. <verse-number id="Jn 5:22">22</verse-number>For the Father does not judge anyone, but he has given all judgment to the Son, <verse-number id="Jn 5:23">23</verse-number>in order that all <supplied>people</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The word “<supplied>people</supplied>” is not in the Greek text but is implied</note> will honor the Son, just as they honor the Father. The one who does not honor the Son does not honor the Father who sent him. <verse-number id="Jn 5:24">24</verse-number>Truly, truly I say to you that the one who hears my word and who believes the one who sent me has eternal life, and does not come into judgment, but has passed from death into life. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 5:25">25</verse-number>“Truly, truly I say to you, that an hour is coming—and now is <supplied>here</supplied>—when the dead will hear the voice of the Son of God, and the ones who hear will live. <verse-number id="Jn 5:26">26</verse-number>For just as the Father has life in himself, thus also he has granted to the Son to have life in himself. <verse-number id="Jn 5:27">27</verse-number>And he has granted him authority to carry out judgment, because he is the Son of Man. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 5:28">28</verse-number>“Do not be astonished <supplied>at</supplied> this, because an hour is coming in which all those in the tombs will hear his voice <verse-number id="Jn 5:29">29</verse-number>and they will come out—those who have done good <supplied>things</supplied> to a resurrection of life, but those who have practiced evil <supplied>things</supplied> to a resurrection of judgment. <verse-number id="Jn 5:30">30</verse-number>I am able to do nothing from myself. Just as I hear, I judge, and my judgment is just, because I do not seek my <supplied>own</supplied> will, but the will of the one who sent me. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Further Testimony About the Son</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 5:31">31</verse-number>“If I testify about myself, my testimony is not true. <verse-number id="Jn 5:32">32</verse-number>There is another who testifies about me, and I know that the testimony which he testifies about me is true. <verse-number id="Jn 5:33">33</verse-number>You have sent to John and he has testified to the truth. <verse-number id="Jn 5:34">34</verse-number>(And I do not receive testimony from people, but I say these <supplied>things</supplied> in order that you may be saved.) <verse-number id="Jn 5:35">35</verse-number>That one was the lamp <supplied>which was</supplied> burning and shining, and you wanted to rejoice for an hour in his light. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 5:36">36</verse-number>“But I have a testimony greater than John’s, for the works which the Father has given to me that I should complete them—the very works which I am doing—<supplied>these</supplied> testify about me, that the Father has sent me. <verse-number id="Jn 5:37">37</verse-number>And the Father who sent me, that one has testified about me. You have neither heard his voice at any time nor seen his form. <verse-number id="Jn 5:38">38</verse-number>And you do not have his word residing in yourselves, because the one whom that one sent, in this one you do not believe. <verse-number id="Jn 5:39">39</verse-number>You search<note>Or “Search” (an imperative)</note> the scriptures because you think that you have eternal life in them, and it is these that testify about me. <verse-number id="Jn 5:40">40</verse-number>And you are not willing to come to me so that you may have life. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 5:41">41</verse-number>“I do not accept glory<note>Or “honor”</note> from people, <verse-number id="Jn 5:42">42</verse-number>but I know you, that you do not have the love of God in yourselves. <verse-number id="Jn 5:43">43</verse-number>I have come in my Father’s name, and you do not accept me. If another should come in his own name, you would accept that one! <verse-number id="Jn 5:44">44</verse-number>How are you able to believe, <supplied>if you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>if</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“accept”) which is understood as conditional</note> accept glory from one another, and do not seek the glory <supplied>which is</supplied> from the only God? <verse-number id="Jn 5:45">45</verse-number>Do not think that I will accuse you before the Father! The one who accuses you is Moses, in whom you have put your hope! <verse-number id="Jn 5:46">46</verse-number>For if you had believed Moses, you would believe me, for that one wrote about me. <verse-number id="Jn 5:47">47</verse-number>But if you do not believe that one’s writings, how will you believe my words?” </p>
		</chapter>