<chapter id="Jn 7">
			<pericope>Jesus’ Brothers Do Not Believe in Him</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 7:1">1</verse-number> And after these <supplied>things</supplied> Jesus was going about in Galilee. For he did not want to go about in Judea, because the Jews were seeking to kill him. <verse-number id="Jn 7:2">2</verse-number>Now the feast of the Jews—the <supplied>feast of</supplied> Tabernacles—was near. <verse-number id="Jn 7:3">3</verse-number>So his brothers said to him, “Depart from here and go to Judea, so that your disciples also can see your works that you are doing. <verse-number id="Jn 7:4">4</verse-number>For no one does anything in secret and <supplied>yet</supplied> he himself desires to be <idiom-start/>publicly recognized<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “with openness”</note> If you are doing these <supplied>things</supplied>, reveal yourself to the world!” <verse-number id="Jn 7:5">5</verse-number>(For not even his brothers believed in him.) </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus at the Feast of Tabernacles</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 7:6">6</verse-number>So Jesus said to them, “My time has not yet come, but your time is always ready. <verse-number id="Jn 7:7">7</verse-number>The world cannot hate you, but it hates me, because I am testifying about it, that its deeds are evil. <verse-number id="Jn 7:8">8</verse-number>You go up to the feast. I am not<note>Most manuscripts read “not yet” here, but this is obviously an easier reading intended to reconcile the statement with Jesus’ later actions</note> going up to this feast, because my time is not yet completed.<note>Or “fulfilled”</note> <verse-number id="Jn 7:9">9</verse-number>And <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had said”) which is understood as temporal</note> had said these <supplied>things</supplied>, he remained in Galilee. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 7:10">10</verse-number>But when his brothers had gone up to the feast, then he also went up, not openly, but (as it were) in secret. <verse-number id="Jn 7:11">11</verse-number>So the Jews were looking for him at the feast, and were saying, “Where is he?” <verse-number id="Jn 7:12">12</verse-number>And there was a lot of grumbling concerning him among the crowds; some were saying, “He is a good <supplied>man</supplied>,” but others were saying, “No, but he deceives the crowd.” <verse-number id="Jn 7:13">13</verse-number>However, no one was speaking openly about him for fear of the Jews. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 7:14">14</verse-number><idiom-start/>Now when the feast was already half over<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “now it being already in the middle of the feast”</note> Jesus went to the temple <supplied>courts</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>courts</supplied>” is supplied to distinguish this area from the interior of the temple building itself</note> and began to teach.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to teach”)</note> <verse-number id="Jn 7:15">15</verse-number>Then the Jews were astonished, saying, “How does this man <idiom-start/>possess knowledge<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “know letters”</note> <supplied>because he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“been taught”) which is understood as causal</note> has not been taught?” <verse-number id="Jn 7:16">16</verse-number>So Jesus answered them and said, “My teaching is not mine, but <supplied>is</supplied> from the one who sent me. <verse-number id="Jn 7:17">17</verse-number>If anyone wants to do his will, he will know about my<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> teaching, whether it is from God or I am speaking from myself. <verse-number id="Jn 7:18">18</verse-number>The one who speaks from himself seeks his own glory. But the one who seeks the glory of the one who sent him—this one is true, and there is no unrighteousness in him. <verse-number id="Jn 7:19">19</verse-number>Has not Moses given you the law, and none of you carries out the law? Why do you seek to kill me?” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 7:20">20</verse-number>The crowd replied, “You have a demon! Who is seeking to kill you?” <verse-number id="Jn 7:21">21</verse-number>Jesus answered and said to them, “I performed one work, and you are all astonished. <verse-number id="Jn 7:22">22</verse-number>Because of this Moses has given you circumcision (not that it is from Moses, but from the fathers), and you circumcise a man on the Sabbath. <verse-number id="Jn 7:23">23</verse-number>If a man receives circumcision on the Sabbath so that the law of Moses would not be broken, are you angry with me because I made a whole man well<note>Or “a man entirely well”</note> on the Sabbath? <verse-number id="Jn 7:24">24</verse-number>Do not judge according to outward appearance, but judge according to righteous judgment!” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Is Jesus the Christ?</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 7:25">25</verse-number>Then some of the inhabitants of Jerusalem began to say,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to say”)</note> “Is this not <supplied>the one</supplied> whom they are seeking to kill? <verse-number id="Jn 7:26">26</verse-number>And behold, he is speaking openly and they are saying nothing to him! Can it be that the rulers truly know that this man is the Christ? <verse-number id="Jn 7:27">27</verse-number>Yet we know where this man is from, but the Christ, whenever he comes—no one knows where he is from!” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 7:28">28</verse-number>Then Jesus cried out in the temple <supplied>courts</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here “<supplied>courts</supplied>” is supplied to distinguish this area from the interior of the temple building itself</note> teaching and saying, “You both know me and you know where I am from! And I have not come from myself, but the one who sent me is true, whom you do not know. <verse-number id="Jn 7:29">29</verse-number>I know him, because I am from him and he sent me.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 7:30">30</verse-number>So they were seeking to seize him, and no one laid a hand on him, because his hour had not yet come. <verse-number id="Jn 7:31">31</verse-number>But from the crowd many believed in him and were saying, “Whenever the Christ comes, he will not perform more signs than this man has done, <supplied>will he</supplied>?”<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here, indicated in the translation by the phrase “<supplied>will he</supplied>”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 7:32">32</verse-number>The Pharisees heard the crowd murmuring these <supplied>things</supplied> about him, and the chief priests and the Pharisees sent officers in order <idiom-start/>to take him into custody <idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “that they could seize him”</note> <verse-number id="Jn 7:33">33</verse-number>Then Jesus said, “Yet a little time I am with you, and I am going to the one who sent me. <verse-number id="Jn 7:34">34</verse-number>You will seek me and will not find <supplied>me</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note><note>Some manuscripts explicitly state “me”</note> and where I am, you cannot come.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 7:35">35</verse-number>So the Jews said to one another, “Where <supplied>is</supplied> this one going to go, that we will not find him? He is not going to go to the Dispersion among the Greeks and teach the Greeks, <supplied>is he</supplied>?<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here, indicated in the translation by the phrase “<supplied>is he</supplied>”</note> <verse-number id="Jn 7:36">36</verse-number>What is this saying that he said, ‘You will seek me and will not find <supplied>me</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note><note>Some manuscripts explicitly state “me”</note> and where I am, you cannot come’?” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Promise of the Spirit</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 7:37">37</verse-number>Now on the last day of the feast—the great <supplied>day</supplied>—Jesus stood and cried out, saying, “If anyone is thirsty, let him come to me, and let him drink, <verse-number id="Jn 7:38">38</verse-number>the one who believes in me.<note>An alternative punctuation of vv. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Jn 7:37–38">37–38</cite> reads: “If anyone is thirsty, let him come to me and let him drink. <b>38</b> The one who believes in me, just as the scripture said, ‘Out of his belly will flow rivers of living water.’ ”</note> Just as the scripture said, ‘Out of his belly will flow rivers of living water.’ ”<note>A quotation from the Old Testament of uncertain origin; texts most often suggested are <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 44:3">Isa 44:3</cite>; <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 55:1">55:1</cite>; <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 58:11">58:11</cite>; <cite title="BibleLEB2: Zec 14:8">Zech 14:8</cite></note> <verse-number id="Jn 7:39">39</verse-number>Now he said this concerning the Spirit, whom those who believed in him were about to receive. For the Spirit was not yet <supplied>given</supplied>,<note>A few manuscripts supply the participle “given” here; while it is unlikely this represents the original reading, many English versions nevertheless supply “given” to avoid the impression that the Spirit did not exist prior to this point</note> because Jesus had not yet been glorified.) </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Different Opinions About Jesus</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 7:40">40</verse-number>Then, <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> heard these words, <supplied>some</supplied> from the crowd began to say,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to say”)</note> “This man is truly the Prophet!” <verse-number id="Jn 7:41">41</verse-number>Others were saying, “This man is the Christ!” But others were saying, “No, for the Christ does not come from Galilee, <supplied>does he</supplied>?<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here, indicated in the translation by the phrase “<supplied>does he</supplied>”</note> <verse-number id="Jn 7:42">42</verse-number>Has not the scripture said that the Christ comes from the descendants of David, and from Bethlehem, the village where David was?” <verse-number id="Jn 7:43">43</verse-number>So there was a division in the crowd because of him. <verse-number id="Jn 7:44">44</verse-number>And some of them were wanting to seize him, but no one laid hands on him. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 7:45">45</verse-number>So the officers came to the chief priests and Pharisees. And they said to them, “<idiom-start/>Why<idiom-end/><note>Literally “because of what”</note> did you not bring him?” <verse-number id="Jn 7:46">46</verse-number>The officers replied, “Never has a man spoken like this!” <verse-number id="Jn 7:47">47</verse-number>Then the Pharisees replied to them, “You have not also been deceived, <supplied>have you</supplied>?<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here, indicated in the translation by the phrase “<supplied>have you</supplied>”</note> <verse-number id="Jn 7:48">48</verse-number><idiom-start/>None<idiom-end/><note>Literally “not anyone”</note> of the rulers or of the Pharisees have believed in him, <supplied>have they</supplied>?<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here, indicated in the translation by the phrase “<supplied>have they</supplied>”</note> <verse-number id="Jn 7:49">49</verse-number>But this crowd who does not know the law is accursed!” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 7:50">50</verse-number>Nicodemus, the one who came to him previously—who was one of them—said to them, <verse-number id="Jn 7:51">51</verse-number>“Our law does not condemn a man unless it first hears from him and knows what he is doing, <supplied>does it</supplied>?”<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here, indicated in the translation by the phrase “<supplied>does it</supplied>”</note> <verse-number id="Jn 7:52">52</verse-number>They answered and said to him, “You are not also from Galilee, <supplied>are you</supplied>?<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here, indicated in the translation by the phrase “<supplied>are you</supplied>”</note> Investigate and see that a prophet does not arise from Galilee!” 〚<verse-number id="Jn 7:53">53</verse-number>And each one went to his <supplied>own</supplied> house.<note><cite title="BibleLEB2: Jn 7:53–8:11">John 7:53–8:11 </cite>is not found in the earliest and best manuscripts and was almost certainly not an original part of the Gospel of John; one significant group of Greek manuscripts places it after <cite title="BibleLEB2: Lk 21:38">Luke 21:38</cite></note> </p>
		</chapter>