<chapter id="Jn 11">
			<pericope>Lazarus Dies</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 11:1">1</verse-number> Now a certain man was sick, Lazarus from Bethany, the village of Mary and her sister Martha. <verse-number id="Jn 11:2">2</verse-number>(Now it was Mary who anointed the Lord with perfumed oil and wiped his feet with her hair, whose brother Lazarus was sick.) <verse-number id="Jn 11:3">3</verse-number>So the sisters sent <supplied>word</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to him, saying, “Lord, behold, <supplied>the one</supplied> whom you love is sick.” <verse-number id="Jn 11:4">4</verse-number>And <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> heard <supplied>it</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> Jesus said, “This sickness is not to death, but for the glory of God, in order that the Son of God may be glorified through it.” <verse-number id="Jn 11:5">5</verse-number>(Now Jesus loved Martha and her sister and Lazarus.) <verse-number id="Jn 11:6">6</verse-number>So when he heard that he was sick, then he remained in the place <idiom-start/>where<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in which”</note> he was two days. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 11:7">7</verse-number>Then after this he said to the disciples, “Let us go to Judea again.” <verse-number id="Jn 11:8">8</verse-number>The disciples said to him, “Rabbi, the Jews were seeking just now to stone you, and are you going there again?” <verse-number id="Jn 11:9">9</verse-number>Jesus replied, Are <supplied>there</supplied> not twelve hours in the day? If anyone walks around in the daylight, he does not stumble, because he sees the light of this world. <verse-number id="Jn 11:10">10</verse-number>But if anyone walks around in the night, he stumbles, because the light is not in him. <verse-number id="Jn 11:11">11</verse-number>He said these <supplied>things</supplied>, and after this he said to them, “Our friend Lazarus has fallen asleep, but I am going so that I can awaken him.” <verse-number id="Jn 11:12">12</verse-number>So the disciples said to him, “Lord, if he has fallen asleep, he will get well.” <verse-number id="Jn 11:13">13</verse-number>(Now Jesus had been speaking about his death, but they thought that he was speaking about <idiom-start/>real sleep<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the sleep of slumber”</note>) <verse-number id="Jn 11:14">14</verse-number>So Jesus then said to them plainly, “Lazarus has died, <verse-number id="Jn 11:15">15</verse-number>and I am glad <idiom-start/>for your sake<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for the sake of you”</note> that I was not there, so that you may believe. But let us go to him.” <verse-number id="Jn 11:16">16</verse-number>Then Thomas (the one who is called Didymus)<note>“Didymus” means “the twin” in Greek</note> said to his fellow disciples, “Let us go also, so that we may die with him.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus the Resurrection and the Life</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 11:17">17</verse-number>So <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“arrived”) which is understood as temporal</note> arrived, Jesus found he had already <supplied>been</supplied> four days in the tomb. <verse-number id="Jn 11:18">18</verse-number>(Now Bethany was near Jerusalem, about fifteen stadia.<note>A “stade” or “stadium” (plur. “stadia”) is about 607 ft (187 m), so this was just under two miles (3 km)</note> <verse-number id="Jn 11:19">19</verse-number>So many of the Jews came to Martha and Mary in order to console them concerning their<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> brother.) <verse-number id="Jn 11:20">20</verse-number>Now Martha, when she heard that Jesus was coming, went to meet him, but Mary was sitting in the house. <verse-number id="Jn 11:21">21</verse-number>So Martha said to Jesus, “Lord, if you had been here, my brother would not have died. <verse-number id="Jn 11:22">22</verse-number>Even<note>Some manuscripts have “But even”</note> now I know that whatever you ask God, God will grant you.” <verse-number id="Jn 11:23">23</verse-number>Jesus said to her, “Your brother will rise again.” <verse-number id="Jn 11:24">24</verse-number>Martha said to him, “I know that he will rise again in the resurrection at the last day.” <verse-number id="Jn 11:25">25</verse-number>Jesus said to her, “I am the resurrection and the life. The one who believes in me, even if he dies, will live, <verse-number id="Jn 11:26">26</verse-number>and everyone who lives and believes in me will never die <idiom-start/>forever<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “for the age”</note> Do you believe this?” <verse-number id="Jn 11:27">27</verse-number>She said to him, “Yes, Lord, I have believed that you are the Christ, the Son of God, who comes into the world.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus Weeps</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 11:28">28</verse-number>And <supplied>when she</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had said”) which is understood as temporal</note> had said this, she went and called her sister Mary privately, saying, “The Teacher is here and is calling for you.” <verse-number id="Jn 11:29">29</verse-number>So that one, when she heard <supplied>it</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> got up quickly and went to him. <verse-number id="Jn 11:30">30</verse-number>(Now Jesus has not yet come into the village, but was still in the place where Martha went to meet him.) <verse-number id="Jn 11:31">31</verse-number>So the Jews who were with her in the house and were consoling her, <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> saw Mary—that she stood up quickly and went out—followed her, <supplied>because they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“thought”) which is understood as causal</note> thought that she was going to the tomb in order to weep there. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 11:32">32</verse-number>Then Mary, when she came where Jesus was <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the participle (“saw”) has been translated as a finite verb in keeping with English style</note> saw him, fell at his feet, saying to him, “Lord, if you had been here, my brother would not have died.” <verse-number id="Jn 11:33">33</verse-number>Then Jesus, when he saw her weeping and the Jews who came with her weeping, was deeply moved in spirit and was troubled within himself. <verse-number id="Jn 11:34">34</verse-number>And he said, “Where have you laid him?” They said to him, “Lord, come and see.” <verse-number id="Jn 11:35">35</verse-number>Jesus wept. <verse-number id="Jn 11:36">36</verse-number>So the Jews were saying, “See how he loved him!” <verse-number id="Jn 11:37">37</verse-number>But some of them said, “Was not this man who opened the eyes of the blind able to do <supplied>something</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> so that this man also would not have died?” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Lazarus Is Raised</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 11:38">38</verse-number>Then Jesus, deeply moved within himself again, came to the tomb. Now it was a cave, and a stone was lying on it. <verse-number id="Jn 11:39">39</verse-number>Jesus said, “Take away the stone.” Martha, the sister of the one who had died, said to him, “Lord, he is stinking already, because it has been four days.” <verse-number id="Jn 11:40">40</verse-number>Jesus said to her, “Did I not say to you that if you believed, you would see the glory of God?” <verse-number id="Jn 11:41">41</verse-number>So they took away the stone. And Jesus lifted up his<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> eyes above and said, “Father, I give thanks to you that you hear me. <verse-number id="Jn 11:42">42</verse-number>And I know that you always hear me, but for the sake of the crowd standing around I said <supplied>it</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> so that they may believe that you sent me.” <verse-number id="Jn 11:43">43</verse-number>And <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had said”) which is understood as temporal</note> had said these <supplied>things</supplied>, he cried out with a loud voice, “Lazarus, come out!” <verse-number id="Jn 11:44">44</verse-number>The one who had died came out, his<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> feet and his<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> hands bound with strips of cloth, and his face wrapped with a facecloth. Jesus said to them, “Untie him and let him go.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Jewish Leaders Plot to Kill Jesus</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 11:45">45</verse-number>Then many of the Jews who had come with Mary and saw <supplied>the things</supplied> which he did believed in him. <verse-number id="Jn 11:46">46</verse-number>But some of them went to the Pharisees and told them <supplied>the things</supplied> which Jesus had done. <verse-number id="Jn 11:47">47</verse-number>So the chief priests and the Pharisees called together the Sanhedrin and said, “What are we doing? For this man is performing many signs! <verse-number id="Jn 11:48">48</verse-number>If we allow him <supplied>to go on</supplied> in this way, everyone will believe in him, and the Romans will come and take away both our place<note>Generally understood to be a reference to the Jerusalem temple</note> and our<note>Literally “both the place and the nation of us”; the possessive pronoun is repeated in the translation (rather than the article) in keeping with English style</note> nation.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 11:49">49</verse-number>But a certain one of them, Caiaphas (who was high priest in that year), said to them, “You do not know anything at all! <verse-number id="Jn 11:50">50</verse-number>Nor do you consider that it is profitable for you that one man should die for the people, and the whole nation not perish.” <verse-number id="Jn 11:51">51</verse-number>(Now he did not say this from himself, but being high priest in that year, he prophesied that Jesus was going to die for the nation, <verse-number id="Jn 11:52">52</verse-number>and not for the nation only, but also that the children of God who are scattered would be gathered into one.) <verse-number id="Jn 11:53">53</verse-number>So from that day they resolved that they should kill him. <verse-number id="Jn 11:54">54</verse-number>So Jesus was no longer walking openly among the Jews, but went away from there to the region near the wilderness, to a city called Ephraim, and there he stayed with the disciples. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 11:55">55</verse-number>Now the Passover of the Jews was near, and many went up to Jerusalem from the <supplied>surrounding</supplied> country before the Passover, so that they could purify themselves. <verse-number id="Jn 11:56">56</verse-number>So they were looking for Jesus, and were speaking with one another <supplied>while</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“standing”) which is understood as temporal</note> standing in the temple <supplied>courts</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here “<supplied>courts</supplied>” is supplied to distinguish this area from the interior of the temple building itself</note> “What do you think? That he will not come to the feast?” <verse-number id="Jn 11:57">57</verse-number>(Now the chief priests and the Pharisees had given orders that if anyone knew where he was, they should report <supplied>it</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> in order that they could arrest him.) </p>
		</chapter>