<chapter id="Jn 13">
			<pericope>Jesus Washes His Disciples’ Feet</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 13:1">1</verse-number> Now before the feast of Passover, Jesus, knowing that his hour had come that he would depart from this world to the Father, <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied in keeping with English style</note> having loved <supplied>his</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> own in the world, loved them to the end. <verse-number id="Jn 13:2">2</verse-number>And <supplied>as</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was taking place”)</note> a dinner was taking place, <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“put”)</note> the devil had already put into the heart of Judas <supplied>son</supplied> of Simon Iscariot that he should betray him, <verse-number id="Jn 13:3">3</verse-number><supplied>because he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“knew”) which is understood as causal</note> knew that the Father had given him all <supplied>things</supplied> into <supplied>his</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> hands, and that he had come forth from God and was going away to God, <verse-number id="Jn 13:4">4</verse-number>he got up from the dinner and took off <supplied>his</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> outer clothing, and taking a towel, tied <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> around himself. <verse-number id="Jn 13:5">5</verse-number>Then he poured water into the washbasin and began to wash the feet of the disciples, and to wipe <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> dry with the towel <idiom-start/>which he had tied around himself<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “with which he was girded”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 13:6">6</verse-number>Then he came to Simon Peter. He said to him, “Lord, are you going to wash my feet?” <verse-number id="Jn 13:7">7</verse-number>Jesus answered and said to him, “What I am doing you do not understand now, but you will understand after these <supplied>things</supplied>.” <verse-number id="Jn 13:8">8</verse-number>Peter said to him, “You will never wash my feet <idiom-start/>forever<idiom-end/>!”<note>Literally “for the age”</note> Jesus replied to him, “Unless I wash you, you do not have a share with me.” <verse-number id="Jn 13:9">9</verse-number>Simon Peter said to him, “Lord, not my feet only, but also <supplied>my</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> hands and <supplied>my</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> head!” <verse-number id="Jn 13:10">10</verse-number>Jesus said to him, “The one who has bathed <idiom-start/>only needs<idiom-end/><note>Literally “does not have need except”</note> to wash <supplied>his</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> feet, but is completely clean. And you are clean, but not all <supplied>of you</supplied>.” <verse-number id="Jn 13:11">11</verse-number>(For he knew the one who would betray him; because of this he said, “Not all <supplied>of you</supplied> are clean.”) </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 13:12">12</verse-number>So when he had washed their feet and taken his outer clothing and reclined at table again, he said to them, “Do you understand what I have done for you? <verse-number id="Jn 13:13">13</verse-number>You call me ‘Teacher’ and ‘Lord,’ and you speak correctly, for I am. <verse-number id="Jn 13:14">14</verse-number>If then I—<supplied>your</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> Lord and Teacher—wash your feet, you also ought to wash one another’s feet. <verse-number id="Jn 13:15">15</verse-number>For I have given you an example, that just as I have done for you, you also do. <verse-number id="Jn 13:16">16</verse-number>Truly, truly I say to you, a slave is not greater than his master, nor a messenger greater than the one who sent him. <verse-number id="Jn 13:17">17</verse-number>If you understand these <supplied>things</supplied>, you are blessed if you do them. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 13:18">18</verse-number>“I am not speaking about all of you. I know whom I have chosen, but in order that the scripture would be fulfilled, ‘The one who eats my bread has lifted up his heel against me.’<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 41:9">Ps 41:9</cite></note> <verse-number id="Jn 13:19">19</verse-number>From now <supplied>on</supplied> I am telling you before <supplied>it</supplied> happens, in order that when <supplied>it</supplied> happens you may believe that I am <supplied>he</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the predicate nominative (“<supplied>he</supplied>”) is understood, but must be supplied in the translation</note> <verse-number id="Jn 13:20">20</verse-number>Truly, truly I say to you, the one who receives anyone I send receives me, and the one who receives me receives the one who sent me.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus Predicts Judas’ Betrayal</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 13:21">21</verse-number><supplied>When he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had said”) which is understood as temporal</note> had said these <supplied>things</supplied>, Jesus was troubled in spirit and testified and said, “Truly, truly I say to you that one of you will betray me.” <verse-number id="Jn 13:22">22</verse-number>The disciples began looking<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began looking”)</note> at one another, uncertain about whom he was speaking. <verse-number id="Jn 13:23">23</verse-number>One of his disciples—the one whom Jesus loved—was reclining <idiom-start/>close beside<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the bosom of” (a position dictated by ancient banqueting practice)</note> Jesus. <verse-number id="Jn 13:24">24</verse-number>So Simon Peter gestured for this one to inquire who it was about whom he was speaking. <verse-number id="Jn 13:25">25</verse-number>He leaned back<note>Some manuscripts have “Then he leaned back”</note> accordingly against Jesus’ chest <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“leaned back”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to him, “Lord, who is it?” <verse-number id="Jn 13:26">26</verse-number>Jesus replied, “It is he to whom I dip the piece of bread and give <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to him.” Then <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“dipping”) which is understood as temporal</note> dipping the piece of bread, he gave <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note>﻿<note>Some manuscripts have “after dipping the piece of bread, he took <supplied>it</supplied> and gave <supplied>it</supplied>”</note> to Judas <supplied>son</supplied> of Simon Iscariot. <verse-number id="Jn 13:27">27</verse-number>And after the piece of bread, then Satan entered into him. Then Jesus said to him, “What you are doing, do quickly!” <verse-number id="Jn 13:28">28</verse-number>(Now no one of those reclining at table knew for what <supplied>reason</supplied> he said this to him. <verse-number id="Jn 13:29">29</verse-number>For some were thinking because Judas had the money box, Jesus was telling him, “Purchase <idiom-start/>what we need<idiom-end/><note>Literally “of which we have need”</note> for the feast,” or that he should give something to the poor.) <verse-number id="Jn 13:30">30</verse-number>So <supplied>after he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had taken”) which is understood as temporal</note> had taken the piece of bread, he went out immediately. And it was night. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus Predicts Peter’s Denial</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 13:31">31</verse-number>Then, when he had gone out, Jesus said, “Now the Son of Man is glorified, and God is glorified in him. <verse-number id="Jn 13:32">32</verse-number>If God is glorified in him, God will also glorify him in himself, and will glorify him immediately. <verse-number id="Jn 13:33">33</verse-number>Children, yet a little <supplied>time</supplied> I am with you. You will seek me and just as I said to the Jews, “Where I am going you cannot come,” now I say also to you. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 13:34">34</verse-number>“A new commandment I give to you: that you love one another—just as I have loved you, that you also love one another. <verse-number id="Jn 13:35">35</verse-number>By this everyone will know that you are my disciples—if you have love for one another.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 13:36">36</verse-number>Simon Peter said to him, “Lord, where are you going?” Jesus replied,<note>Some manuscripts have “replied to him”</note> “Where I am going you cannot follow me now, but you will follow later.” <verse-number id="Jn 13:37">37</verse-number>Peter said to him, “Lord, why am I not able to follow you now? I will lay down my life for you!” <verse-number id="Jn 13:38">38</verse-number>Jesus replied, “Will you lay down your life for me? Truly, truly I say to you, the rooster will not crow until you have denied me three times! </p>
		</chapter>