<chapter id="Jn 15">
			<pericope>The Vine and the Branches</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 15:1">1</verse-number> “I am the true vine, and my Father is the vinedresser. <verse-number id="Jn 15:2">2</verse-number>Every branch that does not bear fruit in me, he removes it, and every <supplied>branch</supplied> that bears fruit, he prunes it in order that it may bear more fruit. <verse-number id="Jn 15:3">3</verse-number>You are already clean because of the word that I have spoken to you. <verse-number id="Jn 15:4">4</verse-number>Remain in me, and I in you. Just as the branch is not able to bear fruit from itself unless it remains in the vine, so neither <supplied>can</supplied> you, unless you remain in me. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 15:5">5</verse-number>“I am the vine; you <supplied>are</supplied> the branches. The one who remains in me and I in him—this one bears much fruit, for apart from me you are not able to do anything. <verse-number id="Jn 15:6">6</verse-number>If anyone does not remain in me, he is thrown out as a branch, and dries up, and they gather them and throw <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> into the fire, and they are burned. <verse-number id="Jn 15:7">7</verse-number>If you remain in me and my words remain in you, ask whatever you want and it will be done for you. <verse-number id="Jn 15:8">8</verse-number>My Father is glorified by this: that you bear much fruit, and prove to be my disciples. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 15:9">9</verse-number>“Just as the Father has loved me, I also have loved you. Remain in my love. <verse-number id="Jn 15:10">10</verse-number>If you keep my commandments, you will remain in my love, just as I have kept my Father’s commandments and remain in his love. <verse-number id="Jn 15:11">11</verse-number>I have spoken these <supplied>things</supplied> to you in order that my joy may be in you, and your joy may be made complete. <verse-number id="Jn 15:12">12</verse-number>This is my commandment: that you love one another just as I have loved you. <verse-number id="Jn 15:13">13</verse-number>No one has greater love than this: that someone lay down his life for his friends. <verse-number id="Jn 15:14">14</verse-number>You are my friends if you do what I command you. <verse-number id="Jn 15:15">15</verse-number>No longer do I call you slaves, because the slave does not know what his master is doing. But I have called you friends, because everything that I have heard from my Father I have revealed to you. <verse-number id="Jn 15:16">16</verse-number>You did not choose me, but I chose you and appointed you that you should go and bear fruit, and your fruit should remain, in order that whatever you ask the Father in my name he will give you. <verse-number id="Jn 15:17">17</verse-number>These <supplied>things</supplied> I command you: that you love one another. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The World’s Hatred for the Disciples</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 15:18">18</verse-number>If the world hates you, you know that it has hated me before <supplied>it hated</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the verb “<supplied>hated</supplied>” is an understood repetition of the verb earlier in this verse</note> you. <verse-number id="Jn 15:19">19</verse-number>If you were of the world, the world would love its own. But because you are not of the world, but I chose you out of the world, for this <supplied>reason</supplied> the world hates you. <verse-number id="Jn 15:20">20</verse-number>Remember the word that I said to you: ‘A slave is not greater than his master.’ If they persecuted me, they will also persecute you. If they kept my word, they will keep yours also. <verse-number id="Jn 15:21">21</verse-number>But they will do all these <supplied>things</supplied> to you on account of my name, because they do not know the one who sent me. <verse-number id="Jn 15:22">22</verse-number>If I had not come and spoken to them, they would not have sin. But now they do not have a valid excuse for their sin. <verse-number id="Jn 15:23">23</verse-number>The one who hates me hates my Father also. <verse-number id="Jn 15:24">24</verse-number>If I had not done among them the works that no one else did, they would not have sin. But now they have both seen and hated both me and my Father. <verse-number id="Jn 15:25">25</verse-number>But <supplied>this happened</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The phrase “<supplied>this happened</supplied>” is not in the Greek text but is implied</note> so that the word that is written in their law would be fulfilled, ‘They hated me without a reason.’ </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 15:26">26</verse-number>“When the Advocate comes, whom I will send to you from the Father—the Spirit of truth, who proceeds from the Father—that one will testify about me. <verse-number id="Jn 15:27">27</verse-number>And you also will testify, because you have been with me from the beginning. </p>
		</chapter>