<chapter id="Jn 16">
			<pericope>Persecution of Disciples Predicted</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 16:1">1</verse-number> “I have said these <supplied>things</supplied> to you so that you will not fall away. <verse-number id="Jn 16:2">2</verse-number><idiom-start/>They will expel you from the synagogue<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “they will make you expelled from the synagogue”</note> but an hour is coming that everyone who kills you will think they are offering service to God. <verse-number id="Jn 16:3">3</verse-number>And they will do these <supplied>things</supplied> because they do not know the Father or me. <verse-number id="Jn 16:4">4</verse-number>But I have said these <supplied>things</supplied> to you so that when their hour comes, you may remember that I told you about them. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus’ Departure and the Coming of the Holy Spirit</pericope>
			<p>“And I have not said these <supplied>things</supplied> to you from the beginning, because I was with you. <verse-number id="Jn 16:5">5</verse-number>But now I am going away to the one who sent me, and none of you is asking me, ‘Where are you going?’ <verse-number id="Jn 16:6">6</verse-number>But because I have said these <supplied>things</supplied> to you, sorrow has filled your hearts. <verse-number id="Jn 16:7">7</verse-number>But I tell you the truth, it is better for you that I go away. For if I do not go away, the Advocate will not come to you; but if I go, I will send him to you. <verse-number id="Jn 16:8">8</verse-number>And <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“comes”) which is understood as temporal</note> comes, he will convict the world concerning sin and concerning righteousness and concerning judgment: <verse-number id="Jn 16:9">9</verse-number>concerning sin, because they do not believe in me, <verse-number id="Jn 16:10">10</verse-number>and concerning righteousness, because I am going away to the Father and you will see me no more, <verse-number id="Jn 16:11">11</verse-number>and concerning judgment, because the ruler of this world has been condemned. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 16:12">12</verse-number>I still have many <supplied>things</supplied> to say to you, but you are not able to bear <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> now. <verse-number id="Jn 16:13">13</verse-number>But when he—the Spirit of truth—comes, he will guide you into all the truth. For he will not speak from himself, but whatever he hears he will speak, and he will proclaim to you the things to come. <verse-number id="Jn 16:14">14</verse-number>He will glorify me, because he will take from what <supplied>is</supplied> mine and will proclaim <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to you. <verse-number id="Jn 16:15">15</verse-number>Everything that the Father has is mine. For this <supplied>reason</supplied> I said that he takes from what <supplied>is</supplied> mine and will proclaim <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to you. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus Predicts His Return to the Disciples</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 16:16">16</verse-number>“A little <supplied>while</supplied> and you will see me no more, and again a little <supplied>while</supplied> and you will see me. <verse-number id="Jn 16:17">17</verse-number>So some of his disciples said to one another, “What is this that he is saying to us, ‘A little <supplied>while</supplied> and you will not see me, and again a little <supplied>while</supplied> and you will see me,’ and ‘Because I am going away to the Father’?” <verse-number id="Jn 16:18">18</verse-number>So they kept on saying, “What is this that he is saying, ‘A little <supplied>while</supplied>’? We do not understand what he is speaking about!” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 16:19">19</verse-number>Jesus knew that they were wanting to ask him, and he said to them, “Are you deliberating with one another about this—that I said, ‘A little <supplied>while</supplied>, and you will not see me, and again a little <supplied>while</supplied> and you will see me’? <verse-number id="Jn 16:20">20</verse-number>Truly, truly I say to you, that you will weep and lament, but the world will rejoice; you will become sorrowful, but your sorrow will change to joy. <verse-number id="Jn 16:21">21</verse-number>A woman, when she gives birth, experiences pain because her hour has come. But when <supplied>her</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> child is born, she no longer remembers the affliction, on account of the joy that a human being has been born into the world. <verse-number id="Jn 16:22">22</verse-number>So you also are experiencing sorrow now, but I will see you again, and your hearts will rejoice, and no one will take away your joy from you. <verse-number id="Jn 16:23">23</verse-number>And on that day you will ask me nothing. Truly, truly I say to you, whatever you ask the Father in my name, he will give you. <verse-number id="Jn 16:24">24</verse-number>Until now you have asked nothing in my name. Ask and you will receive, so that your joy may be complete. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus’ Victory Over the World</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 16:25">25</verse-number>“I have said these <supplied>things</supplied> to you in figurative sayings. An hour is coming when I will speak to you in figurative sayings no longer, but I will tell you plainly about the Father. <verse-number id="Jn 16:26">26</verse-number>On that day you will ask in my name, and I do not say to you that I will ask the Father on your behalf. <verse-number id="Jn 16:27">27</verse-number>For the Father himself loves you, because you have loved me and have believed that I came from God. <verse-number id="Jn 16:28">28</verse-number>I have gone out from the Father and have come into the world; again, I am leaving the world and am going to the Father.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 16:29">29</verse-number>His disciples said, “Behold, now you are speaking <idiom-start/>plainly<idiom-end/><note>Literally “with plainness”</note> and are telling <supplied>us</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> no figurative saying! <verse-number id="Jn 16:30">30</verse-number>Now we know that you know everything and do not <idiom-start/>need for<idiom-end/><note>Literally “have need that”</note> anyone to ask you <supplied>questions</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the word “<supplied>questions</supplied>” is not in the Greek text but is implied</note> By this we believe that you have come from God.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 16:31">31</verse-number>Jesus replied to them, “Now do you believe? <verse-number id="Jn 16:32">32</verse-number>Behold, an hour is coming—and has come—that you will be scattered each one to his own <supplied>home</supplied>,<note>Or “to his own things”; or “to his own people” (i.e., family); the Greek text is somewhat ambiguous here</note> and you will leave me alone. And I am not alone, because the Father is with me. <verse-number id="Jn 16:33">33</verse-number>I have said these <supplied>things</supplied> to you so that in me you may have peace. In the world you have affliction, but have courage! I have conquered the world.” </p>
		</chapter>