<chapter id="Jn 17">
			<pericope>Jesus Prays to be Glorified</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 17:1">1</verse-number> Jesus said these <supplied>things</supplied>, and lifting up his eyes to heaven he said, “Father, the hour has come! Glorify your Son, in order that your Son may glorify you—<verse-number id="Jn 17:2">2</verse-number>just as you have given him authority over all flesh, in order that he would give eternal life to them—everyone whom you have given him. <verse-number id="Jn 17:3">3</verse-number>Now this is eternal life: that they know you, the only true God, and Jesus Christ, whom you have sent. <verse-number id="Jn 17:4">4</verse-number>I have glorified you on earth <supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“completing”) which is understood as means</note> completing the work that you have given me <idiom-start/>to do<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “that I may do it”</note> <verse-number id="Jn 17:5">5</verse-number>And now, Father, you glorify me <idiom-start/>at your side<idiom-end/><note>Literally “by the side of yourself”</note> with the glory that I had <idiom-start/>at your side<idiom-end/><note>Literally “by the side of you”</note> before the world existed. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus Prays for His Disciples</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 17:6">6</verse-number>“I have revealed your name to the men whom you gave me out of the world. They were yours, and you have given them to me, and they have kept your word. <verse-number id="Jn 17:7">7</verse-number>Now they understand that all <supplied>the things</supplied> that<note>Literally “whatever”</note> you have given me are from you, <verse-number id="Jn 17:8">8</verse-number>because the words that you gave to me I have given to them, and they received <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and know truly that I have come from you, and they have believed that you have sent me. <verse-number id="Jn 17:9">9</verse-number>I am asking on behalf of them. I am not asking on behalf of the world, but on behalf of those whom you have given me, because they are yours, <verse-number id="Jn 17:10">10</verse-number>and all my <supplied>things</supplied> are yours, and your <supplied>things</supplied> <supplied>are</supplied> mine, and I have been glorified in<note>Or “by”; or “through”</note> them. <verse-number id="Jn 17:11">11</verse-number>And I am no longer in the world, and they are in the world, and I am coming to you. Holy Father, keep them in your name, which you have given to me, so that they may be one, just as we <supplied>are</supplied>. <verse-number id="Jn 17:12">12</verse-number>When I was with them, I kept them in your name, which you have given to me, and guarded <supplied>them</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and none of them has perished except the son of destruction, in order that the scripture would be fulfilled. <verse-number id="Jn 17:13">13</verse-number>And now I am coming to you, and I am saying these <supplied>things</supplied> in the world so that they may have my joy completed in themselves. <verse-number id="Jn 17:14">14</verse-number>I have given them your word, and the world has hated them, because they are not of the world just as I am not of the world. <verse-number id="Jn 17:15">15</verse-number>I do not ask that you take them out of the world, but that you protect them from the evil one. <verse-number id="Jn 17:16">16</verse-number>They are not of the world, just as I am not of the world. <verse-number id="Jn 17:17">17</verse-number>Sanctify them in the truth—your word is truth. <verse-number id="Jn 17:18">18</verse-number>Just as you sent me into the world, I also have sent them into the world. <verse-number id="Jn 17:19">19</verse-number>And for them I sanctify myself, so that <supplied>they</supplied> themselves also may be sanctified in the truth. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus Prays for the Unity of Believers</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 17:20">20</verse-number>“And I do not ask on behalf of these only, but also on behalf of those who believe in me through their word, <verse-number id="Jn 17:21">21</verse-number>that they all may be one, just as you, Father, <supplied>are</supplied> in me and I <supplied>am</supplied> in you, that they also may be in us, in order that the world may believe that you sent me. <verse-number id="Jn 17:22">22</verse-number>And the glory that you have given to me, I have given to them, in order that they may be one, just as we <supplied>are</supplied> one—<verse-number id="Jn 17:23">23</verse-number>I in them, and you in me, in order that they may be completed in one, so that the world may know that you sent me, and you have loved them just as you have loved me. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 17:24">24</verse-number>“Father, <supplied>those</supplied> whom you have given to me—I want that those also may be with me where I am, in order that they may see my glory that you have given me because you loved me before the foundation of the world. <verse-number id="Jn 17:25">25</verse-number>Righteous Father, although the world does not know you, yet I have known you, and these <supplied>men</supplied> have come to know that you sent me. <verse-number id="Jn 17:26">26</verse-number>And I made known to them your name, and will make <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> known, in order that the love <supplied>with</supplied> which you loved me may be in them, and I <supplied>may be</supplied> in them.” </p>
		</chapter>