<chapter id="Jn 18">
			<pericope>Jesus Is Betrayed and Arrested</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 18:1">1</verse-number> <supplied>When</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had said”) which is understood as temporal</note> Jesus had said these <supplied>things</supplied>, he went out with his disciples to the other side of the ravine of the Kidron, where <supplied>there</supplied> was a garden into which he and his disciples entered. <verse-number id="Jn 18:2">2</verse-number>(Now Judas, the one who betrayed him, also knew about the place, because Jesus often gathered there with his disciples.) <verse-number id="Jn 18:3">3</verse-number>So Judas, taking the cohort and officers from the chief priests and from the Pharisees, came there with lanterns and torches and weapons. <verse-number id="Jn 18:4">4</verse-number>Then Jesus, <supplied>because he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“knew”) which is understood as causal</note> knew all the things that were coming upon him, went out and said to them, “Who are you looking for?” <verse-number id="Jn 18:5">5</verse-number>They replied to him, “Jesus the Nazarene.” He said to them, “I am <supplied>he</supplied>.”<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the predicate nominative is supplied from context in the English translation</note> (Now Judas, the one who betrayed him, was also standing with them.) <verse-number id="Jn 18:6">6</verse-number>So when he said to them, “I am <supplied>he</supplied>,”<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the predicate nominative is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <idiom-start/>they drew back<idiom-end/><note>Literally “they went to the back”</note> and fell to the ground. <verse-number id="Jn 18:7">7</verse-number>Then he asked them again, “Who are you looking for?” And they said, “Jesus the Nazarene.” <verse-number id="Jn 18:8">8</verse-number>Jesus replied, “I said to you that I am <supplied>he</supplied>!<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the predicate nominative is supplied from context in the English translation</note> So if you are looking for me, let these <supplied>men</supplied> go,” <verse-number id="Jn 18:9">9</verse-number>in order that the word that he had spoken would be fulfilled: “Those whom you have given to me—I have not lost anyone of them.”<note>A paraphrase of the statement in <cite title="BibleLEB2: Jn 17:12">John 17:12</cite></note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 18:10">10</verse-number>Then Simon Peter, who had a sword, drew it and struck the slave of the high priest and cut off his right ear. (Now the name of the slave was Malchus.) <verse-number id="Jn 18:11">11</verse-number>So Jesus said to Peter, “Put the sword into <supplied>its</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> sheath! The cup that the Father has given me—shall I not drink it?” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus Taken to Annas</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 18:12">12</verse-number>Then the cohort and the military tribune and the officers of the Jews seized Jesus and tied him up, <verse-number id="Jn 18:13">13</verse-number>and brought <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to Annas first, for he was the father-in-law of Caiaphas, who was high priest that year. <verse-number id="Jn 18:14">14</verse-number>(Now it was Caiaphas who had advised the Jews that it was better <supplied>that</supplied> one man die for the people.) </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Peter Denies Jesus the First Time</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 18:15">15</verse-number>So Simon Peter and another disciple followed Jesus. (Now that disciple was known to the high priest, and entered with Jesus into the courtyard of the high priest.) <verse-number id="Jn 18:16">16</verse-number>But Peter was standing by the door outside. So the other disciple <supplied>who was</supplied> known to the high priest went out and spoke to the doorkeeper and brought Peter in. <verse-number id="Jn 18:17">17</verse-number>Then the female slave <supplied>who was</supplied> the doorkeeper said to Peter, “You are not also <supplied>one</supplied> of the disciples of this man, <supplied>are you</supplied>?”<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here, indicated in the translation by the phrase “<supplied>are you</supplied>”</note> He said, “I am not!” <verse-number id="Jn 18:18">18</verse-number>(Now the slaves and the officers were standing there, having made a charcoal fire because it was cold, and they were warming themselves. And Peter was also standing there with them and warming himself.) </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus Before Annas</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 18:19">19</verse-number>So the high priest questioned Jesus about his disciples and about his teaching. <verse-number id="Jn 18:20">20</verse-number>Jesus replied to him, “I have spoken openly to the world. I always taught in the synagogue and in the temple <supplied>courts</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>courts</supplied>” is supplied to distinguish this area from the interior of the temple building itself</note> where all the Jews assemble, and I have said nothing in secret. <verse-number id="Jn 18:21">21</verse-number>Why are you asking me? Ask those who heard what I have said to them! Behold, these <supplied>people</supplied> know what I said.” <verse-number id="Jn 18:22">22</verse-number>Now <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“had said”)</note> he had said these <supplied>things</supplied>, one of the officers who was standing by gave a slap in the face to Jesus, saying, “Do you reply to the high priest in this way?” <verse-number id="Jn 18:23">23</verse-number>Jesus replied to him, “If I have spoken wrongly, testify about what <supplied>is</supplied> wrong! But if <supplied>I have spoken</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The phrase “I have spoken” is an implied repetition of the earlier phrase in this verse</note> correctly, why do you strike me?” <verse-number id="Jn 18:24">24</verse-number>Then Annas sent him, tied up, to Caiaphas the high priest. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Peter Denies Jesus the Second and Third Times</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 18:25">25</verse-number>Now Simon Peter was standing there and warming himself. So they said to him, “You are not also <supplied>one</supplied> of his disciples, <supplied>are you</supplied>?”<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here, indicated in the translation by the phrase “<supplied>are you</supplied>”</note> He denied <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and said, “I am not!” <verse-number id="Jn 18:26">26</verse-number>One of the slaves of the high priest, who was related to the one whose ear Peter had cut off, said, “Did I not see you in the garden with him?” <verse-number id="Jn 18:27">27</verse-number>So Peter denied <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> again, and immediately a rooster crowed. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus Brought Before Pilate</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 18:28">28</verse-number>Then they brought Jesus from Caiaphas to the governor’s residence. Now it was early, and they did not enter into the governor’s residence so that they would not be defiled, but could eat the Passover. <verse-number id="Jn 18:29">29</verse-number>So Pilate came outside to them and said, “What accusation do you bring against this man?” <verse-number id="Jn 18:30">30</verse-number>They answered and said to him, “If this man were not doing evil, we would not have handed him over to you!” <verse-number id="Jn 18:31">31</verse-number>So Pilate said to them, “You take him and judge him according to your law!” The Jews said to him, “It is not permitted for us to kill anyone,” <verse-number id="Jn 18:32">32</verse-number>in order that the word of Jesus would be fulfilled that he had spoken, indicating by what sort of death he was going to die. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Pilate Questions Jesus</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 18:33">33</verse-number>Then Pilate entered again into the governor’s residence and summoned Jesus and said to him, “Are you the king of the Jews?” <verse-number id="Jn 18:34">34</verse-number>Jesus replied, “Do you say this from yourself, or have others said <supplied>this</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to you about me?” <verse-number id="Jn 18:35">35</verse-number>Pilate replied, “I am not a Jew, <supplied>am I</supplied>?<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here, indicated in the translation by the phrase “<supplied>am I</supplied>”</note> Your people and the chief priests handed you over to me! What have you done?” <verse-number id="Jn 18:36">36</verse-number>Jesus replied, “My kingdom is not of this world. If my kingdom were of this world, my servants would be fighting so that I would not be handed over to the Jews. But now my kingdom is not from here.” <verse-number id="Jn 18:37">37</verse-number>Then Pilate said to him, “So then you are a king!” Jesus replied, “You say that I am a king. For this <supplied>reason</supplied> I was born, and for this reason I have come into the world: in order that I can testify to the truth. Everyone who is of the truth hears my voice.” <verse-number id="Jn 18:38">38</verse-number>Pilate said to him, “What is truth?” </p>
			<p>And <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had said”) which is understood as temporal</note> had said this, he went out again to the Jews and said to them, “I find no basis for an accusation against him. <verse-number id="Jn 18:39">39</verse-number>But it is your custom that I release for you one <supplied>prisoner</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The word “<supplied>prisoner</supplied>” is not in the Greek text, but is implied</note> at the Passover. So do you want <supplied>me</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to release for you the king of the Jews?” <verse-number id="Jn 18:40">40</verse-number>Then they shouted again, saying, “Not this man, but Barabbas!” (Now Barabbas was a revolutionary.)<note>Or perhaps “robber”</note> </p>
		</chapter>