<chapter id="Jn 20">
			<pericope>Jesus Is Raised</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 20:1">1</verse-number> Now on the first <supplied>day</supplied> of the week, Mary Magdalene came to the tomb early, <supplied>while it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was”)</note> was still dark, and saw the stone had been taken away from the tomb. <verse-number id="Jn 20:2">2</verse-number>So she ran and came to Simon Peter and to the other disciple whom Jesus loved and said to them, “They have taken away the Lord from the tomb and we do not know where they have put him!” <verse-number id="Jn 20:3">3</verse-number>Then Peter and the other disciple went out and were going to the tomb. <verse-number id="Jn 20:4">4</verse-number>And the two were running together, and the other disciple ran ahead, faster than Peter, and came to the tomb first. <verse-number id="Jn 20:5">5</verse-number>And bending over to look, he saw the <supplied>strips of</supplied> linen cloth lying there, though he did not go in. <verse-number id="Jn 20:6">6</verse-number>Then Simon Peter also came following him, and he went into the tomb and saw the <supplied>strips of</supplied> linen cloth lying there, <verse-number id="Jn 20:7">7</verse-number>and the facecloth that was on his head—not lying with the <supplied>strips of</supplied> linen cloth, but folded up separately in one place. <verse-number id="Jn 20:8">8</verse-number>So then the other disciple who had come to the tomb first also went in, and he saw and believed. <verse-number id="Jn 20:9">9</verse-number>(For they did not yet know the scripture that it was necessary for him to rise from the dead.) </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus Appears to Mary Magdalene</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 20:10">10</verse-number>Then the disciples went away again to their <supplied>own homes</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The phrase “<supplied>own homes</supplied>” is not in the Greek text but is implied</note> <verse-number id="Jn 20:11">11</verse-number>But Mary stood outside at the tomb, weeping. Then, while she was weeping, she bent over to look into the tomb, <verse-number id="Jn 20:12">12</verse-number>and she saw two angels in white, seated one at the head and one at the feet where the body of Jesus had been lying. <verse-number id="Jn 20:13">13</verse-number>And they said to her, “Woman, why are you weeping?” She said to them, “They have taken away my Lord, and I do not know where they have put him!” <verse-number id="Jn 20:14">14</verse-number><supplied>When she</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had said”) which is understood as temporal</note> had said these <supplied>things</supplied>, she turned <idiom-start/>around<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the back”</note> and saw Jesus standing there, and she did not know that it was Jesus. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 20:15">15</verse-number>Jesus said to her, “Woman, why are you weeping? Who are you looking for?” She thought that it was the gardener, <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“thought”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to him, “Sir, if you have carried him away, tell me where you have put him, and I will take him.” <verse-number id="Jn 20:16">16</verse-number>Jesus said to her, “Mary.” She turned around <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“turned around”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to him in Aramaic, “<i>Rabboni</i>” (which means “Teacher”). <verse-number id="Jn 20:17">17</verse-number>Jesus said to her, “Do not touch me, for I have not yet ascended to the Father. But go to my brothers and tell them, ‘I am ascending to my Father and your Father, and my God and your God.’ ” <verse-number id="Jn 20:18">18</verse-number>Mary Magdalene came <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the participle (“announced”) has been translated as a finite verb in keeping with English style</note> announced to the disciples, “I have seen the Lord,” and he had said these <supplied>things</supplied> to her. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus Appears to the Disciples</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 20:19">19</verse-number>Now <supplied>when it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was”)</note> was evening on that day—the first <supplied>day</supplied> of the week—and the doors had been shut where the disciples were because of fear of the Jews, Jesus came and stood in their midst and said to them, “Peace to you.” <verse-number id="Jn 20:20">20</verse-number>And <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had said”) which is understood as temporal</note> had said this, he showed <supplied>his</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> hands and <supplied>his</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> side to them. Then the disciples rejoiced <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> saw the Lord. <verse-number id="Jn 20:21">21</verse-number>So Jesus said to them again, “Peace to you. As the Father has sent me, I also send you.” <verse-number id="Jn 20:22">22</verse-number>And <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had said”) which is understood as temporal</note> had said this, he breathed on <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and said to them, “Receive the Holy Spirit. <verse-number id="Jn 20:23">23</verse-number>If you forgive the sins of any, they are forgiven them. If you retain <supplied>the sins</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*An understood repetition of the phrase from earlier in the verse</note> of any, they are retained.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Thomas Doubts But Later Believes</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 20:24">24</verse-number>Now Thomas, one of the twelve, who was called Didymus,<note>The Greek term means “the Twin”</note> was not with them when Jesus came. <verse-number id="Jn 20:25">25</verse-number>So the other disciples said to him, “We have seen the Lord!” But he said to them, “Unless I see in his hands the mark of the nails, and put my finger into the mark of the nails, and put my hand into his side, I will never believe!” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 20:26">26</verse-number>And after eight days his disciples were again inside, and Thomas with them. <supplied>Although</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>although</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had been shut”) which is understood as concessive</note> the doors had been shut, Jesus came and stood in their midst and said, “Peace to you.” <verse-number id="Jn 20:27">27</verse-number>Then he said to Thomas, “Place your finger here and see my hands, and place your hand and put <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> into my side. And do not be unbelieving, but believing!” <verse-number id="Jn 20:28">28</verse-number>Thomas answered and said to him, “My Lord and my God!” <verse-number id="Jn 20:29">29</verse-number>Jesus said to him, “Because you have seen me, have you believed? Blessed <supplied>are</supplied> those who have not seen and have believed.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Why This Book Was Written</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 20:30">30</verse-number>Now Jesus also performed many other signs in the presence of the disciples<note>Some manuscripts have “his disciples”</note> which are not recorded in this book, <verse-number id="Jn 20:31">31</verse-number>but these <supplied>things</supplied> are recorded in order that you may believe that Jesus is the Christ, the Son of God, and that <supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“believing”) which is understood as means</note> believing you may have life in his name. </p>
		</chapter>