<chapter id="Jn 21">
			<pericope>Jesus Appears to the Disciples in Galilee</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 21:1">1</verse-number> After these <supplied>things</supplied> Jesus revealed himself again to the disciples by the Sea of Tiberias. Now he revealed <supplied>himself</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> in this way: <verse-number id="Jn 21:2">2</verse-number>Simon Peter and Thomas (who was called Didymus)<note>The Greek term means “the Twin”</note> and Nathanael from Cana in Galilee and the <supplied>sons</supplied> of Zebedee and two others of his disciples were together. <verse-number id="Jn 21:3">3</verse-number>Simon Peter said to them, “I am going fishing!” They said to him, “We also are coming with you.” They went out and got into the boat, and during that night they caught nothing. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 21:4">4</verse-number>Now <supplied>when it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was”)</note> was already early morning, Jesus stood on the beach. However, the disciples did not know that it was Jesus. <verse-number id="Jn 21:5">5</verse-number>So Jesus said to them, “Children, you do not have any fish to eat, <supplied>do you</supplied>?<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here, indicated in the translation by the phrase “<supplied>do you</supplied>”</note> They answered him, “No.” <verse-number id="Jn 21:6">6</verse-number>And he said to them, “Throw the net on the right side of the boat, and you will find <supplied>some</supplied>.”<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> So they threw <supplied>it</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and were no longer able to haul it in from the large number of the fish. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 21:7">7</verse-number>Then that disciple whom Jesus loved said to Peter, “It is the Lord!” So Simon Peter, <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> heard that it was the Lord, tied around himself his outer garment (for he was naked)<note>I.e., “he was naked underneath the outer garment,” which he tucked into his belt; alternatively, this could mean “for he was stripped for work”</note> and threw himself into the sea. <verse-number id="Jn 21:8">8</verse-number>But the other disciples came in the boat, dragging the net of fish, because they were not far from the land, but about two hundred cubits<note>Approximately 100 yards or 92 meters, based on a cubit of 18 inches.</note> away. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 21:9">9</verse-number>So when they got out on the land, they saw a charcoal fire laid <supplied>there</supplied>, and a fish lying on <supplied>it</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and bread. <verse-number id="Jn 21:10">10</verse-number>Jesus said to them, “Bring some of the fish that you have just now caught.” <verse-number id="Jn 21:11">11</verse-number>So Simon Peter got into <supplied>the boat</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and hauled the net to the land, full of large fish—one hundred fifty-three—and <supplied>although there</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>although</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“were”) which is understood as concessive</note> were so many, the net was not torn. <verse-number id="Jn 21:12">12</verse-number>Jesus said to them, “Come, eat breakfast!” But none of the disciples dared to ask him, “Who are you?” <supplied>because they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“knew”) which is understood as causal</note> knew that it was the Lord. <verse-number id="Jn 21:13">13</verse-number>Jesus came and took the bread and gave <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to them, and the fish likewise. <verse-number id="Jn 21:14">14</verse-number>This <supplied>was</supplied> now <supplied>the</supplied> third <supplied>time</supplied> Jesus was revealed to the disciples <supplied>after he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had been raised”) which is understood as temporal</note> had been raised from the dead. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Peter Is Restored Three Times</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 21:15">15</verse-number>Now when they had eaten breakfast, Jesus said to Simon Peter, “Simon <supplied>son</supplied> of John, do you love me more than these?” He said to him, “Yes, Lord, you know that I love you.” He said to him, “Feed my lambs!” <verse-number id="Jn 21:16">16</verse-number>He said to him again a second time, “Simon <supplied>son</supplied> of John, do you love me?” He said to him, “Yes, Lord, you know that I love you.” He said to him, “Shepherd my sheep!” <verse-number id="Jn 21:17">17</verse-number>He said to him a third <supplied>time</supplied>, “Simon <supplied>son</supplied> of John, do you love me?” Peter was distressed because he said to him a third <supplied>time</supplied>, “Do you love me?” and he said to him, “Lord, you know everything! You know that I love you!” Jesus said to him, “Feed my sheep! <verse-number id="Jn 21:18">18</verse-number>Truly, truly I say to you, when you were young, you tied <supplied>your clothes</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The words “<supplied>your clothes</supplied>” are not in the Greek text but are implied</note> around yourself and walked wherever you wanted. But when you grow old, you will stretch out your hands, and someone else will tie you up and carry <supplied>you</supplied> where you do not want <supplied>to go</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The words “<supplied>to go</supplied>” are not in the Greek text but are implied</note> <verse-number id="Jn 21:19">19</verse-number>(Now he said this to indicate by what kind of death he would glorify God.) And <supplied>after he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had said”) which is understood as temporal</note> had said this, he said to him, “Follow me!” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Peter and the Other Disciple Jesus Loved</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 21:20">20</verse-number>Peter turned <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“turned”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> saw the disciple whom Jesus loved following <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> (who also leaned back on his chest at the dinner and said, “Lord, who is the one betraying you?”) <verse-number id="Jn 21:21">21</verse-number>So <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> saw this one, Peter said to Jesus, “Lord, but what about this one?” <verse-number id="Jn 21:22">22</verse-number>Jesus said to him, “If I want him to remain until I come, what <supplied>is that</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The words “<supplied>is that</supplied>” are not in the Greek text but are supplied in keeping with English style</note> to you? You follow me!” <verse-number id="Jn 21:23">23</verse-number>So this saying went out to the brothers that that disciple would not die. But Jesus did not say to him that he would not die, but “If I want him to remain until I come, what <supplied>is that</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The words “<supplied>is that</supplied>” are not in the Greek text but are supplied in keeping with English style</note> to you?” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A Concluding Word of Testimony</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jn 21:24">24</verse-number>This is the disciple who is testifying about these <supplied>things</supplied>, and who has written down these <supplied>things</supplied>. And we know that his testimony is true. <verse-number id="Jn 21:25">25</verse-number>Now there are also many other <supplied>things</supplied> that Jesus did, which—if they were written down one after the other—I suppose not even the world itself could contain the books that would be written. </p>
		</chapter>