<chapter id="Mk 1">
			<pericope>John the Baptist Begins His Ministry</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 1:1">1</verse-number> The beginning of the gospel of Jesus Christ.<note>Some manuscripts add “the Son of God”</note> <verse-number id="Mk 1:2">2</verse-number>Just as it is written in the prophet Isaiah, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Behold, I am sending my messenger before your face, </li1>
				<li2>who will prepare your way, </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Mk 1:3">3</verse-number>the voice of one shouting in the wilderness, </li1>
				<li2>‘Prepare the way of the Lord, </li2>
				<li2>make straight his paths!’ ”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 40:3">Isa 40:3</cite></note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 1:4">4</verse-number>John was there baptizing in the wilderness, proclaiming<note>Some manuscripts have “and proclaiming”</note> a baptism of repentance for the forgiveness of sins. <verse-number id="Mk 1:5">5</verse-number>And all the Judean region and all the inhabitants of Jerusalem went out to him and were being baptized by him in the Jordan River, confessing their sins. <verse-number id="Mk 1:6">6</verse-number>And John was dressed in camel’s hair and a belt made of leather around his waist, and he ate locusts and wild honey. <verse-number id="Mk 1:7">7</verse-number>And he was preaching, saying, “One <supplied>who is</supplied> more powerful than I is coming after me, of whom I am not worthy to bend down <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“bend down”) has been translated as an infinitive</note> untie the strap of his sandals. <verse-number id="Mk 1:8">8</verse-number>I baptized you with water, but he will baptize you with the Holy Spirit.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Baptism of Jesus</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 1:9">9</verse-number>And it happened that in those days Jesus came from Nazareth in Galilee and was baptized in the Jordan by John. <verse-number id="Mk 1:10">10</verse-number>And immediately <supplied>as he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was coming up”) which is understood as temporal</note> was coming up out of the water, he saw the heavens being split apart and the Spirit descending like a dove on him. <verse-number id="Mk 1:11">11</verse-number>And a voice came from heaven, “You are my beloved Son; with you I am well pleased.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Temptation of Jesus</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 1:12">12</verse-number>And immediately the Spirit drove him out into the wilderness. <verse-number id="Mk 1:13">13</verse-number>And he was in the wilderness forty days being tempted by Satan. And he was with the wild animals, and the angels were ministering to him. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Public Ministry in Galilee</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 1:14">14</verse-number>And after<note>Some manuscripts have “Now after”</note> John <idiom-start/>had been taken into custody<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “had been handed over”</note> Jesus went into Galilee proclaiming the gospel of God <verse-number id="Mk 1:15">15</verse-number>and saying, “The time is fulfilled and the kingdom of God has come near. Repent and believe in the gospel!” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus Calls His First Disciples</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 1:16">16</verse-number>And <supplied>as he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was passing by”) which is understood as temporal</note> was passing by along the Sea of Galilee, he saw Simon and Andrew, Simon’s brother, casting <supplied>a net</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> into the sea (for they were fishermen). <verse-number id="Mk 1:17">17</verse-number>And Jesus said to them, “<idiom-start/>Follow<idiom-end/><note>Literally “come after”</note> me and I will make you become fishers of people.” <verse-number id="Mk 1:18">18</verse-number>And immediately they left their nets <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“left”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> followed him. <verse-number id="Mk 1:19">19</verse-number>And going on a little <supplied>farther</supplied>, he saw James the <supplied>son</supplied> of Zebedee and his brother John, and they <supplied>were</supplied> in the boat mending the nets. <verse-number id="Mk 1:20">20</verse-number>And immediately he called them, and they left their father Zebedee in the boat with the hired men <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“left”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> went away after him. <verse-number id="Mk 1:21">21</verse-number>And they went into Capernaum and immediately on the Sabbath he began to teach in the synagogue.<note>Some manuscripts have “he went into the synagogue and began to teach”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A Man with an Unclean Spirit Healed</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 1:22">22</verse-number>And they were amazed at his teaching, because he was teaching them like one who had authority, and not like the scribes. <verse-number id="Mk 1:23">23</verse-number>And so then there was a man in their synagogue with an unclean spirit, and he cried out, <verse-number id="Mk 1:24">24</verse-number>saying, “<idiom-start/>Leave us alone<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “what to us and to you”</note> Jesus the Nazarene! Have you come to destroy us? I know who you are—the Holy One of God!” <verse-number id="Mk 1:25">25</verse-number>And Jesus rebuked him, saying, “Be silent, and come out of him!” <verse-number id="Mk 1:26">26</verse-number>And <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“convulsing”) which is understood as temporal</note> convulsing him and crying out with a loud voice, the unclean spirit came out of him. <verse-number id="Mk 1:27">27</verse-number>And they were all amazed, so that <supplied>they began</supplied> to discuss with one another, saying, “What is this? A new teaching with authority! He even commands the unclean spirits and they obey him.” <verse-number id="Mk 1:28">28</verse-number>And the report about him then went out everywhere in the whole surrounding region of Galilee. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Many at Capernaum Are Healed</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 1:29">29</verse-number>And so then he departed from the synagogue <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“departed”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> came into the house of Simon and Andrew with James and John. <verse-number id="Mk 1:30">30</verse-number>Now Simon’s mother-in-law was lying down, suffering with a fever, and at once they told him about her. <verse-number id="Mk 1:31">31</verse-number>And he came <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> raised her up <supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“taking hold of”) which is understood as means</note> taking hold of her<note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> hand, and the fever left her, and she began to serve them. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 1:32">32</verse-number>Now <supplied>when it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was”)</note> was evening, when the sun had set, they began bringing<note>The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began bringing”)</note> to him all those <idiom-start/>who were sick<idiom-end/><note>Literally “who were having badly”</note> and those who were demon-possessed. <verse-number id="Mk 1:33">33</verse-number>And the whole town was gathered together at the door. <verse-number id="Mk 1:34">34</verse-number>And he healed many <idiom-start/>who were sick<idiom-end/><note>Literally “who were having badly”</note> with various diseases and expelled many demons. And he did not permit the demons to speak, because they knew him. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Preaching Throughout Galilee</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 1:35">35</verse-number>And getting up early in the morning <supplied>while it was</supplied> very dark, he departed and went to a deserted place, and there he was praying. <verse-number id="Mk 1:36">36</verse-number>And Simon and those <supplied>who were</supplied> with him searched diligently for him. <verse-number id="Mk 1:37">37</verse-number>And they found him and said to him, “Everyone is looking for you!” <verse-number id="Mk 1:38">38</verse-number>And he said to them, “Let us go elsewhere, into the neighboring rural towns, so that I can preach there also, because I have come out for this <supplied>very</supplied> reason.” <verse-number id="Mk 1:39">39</verse-number>And he went into all Galilee preaching in their synagogues and expelling demons. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A Leper Cleansed</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 1:40">40</verse-number>And a leper came to him, entreating him and kneeling down, saying<note>Some manuscripts have “and saying”</note> to him, “If you are willing, you are able to make me clean.” <verse-number id="Mk 1:41">41</verse-number>And becoming angry,<note>Some manuscripts have “having compassion”</note> he stretched out his hand <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“stretched out”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> touched <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note>, and said to him, “I am willing; be made clean.” <verse-number id="Mk 1:42">42</verse-number>And immediately the leprosy went away from him and he was made clean. <verse-number id="Mk 1:43">43</verse-number>And warning him sternly, he sent him away at once. <verse-number id="Mk 1:44">44</verse-number>And he said to him, “See to it that you say nothing to anyone, but go, show yourself to the priest and bring for your cleansing <supplied>the things</supplied> which Moses commanded, for a testimony to them. <verse-number id="Mk 1:45">45</verse-number>But he went out <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went out”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> began to proclaim <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> freely and to spread abroad the account, so that he was no longer able to enter publicly into a town. But he was staying outside in deserted places, and they were coming to him from all directions. </p>
		</chapter>