<chapter id="Mk 3">
			<pericope>A Man with a Withered Hand Healed</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 3:1">1</verse-number> And he entered into the synagogue again, and a man who had a withered hand was there. <verse-number id="Mk 3:2">2</verse-number>And they were watching him closely <supplied>to see</supplied> if he would heal him on the Sabbath, in order that they could accuse him. <verse-number id="Mk 3:3">3</verse-number>And he said to the man who had the withered hand, “Come into the middle.” <verse-number id="Mk 3:4">4</verse-number>And he said to them, “Is it permitted on the Sabbath to do good or to do evil, to save life or to kill?” But they were silent. <verse-number id="Mk 3:5">5</verse-number>And looking around at them with anger, grieved at the hardness of their hearts, he said to the man, “Stretch out your<note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> hand.” And he stretched <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> out, and his hand was restored. <verse-number id="Mk 3:6">6</verse-number>And the Pharisees went out immediately with the Herodians <idiom-start/>and began to conspire<idiom-end/><note>Literally “began to give counsel”; the imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive (“began to”)</note> against him with regard to how they could destroy him. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus Heals Crowds by the Sea</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 3:7">7</verse-number>And Jesus went away with his disciples to the sea,<note>That is, the Sea of Galilee</note> and a great crowd from Galilee followed <supplied>him</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> And from Judea <verse-number id="Mk 3:8">8</verse-number>and from Jerusalem and from Idumea and the other side of the Jordan and around Tyre and Sidon a great crowd came to him <supplied>because they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as causal</note> heard all that he was doing. <verse-number id="Mk 3:9">9</verse-number>And he told his disciples that a small boat should stand ready for him because of the crowd, so that they would not press upon him. <verse-number id="Mk 3:10">10</verse-number>For he had healed many, so that all those who <idiom-start/>were suffering from diseases<idiom-end/><note>Literally “had suffering”</note> pressed about him in order that they could touch him. <verse-number id="Mk 3:11">11</verse-number>And the unclean spirits, whenever they saw him, were falling down before him and crying out, saying, “You are the Son of God!” <verse-number id="Mk 3:12">12</verse-number>And he warned them strictly that they should not make him known. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Selection of the Twelve Apostles</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 3:13">13</verse-number>And he went up on the mountain and summoned <supplied>those</supplied> whom he wanted, and they came to him. <verse-number id="Mk 3:14">14</verse-number>And he appointed twelve,<note>Some manuscripts add “whom he also named apostles”</note> so that they would be with him and so that he could send them out to preach <verse-number id="Mk 3:15">15</verse-number>and to have authority to expel demons. <verse-number id="Mk 3:16">16</verse-number>And he appointed the twelve.<note>Most Greek manuscripts omit the phrase “and he appointed the twelve”</note> And to Simon he gave the name Peter, <verse-number id="Mk 3:17">17</verse-number>and James the <supplied>son</supplied> of Zebedee and John the brother of James (and he gave to them the name Boanerges, that is, “Sons of Thunder”), <verse-number id="Mk 3:18">18</verse-number>and Andrew, and Philip, and Bartholomew, and Matthew, and Thomas, and James the <supplied>son</supplied> of Alphaeus, and Thaddaeus, and Simon the Zealot,<note>Literally “the Cananean,” but according to BDAG 507 s.v., this term has no relation at all to the geographical terms for Cana or Canaan, but is derived from the Aramaic term for “enthusiast, zealot” (see <cite title="BibleLEB2: Lk 6:15">Luke 6:15</cite>; <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ac 1:13">Acts 1:13</cite>)</note> <verse-number id="Mk 3:19">19</verse-number>and Judas Iscariot, who also betrayed him. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A House Divided Cannot Stand</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 3:20">20</verse-number>And he went home, and the crowd gathered again, so that they were not even able to eat a meal. <verse-number id="Mk 3:21">21</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> <idiom-start/>his family<idiom-end/><note>Literally <supplied>those</supplied> “close to him”</note> heard <supplied>this</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> they went out to restrain him, for they were saying, “He has lost his mind!” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 3:22">22</verse-number>And the scribes who had come down from Jerusalem were saying, “He is possessed by Beelzebul!” and “By the ruler of the demons he expels the demons!” <verse-number id="Mk 3:23">23</verse-number>And he called them to himself <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“called”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> was speaking to them in parables, “How can Satan expel Satan? <verse-number id="Mk 3:24">24</verse-number>And if a kingdom is divided against itself, that kingdom is not able to stand. <verse-number id="Mk 3:25">25</verse-number>And if a house is divided against itself, that house will not be able to stand. <verse-number id="Mk 3:26">26</verse-number>And if Satan has risen up against himself and is divided, he is not able to stand, but is at an end! <verse-number id="Mk 3:27">27</verse-number>But no one is able to enter into the house of a strong <supplied>man</supplied> <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“enter”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> plunder his property unless he first ties up the strong <supplied>man</supplied>, and then he can thoroughly plunder his house. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 3:28">28</verse-number>“Truly I say to you that all the sins and the blasphemies will be forgiven the sons of men, however much they blaspheme. <verse-number id="Mk 3:29">29</verse-number>But whoever blasphemes against the Holy Spirit does not have forgiveness <idiom-start/>forever<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “for the age”</note> but is guilty of <supplied>an</supplied> eternal sin”—<verse-number id="Mk 3:30">30</verse-number>because they were saying, “He has an unclean spirit.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus’ Mother and Brothers</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 3:31">31</verse-number>And his mother and his brothers arrived, and standing outside, they sent <supplied>word</supplied> to him to summon him. <verse-number id="Mk 3:32">32</verse-number>And a crowd was sitting around him, and they told him, “Behold, your mother and your brothers<note>Some manuscripts add “and your sisters”</note> <supplied>are</supplied> outside looking for you.” <verse-number id="Mk 3:33">33</verse-number>And he answered them <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “Who is my mother or<note>Some manuscripts have “and”</note> my brothers?” <verse-number id="Mk 3:34">34</verse-number>And looking around at those who were sitting around him in a circle, he said, “Behold, my mother and my brothers! <verse-number id="Mk 3:35">35</verse-number>For whoever does the will of God, this person is my brother and sister and mother.” </p>
		</chapter>