<chapter id="Mk 4">
			<pericope>The Parable of the Sower</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 4:1">1</verse-number> And again he began to teach beside the sea,<note>That is, the Sea of Galilee</note> and a very large crowd was gathered to him, so that he got into a boat <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “and” is supplied because the previous participle (“got”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> sat on the sea, and the whole crowd was at the sea on the land. <verse-number id="Mk 4:2">2</verse-number>And he began to teach<note>The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to teach”)</note> them many <supplied>things</supplied> in parables, and was saying to them in his teaching, <verse-number id="Mk 4:3">3</verse-number>“Listen! Behold, the sower went out to sow. <verse-number id="Mk 4:4">4</verse-number>And it happened that while <supplied>he</supplied> was sowing, <idiom-start/>some seed<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<supplied>some of</supplied> which”</note> fell on the side of the path, and the birds came and devoured it. <verse-number id="Mk 4:5">5</verse-number>And other <supplied>seed</supplied> fell on the rocky ground where it did not have much soil, and it sprang up at once, because it did not have <supplied>any</supplied> depth of soil. <verse-number id="Mk 4:6">6</verse-number>And when the sun rose it was scorched, and because it did not have <supplied>enough</supplied> root, it withered. <verse-number id="Mk 4:7">7</verse-number>And other <supplied>seed</supplied> fell among the thorn plants, and the thorn plants came up and choked it, and it did not produce grain.<note>Literally “fruit,” describing here the grain harvested from the healthy plants; in contemporary English this would more naturally be expressed by terms like “grain” or “crop”</note> <verse-number id="Mk 4:8">8</verse-number>And other <supplied>seed</supplied> fell on the good soil, and produced grain,<note>Literally “fruit,” describing here the grain harvested from the healthy plants; in contemporary English this would more naturally be expressed by terms like “grain” or “crop”</note> coming up and increasing, and it bore <supplied>a crop</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note>—one thirty and one sixty and one a hundred <supplied>times as much</supplied>.<note>The phrase “<supplied>times as much</supplied>” is not in the Greek text but is implied</note> <verse-number id="Mk 4:9">9</verse-number>And he said, “Whoever has ears to hear, let him hear!” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Reason for the Parables</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 4:10">10</verse-number>And when he was alone, those around him together with the twelve began asking<note>The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began asking”)</note> him about the parables. <verse-number id="Mk 4:11">11</verse-number>And he said to them, “To you has been granted the secret of the kingdom of God, but to those who are outside everything is in parables, <verse-number id="Mk 4:12">12</verse-number>so that </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>‘<idiom-start/>they may look closely<idiom-end/><note>Literally “seeing they may see”</note> and not perceive, </li1>
				<li2>and <idiom-start/>they may listen carefully<idiom-end/><note>Literally “hearing they may hear”</note> and not understand, </li2>
				<li1>lest they turn and it be forgiven them.’ ”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 6:9–10">Isa 6:9–10</cite></note> </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Parable of the Sower Interpreted</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 4:13">13</verse-number>And he said to them, “Do you not understand this parable? And how will you understand all the parables? <verse-number id="Mk 4:14">14</verse-number>The sower sows the word. <verse-number id="Mk 4:15">15</verse-number>And these are the ones beside the path where the word is sown, and whenever they hear <supplied>it</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> immediately Satan comes and takes away the word that was sown in them. <verse-number id="Mk 4:16">16</verse-number>And these are like<note>Some manuscripts omit “like”</note> the ones sown on the rocky ground, who whenever they hear the word immediately receive it with joy. <verse-number id="Mk 4:17">17</verse-number>And they have no root in themselves, but are temporary. Then <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“comes”)</note> affliction or persecution comes because of the word, immediately they fall away. <verse-number id="Mk 4:18">18</verse-number>And others are the ones sown among the thorn plants—these are the ones who hear the word, <verse-number id="Mk 4:19">19</verse-number>and the cares of the world and the deceitfulness of wealth and the desires for other <supplied>things</supplied> come in <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“come in”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> choke the word and it becomes unproductive. <verse-number id="Mk 4:20">20</verse-number>And those are the ones sown on the good soil, who hear the word and receive <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and bear fruit—one thirty and one sixty and one a hundred <supplied>times as much</supplied>.”<note>The phrase “<supplied>times as much</supplied>” is not in the Greek text but is implied</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Parable of the Lamp</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 4:21">21</verse-number>And he said to them, “Surely a lamp is not brought so that it may be put under a bushel basket or under a bed, <supplied>is it</supplied>?<note>The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here, indicated in the translation by the phrase “<supplied>is it</supplied>”</note> <supplied>Is it</supplied> not<note>The negative construction in Greek anticipates a positive answer here</note> so that it may be put on a lampstand? <verse-number id="Mk 4:22">22</verse-number>For nothing is secret except so that it may be revealed, nor has become hidden except so that it will come to light. <verse-number id="Mk 4:23">23</verse-number>If anyone has ears to hear, let him hear!” <verse-number id="Mk 4:24">24</verse-number>And he said to them, “Take care what you hear! With the measure by which you measure out, it will be measured out to you, and will be added to you. <verse-number id="Mk 4:25">25</verse-number>For whoever has, <supplied>more</supplied> will be given to him, and whoever does not have, even what he has will be taken away from him.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Parable of the Seed that Grows by Itself</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 4:26">26</verse-number>And he said, “The kingdom of God is like this: like a man scatters seed on the ground. <verse-number id="Mk 4:27">27</verse-number>And he sleeps and gets up, night and day, and the seed sprouts and grows—<idiom-start/>he does not know how<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “<supplied>in such a way</supplied> as he does not know”</note> <verse-number id="Mk 4:28">28</verse-number>By itself the soil produces a crop: first the grass, then the head of grain, then the full grain in the head. <verse-number id="Mk 4:29">29</verse-number>But when the crop permits, he sends <supplied>in</supplied> the sickle right away, because the harvest has come.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Parable of the Mustard Seed</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 4:30">30</verse-number>And he said, “With what can we compare the kingdom of God, or by what parable can we present it? <verse-number id="Mk 4:31">31</verse-number><supplied>It is</supplied> like a mustard seed that when sown on the ground, <supplied>although it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>although</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“is”) which is understood as concessive</note> is the smallest of all the seeds that <supplied>are</supplied> on the ground, <verse-number id="Mk 4:32">32</verse-number>but when it is sown it grows up and becomes the largest of all the garden herbs, and sends out large branches so that the birds of the sky are able to nest in its shade.” <verse-number id="Mk 4:33">33</verse-number>And with many parables such as these he was speaking the word to them, as they were able to hear <supplied>it</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <verse-number id="Mk 4:34">34</verse-number>And he did not speak to them without a parable, but in private he explained everything to his own disciples. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Calming of a Storm</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 4:35">35</verse-number>And on that day, <supplied>when it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was”)</note> was evening, he said to them, “Let us cross over to the other side.” <verse-number id="Mk 4:36">36</verse-number>And leaving the crowd, they took him along, as he was, in the boat. And other boats were with him. <verse-number id="Mk 4:37">37</verse-number>And a great storm of wind developed, and the waves were breaking into the boat, so that the boat was already being filled <supplied>with water</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The words “<supplied>with water</supplied>” are not in the Greek text but are implied</note> <verse-number id="Mk 4:38">38</verse-number>And he was in the stern sleeping on the cushion, and they woke him up and said to him, “Teacher, is it not a concern to you that we are perishing?” <verse-number id="Mk 4:39">39</verse-number>And he woke up <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“woke up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> rebuked the wind, and said to the sea, “Be quiet! Be silent!” And the wind abated and there was a great calm. <verse-number id="Mk 4:40">40</verse-number>And he said to them, “Why are you fearful? Do you not yet have faith?” <verse-number id="Mk 4:41">41</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>they were terribly frightened<idiom-end/><note>Literally “they feared a great fear”</note> and began to say<note>The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to say”)</note> to one another, “Who then is this, that even the wind and the sea obey him?” </p>
		</chapter>