<chapter id="Mk 9">
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 9">9</verse-number><verse-number id="Mk 9:1">1</verse-number> And he said to them, “Truly I say to you, that there are some of those standing here who will never experience death until they see the kingdom of God having come with power.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Transfiguration</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 9:2">2</verse-number>And after six days, Jesus took along Peter and James and John, and led them to a high mountain by themselves alone. And he was transfigured before them, <verse-number id="Mk 9:3">3</verse-number>and his clothing became radiant—extremely white, like no cloth refiner on earth can <idiom-start/>make so white<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “make white like this”</note> <verse-number id="Mk 9:4">4</verse-number>And Elijah appeared to them together with Moses, and they were talking with Jesus. <verse-number id="Mk 9:5">5</verse-number>And Peter answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to Jesus, “Rabbi, it is good <supplied>that</supplied> we are here! And let us make three shelters, one for you and one for Moses and one for Elijah.” <verse-number id="Mk 9:6">6</verse-number>(For he did not know what he should answer, because they were terrified.) <verse-number id="Mk 9:7">7</verse-number>And a cloud came, overshadowing them, and a voice came from the cloud, “This is my beloved Son. Listen to him!” <verse-number id="Mk 9:8">8</verse-number>And suddenly, looking around, they no longer saw anyone with them but Jesus alone. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 9:9">9</verse-number>And <supplied>as</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“were coming down”)</note> they were coming down from the mountain, he ordered them that they should tell no one <supplied>the things</supplied> that they had seen, except when the Son of Man had risen from the dead. <verse-number id="Mk 9:10">10</verse-number>And they kept the matter to themselves, discussing what this rising from the dead <idiom-start/>meant<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “is”</note> <verse-number id="Mk 9:11">11</verse-number>And they asked him, saying, “<idiom-start/>Why do<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<supplied>what is it</supplied> that”</note> the scribes say that Elijah must come first?” <verse-number id="Mk 9:12">12</verse-number>And he said to them, “Elijah indeed does come first <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“does come”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> restores all <supplied>things</supplied>. And how is it written concerning the Son of Man that he should suffer many <supplied>things</supplied> and be treated with contempt? <verse-number id="Mk 9:13">13</verse-number>But I tell you that indeed Elijah has come, and they did to him whatever they wanted, just as it is written about him.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A Demon-possessed Boy Healed</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 9:14">14</verse-number>And <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“came”) which is understood as temporal</note> came to the disciples, they saw a large crowd around them and scribes arguing with them. <verse-number id="Mk 9:15">15</verse-number>And immediately the whole crowd, <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> saw him, were amazed, and ran up to <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“ran up to”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> greeted him. <verse-number id="Mk 9:16">16</verse-number>And he asked them, “What are you arguing <supplied>about</supplied> with them?” <verse-number id="Mk 9:17">17</verse-number>And one <supplied>individual</supplied> from the crowd answered him, “Teacher, I brought to you my son who has <idiom-start/>a spirit that makes him mute<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “a mute spirit”</note> <verse-number id="Mk 9:18">18</verse-number>And whenever it seizes him, it throws him down and he foams at the mouth and grinds his<note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> teeth and becomes paralyzed. And I told your disciples that they should expel it, and they were not able <supplied>to do so</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The words “<supplied>to do so</supplied>” are not in the Greek text but are implied</note> <verse-number id="Mk 9:19">19</verse-number>And he answered them <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “O unbelieving generation! <idiom-start/>How long<idiom-end/><note>Literally “until when”</note> will I be with you? <idiom-start/>How long<idiom-end/><note>Literally “until when”</note> must I put up with you? Bring him to me!” <verse-number id="Mk 9:20">20</verse-number>And they brought him to him. And <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> saw him, the spirit immediately convulsed him, and falling on the ground, he began to roll around, foaming at the mouth. <verse-number id="Mk 9:21">21</verse-number>And he asked his father how long it was since this had been happening to him. And he said, “From childhood. <verse-number id="Mk 9:22">22</verse-number>And often it has thrown him both into fire and into water, in order that it could destroy him. But if you are able <supplied>to do</supplied> anything, have compassion on us <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied and the following participle (“have compassion”) has been translated as a finite verb and placed before the verb “help” in keeping with English style</note> help us!” <verse-number id="Mk 9:23">23</verse-number>But Jesus said to him, “If you are able! All <supplied>things</supplied> <supplied>are</supplied> possible for the one who believes!” <verse-number id="Mk 9:24">24</verse-number>Immediately the father of the child cried out <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“cried out”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “I believe! Help my unbelief!” <verse-number id="Mk 9:25">25</verse-number>Now <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> Jesus saw that a crowd was running together, he rebuked the unclean spirit, saying to it, “Mute and deaf spirit, I command you, come out of him, and enter into him no more!” <verse-number id="Mk 9:26">26</verse-number>And it came out, screaming and convulsing <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> greatly, and he became as if <supplied>he were</supplied> dead, so that most <supplied>of them</supplied> said, “He has died!” <verse-number id="Mk 9:27">27</verse-number>But Jesus took hold of his hand <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“took hold of”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> raised him up, and he stood up. <verse-number id="Mk 9:28">28</verse-number>And <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“had entered”)</note> he had entered into the house, his disciples asked him privately, “Why were we not able to expel it?” <verse-number id="Mk 9:29">29</verse-number>And he said to them, “This kind can come out by nothing except by prayer.”<note>Some manuscripts add “and fasting”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus Predicts His Death and Resurrection a Second Time</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 9:30">30</verse-number>And from there they went out <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went out”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> passed through Galilee. And he did not want anyone to know, <verse-number id="Mk 9:31">31</verse-number>for he was teaching his disciples and was telling them, “The Son of Man is being betrayed into the hands of men, and they will kill him. And <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“is killed”) which is understood as temporal</note> is killed, after three days he will rise.” <verse-number id="Mk 9:32">32</verse-number>But they did not understand the statement, and they were afraid to ask him. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Question About Who Is Greatest</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 9:33">33</verse-number>And they came to Capernaum. And <supplied>after he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was”) which is understood as temporal</note> was in the house, he asked them, “What were you discussing on the way?” <verse-number id="Mk 9:34">34</verse-number>But they were silent, because they had argued with one another on the way <supplied>about</supplied> who <supplied>was</supplied> greatest. <verse-number id="Mk 9:35">35</verse-number>And he sat down <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“sat down”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> called the twelve and said to them, “If anyone wants to be first, he will be last of all and servant of all.” <verse-number id="Mk 9:36">36</verse-number>And he took a young child <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“took”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> had him stand <idiom-start/>among them<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “in the midst of them”</note> And taking him in his arms, he said to them, <verse-number id="Mk 9:37">37</verse-number>“Whoever welcomes one of the young children such as these in my name welcomes me, and whoever welcomes me does not welcome me, but the one who sent me.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Whoever Is Not Against Us Is for Us</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 9:38">38</verse-number>John said to him, “Teacher, we saw someone expelling demons in your name, and we tried to prevent him because he was not following us.” <verse-number id="Mk 9:39">39</verse-number>But Jesus said, “Do not prevent him, because there is no one who does a miracle in my name and will be able soon afterward to speak evil of me. <verse-number id="Mk 9:40">40</verse-number>For whoever is not against us is for us. <verse-number id="Mk 9:41">41</verse-number>For whoever gives you a cup of water to drink in <supplied>my</supplied> name because you are Christ’s, truly I say to you that he will never lose his reward. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Temptations to Sin</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 9:42">42</verse-number>“And whoever causes one of these little ones who believe in me to sin, it is better for him if instead <idiom-start/>a large millstone<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a millstone of a donkey”</note> is placed around his neck and he is thrown into the sea. <verse-number id="Mk 9:43">43</verse-number>And if your hand causes you to sin, cut it off! It is better <supplied>for</supplied> you to enter into life crippled than, having two hands, to go into hell—into the unquenchable fire!<note>Most later Greek manuscripts add v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Mk 9:44">44</cite> after v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Mk 9:43">43</cite>, “where their worm does not die and the fire is not extinguished” (identical to v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Mk 9:48">48</cite>)</note> <verse-number id="Mk 9:45">45</verse-number>And if your foot causes you to sin, cut it off! It is better <supplied>for</supplied> you to enter into life lame than, having two feet, to be thrown into hell!<note>Most later Greek manuscripts add v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Mk 9:46">46</cite> after v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Mk 9:45">45</cite>, “where their worm does not die and the fire is not extinguished” (identical to v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Mk 9:48">48</cite>)</note> <verse-number id="Mk 9:47">47</verse-number>And if your eye causes you to sin, tear it out! It is better <supplied>for</supplied> you to enter into the kingdom of God with one eye than, having two eyes, to be thrown into hell, <verse-number id="Mk 9:48">48</verse-number>‘where their worm does not die and the fire is not extinguished.’<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 66:24">Isa 66:24</cite></note> <verse-number id="Mk 9:49">49</verse-number>For everyone will be salted with fire. <verse-number id="Mk 9:50">50</verse-number>Salt <supplied>is</supplied> good, but if the salt becomes deprived of its salt content, by what can you make it salty? Have salt among yourselves, and be at peace with one another.” </p>
		</chapter>