<chapter id="Mk 11">
			<pericope>The Triumphal Entry</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 11:1">1</verse-number> And when they came near to Jerusalem, to Bethphage and Bethany at the Mount of Olives, he sent two of his disciples <verse-number id="Mk 11:2">2</verse-number>and said to them, “Go into the village before you, and right away <supplied>as you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“enter”) which is understood as temporal</note> enter into it you will find a colt tied, on which no one <supplied>has</supplied> ever sat. Untie it and bring <supplied>it</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <verse-number id="Mk 11:3">3</verse-number>And if anyone says to you, ‘Why are you doing this?’ say<note>Some manuscripts omit “that” after “say” here; though understood to be present in the underlying Greek text, it introduces direct discourse here and is left untranslated, functioning much like English quotation marks</note> ‘The Lord has need of it, and will send it here again at once.’ ” <verse-number id="Mk 11:4">4</verse-number>And they went away and found a colt tied at a door outside in the street, and they untied it. <verse-number id="Mk 11:5">5</verse-number>And some of those who were standing there said to them, “What are you doing, untying the colt?” <verse-number id="Mk 11:6">6</verse-number>So they told them, just as Jesus had said, and they allowed them <supplied>to take it</supplied>.<note>The phrase “<supplied>to take it</supplied>” is not in the Greek text, but is implied</note> <verse-number id="Mk 11:7">7</verse-number>And they brought the colt to Jesus and threw their cloaks over it, and he sat on it. <verse-number id="Mk 11:8">8</verse-number>And many <supplied>people</supplied> spread their cloaks on the road, and others <supplied>spread</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the verb “<supplied>spread</supplied>” is an understood repetition of the verb earlier in this verse</note> leafy branches <supplied>they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the participle “had cut” has been translated as a finite verb; it agrees in number, gender, and case with “others,” so “<supplied>they</supplied>’ has been supplied to indicate this</note> had cut from the fields. <verse-number id="Mk 11:9">9</verse-number>And those who went ahead and those who were following were shouting, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Hosanna! </li1>
				<li1>Blessed <supplied>is</supplied> the one who comes in the name of the Lord!<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 118:25–26">Ps 118:25–26</cite></note> </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Mk 11:10">10</verse-number>Blessed <supplied>is</supplied> the coming kingdom of our father David! </li1>
				<li2>Hosanna in the highest <supplied>heaven</supplied>!”<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here “heaven” is understood</note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 11:11">11</verse-number>And he went into Jerusalem to the temple, and <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“looking around”) which is understood as temporal</note> looking around at everything, <supplied>because</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was”) which is understood as causal</note> the hour was already late, he went out to Bethany with the twelve. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A Barren Fig Tree Cursed</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 11:12">12</verse-number>And on the next day <supplied>as</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“were departing”)</note> they were departing from Bethany, he was hungry. <verse-number id="Mk 11:13">13</verse-number>And <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> saw from a distance a fig tree that had leaves, he went <supplied>to see</supplied> if perhaps he would find anything on it. And <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“came up”) which is understood as temporal</note> came up to it he found nothing except leaves, because it was not the season for figs. <verse-number id="Mk 11:14">14</verse-number>And he responded <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“responded”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to it, “Let no one eat fruit from you any more <idiom-start/>forever<idiom-end/>!”<note>Literally “for the age”</note> And his disciples heard <supplied>it</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Cleansing of the Temple</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 11:15">15</verse-number>And they came to Jerusalem. And he entered into the temple <supplied>courts</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>courts</supplied>” is supplied to distinguish this area from the interior of the temple building itself</note> <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“entered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> began to drive out those who were selling and those who were buying in the temple <supplied>courts</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here “<supplied>courts</supplied>” is supplied to distinguish this area from the interior of the temple building itself</note> and overturned the tables of the money changers and the chairs of those who were selling doves. <verse-number id="Mk 11:16">16</verse-number>And he did not permit anyone to carry objects<note>Or “merchandise”</note> through the temple <supplied>courts</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here “<supplied>courts</supplied>” is supplied to distinguish this area from the interior of the temple building itself</note> <verse-number id="Mk 11:17">17</verse-number>And he began to teach<note>The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to teach”)</note> and was saying to them, “Is it not written, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>‘My house will be called a house of prayer </li1>
				<li2>for all the nations,’<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 56:7">Isa 56:7</cite></note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p>but you have made it a cave of robbers!” <verse-number id="Mk 11:18">18</verse-number>And the chief priests and the scribes heard <supplied>it</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and began considering<note>The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began considering”)</note> how they could destroy him. For they were afraid of him because the whole crowd was astounded by his teaching. <verse-number id="Mk 11:19">19</verse-number>And when evening came they went out of the city. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Barren Fig Tree Withered</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 11:20">20</verse-number>And <supplied>as they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“passed by”) which is understood as temporal</note> passed by early in the morning, they saw the fig tree withered from the roots. <verse-number id="Mk 11:21">21</verse-number>And Peter remembered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“remembered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to him, “Rabbi, look! The fig tree that you cursed has withered!” <verse-number id="Mk 11:22">22</verse-number>And Jesus answered <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to them, “Have faith in God! <verse-number id="Mk 11:23">23</verse-number>Truly I say to you that whoever says to this mountain, ‘Be lifted up and thrown into the sea!’ and does not doubt in his heart, but believes that what he says will happen, it will be <supplied>done</supplied> for him. <verse-number id="Mk 11:24">24</verse-number>For this <supplied>reason</supplied> I say to you, whatever you pray and ask for, believe that you have received <supplied>it</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and it will be <supplied>done</supplied> for you. <verse-number id="Mk 11:25">25</verse-number>And whenever you stand praying, if you have anything against anyone, forgive <supplied>him</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> so that your Father who <supplied>is</supplied> in heaven will also forgive you your sins.”<note>Most later Greek manuscripts add v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Mk 11:26">26</cite> after v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Mk 11:25">25</cite>, “But if you do not forgive, neither will your Father in heaven forgive your sins”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus’ Authority Challenged</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 11:27">27</verse-number>And they came again to Jerusalem. And <supplied>as</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was walking”)</note> he was walking in the temple <supplied>courts</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here “<supplied>courts</supplied>” is supplied to distinguish this area from the interior of the temple building itself</note> the chief priests and the scribes and the elders came up to him <verse-number id="Mk 11:28">28</verse-number>and said to him, “By what authority are you doing these <supplied>things</supplied>, or who gave you this authority that you do these <supplied>things</supplied>?” <verse-number id="Mk 11:29">29</verse-number>So Jesus said to them, “I will ask you one question. Answer me and I will tell you by what authority I am doing these <supplied>things</supplied>. <verse-number id="Mk 11:30">30</verse-number>The baptism of John—was <supplied>it</supplied> from heaven or from men? Answer me!” <verse-number id="Mk 11:31">31</verse-number>And they began to discuss<note>The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to discuss”)</note> <supplied>this</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> with one another, saying, “What should we say?<note>Some manuscripts omit “What should we say?”</note> If we say ‘From heaven,’ he will say, ‘Why then did you not believe him?’ <verse-number id="Mk 11:32">32</verse-number>But if we say, ‘From men’ ”—they were afraid of the crowd, because they all looked upon John <idiom-start/>as truly a prophet<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “that he was truly a prophet”</note> <verse-number id="Mk 11:33">33</verse-number>And they replied to Jesus saying, “We do not know.” And Jesus said to them, “Neither will I tell you by what authority I am doing these <supplied>things</supplied>.” </p>
		</chapter>