<chapter id="Mk 12">
			<pericope>The Parable of the Tenant Farmers in the Vineyard</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 12:1">1</verse-number> And he began to speak to them in parables: “A man planted a vineyard, and put a fence <supplied>around it</supplied>, and dug a trough for the winepress, and built a watchtower, and leased it to tenant farmers, and went on a journey. <verse-number id="Mk 12:2">2</verse-number>And he sent a slave to the tenant farmers at the proper time, so that he could collect <supplied>some</supplied> of the fruit of the vineyard from the tenant farmers. <verse-number id="Mk 12:3">3</verse-number>And they seized him <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“seized”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> beat <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and sent <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> away empty-handed. <verse-number id="Mk 12:4">4</verse-number>And again he sent to them another slave, and that one they struck on the head and dishonored. <verse-number id="Mk 12:5">5</verse-number>And he sent another, and that one they killed. And <supplied>he sent</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The words “<supplied>he sent</supplied>” are not in the Greek text, but are an implied repetition from earlier in the verse</note> many others, <supplied>some</supplied> of whom they beat and <supplied>some</supplied> of whom they killed. <verse-number id="Mk 12:6">6</verse-number>He had one more, a beloved son. Last <supplied>of all</supplied> he sent him to them, saying, ‘They will respect my son.’ <verse-number id="Mk 12:7">7</verse-number>But those tenant farmers said to one another, ‘This is the heir. Come, let us kill him and the inheritance will be ours!’ <verse-number id="Mk 12:8">8</verse-number>And they seized <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“seized”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> killed him and threw him out of the vineyard. <verse-number id="Mk 12:9">9</verse-number>What<note>Some manuscripts have “What then”</note> will the owner of the vineyard do? He will come and destroy the tenant farmers and give the vineyard to others. <verse-number id="Mk 12:10">10</verse-number>Have you not read this scripture: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>‘The stone which the builders rejected, </li1>
				<li2>this has become <idiom-start/>the cornerstone<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the head of the corner”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Mk 12:11">11</verse-number>This came about from the Lord, </li1>
				<li2>and it is marvelous in our eyes’?”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 118:22–23">Ps 118:22–23</cite></note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 12:12">12</verse-number>And they were seeking to arrest him, and they were afraid of the crowd, because they knew that he had told the parable with reference to them. And they left him <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“left”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> went away. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Paying Taxes to Caesar</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 12:13">13</verse-number>And they sent some of the Pharisees and the Herodians to him so that they could catch him unawares in a statement. <verse-number id="Mk 12:14">14</verse-number>And <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“came”) which is understood as temporal</note> came, they said to him, “Teacher, we know that you are truthful and <idiom-start/>you do not care what anyone thinks<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “it is not a care to you concerning anyone”</note> <idiom-start/>because you do not regard the opinion of people<idiom-end/><note>Literally “because you do not look at the face of men”</note> but teach the way of God in truth. Is it permitted to pay taxes to Caesar or not? Should we pay or should we not pay?” <verse-number id="Mk 12:15">15</verse-number>But <supplied>because he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“knew”) which is understood as causal</note> knew their hypocrisy, he said to them, “Why are you testing me? Bring me a denarius so that I can look at <supplied>it</supplied>!”<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <verse-number id="Mk 12:16">16</verse-number>So they brought <supplied>one</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> And he said to them, “Whose image and inscription <supplied>is</supplied> this?” And they said to him, “Caesar’s.” <verse-number id="Mk 12:17">17</verse-number>And Jesus said to them, “Give to Caesar the things of Caesar, and to God the things of God!” And they were utterly amazed at him. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A Question About Marriage and the Resurrection</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 12:18">18</verse-number>And Sadducees—who say there is no resurrection—came up to him and began to ask<note>The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to ask”)</note> him, saying, <verse-number id="Mk 12:19">19</verse-number>“Teacher, Moses wrote for us that if someone’s brother dies and he leaves behind a wife and does not leave a child, that his brother should take the wife and <idiom-start/>father<idiom-end/><note>Literally “raise up”</note> descendants for his brother. <verse-number id="Mk 12:20">20</verse-number>There were seven brothers, and the first took a wife. And <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“died”) which is understood as temporal</note> died, he did not leave descendants. <verse-number id="Mk 12:21">21</verse-number>And the second took her, and he died without leaving descendants. And the third likewise. <verse-number id="Mk 12:22">22</verse-number>And the seven did not leave descendants. Last of all the woman also died. <verse-number id="Mk 12:23">23</verse-number>In the resurrection, when they rise, <idiom-start/>whose<idiom-end/><note>Literally “who of them”</note> wife will she be? For the seven had her <supplied>as</supplied> wife. <verse-number id="Mk 12:24">24</verse-number>Jesus said to them, “Are you not deceived because of this, <supplied>because you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“know”) which is understood as causal</note> do not know the scriptures or the power of God? <verse-number id="Mk 12:25">25</verse-number>For when they rise from the dead, they neither marry nor are given in marriage, but are like angels in heaven. <verse-number id="Mk 12:26">26</verse-number>Now concerning the dead, that they are raised, have you not read in the book of Moses <idiom-start/>in the passage about the bush<idiom-end/><note>Literally “at the bush”</note> how God spoke to him, saying, ‘I <supplied>am</supplied> the God of Abraham and the God of Isaac and the God of Jacob’?<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ex 3:6">Exod 3:6</cite></note> <verse-number id="Mk 12:27">27</verse-number>He is not God of the dead, but of the living. You are very much mistaken!” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Greatest Commandment</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 12:28">28</verse-number>And one of the scribes came up <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> heard them debating. <supplied>When he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> saw that he answered them well, he asked him, “Which commandment is the most important of all?” <verse-number id="Mk 12:29">29</verse-number>Jesus answered, “The most important is, ‘Listen, Israel! The Lord our God, the Lord is one. <verse-number id="Mk 12:30">30</verse-number>And you shall love the Lord your God from your whole heart and from your whole soul and from your whole mind and from your whole strength.’<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Dt 6:4–5">Deut 6:4–5</cite>; <cite title="BibleLEB2: Jos 22:5">Josh 22:5</cite></note> <verse-number id="Mk 12:31">31</verse-number>The second <supplied>is</supplied> this: ‘You shall love your neighbor as yourself.’<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Le 19:18">Lev 19:18</cite></note> There is no other commandment greater than these.” <verse-number id="Mk 12:32">32</verse-number>And the scribe said to him, “That is true, Teacher. You have said <idiom-start/>correctly<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in accordance with truth”</note> that he is one and there is no other except him. <verse-number id="Mk 12:33">33</verse-number>And to love him from your<note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> whole heart and from your<note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> whole understanding and from your<note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> whole strength, and to love your<note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> neighbor as yourself, is much more than all whole burnt offerings and sacrifices.” <verse-number id="Mk 12:34">34</verse-number>And Jesus, <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> saw that he had answered thoughtfully, said to him, “You are not far from the kingdom of God.” And no one dared to put a question to him any longer. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>David’s Son and Lord</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 12:35">35</verse-number>And continuing, Jesus said <supplied>while</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“teaching”) which is understood as temporal</note> teaching in the temple <supplied>courts</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here “<supplied>courts</supplied>” is supplied to distinguish this area from the interior of the temple building itself</note> “How can the scribes say that the Christ is David’s son? <verse-number id="Mk 12:36">36</verse-number>David himself said by the Holy Spirit, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>‘The Lord said to my Lord, </li1>
				<li2>“Sit at my right hand, </li2>
				<li1>until I put your enemies </li1>
				<li2>under your feet.” ’<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 110:1">Ps 110:1</cite></note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 12:37">37</verse-number>David himself calls him ‘Lord,’ and how is he his son?” And the large crowd was listening to him gladly. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Warning to Beware of the Scribes</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 12:38">38</verse-number>And in his teaching he said, “Beware of the scribes, who like walking around in long robes and greetings in the marketplaces <verse-number id="Mk 12:39">39</verse-number>and the best seats in the synagogues and the places of honor at banquets, <verse-number id="Mk 12:40">40</verse-number>who devour the houses of widows and pray lengthy <supplied>prayers</supplied> for the sake of appearance. These will receive more severe condemnation!” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A Poor Widow’s Offering</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 12:41">41</verse-number>And he sat down opposite the contribution box <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“sat down”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> was observing how the crowd was putting coins into the contribution box. And many rich people were putting in many <supplied>coins</supplied>.<note>Although often translated “large sums,” the plural here suggests large numbers of individual coins, which would make an impressive noise</note> <verse-number id="Mk 12:42">42</verse-number>And one poor widow came <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> put in two small copper coins<note>This coin was the <i>lepton</i>, worth 1/128 of a denarius</note> (that is, a penny).<note>This coin was the <i>quadrans</i>, the smallest Roman coin, worth 2 <i>lepta</i></note> <verse-number id="Mk 12:43">43</verse-number>And summoning his disciples, he said to them, “Truly I say to you that this poor widow put in more than all those who put <supplied>offerings</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> into the contribution box. <verse-number id="Mk 12:44">44</verse-number>For they all <idiom-start/>contributed<idiom-end/><note>Literally “put in”</note> out of their abundance, but she out of her poverty put in everything she had, her whole means of subsistence.” </p>
		</chapter>