<chapter id="Mk 15">
			<pericope>Jesus Taken to Pilate</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 15:1">1</verse-number> And as soon as morning <supplied>came</supplied>, <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“formulating”) which is understood as temporal</note> formulating a plan, the chief priests, with the elders and scribes and the whole Sanhedrin, tied up Jesus, led <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> away, and handed <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> over to Pilate. <verse-number id="Mk 15:2">2</verse-number>And Pilate asked him, “Are you the king of the Jews?” And he answered him <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “You say <supplied>so</supplied>.” <verse-number id="Mk 15:3">3</verse-number>And the chief priests began to accuse<note>The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to accuse”)</note> him <supplied>of</supplied> many <supplied>things</supplied>. <verse-number id="Mk 15:4">4</verse-number>So Pilate asked him again, saying, “Do you not answer anything? See how many <supplied>charges</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The word “charges” is not in the Greek text but is implied</note> they are bringing against you!” <verse-number id="Mk 15:5">5</verse-number>But Jesus did not answer anything further, so that Pilate was astonished. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Pilate Releases Barabbas</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 15:6">6</verse-number>Now at each feast he customarily released<note>The imperfect tense has been translated as customary here (“customarily released”)</note> for them one prisoner whom they requested. <verse-number id="Mk 15:7">7</verse-number>And the one named Barabbas<note>“Barabbas” means “son of the father” in Aramaic</note> was imprisoned with the rebels who had committed murder in the rebellion. <verse-number id="Mk 15:8">8</verse-number>And the crowd came up <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> began to ask him to do as he customarily did<note>The imperfect tense has been translated as customary here (“customarily did”)</note> for them. <verse-number id="Mk 15:9">9</verse-number>So Pilate answered them, saying, “Do you want me to release for you the king of the Jews?” <verse-number id="Mk 15:10">10</verse-number>(For he realized that the chief priests had handed him over because of envy.) <verse-number id="Mk 15:11">11</verse-number>But the chief priests incited the crowd so that he would release for them Barabbas<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> instead. <verse-number id="Mk 15:12">12</verse-number>So Pilate answered <supplied>and</supplied> said to them again, “Then what do you want me to do with <supplied>the one</supplied> whom you call the king of the Jews?” <verse-number id="Mk 15:13">13</verse-number>And they shouted again, “Crucify him!” <verse-number id="Mk 15:14">14</verse-number>And Pilate said to them, “Why? What evil has he done?” But they shouted even louder, “Crucify him!” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 15:15">15</verse-number>So Pilate, <supplied>because he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“wanted”) which is understood as causal</note> wanted <idiom-start/>to satisfy<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to make sufficient”</note> the crowd, released for them Barabbas. And <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“flogged”) which is understood as temporal</note> he had Jesus flogged, he handed <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> over so that he could be crucified. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus Is Mocked</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 15:16">16</verse-number>So the soldiers led him away into the palace (that is, the governor’s residence) and called together the whole cohort. <verse-number id="Mk 15:17">17</verse-number>And they put a purple cloak on him, and <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“weaving”) which is understood as temporal</note> weaving a crown of thorns they placed <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> on him. <verse-number id="Mk 15:18">18</verse-number>And they began to greet him, “Hail, king of the Jews!” <verse-number id="Mk 15:19">19</verse-number>And they repeatedly struck<note>The imperfect tense has been translated as iterative here (“repeatedly struck”)</note> him on the head with a reed, and were spitting on him, and <idiom-start/>they knelt down<idiom-end/><note>Literally “bending the knees”</note> <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“knelt down”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> did obeisance to him. <verse-number id="Mk 15:20">20</verse-number>And when they had mocked him, they stripped him of the purple cloak and put his own clothes<note>Some manuscripts have “his clothes” in place of “his own clothes”</note> on him, and they led him out so that they could crucify him. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus Is Crucified</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 15:21">21</verse-number>And they forced a certain man who was passing by, Simon of Cyrene (the father of Alexander and Rufus), who was coming from the country, to carry his cross. <verse-number id="Mk 15:22">22</verse-number>And they brought him to the place <i>Golgotha</i> (which is translated “Place of a Skull”). <verse-number id="Mk 15:23">23</verse-number>And they attempted to give<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the imperfect tense is translated as a conative imperfect (“attempted to give”)</note> him wine mixed with myrrh, but he did not take it. <verse-number id="Mk 15:24">24</verse-number>And they crucified him and divided his clothes among themselves<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “among themselves” reflects the middle voice of the verb “divided”</note> <supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“casting”) which is understood as means</note> casting lots for them <supplied>to see</supplied> who should take what. <verse-number id="Mk 15:25">25</verse-number>Now it was the third hour when they crucified him. <verse-number id="Mk 15:26">26</verse-number>And the inscription of the charge against him was written, “The king of the Jews.” <verse-number id="Mk 15:27">27</verse-number>And with him they crucified two robbers, one on <supplied>his</supplied> right and one on <supplied>his</supplied> left.<note>Most later Greek manuscripts add v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Mk 15:28">28</cite> (a quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 53:12">Isa 53:12</cite>) after v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Mk 15:27">27</cite>, “And the scripture was fulfilled that says, ‘And he was counted with the lawless ones’ ”</note> <verse-number id="Mk 15:29">29</verse-number>And those who passed by reviled him, shaking their heads and saying, “Aha! The one who would destroy the temple and rebuild <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> in three days, <verse-number id="Mk 15:30">30</verse-number>save yourself <supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“coming down”) which is understood as means</note> coming down from the cross!” <verse-number id="Mk 15:31">31</verse-number>In the same way also the chief priests, along with the scribes, were mocking <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to one another, saying, “He saved others; he is not able to save himself! <verse-number id="Mk 15:32">32</verse-number>Let the Christ, the king of Israel, come down now from the cross, so that we may see and believe! Even those who were crucified with him were reviling him. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus Dies on the Cross</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 15:33">33</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“came”)</note> the sixth hour came, darkness came over the whole land until the ninth hour. <verse-number id="Mk 15:34">34</verse-number>And at the ninth hour Jesus cried out with a loud voice, “<i>Eloi, Eloi, lema sabachthani?</i>” (which is translated, “My God, my God, <idiom-start/>why<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for what <supplied>reason</supplied>”</note> have you forsaken me?”)<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 22:1">Ps 22:1</cite></note> <verse-number id="Mk 15:35">35</verse-number>And some of the bystanders, <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> heard <supplied>it</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> said, “Behold, he is summoning Elijah!” <verse-number id="Mk 15:36">36</verse-number>And someone ran and filled a sponge with sour wine, put <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> on a reed, <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the two previous participles (“ran” and “filled”) have been translated as finite verbs</note> gave <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to him to drink, saying, “Leave <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> alone! Let us see if Elijah is coming to take him down.” <verse-number id="Mk 15:37">37</verse-number>But Jesus uttered a loud cry <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“uttered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> expired. <verse-number id="Mk 15:38">38</verse-number>And the curtain of the temple was torn in two from top to bottom. <verse-number id="Mk 15:39">39</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> the centurion who was standing opposite him saw that he expired like this, he said, “Truly this man was God’s Son!” <verse-number id="Mk 15:40">40</verse-number>And there were also women observing from a distance, among whom <supplied>were</supplied> Mary Magdalene, and Mary the mother of James the younger<note>Or perhaps “the short,” referring to stature</note> and Joses,<note>This name appears in <cite title="BibleLEB2: Mt 27:56">Matt 27:56 </cite>as “Joseph”</note> and Salome, <verse-number id="Mk 15:41">41</verse-number>who used to follow<note>The imperfect tense has been translated as customary here (“used to follow”)</note> him and serve him when he was in Galilee, and many other <supplied>women</supplied> who went up with him to Jerusalem. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jesus Is Buried</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 15:42">42</verse-number>And <supplied>when it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was”)</note> was already evening, since it was the day of preparation (that is, the day before the Sabbath), <verse-number id="Mk 15:43">43</verse-number>Joseph of Arimathea, a prominent member of the council who was also himself looking forward to<note>Or “waiting for”</note> the kingdom of God, came acting courageously <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> went in to Pilate and asked for the body of Jesus. <verse-number id="Mk 15:44">44</verse-number>And Pilate was surprised that he was already dead, and summoning the centurion, asked him whether he had died already. <verse-number id="Mk 15:45">45</verse-number>And <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“learned of”) which is understood as temporal</note> learned of <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> from the centurion, he granted the corpse to Joseph. <verse-number id="Mk 15:46">46</verse-number>And <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“purchasing”) which is understood as temporal</note> purchasing a linen cloth <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the participle (“taking...down”) has been translated as a finite verb in keeping with English style</note> taking him down, he wrapped <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> in the linen cloth and placed him in a tomb that had been cut from the rock. And he rolled a stone over the entrance of the tomb. <verse-number id="Mk 15:47">47</verse-number>Now Mary Magdalene and Mary the <supplied>mother</supplied> of Joses saw where he was placed. </p>
		</chapter>