<chapter id="Mk 16">
			<pericope>Jesus Is Raised</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 16:1">1</verse-number> And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was over”)</note> the Sabbath was over, Mary Magdalene, and Mary the <supplied>mother</supplied> of James, and Salome purchased fragrant spices so that they could go <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“go”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> anoint him. <verse-number id="Mk 16:2">2</verse-number>And very early in the morning on the first <supplied>day</supplied> of the week they came to the tomb <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“had risen”)</note> the sun had risen. <verse-number id="Mk 16:3">3</verse-number>And they were saying to one another, “Who will roll away the stone for us from the entrance of the tomb?” <verse-number id="Mk 16:4">4</verse-number>And <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“looked up”) which is understood as temporal</note> looked up, they saw that the stone had been rolled away (for it was very large). <verse-number id="Mk 16:5">5</verse-number>And <supplied>as they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“going”) which is understood as temporal</note> were going into the tomb, they saw a young man dressed in a white robe sitting on the right side, and they were alarmed. <verse-number id="Mk 16:6">6</verse-number>But he said to them, “Do not be alarmed. You are looking for Jesus the Nazarene who was crucified. He has been raised, he is not here! See the place where they laid him! <verse-number id="Mk 16:7">7</verse-number>But go, tell his disciples and Peter that he is going ahead of you to Galilee. You will see him there, just as he told you.” <verse-number id="Mk 16:8">8</verse-number>And they went out <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went out”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> fled from the tomb, because trembling and amazement had seized them. And they said nothing to anyone, because they were afraid.<note>The Gospel of Mark ends at this point in some manuscripts, including two of the most important ones, while other manuscripts supply a shorter ending (sometimes included as part of v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Mk 16:8">8</cite>), others supply the traditional longer ending (vv. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Mk 16:9–20">9–20</cite>), and still other manuscripts supply both the shorter ending and vv. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Mk 16:9–20">9–20</cite>; due to significant questions about the authenticity of these alternative endings, many scholars regard 16:8 as the last verse of the Gospel of Mark</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Shorter Ending of Mark</pericope>
			<p>〚So they promptly reported all the <supplied>things</supplied> they had been commanded to those around Peter. And after these <supplied>things</supplied>, Jesus himself also sent out through them from the east even as far as the west the holy and imperishable proclamation of eternal salvation. Amen.〛 </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Longer Ending of Mark</pericope>
			<p>〚<verse-number id="Mk 16:9">9</verse-number>Now early on the first <supplied>day</supplied> of the week, <supplied>after he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“rose”) which is understood as temporal</note> rose, he appeared first to Mary Magdalene, from whom he had expelled seven demons. <verse-number id="Mk 16:10">10</verse-number>She went out <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went out”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> announced <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to those who were with him <supplied>while they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“were”) which is understood as temporal</note> were mourning and weeping. <verse-number id="Mk 16:11">11</verse-number>And those, <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> heard that he was alive and had been seen by her, refused to believe <supplied>it</supplied>.<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <verse-number id="Mk 16:12">12</verse-number>And after these <supplied>things</supplied>, he appeared in a different form to two of them <supplied>as they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“were walking”) which is understood as temporal</note> were walking, <supplied>while they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“were going out”) which is understood as temporal</note> were going out into the countryside. <verse-number id="Mk 16:13">13</verse-number>And these went <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> reported <supplied>it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to the others, and they did not believe them. <verse-number id="Mk 16:14">14</verse-number>And later, <supplied>while</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“were reclining at table”) which is understood as temporal</note> they were reclining at table, he appeared to the eleven. And he reprimanded their unbelief and hardness of heart, because they did not believe those who had seen him <supplied>after he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had been raised”) which is understood as temporal</note> had been raised. <verse-number id="Mk 16:15">15</verse-number>And he said to them, “Go<note>As a participle of attendant circumstance this participle carries imperatival force picked up from the main verb (“preach”)</note> into all the world <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“go”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> preach the gospel to all creation. <verse-number id="Mk 16:16">16</verse-number>The one who believes and is baptized will be saved, but the one who refuses to believe will be condemned. <verse-number id="Mk 16:17">17</verse-number>And these signs will accompany those who believe: in my name they will expel demons, they will speak in new tongues, <verse-number id="Mk 16:18">18</verse-number>they will pick up<note>Some manuscripts have “and they will pick up”</note> snakes.<note>Some manuscripts add “with their hands”</note> And if they drink any deadly <supplied>poison</supplied> it will never hurt them; they will lay hands on the sick and <idiom-start/>they will get<idiom-end/><note>Literally “they will have”</note> well.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Mk 16:19">19</verse-number>Then the Lord Jesus, after <supplied>he</supplied> had spoken to them, was taken up into heaven and sat down at the right hand of God. <verse-number id="Mk 16:20">20</verse-number>And they went out <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went out”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> proclaimed everywhere, <supplied>while</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was working together with”)</note> the Lord was working together with <supplied>them</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and confirming the message through the accompanying signs.〛 </p>
		</chapter>