<chapter id="Heb 1">
			<pericope>God’s Full and Final Revelation in the Son</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 1:1">1</verse-number> <supplied>Although</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>although</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“spoke”) which is understood as concessive</note> God spoke long ago in many parts<note>Or “portions”</note> and in many ways to the fathers by the prophets, <verse-number id="Heb 1:2">2</verse-number>in these last days he has spoken to us by a Son, whom he appointed heir of all <supplied>things</supplied>, through whom also he made the world,<note>Or “the universe”; literally “the ages”</note> <verse-number id="Heb 1:3">3</verse-number>who is the radiance of his glory and the representation of his essence, sustaining all <supplied>things</supplied> by the word of power.<note>Some manuscripts have “by the word of his power. <supplied>When he</supplied> had made purification for sins, he sat down”</note> <supplied>When he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had made”) which is understood as temporal</note> had made purification for sins through him, he sat down at the right hand of the Majesty on high, <verse-number id="Heb 1:4">4</verse-number>having become by so much better than the angels, by as much as he has inherited a more excellent name than theirs. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Son Superior to the Angels</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 1:5">5</verse-number>For to which of the angels did he ever say, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“You are my son, </li1>
				<li2>today I have begotten you,”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 2:7">Ps 2:7</cite></note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p>and again, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“I will be <idiom-start/>his father<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to him for a father”</note>, </li1>
				<li2>and he will be <idiom-start/>my son<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to me for a son”</note>”?<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: 2 Sa 7:14">2 Sam 7:14 </cite>(cf. <cite title="BibleLEB2: 1 Ch 17:13">1 Chr 17:13</cite>)</note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 1:6">6</verse-number>And again, when he brings the firstborn into the world, he says, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“And let all <supplied>the</supplied> angels of God worship him.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Dt 32:43">Deut 32:43 </cite>and <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 97:7">Ps 97:7</cite></note> </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 1:7">7</verse-number>And concerning the angels he says, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“The one who makes his angels winds, </li1>
				<li1>and his servants a flame of fire,”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 104:4">Ps 104:4</cite></note> </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 1:8">8</verse-number>but concerning the Son, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Your throne, O God, <supplied>is</supplied> <idiom-start/>forever and ever<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for the age of the age”</note>, </li1>
				<li1>and the scepter of righteous <supplied>is the</supplied> scepter of your kingdom. </li1>
				<li2><verse-number id="Heb 1:9">9</verse-number>You have loved righteousness and hated lawlessness; </li2>
				<li1>because of this God, your God, has anointed you </li1>
				<li2>with the olive oil of joy more than your companions.<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 45:6–7">Ps 45:6–7</cite></note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 1:10">10</verse-number>And, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“You, Lord, laid the foundation of the earth in the beginning, </li1>
				<li1>and the heavens are the works of your hands; </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Heb 1:11">11</verse-number>they will perish, but you continue, </li1>
				<li2>and they will all become old like a garment, </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Heb 1:12">12</verse-number>and like a robe you will roll them up, </li1>
				<li1>and like a garment they will be changed; </li1>
				<li1>but you are the same, and your years will not run out.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 102:25–27">Ps 102:25–27</cite></note> </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 1:13">13</verse-number>But to which of the angels has he ever said, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Sit down at my right hand, </li1>
				<li1>until I make your enemies a footstool for your feet.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 110:1">Ps 110:1</cite></note> </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 1:14">14</verse-number>Are they not all spirits engaged in special service, sent on assignment for the sake of those who are going to inherit salvation? </p>
		</chapter>