<chapter id="Heb 2">
			<pericope>Warning Not to Neglect Salvation</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 2:1">1</verse-number> Because of this, <supplied>it is</supplied> all the more necessary <supplied>that</supplied> we pay attention to the <supplied>things</supplied> we have heard, lest we drift away. <verse-number id="Heb 2:2">2</verse-number>For if the word spoken through angels was binding and every transgression and act of disobedience received a just penalty, <verse-number id="Heb 2:3">3</verse-number>how will we escape <supplied>if we</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>if</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“neglect”) which is understood as conditional</note> neglect so great a salvation which had <supplied>its</supplied> beginning <supplied>when it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal infinitive (“was spoken”)</note> was spoken through the Lord <supplied>and</supplied> was confirmed to us by those who heard, <verse-number id="Heb 2:4">4</verse-number><supplied>while</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was testifying at the same time”)</note> God was testifying at the same time by signs and wonders and various miracles and distributions of the Holy Spirit according to his will. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Son’s Humiliation and Suffering</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 2:5">5</verse-number>For he did not subject to angels the world to come, about which we are speaking. <verse-number id="Heb 2:6">6</verse-number>But someone testified somewhere, saying, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“What is man, that you remember him, </li1>
				<li2>or the son of man, that you care for him? </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Heb 2:7">7</verse-number>You made him for a short <supplied>time</supplied> lower than the angels; </li1>
				<li2>you crowned him with glory and honor;<note>Several important manuscripts add “and placed him over the works of your hands” to the end of v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Heb 2:7">7</cite></note> </li2>
				<li2><verse-number id="Heb 2:8">8</verse-number>you subjected all <supplied>things</supplied> under his feet.<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 8:4–6">Ps 8:4–6</cite></note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p>For in subjecting all <supplied>things</supplied>,<note>Some manuscripts have “subjecting all things to him”</note> he left nothing <supplied>that was</supplied> not subject to him. But now we do not yet see all <supplied>things</supplied> subjected to him, <verse-number id="Heb 2:9">9</verse-number>but we see Jesus, for a short <supplied>time</supplied> made lower than the angels, because of the suffering of death crowned with glory and honor, so that apart from God<note>Some manuscripts have “so that by the grace of God”</note> he might taste death on behalf of everyone. <verse-number id="Heb 2:10">10</verse-number>For it was fitting for him for whom <supplied>are</supplied> all <supplied>things</supplied> and through whom <supplied>are</supplied> all <supplied>things</supplied> in bringing many sons to glory to perfect the originator of their salvation through sufferings. <verse-number id="Heb 2:11">11</verse-number>For both the one who sanctifies and the ones who are sanctified <supplied>are</supplied> all from one, for which reason he is not ashamed to call them brothers, <verse-number id="Heb 2:12">12</verse-number>saying, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“I will proclaim your name to my brothers; </li1>
				<li1>in the midst of the assembly I will sing in praise of you.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 22:22">Ps 22:22</cite></note> </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 2:13">13</verse-number>And again, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“I will trust in him.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 8:17">Isa 8:17</cite></note> </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p>And again, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Behold, I and the children God has given me.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 8:18">Isa 8:18</cite></note> </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 2:14">14</verse-number>Therefore, since the children share in blood and flesh, he also in like manner shared in these <supplied>same things</supplied>, in order that through death he could destroy the one who has the power of death, that is, the devil, <verse-number id="Heb 2:15">15</verse-number>and could set free these who through fear of death were subject to slavery throughout all their lives. <verse-number id="Heb 2:16">16</verse-number>For surely he is not concerned with angels, but he is concerned with the descendants of Abraham. <verse-number id="Heb 2:17">17</verse-number>Therefore he was obligated to be made like his brothers in all <supplied>respects</supplied>, in order that he could become a merciful and faithful high priest in the things relating to God, in order to make atonement for the sins of the people. <verse-number id="Heb 2:18">18</verse-number>For in that which he himself suffered <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was tempted”) which is understood as temporal</note> was tempted, he is able to help those who are tempted. </p>
		</chapter>