<chapter id="Heb 3">
			<pericope>The Superiority of Jesus to Moses</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 3:1">1</verse-number> Therefore, holy brothers, sharers in a heavenly calling, consider Jesus, the apostle and high priest of our confession, <verse-number id="Heb 3:2">2</verse-number>who was faithful to the one who appointed him, as Moses also <supplied>was</supplied> in his household.<note>Some manuscripts have “in all his household”</note> <verse-number id="Heb 3:3">3</verse-number>For this one is considered worthy of greater glory than Moses, inasmuch as the one who builds it has greater honor than the house. <verse-number id="Heb 3:4">4</verse-number>For every house is built by someone, but the one who built all <supplied>things</supplied> <supplied>is</supplied> God. <verse-number id="Heb 3:5">5</verse-number>And Moses <supplied>was</supplied> faithful in all his house as a servant, for a testimony to the things that would be spoken, <verse-number id="Heb 3:6">6</verse-number>but Christ <supplied>was faithful</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The words “<supplied>was faithful</supplied>” are not in the Greek text, but are an understood repetition from the previous verse and v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Heb 3:2">2</cite></note> as a son over his house, whose house we are, if<note>Some manuscripts have “if indeed”</note> we hold fast to our confidence and the hope we can be proud of. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A Serious Warning Against Unbelief</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 3:7">7</verse-number>Therefore, just as the Holy Spirit says, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Today, if you hear his voice, </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Heb 3:8">8</verse-number>do not harden your hearts as in the rebellion, </li1>
				<li2>in the day of testing in the wilderness, </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Heb 3:9">9</verse-number>where your fathers tested <supplied>me</supplied> by trial </li1>
				<li2>and saw my works <verse-number id="Heb 3:10">10</verse-number><supplied>for</supplied> forty years. </li2>
				<li1>Therefore I was angry with this generation, </li1>
				<li2>and I said, ‘They always go astray in their heart, </li2>
				<li1>and they do not know my ways.’ </li1>
				<li2><verse-number id="Heb 3:11">11</verse-number>As I swore in my anger, </li2>
				<li1>‘<idiom-start/>They will never enter<idiom-end/><note>Literally “if they will enter”</note> into my rest.’ ”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 95:7b–11">Ps 95:7b-11</cite></note> </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 3:12">12</verse-number>Watch out, brothers, lest there be in some of you an evil, unbelieving heart, <supplied>with the result that you</supplied> fall away<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>with the result that</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the infinitive (“fall away”) which is understood as result</note> from the living God. <verse-number id="Heb 3:13">13</verse-number>But encourage one another <idiom-start/>day by day<idiom-end/><note>Literally “by each day”</note>, as long as it is called “today,” so that <idiom-start/>none of you become hardened<idiom-end/><note>Literally “not anyone of you be hardened”</note> by the deception of sin. <verse-number id="Heb 3:14">14</verse-number>For we have become partners of Christ, if indeed we hold fast the beginning of <supplied>our</supplied> commitment steadfast until the end, <verse-number id="Heb 3:15">15</verse-number><idiom-start/>while it is said<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the saying”</note>, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Today, if you hear his voice, </li1>
				<li1>do not harden your hearts as in the rebellion.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 95:7b–8">Ps 95:7b-8</cite></note> </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 3:16">16</verse-number>For who, <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> heard <supplied>it</supplied>, were disobedient? Surely <supplied>it was</supplied> not all who went out from Egypt through Moses? <verse-number id="Heb 3:17">17</verse-number>And with whom was he angry <supplied>for</supplied> forty years? <supplied>Was it</supplied> not with those who sinned, whose dead bodies fell in the wilderness? <verse-number id="Heb 3:18">18</verse-number>And to whom did he swear <supplied>they would</supplied> not enter into his rest, except those who were disobedient? <verse-number id="Heb 3:19">19</verse-number>And <supplied>so</supplied> we see that they were not able to enter because of unbelief. </p>
		</chapter>