<chapter id="Heb 5">
			<pericope>A High Priest Like Melchizedek</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 5:1">1</verse-number> For every high priest taken from among men is appointed on behalf of people in the things relating to God, in order that he can offer both gifts and sacrifices on behalf of sins, <verse-number id="Heb 5:2">2</verse-number>being able to deal gently with those who are ignorant and led astray, since he himself also is surrounded by weakness, <verse-number id="Heb 5:3">3</verse-number>and because of it he is obligated to offer <supplied>sacrifices</supplied> for sins <idiom-start/>for himself also, as well as for the people<idiom-end/><note>Literally “as for the people so also for himself”</note>. <verse-number id="Heb 5:4">4</verse-number>And someone does not take for himself the honor, but is called by God, just as Aaron also <supplied>was</supplied>. <verse-number id="Heb 5:5">5</verse-number>Thus also Christ did not glorify himself to become high priest, but the one who said to him, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“You are my Son, today I have begotten you,”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 2:7">Ps 2:7</cite></note> </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 5:6">6</verse-number>just as also in another <supplied>place</supplied> he says, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“You <supplied>are</supplied> a priest <idiom-start/>forever<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for the age”</note> according to the order of Melchizedek,”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 110:4">Ps 110:4</cite></note> </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 5:7">7</verse-number>who in the days of his flesh offered up both prayers and supplications, with loud crying and tears, to the one who was able to save him from death, and he was heard as a result of his reverence. <verse-number id="Heb 5:8">8</verse-number>Although he was a son, he learned obedience from what he suffered, <verse-number id="Heb 5:9">9</verse-number>and being perfected, he became the source of eternal salvation to all those who obey him, <verse-number id="Heb 5:10">10</verse-number>being designated by God a high priest according to the order of Melchizedek. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Advanced Teaching Hindered by Immaturity</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 5:11">11</verse-number>Concerning this<note>Literally “which”</note> <idiom-start/>we have much to say and it is difficult to explain<idiom-end/><note>Literally “great for us the message and hard to explain to say”</note>, since you have become sluggish in hearing. <verse-number id="Heb 5:12">12</verse-number>For indeed, <supplied>although you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>although</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“ought”) which is understood as concessive</note> ought to be teachers <idiom-start/>by this time<idiom-end/><note>Literally “because of the time”</note>, you have need of someone to teach you again the beginning elements of the oracles of God, and <idiom-start/>you have need of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “you are having need of”</note> milk, not<note>Some manuscripts have “and not”</note> solid food. <verse-number id="Heb 5:13">13</verse-number>For everyone who partakes of milk <supplied>is</supplied> unacquainted with the message of righteousness, because he is an infant. <verse-number id="Heb 5:14">14</verse-number>But solid food is for the mature, who because of practice have trained their faculties for the distinguishing of both good and evil. </p>
		</chapter>