<chapter id="Heb 6">
			<pericope>A Serious Warning Against Falling Away</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 6:1">1</verse-number> Therefore, leaving behind the elementary message about Christ, let us move on to maturity, not laying again a foundation of repentance from dead works and faith in God, <verse-number id="Heb 6:2">2</verse-number>teaching about baptisms and laying on of hands, and resurrection of the dead and eternal judgment. <verse-number id="Heb 6:3">3</verse-number>And this we will do, if God permits. <verse-number id="Heb 6:4">4</verse-number>For <supplied>it is</supplied> impossible <supplied>concerning</supplied> those who have once been enlightened, and have tasted the heavenly gift, and become sharers of the Holy Spirit, <verse-number id="Heb 6:5">5</verse-number>and have tasted the good word of God and the powers of the coming age, <verse-number id="Heb 6:6">6</verse-number>and having fallen away, to renew <supplied>them</supplied> again to repentance, <supplied>because they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“have crucified again”) which is understood as causal</note> have crucified again for themselves the Son of God and held him up to contempt. <verse-number id="Heb 6:7">7</verse-number>For ground that drinks the rain that comes often upon it, and brings forth vegetation usable to those <supplied>people</supplied> <idiom-start/>for whose sake<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for the sake of whom”</note> <supplied>it is</supplied> also cultivated, shares a blessing from God. <verse-number id="Heb 6:8">8</verse-number>But <supplied>if it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>if</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“produces”) which is understood as conditional</note> produces thorns and thistles, <supplied>it is</supplied> worthless and near to a curse, whose end <supplied>is</supplied> for burning. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 6:9">9</verse-number>But even if we are speaking in this way, dear friends, we are convinced of better <supplied>things</supplied> concerning you, and belonging to salvation. <verse-number id="Heb 6:10">10</verse-number>For God <supplied>is</supplied> not unjust, <supplied>so as</supplied> to forget your work and the love which you demonstrated for his name <supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“having served”) which is understood as means</note> having served the saints, and continuing to serve <supplied>them</supplied>. <verse-number id="Heb 6:11">11</verse-number>And we desire each one of you to demonstrate the same diligence for the full assurance of <supplied>your</supplied> hope until the end, <verse-number id="Heb 6:12">12</verse-number>in order that you may not be sluggish, but imitators of those who inherit the promises through faith and patience. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Reliability of God’s Promise</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 6:13">13</verse-number>For <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal participle (“made a promise”)</note> God made a promise to Abraham, since he had no one greater to swear by, he swore by himself, <verse-number id="Heb 6:14">14</verse-number>saying, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Surely <idiom-start/>I will greatly bless<idiom-end/><note>Literally “blessing I will bless”</note> you, and <idiom-start/>I will greatly multiply<idiom-end/><note>Literally “multiplying I will multiply”</note> you.” </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 6:15">15</verse-number>And so, <supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“persevering”) which is understood as means</note> persevering, he obtained the promise. <verse-number id="Heb 6:16">16</verse-number>For people swear by what is greater <supplied>than themselves</supplied>, and the oath for confirmation <supplied>is the</supplied> end of all dispute for them. <verse-number id="Heb 6:17">17</verse-number>In the same way God, <supplied>because he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“wanted”) which is understood as causal</note> wanted to show even more to the heirs of the promise the unchangeableness of his resolve, guaranteed <supplied>it</supplied> with an oath, <verse-number id="Heb 6:18">18</verse-number>in order that through two unchangeable things, in which <supplied>it is</supplied> impossible for God to lie, we who have taken refuge may have powerful encouragement to hold fast to the hope set before <supplied>us</supplied>, <verse-number id="Heb 6:19">19</verse-number>which we have like an anchor of the soul, both firm and steadfast, and entering into the inside of the curtain, <verse-number id="Heb 6:20">20</verse-number>where Jesus, the forerunner for us, entered, <supplied>because he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“became”) which is understood as causal</note> became a high priest <idiom-start/>forever<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the age”</note> according to the order of Melchizedek. </p>
		</chapter>