<chapter id="Heb 9">
			<pericope>The Earthly Ministry of the Old Covenant</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 9:1">1</verse-number> Now<note>Some manuscripts have “Now even”</note> the first <supplied>covenant</supplied> had regulations for worship and the earthly sanctuary. <verse-number id="Heb 9:2">2</verse-number>For a tent was prepared, the first <supplied>one</supplied>, in which <supplied>were</supplied> the lampstand and the table and the presentation of the loaves, which is called the holy place. <verse-number id="Heb 9:3">3</verse-number>And after the second curtain <supplied>was</supplied> a tent called the holy of holies, <verse-number id="Heb 9:4">4</verse-number>containing the golden incense altar and the ark of the covenant covered on all sides with gold, in which <supplied>were</supplied> a golden jar containing the manna and the rod of Aaron that budded and the tablets of the covenant. <verse-number id="Heb 9:5">5</verse-number>And above it <supplied>were</supplied> the cherubim of glory overshadowing the mercy seat, about which it is not now <supplied>possible</supplied> to speak in detail. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 9:6">6</verse-number>Now these things having been prepared in this way, the priests enter into the first tent <idiom-start/>continually<idiom-end/><note>Literally “throughout all”</note> <supplied>as they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal participle (“accomplish”)</note> accomplish their service, <verse-number id="Heb 9:7">7</verse-number>but only the high priest <supplied>enters</supplied> into the second <supplied>tent</supplied> once a year, not without blood, which he offers on behalf of himself and the <supplied>sins</supplied> of the people committed in ignorance. <verse-number id="Heb 9:8">8</verse-number>The Holy Spirit <supplied>was</supplied> making this clear, <supplied>that</supplied> the way <supplied>into</supplied> the holy place <supplied>was</supplied> not yet revealed, <supplied>while</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal participle (“was”)</note> the first tent was still in existence, <verse-number id="Heb 9:9">9</verse-number>which <supplied>was</supplied> a symbol for the present time, in which both the gifts and sacrifices which were offered were not able to perfect the worshiper with respect to the conscience, <verse-number id="Heb 9:10">10</verse-number>concerning <supplied>instead</supplied> only food and drink and different washings, regulations of outward things imposed until the time of setting <supplied>things</supplied> right. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Heavenly Ministry of the New Covenant</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 9:11">11</verse-number>But Christ has arrived <supplied>as</supplied> a high priest of the good <supplied>things</supplied> to come. Through the greater and more perfect tent not made by hands, that is, not of this creation, <verse-number id="Heb 9:12">12</verse-number>and not by the blood of goats and calves, but by his own blood, he entered once for all into the <supplied>most</supplied> holy place, obtaining eternal redemption. <verse-number id="Heb 9:13">13</verse-number>For if the blood of goats and bulls and the ashes of a young cow sprinkled on those who are defiled sanctify <supplied>them</supplied> for the ritual purity of the flesh, <verse-number id="Heb 9:14">14</verse-number>how much more will the blood of Christ, who through the eternal Spirit offered himself without blemish to God, cleanse our consciences from dead works to serve <supplied>the</supplied> living God? </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 9:15">15</verse-number>And because of this, he is the mediator of a new covenant, in order that, <supplied>because</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“has taken place”) which is understood as causal</note> a death has taken place for the redemption of transgressions <supplied>committed</supplied> during the first covenant, those who are the called may receive the promise of the eternal inheritance. <verse-number id="Heb 9:16">16</verse-number>For where <supplied>there is</supplied> a will, <supplied>it is</supplied> a necessity <supplied>for</supplied> the death of the one who made the will to be established. <verse-number id="Heb 9:17">17</verse-number>For a will <supplied>is</supplied> in force concerning those who are dead, since <supplied>it is</supplied> never in force when the one who made the will is alive. <verse-number id="Heb 9:18">18</verse-number>Therefore not even the first <supplied>covenant</supplied> was ratified without blood. <verse-number id="Heb 9:19">19</verse-number>For <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal participle (“had been spoken”)</note> every commandment had been spoken by Moses to all the people according to the law, <supplied>he</supplied> took the blood of calves<note>Some manuscripts have “calves and goats”</note> with water and scarlet wool and hyssop <supplied>and</supplied> sprinkled both the scroll itself and all the people, <verse-number id="Heb 9:20">20</verse-number>saying, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“This <supplied>is</supplied> the blood of the covenant that God has commanded for you.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ex 24:8">Exod 24:8</cite></note> </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 9:21">21</verse-number>And likewise he sprinkled both the tabernacle and all the utensils of service with the blood. <verse-number id="Heb 9:22">22</verse-number>Indeed, nearly everything is purified with blood according to the law, and apart from the shedding of blood there is no forgiveness. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 9:23">23</verse-number>Therefore <supplied>it was</supplied> necessary <supplied>for</supplied> the sketches of the <supplied>things</supplied> in heaven to be purified with these <supplied>sacrifices</supplied>, but the heavenly <supplied>things</supplied> themselves <supplied>to be purified</supplied> with better sacrifices than these. <verse-number id="Heb 9:24">24</verse-number>For Christ did not enter into a sanctuary made by hands, a <supplied>mere</supplied> copy of the true <supplied>one</supplied>, but into heaven itself, now to appear in the presence of God on our behalf, <verse-number id="Heb 9:25">25</verse-number>and not in order that he can offer himself many times, as the high priest enters into the sanctuary <idiom-start/>year by year<idiom-end/><note>Literally “according to year”</note> with blood not his own, <verse-number id="Heb 9:26">26</verse-number>since it would have been necessary for him to suffer many times from the foundation of the world, but now he has appeared once at the end of the ages for the removal of sin by the sacrifice of himself. <verse-number id="Heb 9:27">27</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>just as<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in as much as”</note> it is destined for people to die once, and after this, judgment, <verse-number id="Heb 9:28">28</verse-number>thus also Christ, having been offered once in order to bear the sins of many, will appear for the second time without reference to sin to those who eagerly await him for salvation. </p>
		</chapter>