<chapter id="Heb 10">
			<pericope>Christ’s One Sacrifice for Sin</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 10:1">1</verse-number> For the law, possessing a shadow of the good <supplied>things</supplied> that are about to come, not the form of things itself, <supplied>is</supplied> never able <idiom-start/>year by year<idiom-end/><note>Literally “according to year”</note> by means of the same sacrifices which they offer without interruption to make perfect those who draw near. <verse-number id="Heb 10:2">2</verse-number>For otherwise, would they not have ceased to be offered, because the ones who worship, having been purified once and for all, would no longer have any consciousness of sins? <verse-number id="Heb 10:3">3</verse-number>But in them <supplied>there is</supplied> a reminder of sins <idiom-start/>year by year<idiom-end/><note>Literally “according to year”</note>. <verse-number id="Heb 10:4">4</verse-number>For <supplied>it is</supplied> impossible <supplied>for</supplied> the blood of bulls and goats to take away sins. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 10:5">5</verse-number>Therefore, <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal participle (“came”)</note> came into the world, he said, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Sacrifice and offering you did not want, </li1>
				<li2>but a body you prepared for me; </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Heb 10:6">6</verse-number>you did not delight in whole burnt offerings and <supplied>offerings</supplied> for sins. </li1>
				<li2><verse-number id="Heb 10:7">7</verse-number>Then I said, ‘Behold, I have come— </li2>
				<li1>in the roll of the book it is written about me— </li1>
				<li2>to do your will, O God.’ </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 10:8">8</verse-number><supplied>When he</supplied> says above, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Sacrifices and offerings and whole burnt offerings and <supplied>offerings</supplied> for sin </li1>
				<li2>you did not want, nor did you delight in,”<note>Various phrases from the quotation of <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 40:6">Ps 40:6 </cite>in <cite title="BibleLEB2: Heb 10:5–6">Heb 10:5–6 </cite>are repeated here</note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p>which are offered according to the law, <verse-number id="Heb 10:9">9</verse-number>then he has said, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Behold, I have come to do your will.”<note>A repetition of <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 40:8">Ps 40:8 </cite>from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Heb 10:7">Heb 10:7; </cite>many later manuscripts add “O God,” making the quotation conform to <cite title="BibleLEB2: Heb 10:7">Heb 10:7 </cite>more closely</note> </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p>He takes away the first in order to establish the second, <verse-number id="Heb 10:10">10</verse-number>by which will we are made holy through the offering of the body of Jesus Christ once for all. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 10:11">11</verse-number>And every priest stands every day serving and offering the same sacrifices many times, which are never able to take away sins. <verse-number id="Heb 10:12">12</verse-number>But this one, <supplied>after he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal participle (“had offered”)</note> had offered one sacrifice for sins for all time, sat down at the right hand of God, <verse-number id="Heb 10:13">13</verse-number>from now on waiting until his enemies are made a footstool for his feet. <verse-number id="Heb 10:14">14</verse-number>For by one offering he has perfected for all time those who are made holy. <verse-number id="Heb 10:15">15</verse-number>And the Holy Spirit also testifies to us, for after saying, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Heb 10:16">16</verse-number>“This <supplied>is</supplied> the covenant that I will decree for them </li1>
				<li2>after those days, says the Lord: </li2>
				<li1>I am putting my laws on their hearts, </li1>
				<li2>and I will write them on their minds.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Je 31:33">Jer 31:33</cite></note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 10:17">17</verse-number><supplied>He</supplied> also <supplied>says</supplied>, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Their sins and their lawless deeds I will never remember again.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Je 31:34">Jer 31:34</cite></note> </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 10:18">18</verse-number>Now where <supplied>there is</supplied> forgiveness of these, <supplied>there is</supplied> no longer an offering for sin. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Hold Fast the Confession of Our Hope</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 10:19">19</verse-number>Therefore, brothers, <supplied>since we</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>since</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“have”) which is understood as causal</note> have confidence for the entrance into the sanctuary by the blood of Jesus, <verse-number id="Heb 10:20">20</verse-number><supplied>by the</supplied> new and living way which he inaugurated for us through the curtain, that is, his flesh, <verse-number id="Heb 10:21">21</verse-number>and <supplied>since we have</supplied><note>These words are an implied repetition from v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Heb 10:19">19</cite> for clarity</note> a great priest over the house of God, <verse-number id="Heb 10:22">22</verse-number>let us approach with a true heart in the full assurance of faith, our hearts sprinkled <supplied>clean</supplied> from an evil conscience and our bodies washed with pure water. <verse-number id="Heb 10:23">23</verse-number>Let us hold fast to the confession of <supplied>our</supplied> hope without wavering, for the one who promised <supplied>is</supplied> faithful. <verse-number id="Heb 10:24">24</verse-number>And let us think about <idiom-start/>how to stir one another up to love<idiom-end/><note>Literally “one another for the stirring up of love”</note> and good works, <verse-number id="Heb 10:25">25</verse-number>not abandoning <idiom-start/>our meeting together<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the meeting of ourselves”</note>, as <supplied>is</supplied> the habit of some, but encouraging <supplied>each other</supplied>, and by so much more as you see the day drawing near. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A Serious Warning Against Continuing Deliberate Sin</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 10:26">26</verse-number>For <supplied>if</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>if</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the conditional genitive absolute participle (“keep on sinning”)</note> we keep on sinning deliberately after receiving the knowledge of the truth, there no longer remains a sacrifice for sins, <verse-number id="Heb 10:27">27</verse-number>but a certain fearful expectation of judgment and a fury of fire that is about to consume the adversaries. <verse-number id="Heb 10:28">28</verse-number>Anyone who rejected the law of Moses dies without mercy on <supplied>the testimony of</supplied> two or three witnesses. <verse-number id="Heb 10:29">29</verse-number>How much worse punishment do you think the person will be considered worthy of who treats with disdain the Son of God and who considers ordinary the blood of the covenant by which he was made holy and who insults the Spirit of grace? <verse-number id="Heb 10:30">30</verse-number>For we know the one who said, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Vengeance <supplied>is</supplied> mine, I will repay,”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Dt 32:35">Deut 32:35</cite></note> </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p>and again, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“The Lord will judge his people.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Dt 32:36">Deut 32:36</cite></note> </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 10:31">31</verse-number><supplied>It is</supplied> a terrifying <supplied>thing</supplied> to fall into the hands of the living God. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 10:32">32</verse-number>But remember the former days in which, <supplied>after you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal participle (“were enlightened”)</note> were enlightened, you endured a great struggle with sufferings, <verse-number id="Heb 10:33">33</verse-number>sometimes being publicly exposed both to insults and to afflictions, and sometimes becoming sharers with those who were treated in this way. <verse-number id="Heb 10:34">34</verse-number>For you both sympathized with the prisoners and put up with the seizure of your belongings with joy <supplied>because you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“knew”) which is understood as causal</note> knew that you yourselves had a better and permanent possession. <verse-number id="Heb 10:35">35</verse-number>Therefore do not throw away your confidence, which has great reward. <verse-number id="Heb 10:36">36</verse-number>For you have need of endurance, in order that <supplied>after you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal participle (“have done”)</note> have done the will of God, you may receive what was promised. <verse-number id="Heb 10:37">37</verse-number>For yet </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“a very, very little <supplied>while</supplied>, </li1>
				<li2><supplied>and</supplied> the one who is coming will come and will not delay. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Heb 10:38">38</verse-number>But my righteous one will live by faith, </li1>
				<li2>and if he shrinks back, my soul is not well pleased with him.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Hab 2:3–4">Hab 2:3–4</cite></note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 10:39">39</verse-number>But we are not among those who shrink back to destruction, but among those who have faith to the preservation of <supplied>our</supplied> souls. </p>
		</chapter>