<chapter id="Heb 11">
			<pericope>Examples of Faith in Action</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 11:1">1</verse-number> Now faith is the realization of what is hoped for, the proof of things not seen. <verse-number id="Heb 11:2">2</verse-number>For by this the people of old were approved. <verse-number id="Heb 11:3">3</verse-number>By faith we understand the worlds were created by the word of God, in order that what is seen did not come into existence from what is visible. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 11:4">4</verse-number>By faith Abel offered to God a greater sacrifice than Cain, by which he was approved that he was righteous, <supplied>because</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal participle (“was”)</note> God approved <supplied>him</supplied> for his gifts, and through it<note>I.e., his faith</note> he still speaks, <supplied>although he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>although</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“is dead”) which is understood as concessive</note> is dead. <verse-number id="Heb 11:5">5</verse-number>By faith Enoch was taken up, so that he did not experience death, and he was not found, because God took him up. For before his removal, he had been approved <idiom-start/>as having been pleasing<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to be pleasing”</note> to God. <verse-number id="Heb 11:6">6</verse-number>Now without faith <supplied>it is</supplied> impossible to please <supplied>him</supplied>, for the one who approaches God must believe that he exists and is a rewarder of those who seek him. <verse-number id="Heb 11:7">7</verse-number>By faith Noah, having been warned about things not yet seen, out of reverence constructed an ark for the deliverance of his family, by which he pronounced sentence on the world and became an heir of the righteousness that comes by faith. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 11:8">8</verse-number>By faith Abraham, <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal participle (“was called”)</note> was called, obeyed to go out to a place that he was going to receive for an inheritance, and he went out, not knowing where he was going. <verse-number id="Heb 11:9">9</verse-number>By faith he lived in the land of promise as a stranger, living in tents with Isaac and Jacob, the fellow heirs of the same promise. <verse-number id="Heb 11:10">10</verse-number>For he was expecting the city that has foundations, whose architect and builder <supplied>is</supplied> God. <verse-number id="Heb 11:11">11</verse-number>By faith also, <idiom-start/>with Sarah<idiom-end/><note>Literally “with her, Sarah”</note>,<note>Some manuscripts have “even though Sarah herself was barren”</note> he received <idiom-start/>the ability to procreate<idiom-end/><note>Literally “power to deposit seed”</note> even <idiom-start/>past the normal age<idiom-end/><note>Literally “beyond the time of maturity”</note>, because he regarded the one who had promised <supplied>to be</supplied> faithful. <verse-number id="Heb 11:12">12</verse-number>And therefore these were fathered from one man, and <supplied>he</supplied> being as good as dead, as the stars of heaven in number and like the innumerable sand by the shore of the sea. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 11:13">13</verse-number>These all died in faith without receiving the promises, but seeing them from a distance and welcoming <supplied>them</supplied>, and admitting that they were strangers and temporary residents on the earth. <verse-number id="Heb 11:14">14</verse-number>For those who say such <supplied>things</supplied> make clear that they are seeking a homeland. <verse-number id="Heb 11:15">15</verse-number>And if they remember<note>Some manuscripts have “they had been remembering”</note> that <supplied>land</supplied> from which they went out, they would have had opportunity to return. <verse-number id="Heb 11:16">16</verse-number>But now they aspire to a better <supplied>land</supplied>, that is, a heavenly <supplied>one</supplied>. Therefore God is not ashamed of them, to be called their God, for he has prepared for them a city. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 11:17">17</verse-number>By faith Abraham, <supplied>when he</supplied> was tested, offered Isaac, and the one who received the promises was ready to offer his one and only <supplied>son</supplied>, <verse-number id="Heb 11:18">18</verse-number>with reference to whom it was said, “In Isaac your descendants will be named,”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ge 21:12">Gen 21:12</cite></note> <verse-number id="Heb 11:19">19</verse-number>having reasoned that God <supplied>was</supplied> able even to raise <supplied>him</supplied> from the dead, from which he received him back also as a symbol. <verse-number id="Heb 11:20">20</verse-number>By faith also Isaac blessed Jacob and Esau concerning things that were going to happen. <verse-number id="Heb 11:21">21</verse-number>By faith Jacob, <supplied>as he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal participle (“was dying”)</note> was dying, blessed each of the sons of Joseph and worshiped, <supplied>leaning</supplied> on the top of his staff. <verse-number id="Heb 11:22">22</verse-number>By faith Joseph, <supplied>as he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal participle (“was dying”)</note> was dying, mentioned about the exodus of the sons of Israel and gave instructions about his bones. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 11:23">23</verse-number>By faith Moses, <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal participle (“afraid of”)</note> was born, was hidden for three months by his parents, because they saw the child <supplied>was</supplied> handsome, and they were not afraid of the edict of the king. <verse-number id="Heb 11:24">24</verse-number>By faith Moses, <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal participle (“was”)</note> was grown up, refused to be called the son of Pharaoh’s daughter, <verse-number id="Heb 11:25">25</verse-number>choosing instead to be mistreated with the people of God <supplied>rather</supplied> than to experience the transitory enjoyment of sin, <verse-number id="Heb 11:26">26</verse-number>considering <idiom-start/>reproach endured for the sake of Christ<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the reproach of Christ”</note> greater wealth than the treasures of Egypt, for he was looking to the reward. <verse-number id="Heb 11:27">27</verse-number>By faith he left Egypt, not fearing the anger of the king, for he persevered as <supplied>if he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>if</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as conditional</note> saw the invisible one. <verse-number id="Heb 11:28">28</verse-number>By faith he kept the Passover and the sprinkling of blood, in order that the one who destroyed the firstborn would not touch them. <verse-number id="Heb 11:29">29</verse-number>By faith they crossed the Red Sea as if on dry land; the Egyptians, <idiom-start/>when they made the attempt<idiom-end/><note>Literally “of which attempt making”</note>, were drowned. <verse-number id="Heb 11:30">30</verse-number>By faith the walls of Jericho fell down <supplied>after they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal participle (“had been marched around”)</note> had been marched around for seven days. <verse-number id="Heb 11:31">31</verse-number>By faith Rahab the prostitute did not perish with those who were disobedient, <supplied>because she</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“welcomed”) which is understood as causal</note> welcomed the spies in peace. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 11:32">32</verse-number>And what more shall I say? For time would fail me to tell about Gideon, Barak, Samson, Jephthah, David, and Samuel and the prophets, <verse-number id="Heb 11:33">33</verse-number>who through faith conquered kingdoms, accomplished justice, obtained what was promised, shut the mouths of lions, <verse-number id="Heb 11:34">34</verse-number>extinguished the effectiveness of fire, escaped the edge of the sword, were made strong from weakness, became mighty in battle, put to flight enemy battle lines. <verse-number id="Heb 11:35">35</verse-number>Women received back their dead by resurrection. But others were tortured, not accepting release, in order that they might gain a better resurrection. <verse-number id="Heb 11:36">36</verse-number>And others <idiom-start/>experienced mocking and flogging<idiom-end/><note>Literally “received experience of mocking and flogging”</note>, and in addition bonds and imprisonment. <verse-number id="Heb 11:37">37</verse-number>They were stoned, they were sawed in two, they died by murder with a sword, they wandered about in sheepskins, in goatskins, impoverished, afflicted, mistreated, <verse-number id="Heb 11:38">38</verse-number>of whom the world was not worthy, wandering about on deserts and mountains and in caves and in holes in the ground. <verse-number id="Heb 11:39">39</verse-number>And <supplied>although they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>although</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“were approved”) which is understood as concessive</note> all were approved<note>Some manuscripts have “And all these, <supplied>although they</supplied> were approved”</note> through their faith, they did not receive what was promised, <verse-number id="Heb 11:40">40</verse-number><supplied>because</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the causal genitive absolute participle (“had provided”)</note> God had provided something better for us, so that they would not be made perfect without us. </p>
		</chapter>