<chapter id="Heb 12">
			<pericope>The Example of Jesus’ Suffering</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 12:1">1</verse-number> Therefore, <supplied>since</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>since</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“have”) which is understood as causal</note> we also have such a great cloud of witnesses surrounding us, putting aside every weight and <idiom-start/>the sin that so easily ensnares us<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the easily ensnaring sin”</note>, let us run with patient endurance the race that has been set before us, <verse-number id="Heb 12:2">2</verse-number>fixing our eyes on Jesus, the originator and perfecter of faith, who for the joy that was set before him endured the cross, disregarding the shame, and has sat down at the right hand of the throne of God. <verse-number id="Heb 12:3">3</verse-number>For consider the one who endured such hostility by sinners against himself,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The plural reflexive pronoun can still be translated as singular; see Louw-Nida 92.25</note> so that you will not grow weary in your souls <supplied>and</supplied> give up. <verse-number id="Heb 12:4">4</verse-number>You have not yet resisted to the point of <supplied>shedding your</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The words “shedding your” are not in the Greek text but are supplied for clarity</note> blood <supplied>as you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal participle (“struggle”)</note> struggle against sin. <verse-number id="Heb 12:5">5</verse-number>And have you completely forgotten the exhortation which instructs you as sons? </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“My son, do not make light of the Lord’s discipline, </li1>
				<li2>or give up <supplied>when you</supplied> are corrected by him. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Heb 12:6">6</verse-number>For the Lord disciplines the one whom he loves, </li1>
				<li2>and punishes every son whom he accepts.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Pr 3:11–12">Prov 3:11–12</cite></note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 12:7">7</verse-number>Endure <supplied>it</supplied> for discipline. God is dealing with you as sons. For what son <supplied>is there</supplied> whom a father does not discipline? <verse-number id="Heb 12:8">8</verse-number>But if you are without discipline, in which all <supplied>legitimate sons</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The phrase “legitimate sons” is not in the Greek text but is implied</note> have become participants, then you are illegitimate and not sons. <verse-number id="Heb 12:9">9</verse-number>Furthermore, we have had <idiom-start/>our earthly fathers<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the flesh of our fathers”</note> who disciplined <supplied>us</supplied>, and we respected <supplied>them</supplied>. Will we not much rather subject ourselves to the Father of spirits and live? <verse-number id="Heb 12:10">10</verse-number>For they disciplined <supplied>us</supplied> for a few days according to what seemed <supplied>appropriate</supplied> to them, but he <supplied>does so</supplied> for our benefit, in order that <supplied>we</supplied> can have a share in his holiness. <verse-number id="Heb 12:11">11</verse-number>Now all discipline seems for the moment not to be joyful but painful, but later it yields the peaceful fruit of righteousness for those who are trained by it. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A Serious Warning Against Refusing God</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 12:12">12</verse-number>Therefore strengthen your slackened hands and your weakened knees, <verse-number id="Heb 12:13">13</verse-number>and make straight paths for your feet, so that what is lame will not be dislocated, but rather be healed. <verse-number id="Heb 12:14">14</verse-number>Pursue peace with everyone, and holiness, without which no one will see the Lord. <verse-number id="Heb 12:15">15</verse-number>Take care <supplied>that</supplied> no one falls short of the grace of God; <supplied>that</supplied> no one growing up <supplied>like</supplied> a root of bitterness causes trouble, and by it many become defiled; <verse-number id="Heb 12:16">16</verse-number><supplied>that</supplied> no one <supplied>be</supplied> a sexually immoral or totally worldly <supplied>person</supplied> like Esau, who for one meal traded his own birthright. <verse-number id="Heb 12:17">17</verse-number>For you know that also afterwards, <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal participle (“wanted”)</note> wanted to inherit the blessing, he was rejected, because he did not find an occasion for repentance, although he sought it with tears. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 12:18">18</verse-number>For you have not come to something that can be touched, and to a burning fire, and to darkness, and to gloom, and to a whirlwind, <verse-number id="Heb 12:19">19</verse-number>and to the noise of a trumpet, and to the sound of words which those who heard begged <supplied>that</supplied> not <supplied>another</supplied> word be spoken to them. <verse-number id="Heb 12:20">20</verse-number>For they could not endure what was commanded: “If even an animal touches the mountain, it must be stoned.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ex 19:12–13">Exod 19:12–13</cite></note> <verse-number id="Heb 12:21">21</verse-number>And the spectacle was so terrifying <supplied>that</supplied> Moses said, “I am terrified and trembling.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Dt 9:19">Deut 9:19</cite></note> <verse-number id="Heb 12:22">22</verse-number>But you have come to Mount Zion, and to the city of the living God, to the heavenly Jerusalem, and to tens of thousands of angels, to the festal gathering <verse-number id="Heb 12:23">23</verse-number>and assembly of the firstborn who are enrolled in heaven, and to God the judge of all, and to the spirits of righteous <supplied>people</supplied> made perfect, <verse-number id="Heb 12:24">24</verse-number>and to Jesus, the mediator of a new covenant, and <idiom-start/>to the sprinkled blood<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the blood of sprinkling”</note> that speaks better than Abel’s <supplied>does</supplied>. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 12:25">25</verse-number>Watch out that you do not refuse the one who is speaking! For if those did not escape <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal participle (“refused”)</note> refused the one who warned <supplied>them</supplied> on earth, much less <supplied>will</supplied> we <supplied>escape</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the verb “will … escape” is an understood repetition from the previous clause</note> <supplied>if we</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>if</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“reject”) which is understood as conditional</note> reject the <supplied>one who warns</supplied> from heaven, <verse-number id="Heb 12:26">26</verse-number>whose voice shook the earth at that time, but now he has promised, saying, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Yet once <supplied>more</supplied> I will shake not only the earth but also heaven.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Hag 2:6">Hag 2:6</cite></note> </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 12:27">27</verse-number>Now the <supplied>phrase</supplied> “yet once <supplied>more</supplied>” indicates the removal of what is shaken, namely, things that have been created, in order that the things that are not shaken may remain. <verse-number id="Heb 12:28">28</verse-number>Therefore, <supplied>since we</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>since</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“are receiving”) which is understood as causal</note> are receiving an unshakable kingdom, let us be thankful, through which let us serve God acceptably, with awe and reverence. <verse-number id="Heb 12:29">29</verse-number>For indeed our God <supplied>is</supplied> a consuming fire. </p>
		</chapter>