<chapter id="Heb 13">
			<pericope>Concluding Ethical Instructions</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 13:1">1</verse-number> Brotherly love must continue. <verse-number id="Heb 13:2">2</verse-number>Do not neglect hospitality, because through this some have received angels as guests without knowing <supplied>it</supplied>. <verse-number id="Heb 13:3">3</verse-number>Remember the prisoners, as <supplied>though you were</supplied> fellow-prisoners; <supplied>remember</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*This is an understood repetition of the verb from the previous clause</note> the mistreated, as <supplied>though</supplied> <supplied>you</supplied> yourselves also are being <supplied>mistreated</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*This is an understood repetition of the participle from the previous clause</note> in the body. <verse-number id="Heb 13:4">4</verse-number>Marriage <supplied>must be</supplied> held in honor by all, and the marriage bed <supplied>be</supplied> undefiled, because God will judge sexually immoral people and adulterers. <verse-number id="Heb 13:5">5</verse-number>Your lifestyle <supplied>must be</supplied> free from the love of money, being content with what you have. For he himself has said, “I will never desert you, and I will never abandon you.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Dt 31:6">Deut 31:6</cite>, <cite title="BibleLEB2: Dt 31:8">8</cite></note> <verse-number id="Heb 13:6">6</verse-number>So then, we can say with confidence, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“The Lord <supplied>is</supplied> my helper, I will not be afraid.<note>Some manuscripts have “and I will not be afraid”</note> </li1>
				<li1>What will man do to me?”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 118:6">Ps 118:6</cite></note> </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 13:7">7</verse-number>Remember your leaders, who spoke the word of God to you; <idiom-start/>considering the outcome of their way of life<idiom-end/><note>Literally “of whom considering the outcome of the way of life”</note>, imitate their faith. <verse-number id="Heb 13:8">8</verse-number>Jesus Christ <supplied>is</supplied> the same yesterday and today and <idiom-start/>forever<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the ages”</note>. <verse-number id="Heb 13:9">9</verse-number>Do not be carried away by various and strange teachings, for <supplied>it is</supplied> good <supplied>for</supplied> the heart to be strengthened by grace, not by foods by which those who participate have not benefited. <verse-number id="Heb 13:10">10</verse-number>We have an altar from which those who serve in the tabernacle do not have the right to eat. <verse-number id="Heb 13:11">11</verse-number>For the bodies of those animals whose blood is brought into the sanctuary by the high priest for sins are burned up outside the camp. <verse-number id="Heb 13:12">12</verse-number>Therefore Jesus also suffered outside the gate, in order that he might sanctify the people by his own blood. <verse-number id="Heb 13:13">13</verse-number>So we must go out to him outside the camp, bearing his reproach. <verse-number id="Heb 13:14">14</verse-number>For here we do not have a permanent city, but we seek the <supplied>city</supplied> that is to come. <verse-number id="Heb 13:15">15</verse-number>Therefore through him let us offer up a sacrifice of praise <idiom-start/>continually<idiom-end/><note>Literally “through all”</note> to God, that is, the fruit of lips that confess his name. <verse-number id="Heb 13:16">16</verse-number>And do not neglect doing good and generosity, for God is pleased with such sacrifices. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 13:17">17</verse-number>Obey your leaders and submit <supplied>to them</supplied>, for they keep watch over your souls as those who will give an account, so that they can do this with joy and not <supplied>with</supplied> groaning, for this <supplied>would be</supplied> unprofitable for you. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 13:18">18</verse-number>Pray for us, for we are convinced that we have a good conscience, <supplied>and</supplied> want to conduct ourselves commendably in every <supplied>way</supplied>. <verse-number id="Heb 13:19">19</verse-number>And I especially urge <supplied>you</supplied> to do this, so that I may be restored to you more quickly. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Benediction</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 13:20">20</verse-number>Now may the God of peace, who brought up from the dead our Lord Jesus, the great shepherd of the sheep, by the blood of the eternal covenant, <verse-number id="Heb 13:21">21</verse-number>equip you with every good <supplied>thing</supplied> to do his will, carrying out in us <supplied>what is</supplied> pleasing before him through Jesus Christ, to whom <supplied>be</supplied> the glory <idiom-start/>forever<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the ages”</note>.<note>Some manuscripts have “forever and ever” (literally, “to the ages of the ages”)</note> Amen. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Conclusion</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Heb 13:22">22</verse-number>Now I urge you, brothers, bear with my word of exhortation, for indeed I have written to you <idiom-start/>briefly<idiom-end/><note>Literally “through few words”</note>. <verse-number id="Heb 13:23">23</verse-number>Know <supplied>that</supplied> our brother Timothy has been released, with whom I will see you, if he comes quickly <supplied>enough</supplied>. <verse-number id="Heb 13:24">24</verse-number>Greet all your leaders and all the saints. Those from Italy greet you. <verse-number id="Heb 13:25">25</verse-number>Grace <supplied>be</supplied> with all of you. </p>
		</chapter>