<chapter id="1 Sa 3">
			<pericope>Samuel’s First Encounter with Yahweh</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 3:1">1</verse-number>Now the boy Samuel was serving Yahweh <idiom-start/>in the presence<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the face of”</note> of Eli. The word of Yahweh was rare in those days; visions were not widespread. <verse-number id="1 Sa 3:2">2</verse-number><idiom-start/>And then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And it happened”</note> one day when Eli was lying in his place (now his eyes had begun <supplied>to grow</supplied> weak so that he was not able to see) <verse-number id="1 Sa 3:3">3</verse-number>and the lamp of God had not yet gone out, Samuel was lying in the temple<note>Although the Hebrew text reads “temple,” this is a reference to the tabernacle (see 1:3, 9)</note> of Yahweh where the ark of God <supplied>was</supplied>. <verse-number id="1 Sa 3:4">4</verse-number>Then Yahweh called out to Samuel and he said, “Here I am!” <verse-number id="1 Sa 3:5">5</verse-number>And he ran to Eli and said, “Here I am, because you called me.” But he said, “I did not call <supplied>you</supplied>. Go back and lie down.” So he went and lay down. <verse-number id="1 Sa 3:6">6</verse-number>And Yahweh called Samuel again, so Samuel got up and went to Eli and said, “Here I am, because you called me.” And he said, “I did not call you, my son. Go back <supplied>and</supplied> lie down.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 3:7">7</verse-number>Now Samuel did not yet know Yahweh, and the word of Yahweh had not yet been revealed to him. <verse-number id="1 Sa 3:8">8</verse-number>Again Yahweh called Samuel a third time, so he got up and went to Eli and said, “Here I am, because you called me.” Then Eli realized that Yahweh was calling the boy. <verse-number id="1 Sa 3:9">9</verse-number>So Eli said to Samuel “Go lie down. <idiom-start/>If he calls<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And it will happen <supplied>that</supplied> if he calls”</note> to you, then you must say, ‘Speak Yahweh, because your servant <supplied>is</supplied> listening.’ ” So Samuel went and lay down in his place. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 3:10">10</verse-number>Then Yahweh came and stood <supplied>there</supplied> and called out <idiom-start/>as before<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “as an occurrence, in an occurrence”</note> “Samuel! Samuel!” And Samuel said, “Speak, because your servant <supplied>is</supplied> listening.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 3:11">11</verse-number>So Yahweh said to Samuel, “Look, I am doing something in Israel <idiom-start/>which will cause<idiom-end/><note>Literally “about which”</note> the two ears of everyone who hears it to tingle. <verse-number id="1 Sa 3:12">12</verse-number>On that day I will fulfill against Eli all that I have spoken against his household, <idiom-start/>from beginning to end<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “begin and finish”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 3:13">13</verse-number>I will make him know that I am about to judge his household forever because of the iniquity that he knew, for his sons <supplied>were</supplied> bringing curses on themselves,<note>LXX reads “were cursing God”</note> but he did not rebuke them. <verse-number id="1 Sa 3:14">14</verse-number>Therefore I swore to the house of Eli <supplied>that</supplied> the iniquity of the house of Eli would not be atoned for<note>Or “be expiated”</note> by sacrifice or by offering forever.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 3:15">15</verse-number>So Samuel lay down until morning; then he opened the doors of the house of Yahweh, but Samuel was afraid of telling the vision to Eli. <verse-number id="1 Sa 3:16">16</verse-number>Then Eli called Samuel and said, “Samuel, my son!” And he said, “Here I am.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 3:17">17</verse-number>And he said, “What <supplied>is</supplied> the message<note>Or “word”</note> that he spoke to you? Please do not conceal <supplied>it</supplied> from me. May God <idiom-start/>punish you severely<idiom-end/><note>Literally “do to you and so may he add”</note> if you conceal anything from me of all the words that he told you.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 3:18">18</verse-number>So Samuel told him all the words and did not conceal <supplied>anything</supplied> from him. And he<note>That is, Eli</note> said, “He <supplied>is</supplied> Yahweh, he will do <idiom-start/>what is<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the”</note> good in his <idiom-start/>sight<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “eyes”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 3:19">19</verse-number>And Samuel grew up, and Yahweh was with him. <idiom-start/>He did not allow any of his prophecies to go unfulfilled<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “He let none from all of his words fall to the ground.”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 3:20">20</verse-number>All Israel from Dan to Beersheba realized that Samuel was faithful<note>Or “reliable” or “trustworthy”</note> as a prophet to Yahweh. <verse-number id="1 Sa 3:21">21</verse-number>And Yahweh appeared again in Shiloh, for Yahweh revealed himself to Samuel in Shiloh through the word of Yahweh. </p>
		</chapter>