<chapter id="1 Sa 4">
			<pericope>The Battle of Aphek</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 4:1">1</verse-number>And the word of Samuel came to all Israel. Now Israel went out to meet <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines for battle, and they encamped at Ebenezer, and <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines encamped at Aphek. <verse-number id="1 Sa 4:2">2</verse-number><supplied>The</supplied> Philistines lined up for the battle to meet Israel, and the battle was prolonged<note>Or “drawn out”</note> until Israel was defeated before <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines, <idiom-start/>who<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and they”</note> killed about four thousand men <idiom-start/>on the battlefield<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “in the battle line in the field”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 4:3">3</verse-number>When the army<note>Or “people”</note> came <supplied>back</supplied> to the camp, the elders of Israel asked, “Why has Yahweh defeated us today before <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines? Let us bring the ark of the covenant of Yahweh to us from Shiloh so that it may come into our midst and deliver<note>Or “save”</note> us from the hand of our enemies.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 4:4">4</verse-number>So the army sent to Shiloh and brought from there the ark of the covenant of Yahweh of hosts who sits <supplied>between</supplied> the cherubim. And the two sons of Eli, Hophni and Phinehas, <supplied>were</supplied> there with the ark of the covenant of God. <verse-number id="1 Sa 4:5">5</verse-number>Now when the ark of the covenant of Yahweh arrived at the camp, all Israel <idiom-start/>let out a loud shout<idiom-end/><note>Literally “shouted a great shout”</note> so that the earth shook. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 4:6">6</verse-number>When <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines heard the noise of the shouting, they said, “What <supplied>is</supplied> the noise of this loud shouting in the camp of the Hebrews?” Then they learned that the ark of Yahweh had come into the camp. <verse-number id="1 Sa 4:7">7</verse-number>So <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines were afraid, for they said, “God has come<note>Or “gods have come”</note> to the camp.” And they said, “Woe to us, <idiom-start/>for this has never happened before!<idiom-end/><note>Literally “it has not happened like this since yesterday and since the day before that”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 4:8">8</verse-number>Woe to us! Who can deliver us from the hand of these mighty gods? These <supplied>are</supplied> the <supplied>same</supplied> gods who struck the Egyptians with all <supplied>sorts of</supplied> plagues in the desert. <verse-number id="1 Sa 4:9">9</verse-number>Take courage and be men, <supplied>you</supplied> Philistines, lest you end up serving the Hebrews just like they have served you. Be men and fight!” <verse-number id="1 Sa 4:10">10</verse-number>So <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines fought and Israel was defeated and each man fled to his tent, for the slaughter was very great. Thirty thousand foot soldiers from Israel fell. <verse-number id="1 Sa 4:11">11</verse-number>Furthermore, the ark of God was captured,<note>Or “taken”</note> and the two sons of Eli, Hophni and Phinehas, died. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 4:12">12</verse-number>A man of Benjamin ran from the battle line and came <supplied>to</supplied> Shiloh that same day, and his clothes <supplied>were</supplied> torn and earth <supplied>was</supplied> on his head. <verse-number id="1 Sa 4:13">13</verse-number>When he came, <idiom-start/>there was<idiom-end/><note>Literally “look”</note> Eli sitting on his chair <idiom-start/>by the side of the road<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<supplied>by</supplied> the hand of <supplied>the</supplied> road”</note> watching, because his heart was anxious about the ark of God. Now the man had come <idiom-start/>to give his report<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to tell”</note> in the city, and all the city cried out. <verse-number id="1 Sa 4:14">14</verse-number>When Eli heard the noise of the outcry, he said, “What <supplied>is</supplied> the noise of this commotion?” Then the man <idiom-start/>came quickly<idiom-end/><note>Literally “hastened and came”</note> and told Eli. <verse-number id="1 Sa 4:15">15</verse-number>Now Eli <supplied>was</supplied> <idiom-start/>ninety-eight years old<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a son of ninety and eight years”</note> and his eyes <idiom-start/>stayed fixed ahead<idiom-end/><note>Literally “were standing”</note> and he was not able to see. <verse-number id="1 Sa 4:16">16</verse-number>And the man said to Eli, “I am the <supplied>one</supplied> who has come from the battle line! I have fled today from the battle line!” And he said, “<idiom-start/>What exactly happened<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “what <supplied>is</supplied> the thing/matter”</note> my son?” <verse-number id="1 Sa 4:17">17</verse-number>Then the messenger answered and said, “Israel has fled before <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines. There has been a great defeat among the troops. Also, your two sons have died, Hophni and Phinehas, and the ark of God has been captured.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 4:18">18</verse-number>Just as he mentioned the ark of God, he<note>That is, Eli</note> fell from his chair backwards against the side of the gate. He broke his neck and died, because the man was old and heavy. He had judged Israel forty years. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 4:19">19</verse-number>Now his daughter-in-law, the wife of Phinehas, <supplied>was</supplied> pregnant and <supplied>about</supplied> to give birth. When she heard the news concerning the capture of the ark of God and that her father-in-law and her husband had died, she <idiom-start/>went into labor<idiom-end/><note>Literally “bowed down”</note> and gave birth, because her labor pains came upon her. <verse-number id="1 Sa 4:20">20</verse-number>Just before the time of her death, those <idiom-start/>attending her<idiom-end/><note>Literally “standing over her”</note> said, “Do not fear, for you have given birth to a son.” But she did not answer, or <idiom-start/>pay any attention<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “set her heart”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 4:21">21</verse-number>She called the boy Ichabod,<note>The name “Ichabod” means “no glory”</note> saying, “The glory has departed from Israel,” referring to the capture of the ark of God and concerning her father-in-law and husband. <verse-number id="1 Sa 4:22">22</verse-number>And she said, “The glory has departed from Israel, because the ark of God was captured.”<note>Or “taken”</note> </p>
		</chapter>