<chapter id="1 Sa 6">
			<pericope>The Return of the Ark of Covenant</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 6:1">1</verse-number>Now the ark of Yahweh had been in the territory of <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines <supplied>for</supplied> seven months, <verse-number id="1 Sa 6:2">2</verse-number>and <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines called to the priests and to those who practiced divination, saying, “What should we do with the ark of Yahweh? Inform us how we should send it to its place.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 6:3">3</verse-number>They said, “If you <supplied>are</supplied> sending the ark of the God of Israel away, you must not send it away empty, but by all means return it with a guilt offering. Then you will be healed and it will become known to you why his hand <supplied>is</supplied> not turned aside from you.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 6:4">4</verse-number>And they said, “What <supplied>is</supplied> the guilt offering that we should return to him?” They said, “The number of the rulers of <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines <supplied>is</supplied> five. Therefore send five gold tumors<note>The Masoretic Hebrew text (<i>Kethib</i>) reads “boils”; the reading tradition (<i>Qere)</i> has “tumors”</note> and five gold mice, because one plague <supplied>was</supplied> on all of you and all your rulers. <verse-number id="1 Sa 6:5">5</verse-number>You must make images of your tumors<note>The Masoretic Hebrew text (<i>Kethib</i>) reads “boils”; the reading tradition (<i>Qere)</i> has “tumors”</note> and images of your mice that <supplied>are</supplied> ravaging the land, and you must give glory to the God of Israel. Perhaps he will lighten his hand on you and on your gods and on your land. <verse-number id="1 Sa 6:6">6</verse-number>Why should you harden your hearts like <supplied>the</supplied> Egyptians and Pharaoh hardened their heart? Is it not just like when he dealt with them wantonly so that they sent them away and they left? <verse-number id="1 Sa 6:7">7</verse-number>So then, <idiom-start/>prepare<idiom-end/><note>Literally “take and make”</note> one new utility cart and two milking cows that have never had a yoke on them, and you must harness the cows to the utility cart and then turn their calves from following them to their stall. <verse-number id="1 Sa 6:8">8</verse-number>And you must take the ark of Yahweh and place it on the utility cart with the gold objects that you <supplied>are</supplied> returning to him as a guilt offering. You must place <supplied>them</supplied> in the container<note>Or perhaps “chest” or “bag”</note> beside <supplied>the ark</supplied> and then send it <supplied>off</supplied> so that it goes away. <verse-number id="1 Sa 6:9">9</verse-number>You must watch; if it goes up by the way of its territory to Beth Shemesh, he has caused this great disaster to <supplied>come on</supplied> us. But if not, then we will know his hand has not struck us; it <supplied>was by</supplied> chance <supplied>that</supplied> this happened to us. <verse-number id="1 Sa 6:10">10</verse-number>So the men did so; they took two milking cows and harnessed them to the utility cart, but they shut up their calves in the stall. <verse-number id="1 Sa 6:11">11</verse-number>Then they put the ark of Yahweh on the utility cart with the container<note>Or perhaps “chest” or “bag”</note> <supplied>holding</supplied> the gold mice and the images of their tumors. <verse-number id="1 Sa 6:12">12</verse-number>The cows went straight on the way on the road to Beth Shemesh, on the one main road, <idiom-start/>lowing as they went<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “they went going and lowing”</note> They did not turn aside to the right or to the left, and the rulers of <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines <supplied>were</supplied> walking after them up to the border of Beth Shemesh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 6:13">13</verse-number>Now <supplied>the people of</supplied> Beth Shemesh <supplied>were</supplied> reaping the wheat harvest in the valley. They lifted their eyes and saw the ark, and they were glad to see <supplied>it</supplied>. <verse-number id="1 Sa 6:14">14</verse-number>The utility cart came to the field of Joshua <supplied>of</supplied> Beth Shemesh and stopped there where there <supplied>was</supplied> a large stone. They split the wood of the utility cart and sacrificed the cows <supplied>as</supplied> a burnt offering to Yahweh. <verse-number id="1 Sa 6:15">15</verse-number>Then the Levites took down the ark of Yahweh and the container<note>Or perhaps “chest” or “bag”</note> that was beside it, in which <supplied>were</supplied> the gold objects, and <supplied>they</supplied> set them on the large stone.<note>The Masoretic Hebrew text reads “Abel” here; some Hebrew manuscripts and LXX read “stone” (see 6:14–15)</note> Then the men of Beth Shemesh offered burnt offerings, and they <idiom-start/>made<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sacrificed”</note> sacrifices to Yahweh on that day. <verse-number id="1 Sa 6:16">16</verse-number>The five rulers of <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines saw <supplied>it</supplied> and returned <supplied>to</supplied> Ekron that <supplied>same</supplied> day. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 6:17">17</verse-number>Now these <supplied>are</supplied> the gold tumors which <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines returned <supplied>as</supplied> a guilt offering to Yahweh: one for Ashdod, one for Gaza, one for Ashkelon, one for Gath, one for Ekron. <verse-number id="1 Sa 6:18">18</verse-number>And the gold mice <supplied>according to</supplied> the number of all the cities of <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines, for their five rulers, from <supplied>the</supplied> fortified city to the unwalled village of the open country as far as the great stone, <idiom-start/>where they set<idiom-end/><note>Literally “which they set down on it”</note> the ark of Yahweh until this day in the field of Joshua <supplied>of</supplied> Beth Shemesh. <verse-number id="1 Sa 6:19">19</verse-number>He<note>That is, Yahweh</note> struck seventy men<note>Though the MT has “seventy men, fifty thousand men” (= 50,070), it is likely the original was “seventy men”</note> among the men of Beth Shemesh because they looked into the ark of Yahweh. So the people mourned because Yahweh had struck a great blow among the people. <verse-number id="1 Sa 6:20">20</verse-number>Then the men of Beth Shemesh asked, “Who <supplied>is</supplied> able to stand before Yahweh, this holy God? And to whom shall it<note>That is, the ark of the covenant (alternatively read as “he,” referring to Yahweh)</note> go up from us?” <verse-number id="1 Sa 6:21">21</verse-number>So they sent messengers to the inhabitants of Kiriath Jearim saying, “<supplied>The</supplied> Philistines have returned the ark of Yahweh. Come down and take it up to yourselves.” </p>
		</chapter>