<chapter id="1 Sa 7">
			<pericope>Revival and Victory at Mizpah</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 7:1">1</verse-number>The men of Kiriath Jearim came and brought up the ark of Yahweh, and they brought it to the house of Abinadab in Gibeah. They consecrated Eleazer his son to guard the ark of Yahweh. <verse-number id="1 Sa 7:2">2</verse-number><idiom-start/>From<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And it happened from”</note> the day the ark stayed in Kiriath Jearim, <idiom-start/>days multiplied and became twenty years<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and the days were numerous, and they were twenty years”</note> while all the house of Israel mourned after Yahweh. <verse-number id="1 Sa 7:3">3</verse-number>And Samuel spoke to all the house of Israel, saying, “If with all your heart you <supplied>are</supplied> turning to Yahweh, remove the foreign gods and Ashtoreths<note>Hebrew plural “Ashtaroth” (Ashtoreth was the female consort of Ba’al)</note> from your midst. Commit your hearts to Yahweh and serve him alone. Then he will deliver you from the hand of <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 7:4">4</verse-number>So the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> removed the Baals<note>Hebrew plural “Be’alim” (Ba’al was a major Canaanite deity)</note> and the Ashtoreths, and they served Yahweh alone. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 7:5">5</verse-number>Then Samuel said, “Gather all Israel to Mizpah, and I will pray to Yahweh for you.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 7:6">6</verse-number>So they gathered to Mizpah and drew water and poured <supplied>it</supplied> out before Yahweh. They fasted on that day and said there, “We have sinned against Yahweh!” So Samuel judged the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> at Mizpah. <verse-number id="1 Sa 7:7">7</verse-number><supplied>Now</supplied> when <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines heard that the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> had gathered at Mizpah, the rulers of the Philistines went up against Israel. And when the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> heard <supplied>of it</supplied>, <idiom-start/>they were afraid of the Philistines<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “and they were afraid from (= because of) the presence of the Philistines”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 7:8">8</verse-number>Then the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> said to Samuel, “<idiom-start/>You must not cease<idiom-end/><note>Literally “You must not be silent from us”</note> from crying out to Yahweh our God, so that he will deliver us from the hand of <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 7:9">9</verse-number>So Samuel took a single <idiom-start/>nursing lamb<idiom-end/><note>Literally “lamb of milk”</note> and sacrificed <supplied>it</supplied> as a whole burnt offering to Yahweh. Then Samuel cried out to Yahweh on behalf of Israel, and Yahweh answered him. <verse-number id="1 Sa 7:10">10</verse-number><idiom-start/>While<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And it happened”</note> Samuel <supplied>was</supplied> sacrificing the burnt offering, <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines drew near for the battle against Israel. But Yahweh thundered against <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines with a great noise on that day and threw them into confusion so that they were defeated before Israel. <verse-number id="1 Sa 7:11">11</verse-number>Then the men of Israel went out from Mizpah and pursued <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines and they struck them down as far as below Beth Car. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 7:12">12</verse-number>So Samuel took a single stone and put <supplied>it</supplied> between Mizpah and Shen, and he named it Ebenezer and said, “Up to here Yahweh has helped us.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 7:13">13</verse-number>So the Philistines were subdued and they did not come into the territory of Israel again, and the hand of Yahweh was against <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines all the days of Samuel. <verse-number id="1 Sa 7:14">14</verse-number>The towns<note>Or “cities”</note> which <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines had taken from Israel <supplied>were</supplied> returned to Israel from Ekron to Gath, and Israel delivered their territories from the hand of <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines. Then there was peace between Israel and the Amorites. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Circuit Ministry of Samuel</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 7:15">15</verse-number>Samuel judged Israel all the days of his life. <verse-number id="1 Sa 7:16">16</verse-number>He used to go <supplied>on the circuit</supplied> <idiom-start/>from year to year<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “from what <supplied>is</supplied> required year in year”</note> He went around Bethel, Gilgal, and Mizpah, and he judged Israel <supplied>in</supplied> all these places. <verse-number id="1 Sa 7:17">17</verse-number>Then <idiom-start/>he returned<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and his return <supplied>was</supplied>”</note> to Ramah, because his house was there, and there he judged Israel, and he built an altar to Yahweh there. </p>
		</chapter>