<chapter id="1 Sa 8">
			<pericope>Israel’s Demand for a King</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 8:1">1</verse-number>When Samuel grew old he appointed his sons as judges over Israel. <verse-number id="1 Sa 8:2">2</verse-number>The name of his firstborn son <supplied>was</supplied> Joel, and the name of his second son <supplied>was</supplied> Abijah. <supplied>They were</supplied> judges in Beersheba. <verse-number id="1 Sa 8:3">3</verse-number>But his sons did not walk in his ways; they turned aside after gain, they took bribes, and they perverted justice. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 8:4">4</verse-number>So all the elders of Israel gathered together and came to Samuel at Ramah. <verse-number id="1 Sa 8:5">5</verse-number>They said to him, “Look, you are old and your sons do not follow in your ways. So then appoint a king for us to judge<note>Or “to rule”</note> us, like all the nations. <verse-number id="1 Sa 8:6">6</verse-number>But the matter <idiom-start/>was displeasing to Samuel<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was evil in the eyes of Samuel”</note> when they said, “Give us a king to judge<note>Or “to rule”</note> us,” so Samuel prayed to Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 8:7">7</verse-number>Then Yahweh said to Samuel, “Listen to the voice of the people concerning all that they say to you; for they have not rejected you, but they have rejected me from being king over them. <verse-number id="1 Sa 8:8">8</verse-number>Like all the deeds they have done from the day I brought them up from Egypt until this day, they have forsaken me and have served other gods—so they <supplied>are</supplied> doing to you also. <verse-number id="1 Sa 8:9">9</verse-number>And so then, listen to their voice. However, you must earnestly warn them; you must explain to them the custom of the king who will rule over them.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 8:10">10</verse-number>So Samuel spoke all the words of Yahweh to the people who <supplied>were</supplied> requesting a king from him. <verse-number id="1 Sa 8:11">11</verse-number>He said, “This will be the custom of the king who will reign over you: he will take your sons and appoint them to his chariots and his horsemen, and they will run before his chariots. <verse-number id="1 Sa 8:12">12</verse-number>He will appoint for himself commanders of thousands and commanders of fifties, and <supplied>those</supplied> <idiom-start/>to do his plowing<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to plow his plowing”</note> and to reap his harvest, and <supplied>those</supplied> to make weapons of war and the equipment for his chariots. <verse-number id="1 Sa 8:13">13</verse-number>He will take your daughters as <supplied>his</supplied> perfume makers and as cooks and as bakers. <verse-number id="1 Sa 8:14">14</verse-number>He will take the best of your fields and your vineyards and your olive trees and will give <supplied>them</supplied> to his servants. <verse-number id="1 Sa 8:15">15</verse-number>He will take a tenth of your seed and your vineyards and give <supplied>it</supplied> to his high officials and to his servants. <verse-number id="1 Sa 8:16">16</verse-number>He will take your male slaves and your female slaves and the best of your young men<note>LXX reads “cattle”</note> and your donkeys and <idiom-start/>will use them for his projects<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “will put <supplied>them</supplied> to his work”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 8:17">17</verse-number>He will take a tenth of your flocks,<note>The Hebrew term refers collectively to both sheep and goats (small livestock animals)</note> and you <supplied>yourselves</supplied> will become his servants. <verse-number id="1 Sa 8:18">18</verse-number>So you will cry out on that day because of your king whom you have chosen for yourselves, but Yahweh will not answer you on that day!” <verse-number id="1 Sa 8:19">19</verse-number>However, the people refused to listen to the voice of Samuel and they said, “No, but there must be a king over us, <verse-number id="1 Sa 8:20">20</verse-number>so that we <idiom-start/>also<idiom-end/><note>Literally “even we”</note> may be like all the nations, and our king may rule us and go out before us and fight our battles.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 8:21">21</verse-number>Now when Samuel heard all the words of the people, he repeated them in the ears of Yahweh. <verse-number id="1 Sa 8:22">22</verse-number>Then Yahweh said to Samuel, “Listen to their voice, and appoint a king for them.” So Samuel spoke to the men of Israel, “Each of you go to his <supplied>own</supplied> town.” </p>
		</chapter>