<chapter id="1 Sa 11">
			<pericope>Saul Defeats the Ammonites</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 11:1">1</verse-number>Now Nahash the Ammonite went up and encamped against Jabesh Gilead. All the men of Jabesh said to Nahash, “<idiom-start/>Make a treaty with us<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Cut with us a covenant”</note> and we will serve you.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 11:2">2</verse-number>But Nahash the Ammonite said to them, “On this <supplied>condition</supplied> <idiom-start/>I will make a treaty<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I will cut”</note> with you, by gouging out the right eye of each of you, so that I can make it a disgrace for all Israel.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 11:3">3</verse-number>So the elders of Jabesh said to him, “Leave us alone for seven days so that we may send messengers in all the territory of Israel, and if there <supplied>is</supplied> no deliverer for us, then we will come out to you.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 11:4">4</verse-number>When the messengers came to Gibeah of Saul, <idiom-start/>they reported these things to<idiom-end/><note>Literally “they spoke the words in the ears of”</note> the people. Then all the people lifted up their voices and wept. <verse-number id="1 Sa 11:5">5</verse-number><idiom-start/>Just then<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “And look/behold”</note> Saul was coming from the field behind the cattle. Saul said, “What <supplied>is the matter</supplied> with the people, that they <supplied>are</supplied> weeping?” So they recounted to him the words of the men of Jabesh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 11:6">6</verse-number>Then the Spirit of God rushed upon Saul when he heard these words, and <idiom-start/>he became very angry<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “his nose became very hot”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 11:7">7</verse-number>So he took a yoke of oxen and cut them into pieces and sent <supplied>them</supplied> throughout all the territory of Israel by the hand of the messengers, saying, “Whoever <supplied>is</supplied> not going out after Saul and after Samuel, so will it be done to his oxen.” Then the fear of Yahweh fell on the people and they went out as one man. <verse-number id="1 Sa 11:8">8</verse-number>He mustered them at Bezek; the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> <supplied>were</supplied> three hundred thousand, and the men of Judah <supplied>were</supplied> thirty thousand. <verse-number id="1 Sa 11:9">9</verse-number>They said to the messengers who had come, “Thus you will say to the men of Jabesh Gilead: ‘Tomorrow deliverance for you will come <idiom-start/>when the sun is hot<idiom-end/>.’ ”<note>Literally “at the heating of the sun”</note> When the messengers went and told the men of Jabesh, they rejoiced. <verse-number id="1 Sa 11:10">10</verse-number>The men of Jabesh said, “Tomorrow we will come out to you and you may do to us <idiom-start/>whatever seems good to you<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “as all <supplied>of</supplied> the good <supplied>that is</supplied> in your eyes”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 11:11">11</verse-number><idiom-start/>And the<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and it happened the”</note> next day Saul placed the people <supplied>in</supplied> three divisions. Then they came into the middle of the camp <idiom-start/>at the early morning watch<idiom-end/><note>Literally “at the night watch of the morning”</note> and struck down <idiom-start/>the Ammonites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Ammon”</note> until the heat of the day. It happened that the remainder were scattered <idiom-start/>so that no two among them remained together<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “and they did not remain among them two together”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 11:12">12</verse-number>Then the people said to Samuel, “Who <supplied>is</supplied> the one who asked, ‘Will Saul reign over us?’ Give the men to us that we may kill them.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 11:13">13</verse-number>But Saul said, “No one will be put to death on this day, because <idiom-start/>today<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the day”</note> Yahweh has provided deliverance in Israel.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 11:14">14</verse-number>Then Samuel said to the people, “Come, let us go to Gilgal, and let us renew the kingship there.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 11:15">15</verse-number>So all the people went to Gilgal and they made Saul king there before Yahweh in Gilgal. They sacrificed fellowship offerings there before Yahweh. Then Saul rejoiced there greatly <supplied>along with</supplied> all the men of Israel. </p>
		</chapter>