<chapter id="1 Sa 14">
			<pericope>Jonathan Leads the Counterattack</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 14:1">1</verse-number><idiom-start/>One day<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And it happened the day”</note> Jonathan the son of Saul said to <idiom-start/>his armor bearer<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the young man carrying his weapons”</note> “Come and let us go over to the garrison of <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines which <supplied>is</supplied> over there.” But he did not tell his father. <verse-number id="1 Sa 14:2">2</verse-number>Now Saul <supplied>was</supplied> staying at the outskirts of Gibeah under the pomegranate tree that <supplied>was</supplied> in Migron, and the troops that <supplied>were</supplied> with him <supplied>were</supplied> about six hundred men. <verse-number id="1 Sa 14:3">3</verse-number>Now Ahijah, the son of Ahitub (the brother of Ichabod), the son of Phinehas, the son of Eli the priest of Yahweh at Shiloh, was carrying an ephod. The troops did not know that Jonathan had gone. <verse-number id="1 Sa 14:4">4</verse-number>Now between the passes where Jonathan sought to go over to the garrison of <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines <supplied>there was</supplied> a crag of rock <idiom-start/>on one side<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from the beyond from this”</note> and a crag of rock <idiom-start/>on the other<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “from the beyond from this”</note> The name of the one <supplied>was</supplied> Bozez and the name of the other <supplied>was</supplied> Seneh. <verse-number id="1 Sa 14:5">5</verse-number>The one crag on the north <supplied>was</supplied> opposite Micmash and the other on the south <supplied>was</supplied> opposite Geba. <verse-number id="1 Sa 14:6">6</verse-number>So Jonathan said to <idiom-start/>his armor bearer<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the young man carrying his weapons”</note> “Come, let us go over to the garrisons of these uncircumcised; perhaps Yahweh will act for us, for there is no hindrance for Yahweh to save by many or by few.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 14:7">7</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>his armor bearer<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<supplied>the one</supplied> carrying his weapons”</note> said, “Do all that <supplied>is</supplied> in your heart <idiom-start/>that you are inclined to do<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “turn/incline for yourself”</note> <idiom-start/>I am with you all of the way<idiom-end/>!<note>Literally “Behold, I am with you according to your heart”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 14:8">8</verse-number>Then Jonathan said, “Look, we <supplied>are about to</supplied> go over to the men; and we will show ourselves to them. <verse-number id="1 Sa 14:9">9</verse-number>If they say to us: ‘Wait until we reach you,’ <idiom-start/>then we will stand as we are<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and we will stand under us”</note> and not go up to them. <verse-number id="1 Sa 14:10">10</verse-number>But if they say, ‘Come up to us,’ then we will go up, for Yahweh has given them into our hand, and this <supplied>will be</supplied> the sign for us.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 14:11">11</verse-number>So the two of them showed themselves to the garrison of <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines, and <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines said, “The Hebrews <supplied>are</supplied> coming out from the holes in which they have hidden themselves.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 14:12">12</verse-number>Then the men of the garrison answered Jonathan and <idiom-start/>his armor bearer<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “<supplied>the one</supplied> carrying his weapons”</note> “Come up to us and we will show you something!” Then Jonathan said to <idiom-start/>his armor bearer<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “<supplied>the one</supplied> carrying his weapons”</note> “Come up after me, for Yahweh has given them into the hand of Israel!” <verse-number id="1 Sa 14:13">13</verse-number>So Jonathan went up on his hands and his feet, with <idiom-start/>his armor bearer<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<supplied>the one</supplied> carrying his weapons”</note> after him. They fell before Jonathan and then <idiom-start/>his armor bearer<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<supplied>the one</supplied> carrying his weapons”</note> would kill them after him. <verse-number id="1 Sa 14:14">14</verse-number>So was the first attack <supplied>in</supplied> which Jonathan and <idiom-start/>his armor bearer<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<supplied>the one</supplied> carrying his weapons”</note> killed about twenty men within about half of a furrow in an acre of <supplied>an</supplied> open field. <verse-number id="1 Sa 14:15">15</verse-number>Then there was terror<note>Or “panic”</note> in the camp, in the open field, and among all the army of the garrison. Even the <idiom-start/>raiders<idiom-end/><note>Literally “destroyers”</note> trembled. The earth shook, and it became <idiom-start/>a very great panic<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “like the panic/terror of God”; some interpreters understand this to be a panic caused by God, while others understand the expression merely as a superlative (“a very great panic”)</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 14:16">16</verse-number>And the lookouts of Saul in Gibeah of Benjamin saw <idiom-start/>that<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and look”</note> the multitude <idiom-start/>surged back and forth<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “waved, going here and there”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 14:17">17</verse-number>Saul said to the troops that <supplied>were</supplied> with him, “Please call the roll and see who has gone from us.” So they called the roll <idiom-start/>and found that<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and look”</note> Jonathan and <idiom-start/>his armor bearer<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<supplied>the one</supplied> carrying his weapons”</note> were not <supplied>present</supplied>. <verse-number id="1 Sa 14:18">18</verse-number>Then Saul said to Ahijah, “Bring near the ark of God”<note>LXX reads “bring near the ephod”</note> (for the ark of God was <idiom-start/>at that time<idiom-end/><note>Literally “on that day”</note> with the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>).<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 14:19">19</verse-number>While<note>Hebrew “And”</note> Saul was still speaking to the priest, the tumult in the camp of <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines <idiom-start/>increased more and more<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “and it went, going and increasing”</note> so Saul said to the priest, “Withdraw your hand!” <verse-number id="1 Sa 14:20">20</verse-number>Then Saul and all the troops who were with him were assembled on command and came up to the battle, and look! Each <supplied>Philistine’s</supplied> sword <supplied>was</supplied> against his friend; <supplied>and there was</supplied> a very great confusion. <verse-number id="1 Sa 14:21">21</verse-number>The Hebrews who had been for <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines <idiom-start/>previously<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “as yesterday three days ago”</note> who had gone up with them into the camp all around, even they <idiom-start/>joined the Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “were with Israel”</note> who were with Saul and Jonathan. <verse-number id="1 Sa 14:22">22</verse-number>All the men of Israel who had hidden themselves in the hill country of Ephraim heard that <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines had fled, so even they pursued them closely in the battle. <verse-number id="1 Sa 14:23">23</verse-number>So on that day Yahweh delivered Israel, and the battle shifted to Beth Aven. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Saul’s Oath Leads to Trouble</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 14:24">24</verse-number>Now the men of Israel were hard pressed on that day, because Saul had made the army take an oath, saying, “Cursed be the man who eats <supplied>any</supplied> food until evening, when I will have avenged myself on my enemies!” So none of the army tasted <supplied>any</supplied> food. <verse-number id="1 Sa 14:25">25</verse-number>(Now all <supplied>the people of</supplied> the land used to go into the forest, for there was honey on the surface of the ground.) <verse-number id="1 Sa 14:26">26</verse-number>When the army came to the forest, look! <supplied>There was</supplied> honey flowing, but no one put his hand to his mouth, for the army was afraid of the solemn oath. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 14:27">27</verse-number>However, Jonathan had not heard about the oath of his father with the army, so he extended the end of the staff which was in his hand, and he dipped it into the honeycomb.<note>Hebrew “the honeycomb of the honey”</note> Then he put his hand to his mouth and his eyes gleamed.<note>The Masoretic Hebrew text (<i>Kethib</i>) reads “saw”; the reading tradition (<i>Qere)</i> reads “gleamed”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 14:28">28</verse-number>Then a man from the army informed <supplied>him</supplied> and said, “Your father made the army swear a solemn <supplied>oath</supplied>, saying, ‘Cursed be the man who eats food today,’ ” so the army <supplied>is</supplied> exhausted. <verse-number id="1 Sa 14:29">29</verse-number>Then Jonathan said, “My father has brought trouble on the land! See now that my eyes have brightened because I have tasted a little of this honey. <verse-number id="1 Sa 14:30">30</verse-number><idiom-start/>How much more could have been done<idiom-end/><note>Literally “even that if”</note> if the troops had eaten freely today from the plunder of their enemies that they had found! For now the loss among <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines <supplied>is</supplied> not great.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 14:31">31</verse-number>They defeated <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines that day from Micmash to Aijalon, and the troops were very weary. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 14:32">32</verse-number>Then the troops took the plunder: they took sheep and cattle and <idiom-start/>calves<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the children of cattle”</note> and slaughtered <supplied>them</supplied> on the ground and the troops ate <supplied>them all</supplied> with the blood. <verse-number id="1 Sa 14:33">33</verse-number>So they reported <supplied>it</supplied> to Saul, saying, “Look! The troops <supplied>are</supplied> sinning against Yahweh by eating <supplied>the animals</supplied> with the blood!” And he said, “You have dealt treacherously! Roll to me a large stone <idiom-start/>today<idiom-end/>!”<note>Literally “the day”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 14:34">34</verse-number>Then Saul said, “Disperse <supplied>yourselves</supplied> among the troops and say to them, ‘Bring to me each <supplied>one</supplied> his ox and each his sheep and slaughter them in this <supplied>place</supplied> and eat, but do not sin against Yahweh by eating <supplied>the animals</supplied> with the blood.’ ” So all the troops brought <supplied>them</supplied>, each <supplied>leading</supplied> his ox in his hand that night, and slaughtered <supplied>it</supplied> there. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jonathan Rescued from His Father Saul</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 14:35">35</verse-number>Then Saul built an altar to Yahweh; <idiom-start/>it was the first altar he built<idiom-end/><note>Literally “with it he began to build an altar”</note> to Yahweh. <verse-number id="1 Sa 14:36">36</verse-number>Saul said, “Let us go down after <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines <supplied>by</supplied> night, and let us plunder them until the morning light, and let us not leave <supplied>alive</supplied> a man among them.” So they said, “Do all that <supplied>is</supplied> good in your eyes.” But the priest said, “Let us draw near to God here.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 14:37">37</verse-number>So Saul inquired of God, “Should I go down after <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines? Will you give them into the hand of Israel?” But he did not answer him on that day. <verse-number id="1 Sa 14:38">38</verse-number>Then Saul said, “Come here, all <supplied>you</supplied> leaders of the people, <idiom-start/>so that we find out<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and know and see”</note> what the sin was this day. <verse-number id="1 Sa 14:39">39</verse-number>For as Yahweh lives, who delivers Israel, <supplied>I swear</supplied> that even if it <supplied>is</supplied> in Jonathan my son, <idiom-start/>he will certainly die<idiom-end/>!”<note>Literally “surely dying he will die”</note> But nobody from all the army answered him. <verse-number id="1 Sa 14:40">40</verse-number>Then he said to all Israel, “You will be <idiom-start/>on one side<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “opposite one”</note> and I and my son Jonathan will be <idiom-start/>on the other<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “opposite one”</note> And the army said to Saul, “Do <supplied>what is</supplied> good in your eyes.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 14:41">41</verse-number>Then Saul said to Yahweh the God of Israel, “<idiom-start/>Render a decision perfectly<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “give <supplied>what is</supplied> perfect”; the LXX includes additional words not found in the Masoretic Hebrew text but included in a number of modern English versions: “If this guilt <supplied>is</supplied> on me or in my son Jonathan, give Urim, but if this guilt <supplied>is</supplied> in your people Israel, give Thummim”</note> Jonathan and Saul were chosen <supplied>by lot</supplied> and the people went out. <verse-number id="1 Sa 14:42">42</verse-number>Then Saul said, “Let them cast <supplied>the lot</supplied> between me and my son Jonathan,” and Jonathan was chosen. <verse-number id="1 Sa 14:43">43</verse-number>So Saul said, “Tell me what you have done.” So Jonathan told him and said, “I <idiom-start/>merely tasted<idiom-end/><note>Literally “tasted I tasted”</note> a little honey with the end of the staff that was in my hand. Here I am, I must die.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 14:44">44</verse-number>Then Saul said, “So may God do <supplied>to me</supplied> and <idiom-start/>more<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “so may he add”</note> you will certainly die today, Jonathan!” <verse-number id="1 Sa 14:45">45</verse-number>But the army said to Saul, “Must Jonathan die, who accomplished this great victory in Israel? Far from it! As Yahweh lives, not a hair from his head will fall to the ground, for he has worked with God this day.” So the army ransomed Jonathan and he did not die. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 14:46">46</verse-number>Saul went up from <supplied>pursuing the</supplied> Philistines, and <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines went to their place. <verse-number id="1 Sa 14:47">47</verse-number>So Saul took the kingship over Israel, and he fought all around against his enemies, against Moab, against the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Ammon”</note> against Edom, against the kings of Zobah, and against the Philistines. He inflicted punishment against all who rebelled. <verse-number id="1 Sa 14:48">48</verse-number>He acted bravely and defeated <supplied>the</supplied> Amalekites and rescued Israel from the hand of those who plundered it. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 14:49">49</verse-number>Now the sons of Saul were Jonathan, Ishvi, and Malki-Shua; the names of his two daughters <supplied>were as follows</supplied>: the name of the firstborn <supplied>was</supplied> Merab and the younger <supplied>was</supplied> Michal. <verse-number id="1 Sa 14:50">50</verse-number>The name of Saul’s wife <supplied>was</supplied> Ahinoam the daughter of Ahimaaz, and the name of the commander of his army <supplied>was</supplied> Abner, the son of Ner, Saul’s uncle. <verse-number id="1 Sa 14:51">51</verse-number>Now Kish <supplied>was</supplied> the father of Saul, but Ner, the father of Abner, <supplied>was</supplied> the son of Abiel. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 14:52">52</verse-number>Warfare was severe against <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines all the days of Saul. Whenever Saul saw <idiom-start/>anyone who was a mighty warrior<idiom-end/><note>Literally “each man who <supplied>was</supplied> a mighty warrior”</note> or <idiom-start/>any brave man<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “each son of ability”</note> he <idiom-start/>conscripted him into his service<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “he gathered him to him<supplied>self</supplied>”</note> </p>
		</chapter>