<chapter id="1 Sa 15">
			<pericope>Israel Defeats the Amalekites</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 15:1">1</verse-number>Then Samuel said to Saul, “Yahweh sent me to anoint you as king over his people Israel. So then, <idiom-start/>listen to the words<idiom-end/><note>Literally “listen to the voice of the words”</note> of Yahweh! <verse-number id="1 Sa 15:2">2</verse-number>Thus says Yahweh of hosts: ‘I have observed what Amalek did to Israel, <idiom-start/>how he opposed him<idiom-end/><note>Literally “what he placed against him in the way”</note> when he went up from Egypt. <verse-number id="1 Sa 15:3">3</verse-number>So then, go and attack Amalek and utterly destroy all that is his! You must not spare him, but kill both man and woman, both child and nursing infant, both ox and sheep, both camel and donkey.’ ” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 15:4">4</verse-number>Saul summoned the army and mustered them at Telaim; two hundred thousand foot soldiers and ten thousand men of Judah. <verse-number id="1 Sa 15:5">5</verse-number>Then Saul came up to the city of Amalek and set an ambush in the wadi.<note>A valley that is usually dry but contains a stream during the rainy season</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 15:6">6</verse-number>Saul said to the Kenites, “Go, leave! Withdraw from among the Amalekites so that I do not destroy you with them. You have shown loyal love to all the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> when they came up from Egypt.” So the Kenites left from among <supplied>the</supplied> Amalekites. <verse-number id="1 Sa 15:7">7</verse-number>Then Saul defeated <supplied>the</supplied> Amalekites from Havilah as one goes to Shur which <supplied>is</supplied> <idiom-start/>east of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “upon the face of”</note> Egypt. <verse-number id="1 Sa 15:8">8</verse-number>He captured Agag the king of Amalek alive, but all the people he utterly destroyed with the <idiom-start/>edge<idiom-end/><note>Literally “mouth”</note> of the sword. <verse-number id="1 Sa 15:9">9</verse-number>However, Saul and the army spared Agag and the best of the sheep and the cattle and the second <supplied>best</supplied> of the young fatlings and <idiom-start/>all that was valuable<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “all the good <supplied>things</supplied>”</note> they were not willing to utterly destroy them. But all the possessions that were despised or worthless, they utterly destroyed. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Samuel Announces the Downfall of Saul</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 15:10">10</verse-number>Then the word of Yahweh came to Samuel, saying, <verse-number id="1 Sa 15:11">11</verse-number>“I regret that I made Saul king, for he has turned back from following me and has not kept my word.” <idiom-start/>Samuel became angry<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “it became hot for Samuel”</note> and he cried out to Yahweh all night. <verse-number id="1 Sa 15:12">12</verse-number>Then Samuel got up early in the morning to meet Saul. Samuel was told, “Saul has gone to Carmel, and look, he <supplied>is</supplied> setting up a monument for himself.” Then he turned around and crossed over and went down to Gilgal. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 15:13">13</verse-number>When Samuel came to Saul, Saul said to him, “May you be blessed by Yahweh! I have kept the word of Yahweh.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 15:14">14</verse-number>But Samuel said, “Then what <supplied>is</supplied> this bleating of the sheep <supplied>that I hear</supplied> in my ears and the lowing of the cattle that I am hearing?” <verse-number id="1 Sa 15:15">15</verse-number>Saul said, “They have brought them from <supplied>the</supplied> Amalekites; the troops spared the best of the sheep and the cattle in order to sacrifice them to Yahweh your God. But the rest we have utterly destroyed.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 15:16">16</verse-number>Then Samuel said to Saul, “Stop and let me tell you what Yahweh said to me last night.” So he said to him, “Speak.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 15:17">17</verse-number>Samuel said, “Even though you <supplied>are</supplied> small in your <supplied>own</supplied> eyes, are you not the head of the tribes of Israel? Yahweh has anointed you as king over Israel. <verse-number id="1 Sa 15:18">18</verse-number>When Yahweh sent you on your way, he said to you: ‘Go! You must utterly destroy the sinners, <supplied>the</supplied> Amalekites, and you must fight against them until you<note>The Masoretic Hebrew text reads “they”; LXX, Peshitta, and Targum read “you”</note> have destroyed them.’ <verse-number id="1 Sa 15:19">19</verse-number>Why did you not listen to the voice of Yahweh and fall with shouting on the plunder? You have done evil in the sight of Yahweh!” <verse-number id="1 Sa 15:20">20</verse-number>Then Saul said to Samuel, “I have listened to the voice of Yahweh, and I have gone on the way that Yahweh sent me! I brought Agag the king of Amalek, and the Amalekites I have utterly destroyed. <verse-number id="1 Sa 15:21">21</verse-number>The troops took from the plunder, sheep and cattle, the best of the things devoted to destruction, to sacrifice to Yahweh your God at Gilgal.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 15:22">22</verse-number>Then Samuel said, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Is there <supplied>as much</supplied> delight for Yahweh in burnt offerings and sacrifices </li1>
				<li2>as <supplied>there is</supplied> in <idiom-start/>obeying<idiom-end/><note>Literally “listening to the voice of”</note> Yahweh? </li2>
				<li1>Look! <idiom-start/>To obey<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Listening”</note> <supplied>is</supplied> better than sacrifice; </li1>
				<li2>to give heed than the fat of rams. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="1 Sa 15:23">23</verse-number>For rebellion <supplied>is like</supplied> the sin of divination; </li1>
				<li2>arrogance <supplied>is like</supplied> iniquity and idolatry. </li2>
				<li1>Because you have rejected the word of Yahweh, </li1>
				<li2>he has rejected you from <supplied>being</supplied> king!” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 15:24">24</verse-number>Then Saul said to Samuel, “I have sinned because I have transgressed <idiom-start/>the commandment of Yahweh<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the mouth of Yahweh”</note> and your words, for I feared the troops and I listened to their voice. <verse-number id="1 Sa 15:25">25</verse-number>So then, please pardon my sin and return with me <idiom-start/>so that I can worship<idiom-end/><note>Literally “so that I can bow down to”</note> Yahweh.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 15:26">26</verse-number>But Samuel said to Saul, “I will not return with you, for you have rejected the word of Yahweh, and he has rejected you from being king over Israel!” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 15:27">27</verse-number>As Samuel turned around to go, he<note>That is, Saul</note> caught hold of the hem of his robe, and it tore. <verse-number id="1 Sa 15:28">28</verse-number>Then Samuel said to him, “Yahweh has torn the kingdom of Israel from you today and has given it to your neighbor <idiom-start/>who is better than you<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the better than you”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 15:29">29</verse-number>Moreover, the Glory of Israel will not break faith and will not regret, for he <supplied>is</supplied> not a human that he should regret.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 15:30">30</verse-number>Then he<note>That is, Saul</note> said, “I have sinned! Now please honor me before the elders of my people and before Israel, and return with me <idiom-start/>so that I can worship<idiom-end/><note>Literally “so that I can bow down to”</note> Yahweh your God.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 15:31">31</verse-number>So Samuel returned after Saul, and Saul <idiom-start/>worshiped<idiom-end/><note>Literally “bowed down to”</note> Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 15:32">32</verse-number>Then Samuel said, “Bring Agag the king of Amalek out to me!” Agag came to him confidently,<note>Or “trembling”; literally “in chains/bonds” (HALOT 609 s.v. 2); the meaning here is uncertain (LXX has “trembling”)</note> for Agag thought, “Surely the bitterness of death <idiom-start/>is over<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “has turned aside”; other English versions follow the LXX and Peshitta and omit “has turned aside,” reading “Surely the bitterness of death!”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 15:33">33</verse-number>Samuel said, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Just as your sword bereaved women, </li1>
				<li2>so will your mother be bereaved among women!” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p>Then Samuel hacked Agag to pieces in the presence of Yahweh at Gilgal. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 15:34">34</verse-number>Then Samuel went to Ramah and Saul went up to his house in Gibeah of Saul. <verse-number id="1 Sa 15:35">35</verse-number>Samuel <idiom-start/>did not see Saul again<idiom-end/><note>Literally “did not add to see Saul”</note> until the day of his death, but Samuel mourned over Saul, and Yahweh regretted that he made Saul king over Israel. </p>
		</chapter>