<chapter id="1 Sa 16">
			<pericope>David Is Anointed</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 16:1">1</verse-number>Then Yahweh said to Samuel, “<idiom-start/>How long<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Until when”</note> will you mourn about Saul? I have rejected him from being king over Israel! Fill up your horn <supplied>with</supplied> oil and go. I will send you to Jesse the Bethlehemite, for I have chosen a king for myself among his sons.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 16:2">2</verse-number>But Samuel said, “How can I go? If Saul hears, he will kill me.” Yahweh said, “You must take a heifer from the herd <idiom-start/>with you<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “in/with your hand”</note> and you must say, ‘I have come to sacrifice to Yahweh.’ <verse-number id="1 Sa 16:3">3</verse-number>You will invite Jesse to the sacrifice and I will make known to you what you must do. You will anoint for me <supplied>the one</supplied> whom I tell you.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 16:4">4</verse-number>So Samuel did what Yahweh said. He came to Bethlehem, and the elders of the city came trembling to meet him. They said, “<idiom-start/>Have you come in peace<idiom-end/>?”<note>Literally “<supplied>Is</supplied> your coming peace?”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 16:5">5</verse-number>He said, “<supplied>I come in</supplied> peace. I have come to sacrifice to Yahweh. Sanctify yourselves and come with me to the sacrifice.” So he sanctified Jesse and his sons and invited them to the sacrifice. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 16:6">6</verse-number><idiom-start/>When they came<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “And it happened at their coming”</note> he<note>That is, Samuel</note> saw Eliab and said, “Surely his anointed one <supplied>is</supplied> before Yahweh!” <verse-number id="1 Sa 16:7">7</verse-number>But Yahweh said to Samuel, “Do not look at his appearance or at the height of his stature, because I have rejected him. For <supplied>God does</supplied> not <supplied>see</supplied> what man sees, for a man <idiom-start/>looks on the outward appearance<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sees as far as the eyes”</note> but Yahweh <idiom-start/>looks on the heart<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “sees as far as the heart”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 16:8">8</verse-number>Then Jesse called Abinadab and made him pass before Samuel, and he said, “This one also Yahweh has not chosen.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 16:9">9</verse-number>So Jesse made Shammah pass <supplied>before Samuel</supplied>, but he said, “Yahweh also has not chosen this one.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 16:10">10</verse-number>And Jesse made seven of his sons pass before Samuel, but Samuel said to Jesse, “Yahweh has not chosen any of these.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 16:11">11</verse-number>Then Samuel said to Jesse, “<idiom-start/>Are all the young men here<idiom-end/>?”<note>Literally “Are the boys finished?”</note> And he said, “The youngest still remains, but look, he <supplied>is</supplied> shepherding the flock.” And Samuel said to Jesse, “Send and bring him, for we cannot <idiom-start/>sit down<idiom-end/><note>Literally “turn”; for “sit down” see HALOT 739 s.v. 2.c</note> until he comes here.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 16:12">12</verse-number>So he sent and brought him. Now he <supplied>was</supplied> ruddy with beautiful eyes and of <idiom-start/>handsome<idiom-end/><note>Literally “good”</note> appearance. And Yahweh said, “Arise, anoint him, for this <supplied>is</supplied> he.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 16:13">13</verse-number>So Samuel took the horn of oil and anointed him in the midst of his brothers. Then the Spirit of Yahweh rushed upon David from that day <idiom-start/>on<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “and forward”</note> Then Samuel got up and went to Ramah. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Saul in Torment</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 16:14">14</verse-number>Now the Spirit of Yahweh departed from Saul and an evil spirit from Yahweh tormented him. <verse-number id="1 Sa 16:15">15</verse-number>So the servants of Saul said to him, “Look please, an evil spirit from God <supplied>is</supplied> tormenting you. <verse-number id="1 Sa 16:16">16</verse-number>Please, let our lord command your servants <supplied>who are</supplied> before you! Let them seek a man skilled in playing on the lyre. <idiom-start/>When<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And it will happen <supplied>that</supplied>”</note> the evil spirit from God <supplied>is</supplied> upon you, he can play <idiom-start/>on it<idiom-end/><note>Literally “with his hand”</note> and <idiom-start/>you will feel better<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “and <supplied>it will be</supplied> good for you”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 16:17">17</verse-number>So Saul said to his servants, “Please select a man <idiom-start/>who plays a stringed instrument well<idiom-end/><note>Literally “doing well to play a stringed instrument”</note> and bring <supplied>him</supplied> to me.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 16:18">18</verse-number>One of the servants answered and said, “Look, I have seen a son of Jesse the Bethlehemite <supplied>who is</supplied> skillful in playing a stringed instrument, a <idiom-start/>brave man, a warrior, prudent in speech, and handsome<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “a hero of ability, a man of war, discerning of word, and a man of appearance”</note> And Yahweh <supplied>is</supplied> with him.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 16:19">19</verse-number>So Saul sent messengers to Jesse and said, “Send me David your son who <supplied>is</supplied> with the sheep.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 16:20">20</verse-number>And Jesse took a donkey <supplied>loaded with</supplied> bread and a skin of wine and one <idiom-start/>young goat<idiom-end/><note>Literally “kid of a goat”</note> and sent <supplied>them</supplied> to Saul by the hand of David his son. <verse-number id="1 Sa 16:21">21</verse-number>So David came to Saul and <idiom-start/>entered his service<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “stood before him”</note> He<note>That is, Saul</note> loved him greatly and <idiom-start/>he became Saul’s armor bearer<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “he became for him a carrier of weapons”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 16:22">22</verse-number>Then Saul sent <supplied>word</supplied> to Jesse, saying, “Please let David stand before me, because he has found favor <idiom-start/>in my sight<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “in my eyes”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 16:23">23</verse-number>So whenever the <supplied>evil</supplied> spirit from God came to Saul, David would take the stringed instrument and play it with his hand. Then <idiom-start/>it would bring relief<idiom-end/><note>Literally “it would be relieved”</note> for Saul; <idiom-start/>he would feel better<idiom-end/><note>Literally “it would be good for him”</note> and the evil spirit would depart from him. </p>
		</chapter>