<chapter id="1 Sa 17">
			<pericope>The Philistine Champion Taunts Israel</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 17:1">1</verse-number><supplied>The</supplied> Philistines gathered their camps<note>Or “armies”</note> for battle and they were gathered <supplied>at</supplied> Socoh which <supplied>belongs</supplied> to Judah. They camped between Socoh and Azekah in Ephes Dammim. <verse-number id="1 Sa 17:2">2</verse-number>Then Saul and the men of Israel were gathered and encamped in the valley of Elah, and they formed ranks <supplied>for the</supplied> battle to meet <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines. <verse-number id="1 Sa 17:3">3</verse-number><supplied>The</supplied> Philistines were standing on the hill on one side and <supplied>the army of</supplied> Israel was standing on the hill on the other side with the valley between them. <verse-number id="1 Sa 17:4">4</verse-number>Then <idiom-start/>a champion<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a man of the space between”</note> went out from the camps of <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines, whose name was Goliath from Gath. His height was six cubits and a span.<note>A cubit was about eighteen inches and a span about nine inches, so the Masoretic Hebrew text gives the height of nine feet, nine inches. Ancient Greek versions variously give Goliath’s height as four, five, or sixteen cubits.</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 17:5">5</verse-number>A bronze helmet was on his head, and he was clothed with scale body armor; the weight of the body armor was five thousand bronze shekels. <verse-number id="1 Sa 17:6">6</verse-number>Bronze greaves<note>Or “shin guards”</note> were on his legs,<note>Hebrew “feet”</note> and a bronze javelin <supplied>was slung</supplied> between his shoulders. <verse-number id="1 Sa 17:7">7</verse-number>The shaft of his spear was like a weaver’s beam and the point of his spear <supplied>weighed</supplied> six hundred iron shekels. <idiom-start/>His shield bearer<idiom-end/><note>Literally “The one who carried his shield”</note> was walking in front of him. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 17:8">8</verse-number>He stood and called to the battle lines of Israel and said to them, “Why have you come out to form ranks <supplied>for</supplied> battle? <supplied>Am</supplied> I not the Philistine, and you the servants of Saul? Commission for yourselves a man and let him come down to me. <verse-number id="1 Sa 17:9">9</verse-number>If he <supplied>is</supplied> able to fight with me and he defeats me, then we will be your servants; but if I prevail over him and defeat him, then you will be our servants and you will serve us.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 17:10">10</verse-number>Then the Philistine said, “I hereby defy the battle lines of Israel today! Give me a man so that we may fight each other!” <verse-number id="1 Sa 17:11">11</verse-number>When Saul and all Israel heard these words of the Philistine, they were dismayed and very afraid. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>David Enters the Scene of Battle</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 17:12">12</verse-number>Now David was the son of an Ephrathite. This <supplied>man was</supplied> from Bethlehem of Judah, and his name was Jesse. <idiom-start/>He had<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And for him were”</note> eight sons; in the days of Saul this man was old, <supplied>yet</supplied> he <supplied>still</supplied> walked among<note>The LXX reads “he went in years”; that is, he was advanced in years</note> the men. <verse-number id="1 Sa 17:13">13</verse-number>The three oldest sons of Jesse had gone and <idiom-start/>followed<idiom-end/><note>Literally “went after”</note> Saul to the battle. The names of his three sons who went to the battle were Eliab the firstborn, his second <supplied>oldest</supplied> was Abinadab, and the third was Shammah. <verse-number id="1 Sa 17:14">14</verse-number>Now David was the youngest. The three oldest <idiom-start/>followed<idiom-end/><note>Literally “went after”</note> Saul, <verse-number id="1 Sa 17:15">15</verse-number>but David went <idiom-start/>back and forth<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<supplied>was</supplied> going and <supplied>was</supplied> returning”</note> from Saul to feed the sheep of his father in Bethlehem. <verse-number id="1 Sa 17:16">16</verse-number>Now the Philistine came forward early and late, and he took his stand <supplied>for</supplied> forty days. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 17:17">17</verse-number>Then Jesse said to his son David, “Please take for your brothers an ephah of this roasted grain and these ten loaves of bread, and bring <supplied>them</supplied> quickly to the camp for your brothers. <verse-number id="1 Sa 17:18">18</verse-number>And these ten portions of cheese you will bring to the commander of the thousand; <idiom-start/>find out how your brothers are doing<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “make a careful inspection as far as peace <supplied>concerning</supplied> your brothers”</note> and take their pledge.”<note>That is, some pledge or token of assurance that they had received the goods</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 17:19">19</verse-number>Now Saul and they<note>That is, David’s brothers</note> and all the men of Israel <supplied>were</supplied> in the valley of Elah fighting <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 17:20">20</verse-number>David rose early in the morning and left the sheep with a keeper, and he took <supplied>the provisions</supplied> and went as Jesse had commanded him. He came to the encampment while the troops <supplied>were</supplied> going to the battle line, and they raised the war cry. <verse-number id="1 Sa 17:21">21</verse-number>Israel and <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines drew up <supplied>in</supplied> battle lines, <idiom-start/>one battle line against the other<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “battle line to oppose battle line”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 17:22">22</verse-number>David left the baggage <supplied>he had</supplied> with him in the <idiom-start/>care<idiom-end/><note>Literally “hand”</note> of the baggage keeper, ran to the battle line, and came and <idiom-start/>asked how his brothers were doing<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “asked his brothers as far as peace”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 17:23">23</verse-number>While he <supplied>was</supplied> speaking to them, <idiom-start/>the champion<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the man of the space between”</note> whose name was Goliath the Philistine from Gath, <supplied>was</supplied> coming up from the caves<note>So the Masoretic Hebrew text (<i>Kethib</i>); the reading tradition (<i>Qere</i>) and LXX have “ranks”</note> of <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines. He spoke <idiom-start/>just as he had previously<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “according to these words”</note> and David heard <supplied>his words</supplied>. <verse-number id="1 Sa 17:24">24</verse-number>When all the men of Israel saw the man, they fled from his presence and were very afraid. <verse-number id="1 Sa 17:25">25</verse-number>And the men of Israel said, “Did you see this man who has come up? For he <supplied>is</supplied> going up to defy Israel! It will be <supplied>that</supplied> the man who defeats him, the king will make him<note>That is, the man who defeats Goliath</note> very rich with great wealth and will give him his daughter <supplied>in marriage</supplied> and will make his father’s house free in Israel.”<note>That is, free from taxation</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 17:26">26</verse-number>Now David had spoken to the men <supplied>who were</supplied> standing with him, saying, “What will be done for the man who defeats this Philistine and removes <supplied>the</supplied> disgrace from Israel? For who <supplied>is</supplied> this uncircumcised Philistine that he defies the battle lines of the living God?” <verse-number id="1 Sa 17:27">27</verse-number>And the troops had spoken to him according to this word, saying, “So it will be done for the man who defeats<note>Or “kills”</note> him.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 17:28">28</verse-number>His oldest brother Eliab heard while he was speaking to the men, <idiom-start/>and Eliab became very angry against David<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and the nose of Eliab became hot concerning David”</note> and said, “Why have you come down today, and with whom have you left those few sheep in the wilderness? I know your presumptuousness and the evil of your heart! For you have come down in order to see the battle!” <verse-number id="1 Sa 17:29">29</verse-number>David replied, “What have I done now? <idiom-start/>I merely asked a question<idiom-end/>!<note>Literally “<supplied>Is</supplied> this not a word?”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 17:30">30</verse-number>He turned around from him to another opposite <supplied>him</supplied> and <idiom-start/>he spoke to him in the same way<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “and he said according to this word”</note> and the people<note>Or “troops”</note> <idiom-start/>answered him as before<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “returned to him a word as the first word”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>David Appears before Saul</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 17:31">31</verse-number>Now the words which David had spoken were heard and they reported <supplied>them</supplied> <idiom-start/>to<idiom-end/><note>Literally “before the face/in the presence of”</note> Saul, and he summoned him. <verse-number id="1 Sa 17:32">32</verse-number>David said to Saul, “Do not let anyone’s heart fail concerning him! Your servant will go and fight with this Philistine.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 17:33">33</verse-number>But Saul said to David, “You will not be able to go against this Philistine to fight with him, because you are <supplied>only</supplied> a boy, whereas <supplied>he has</supplied> been a man of war since his childhood!” <verse-number id="1 Sa 17:34">34</verse-number>And David said to Saul, “Your servant has been a shepherd of the flock for his father. If the lion or the bear would come and carry off a sheep from the group, <verse-number id="1 Sa 17:35">35</verse-number>I would go out after it and strike it down and rescue <supplied>the sheep</supplied> from its mouth. If it rose against me, I would grab <supplied>it</supplied> by its beard and strike it down and kill it. <verse-number id="1 Sa 17:36">36</verse-number>Your servant has struck down both the lion and the bear, and this uncircumcised Philistine will be like one of them, because he defied the battle lines of the living God.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 17:37">37</verse-number>And David said, “Yahweh, who rescued me from the hand of the lion and from the hand of the bear, will rescue me from the hand of this Philistine!” Then Saul said to David, “Go and may Yahweh be with you!” <verse-number id="1 Sa 17:38">38</verse-number>Then Saul clothed David with his <supplied>own</supplied> fighting attire and put a helmet of bronze on his head and clothed him <supplied>with</supplied> body armor. <verse-number id="1 Sa 17:39">39</verse-number>Then David strapped on his sword over his fighting attire, but he tried in vain to walk <supplied>around</supplied>, for he was not trained to use <supplied>them</supplied>. So David said to Saul, “I am not able to walk with these, because I am not trained to use <supplied>them</supplied>.” So David removed them. <verse-number id="1 Sa 17:40">40</verse-number>Then he took his staff in his hand, picked out for himself five smooth stones from the wadi,<note>A valley that is usually dry but contains a stream during the rainy season</note> and he put them in his shepherd’s bag, in the pouch. And with his sling in his hand, he approached the Philistine. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 17:41">41</verse-number>Then the Philistine <idiom-start/>came on, getting nearer and nearer<idiom-end/><note>Literally “went going and near”</note> to David, with <idiom-start/>his shield bearer<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the man carrying the shield”</note> in front of him. <verse-number id="1 Sa 17:42">42</verse-number>When the Philistine looked and saw David, he despised him, for he was <supplied>only</supplied> a boy and ruddy with a handsome appearance. <verse-number id="1 Sa 17:43">43</verse-number>So the Philistine said to David, “<supplied>Am</supplied> I a dog, that you <supplied>are</supplied> coming to me with sticks?” Then the Philistine cursed David by his gods. <verse-number id="1 Sa 17:44">44</verse-number>The Philistine said to David, “Come to me so that I can give your flesh to the birds of heaven and to the wild animals of the field!” <verse-number id="1 Sa 17:45">45</verse-number>Then David said to the Philistine, “You <supplied>are</supplied> coming to me with a sword and with a spear and with a javelin, but I am coming to you in the name of Yahweh of hosts, the God of the battle lines of Israel, whom you have defied! <verse-number id="1 Sa 17:46">46</verse-number>This day Yahweh will deliver you into my hand, and I will strike you down <idiom-start/>and cut off your head<idiom-end/>!<note>Literally “and I will remove your head from upon you”</note> Then I will give <supplied>the</supplied> corpses of the army of <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines this day to the birds of heaven and to the animals of the earth, so that all the earth may know that there is a God <supplied>who is</supplied> for Israel. <verse-number id="1 Sa 17:47">47</verse-number>And all of this assembly will know that Yahweh does not rescue with sword or with spear, for the battle <supplied>belongs</supplied> to Yahweh, and he will give you into our hands!” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>David Defeats Goliath</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 17:48">48</verse-number><idiom-start/>When<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And it happened that when”</note> the Philistine got up and came and drew near to meet David, David <idiom-start/>ran quickly<idiom-end/><note>Literally “made quickly and he ran”</note> to the battle line to meet the Philistine. <verse-number id="1 Sa 17:49">49</verse-number>Then David put his hand into the bag and took a stone from it and slung <supplied>it</supplied>. He struck the Philistine on his forehead, and the stone sank into his forehead, and he fell on his face to the ground. <verse-number id="1 Sa 17:50">50</verse-number>So David prevailed over the Philistine with the sling and with the stone, and he struck down the Philistine and killed him, but there was no sword in David’s hand. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 17:51">51</verse-number>Then David ran and stood over the Philistine and took his sword and drew it from its sheath and killed him and cut off his head with it. When the Philistines saw that their champion was dead, they fled. <verse-number id="1 Sa 17:52">52</verse-number>The men of Israel and Judah got up, raised the war cry, and pursued <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines <idiom-start/>as far as<idiom-end/><note>Literally “up to your coming <supplied>to</supplied>”</note> the valley<note>So the Masoretic Hebrew text; LXX reads “Gath”</note> and up to the gates of Ekron. So the slain of <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines fell on the way<note>Or “road”</note> to Shaaraim up to Gath and as far as Ekron. <verse-number id="1 Sa 17:53">53</verse-number>Then the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> returned from pursuing <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines and plundered their camp. <verse-number id="1 Sa 17:54">54</verse-number>And David took the head of the Philistine and brought it to Jerusalem and placed his weapons in his tent. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 17:55">55</verse-number>Now when Saul saw David going out to meet the Philistine, he said to Abner, the commander of the army, “Whose son <supplied>is</supplied> this young man, Abner?” And Abner said, “As your soul lives, O king, I do not know.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 17:56">56</verse-number>Then the king said, “You inquire whose son this young man <supplied>is</supplied>.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 17:57">57</verse-number>So when David returned from striking down the Philistine, Abner took him and brought him before Saul. The head of the Philistine <supplied>was</supplied> in his hand. <verse-number id="1 Sa 17:58">58</verse-number>Then Saul said to him, “Whose son are you, young man?” And David said, “<supplied>I am</supplied> the son of your servant Jesse the Bethlehemite.” </p>
		</chapter>