<chapter id="1 Sa 19">
			<pericope>Jonathan Intercedes for David</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 19:1">1</verse-number>Now Saul spoke to Jonathan his son and to all his servants about killing David, but Saul’s son Jonathan <idiom-start/>liked David very much<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “delighted in David very”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 19:2">2</verse-number>So Jonathan informed David, saying, “My father Saul <supplied>is</supplied> trying to kill you; now please take care! In the morning you should stay in the hiding place and conceal yourself. <verse-number id="1 Sa 19:3">3</verse-number>I will go out and stand <idiom-start/>at my father’s side<idiom-end/><note>Literally “at the hand of my father”</note> in the field where you are, and I will speak about you to my father; <idiom-start/>if I find out anything<idiom-end/><note>Literally “if I see and what?”</note> I will tell <supplied>it</supplied> to you.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 19:4">4</verse-number>So Jonathan spoke well about David to his father Saul and said to him, “The king should not sin against his servant David, because he has not sinned against you, and because his service for you <supplied>has been</supplied> very good. <verse-number id="1 Sa 19:5">5</verse-number>He put his life in his hand and attacked the Philistine, and Yahweh brought about a great victory for all of Israel, and you saw <supplied>it</supplied> and rejoiced! Now why should you sin against innocent blood by killing David without cause?” <verse-number id="1 Sa 19:6">6</verse-number>And Saul listened to the voice of Jonathan and swore, “<idiom-start/>As Yahweh lives<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the life of Yahweh”</note> he will not be put to death!” <verse-number id="1 Sa 19:7">7</verse-number>Jonathan called to David and told him all of these words. Then Jonathan brought David to Saul and he was before him as <idiom-start/>formerly<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “yesterday three days ago”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>David Has to Flee Again</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 19:8">8</verse-number>War came again, so David went out and fought against <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines and <idiom-start/>defeated them thoroughly<idiom-end/><note>Literally “he struck them down with a great blow”</note> so that they fled before him. <verse-number id="1 Sa 19:9">9</verse-number>Then the evil spirit from Yahweh came upon Saul while he was sitting in his house <supplied>with</supplied> his spear in his hand. And David <supplied>was</supplied> playing a stringed instrument in <supplied>his</supplied> hand. <verse-number id="1 Sa 19:10">10</verse-number>So Saul tried <idiom-start/>to pin David to the wall with the spear<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to strike with the spear on David and to the wall”</note> but <idiom-start/>he eluded Saul<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “he escaped from the presence of Saul”</note> so that he struck the spear into the wall, and David fled and escaped that <supplied>same</supplied> night. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 19:11">11</verse-number>Then Saul sent messengers to David’s house to guard him and to kill him in the morning, but Michal his wife told David, saying, “If <idiom-start/>you do not save your life<idiom-end/><note>Literally “you are not saving your life”</note> tonight, <supplied>then</supplied> tomorrow you <supplied>will be</supplied> killed!” <verse-number id="1 Sa 19:12">12</verse-number>So Michal lowered David through the window, and he went and fled and escaped. <verse-number id="1 Sa 19:13">13</verse-number>Then Michal took the household god<note>Hebrew <i>teraphim</i></note> and put it on the bed and put a quilt of goat’s hair at its head and covered <supplied>it</supplied> with the clothes. <verse-number id="1 Sa 19:14">14</verse-number>And Saul sent messengers to arrest David, but she said, “He <supplied>is</supplied> ill.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 19:15">15</verse-number>So Saul sent the messengers to see David, saying, “Bring him up to me in the bed, so that I can kill him.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 19:16">16</verse-number>When the messengers came, <idiom-start/>to their surprise<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and look”</note> the idol <supplied>was</supplied> on the bed <supplied>with</supplied> the quilt of goat’s hair at the head. <verse-number id="1 Sa 19:17">17</verse-number>Then Saul said to Michal, “Why have you deceived me like this and sent away my enemy, so that he escaped?” Michal said to Saul, “He said to me, ‘Let me go, why should I kill you?’ ” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 19:18">18</verse-number>So David fled and escaped, and he came to Samuel at Ramah and told him all that Saul had done to him. Then he and Samuel went and stayed in Naioth. <verse-number id="1 Sa 19:19">19</verse-number>And it was told to Saul, “David <supplied>is</supplied> in Naioth in Ramah.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 19:20">20</verse-number>So Saul sent messengers to capture David. When they saw the company of the prophets prophesying and Samuel standing <supplied>as</supplied> chief over them, then the Spirit of God came upon Saul’s messengers, and they also prophesied. <verse-number id="1 Sa 19:21">21</verse-number>So they told Saul, and he sent other messengers, and they also prophesied. Again Saul sent messengers a third <supplied>time</supplied>, and they also prophesied. <verse-number id="1 Sa 19:22">22</verse-number>Then he also went to Ramah. When he came to the great cistern which <supplied>was</supplied> in Secu, he asked and said, “Where <supplied>are</supplied> Samuel and David?” Someone said, “Look <supplied>they are</supplied> in Naioth in Ramah.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 19:23">23</verse-number>So he went there to Naioth in Ramah and the Spirit of God came upon him also, and <idiom-start/>he walked along prophesying<idiom-end/><note>Literally “he went going and he prophesied”</note> until he came to Naioth in Ramah. <verse-number id="1 Sa 19:24">24</verse-number>He also stripped <supplied>off</supplied> his clothes and prophesied before Samuel. He lay naked all that day and all night. Therefore they say, “<supplied>Is</supplied> Saul also among the prophets?” </p>
		</chapter>