<chapter id="1 Sa 20">
			<pericope>Jonathan Supports David over Saul</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 20:1">1</verse-number>Then David fled from Naioth in Ramah and came and said before Jonathan, “What have I done? What <supplied>is</supplied> my guilt and what <supplied>is</supplied> my sin before your father that <supplied>he is</supplied> <idiom-start/>trying to kill me<idiom-end/>?<note>Literally “seeking my life”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 20:2">2</verse-number>And he said to him, “Far from it! You will not die! Look, my father does not do<note>The Masoretic Hebrew text (<i>Kethib</i>) reads “he does to/for him”; the translation follows the reading tradition (<i>Qere)</i> which has “does not do”</note> <idiom-start/>anything large or small unless he reveals it to me<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “a large thing or a small thing and he <supplied>does</supplied> not reveal <supplied>to</supplied> my ear”</note> Why should my father hide this thing or anything from me?” <verse-number id="1 Sa 20:3">3</verse-number>Then David <idiom-start/>took an oath<idiom-end/><note>Literally “swore”</note> again and said, “Your father knows very well that I have found favor in your eyes, and he thought, ‘Do not let Jonathan know this, lest he worry.’ But <idiom-start/>as Yahweh lives<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the life of Yahweh”</note> and <idiom-start/>as your soul lives<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “<supplied>the</supplied> life of your soul”</note> surely <supplied>there is</supplied> merely a step between me and death!” <verse-number id="1 Sa 20:4">4</verse-number>Then Jonathan said to David, “<idiom-start/>Whatever you wish<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “What your soul says”</note> I will do for you.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 20:5">5</verse-number>David said to Jonathan, “Look, tomorrow <supplied>is</supplied> the new moon, and I should certainly sit with the king to eat. You must send me away so that I can hide myself in the field until the third evening. <verse-number id="1 Sa 20:6">6</verse-number>If your father misses me at all, then you must say, ‘David earnestly asked from me to run to Bethlehem his city, for <idiom-start/>the yearly sacrifice<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the sacrifice of the days”</note> <supplied>is</supplied> there for all the clan.’ <verse-number id="1 Sa 20:7">7</verse-number>If he says ‘Good,’ <supplied>it will mean</supplied> peace for your servant; but if he <supplied>is</supplied> very angry, know that <idiom-start/>he has decided to do me harm<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the evil has been determined from with him”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 20:8">8</verse-number>So you must show loyal love to your servant, for you have brought your servant into a covenant of Yahweh with you. But if there <supplied>is</supplied> guilt in me, <supplied>then</supplied> kill me yourself! But why should you bring me to your father?” <verse-number id="1 Sa 20:9">9</verse-number>Then Jonathan said, “Far be it from you! For if I know for certain that <idiom-start/>my father decided evil should come upon you<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the evil <supplied>is</supplied> determined from with my father to come over you”</note> would I not have told it to you?” <verse-number id="1 Sa 20:10">10</verse-number>Then David said to Jonathan, “Who will tell me if what your father answers you <supplied>is</supplied> harsh?” <verse-number id="1 Sa 20:11">11</verse-number>And Jonathan said to David, “Come, let us go out to the field.” So the two of them went out to the field. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 20:12">12</verse-number>Then Jonathan said to David, “Yahweh the God of Israel <supplied>is my witness</supplied><note>The phrase “is my witness” is supplied based on the Syriac version</note> that I will question my father <idiom-start/>by this time the day after tomorrow<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “as the time tomorrow the third”</note> And look, <idiom-start/>if he is well disposed toward you<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “<supplied>if he is</supplied> good to David”</note> will I not send <supplied>word</supplied> to you and <idiom-start/>disclose it to you<idiom-end/>?<note>Literally “I will reveal <supplied>it to</supplied> your ear”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 20:13">13</verse-number><idiom-start/>So may Yahweh punish Jonathan and more<idiom-end/><note>Literally “So may Yahweh do to Jonathan and so may he add”</note> if <idiom-start/>my father decides to do you harm<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the evil over you <supplied>is</supplied> regarded as good by my father”</note> and if <idiom-start/>I fail to disclose it to you<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I will reveal <supplied>it</supplied> to your ear”</note> and send word to you that you can go safely. And may Yahweh be with you, as he has been with my father. <verse-number id="1 Sa 20:14">14</verse-number>And not while I am still alive, will you not show the loyal love of Yahweh with me, that I may not die?<note>Or perhaps “and <supplied>if</supplied> I die, may you not …”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 20:15">15</verse-number>And do not cut off your loyal love from <idiom-start/>my family<idiom-end/><note>Literally “my house”</note> forever, not <supplied>even</supplied> when Yahweh <idiom-start/>exterminates<idiom-end/><note>Literally “cuts off”</note> each of the enemies of David from the face of the earth.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 20:16">16</verse-number>So Jonathan <idiom-start/>made a covenant<idiom-end/><note>Literally “cut <supplied>a covenant</supplied>”</note> with the house of David, <supplied>saying,</supplied> “May Yahweh <idiom-start/>call the enemies of David to account<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “seek from the hand of the enemies of David”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 20:17">17</verse-number>And Jonathan again made David swear an oath, because he loved him; for with the love of his soul he loved him. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 20:18">18</verse-number>Then Jonathan said to him, “Tomorrow <supplied>is</supplied> the new moon, and you will be missed, for your seat will stay empty. <verse-number id="1 Sa 20:19">19</verse-number>On the third day you must go down quickly and go to the place where you hid yourself <idiom-start/>on the day all this started<idiom-end/><note>Literally “on the day of the deed”</note> and remain beside the stone Ezel. <verse-number id="1 Sa 20:20">20</verse-number>I will shoot three arrows <supplied>to the</supplied> side as <supplied>if</supplied> I were shooting at a target. <verse-number id="1 Sa 20:21">21</verse-number><idiom-start/>Then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And look”</note> I will send <supplied>word to</supplied> my servant, ‘Go, find the arrows!’ If I clearly say to the boy, ‘Look, the arrows <supplied>are</supplied> <idiom-start/>on this side of you<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “from you and here”</note> <idiom-start/>bring<idiom-end/><note>Literally “take”</note> it,’ then<note>Hebrew “and”</note> come, for <supplied>it means</supplied> peace for you. And there is no problem, <idiom-start/>as Yahweh lives<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the life of Yahweh”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 20:22">22</verse-number>But if I say this to the young man, ‘Look, the arrows <supplied>are</supplied> <idiom-start/>beyond you<idiom-end/>,’<note>Literally “from you and beyond”</note> go, for Yahweh has sent you away. <verse-number id="1 Sa 20:23">23</verse-number>And <supplied>as for</supplied> the matter about which you and I spoke, look, Yahweh <supplied>is</supplied> between you and me forever.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 20:24">24</verse-number>So David hid himself in the field. <idiom-start/>When the new moon came<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “And it was the new moon”</note> <idiom-start/>the king was seated at the feast<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the king sat at the food to eat”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 20:25">25</verse-number>The king sat at his seat <idiom-start/>as before<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “as occurrence at occurrence”</note> the seat by the wall, and Jonathan got up, and Abner sat beside Saul, but David’s place was empty. <verse-number id="1 Sa 20:26">26</verse-number>But Saul said nothing on that day, for he thought, “<idiom-start/>Something happened to him<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “It <supplied>is</supplied> incident”</note> He <supplied>is</supplied> not <supplied>ceremonially</supplied> clean; surely he <supplied>is</supplied> not clean.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 20:27">27</verse-number><idiom-start/>And then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And it happened”</note> on the next day, the second day of the new moon, that David’s place was empty. So Saul asked Jonathan his son, “Why did the son of Jesse not come either yesterday or today to the feast?” <verse-number id="1 Sa 20:28">28</verse-number>Jonathan answered Saul, “David earnestly asked permission from me <supplied>to go</supplied> up to Bethlehem. <verse-number id="1 Sa 20:29">29</verse-number>He said, ‘Send me away, please, for our clan sacrifice <supplied>is</supplied> in the city, and my brother commanded<note>Or “urged”</note> me <supplied>to be present</supplied>. So then, if I have found favor in your eyes, please let me slip away and see my brothers.’ Therefore he has not come to the table of the king.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 20:30">30</verse-number>Then <idiom-start/>Saul became angry<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the nose of Saul became hot”</note> at Jonathan and said to him, “<supplied>You</supplied> son of a perverse, rebellious woman!<note>Or “bastard of a wayward woman” (HALOT 796)</note> Do I not know that you have chosen the son of Jesse to your shame and to the shame of your mother’s nakedness? <verse-number id="1 Sa 20:31">31</verse-number>For <idiom-start/>as long as<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all the days which”</note> the son of Jesse <supplied>is</supplied> alive on the earth, you and your kingdom will not be established! So then, send and bring him to me, for <idiom-start/>he will surely die<idiom-end/>!”<note>Literally “he <supplied>is</supplied> a son of death”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 20:32">32</verse-number>But Jonathan answered his father Saul and said to him, “Why should he be put to death? What has he done?” <verse-number id="1 Sa 20:33">33</verse-number>Then Saul hurled his<note>Hebrew “the”</note> spear at him to kill him. So Jonathan knew <idiom-start/>that his father had decided<idiom-end/><note>Literally “it was complete from with his father”</note> to kill David. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 20:34">34</verse-number>Jonathan got up from the table <idiom-start/>enraged<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “with burning of nose”</note> and did not eat on the second day of the new moon because he was upset about David, because his father had disgraced him. <verse-number id="1 Sa 20:35">35</verse-number><idiom-start/>And then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And it happened”</note> in the morning Jonathan went out to the field for the appointment with David, and a young boy<note>Or “young servant”</note> <supplied>was</supplied> with him. <verse-number id="1 Sa 20:36">36</verse-number>He said to his servant,<note>Or “boy”</note> “Run, please find the arrows that I am shooting!” The boy<note>Or “servant”</note> ran, and he shot the arrow to pass <supplied>over</supplied> him. <verse-number id="1 Sa 20:37">37</verse-number>When the boy came up to the place of the arrow that Jonathan had shot, Jonathan called out after the boy and said, “<supplied>Is</supplied> not the arrow <idiom-start/>beyond you<idiom-end/>?”<note>Literally “from you and beyond”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 20:38">38</verse-number>Then Jonathan called out after the boy, “Quick, hurry, do not linger!” And Jonathan’s servant collected the arrows and came to his master. <verse-number id="1 Sa 20:39">39</verse-number>But the boy did not know anything <supplied>about this</supplied>; only Jonathan and David knew the matter. <verse-number id="1 Sa 20:40">40</verse-number>Jonathan gave his weapons to his servant and said to him, “Go, bring <supplied>them</supplied> to the city.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 20:41">41</verse-number>The boy left, and then David got up from the south side,<note>So Masoretic Hebrew text; LXX reads “from the mound” (of stones)</note> and he fell on his face to the ground and bowed three times. And they kissed <idiom-start/>each other<idiom-end/><note>Literally “each his friend”</note> and wept <idiom-start/>together<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “each with his friend”</note> but David <supplied>wept</supplied> the most. <verse-number id="1 Sa 20:42">42</verse-number>Jonathan said to David, “Go in peace, because we have sworn, the two of us, <supplied>an oath</supplied> in the name of Yahweh, saying, “Yahweh will be between me and you, and between my offspring and your offspring forever.”<note>In the Hebrew Bible, <cite title="BibleLEB2: 1 Sa 21">1 Sam 21 </cite>begins here. <cite title="BibleLEB2: 1 Sa 20:42b–21:15">1 Samuel 20:42b–21:15 </cite>in the English Bible is 21:1–16 in the Hebrew Bible</note> Then he got up and left, and Jonathan went into the city. </p>
		</chapter>