<chapter id="1 Sa 22">
			<pericope>Saul Takes Revenge on the Priests Who Helped David</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 22:1">1</verse-number>David went from there and escaped to the cave of Adullam. When his brothers and all his father’s household<note>Or “family”</note> heard, they came down to him there. <verse-number id="1 Sa 22:2">2</verse-number>Every man in distress and every man who had a creditor and every embittered man gathered to him, and he became <idiom-start/>their commander<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “over them as commander”</note> Now there <supplied>were</supplied> about four hundred men with him. <verse-number id="1 Sa 22:3">3</verse-number>And David went up from there to Mizpah of Moab. He said to the king of Moab, “Please let my father and my mother <idiom-start/>stay<idiom-end/><note>Literally “come/go out”</note> with you until I know what God will do for me.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 22:4">4</verse-number>So <idiom-start/>he brought them before the king of Moab<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “he led them into the presence of the king of Moab”</note> and they stayed with him all the days David was in the stronghold. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 22:5">5</verse-number>Then Gad the prophet said to David, “You should not stay in the stronghold; leave and go into the land of Judah.” So David left and came <supplied>to</supplied> the forest of Hereth. <verse-number id="1 Sa 22:6">6</verse-number>Now Saul heard that David and the men who <supplied>were</supplied> with him had been located. Saul <supplied>was</supplied> sitting at Gibeah under the tamarisk <supplied>tree</supplied> at Ramah. Now his spear <supplied>was</supplied> in his hand and all his servants <supplied>were</supplied> stationed around him. <verse-number id="1 Sa 22:7">7</verse-number>Then Saul said to the servants who <supplied>were</supplied> standing around him, “Please listen, <idiom-start/>Benjaminites<idiom-end/>!<note>Literally “children of Benjamin”</note> Will the son of Jesse give you all fields and vineyards? Will he make all of you commanders of thousands and commanders of hundreds? <verse-number id="1 Sa 22:8">8</verse-number>For all of you have conspired against me, and <idiom-start/>no one discloses to me<idiom-end/><note>Literally “there is no <supplied>one</supplied> revealing <supplied>to</supplied> my ear”</note> the <idiom-start/>making<idiom-end/><note>Literally “cutting”</note> <supplied>of an agreement</supplied> between my son and the son of Jesse! None of you have had sympathy for me or <idiom-start/>disclosed to me<idiom-end/><note>Literally “revealing <supplied>to</supplied> my ear”</note> <supplied>that</supplied> <idiom-start/>my son commissioned my servant against me to ambush me<idiom-end/><note>Literally “my son has raised my servant against me to an ambush”</note> as <supplied>has been done</supplied> this day!” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 22:9">9</verse-number>But Doeg the Edomite, who <supplied>was</supplied> stationed among the servants of Saul, answered and said, “I saw the son of Jesse going to Nob, to Ahimelech the son of Ahitub. <verse-number id="1 Sa 22:10">10</verse-number>And he inquired of Yahweh for him and gave him provisions and gave him the sword of Goliath the Philistine.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 22:11">11</verse-number>So the king sent to summon Ahimelech the son of Ahitub the priest, and all his father’s household, the priests who <supplied>were</supplied> at Nob. So all of them came to the king. <verse-number id="1 Sa 22:12">12</verse-number>Saul said, “Listen please, son of Ahitub.” He said, “Here I <supplied>am</supplied>, my lord.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 22:13">13</verse-number>Then Saul said to him, “Why did you conspire against me, you and the son of Jesse, when you gave to him bread and a sword, and by inquiring of God for him so that he might arise against me to ambush <supplied>me</supplied> as <supplied>has been done</supplied> this day?” <verse-number id="1 Sa 22:14">14</verse-number>But Ahimelech answered the king and said, “And who among all your servants <supplied>is</supplied> as faithful as David? He <supplied>is</supplied> the son-in-law of the king who moves <supplied>quickly</supplied> to safeguard you and is honored in your house. <verse-number id="1 Sa 22:15">15</verse-number><supplied>Only</supplied> today I began to inquire of God for him. Far be it from me that <idiom-start/>the king should impute anything against his servant<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the king will not put against his servant a matter”</note> or against my father’s household, for your servant has not known any of this matter, little or much.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 22:16">16</verse-number>Then the king said, “You must certainly die, Ahimelech, you and all your father’s household!” <verse-number id="1 Sa 22:17">17</verse-number>So the king said to the runners <supplied>who were</supplied> stationed around him, “Turn and kill the priests of Yahweh, because <idiom-start/>they also support David<idiom-end/><note>Literally “also their hand <supplied>is</supplied> with David”</note> and because they knew that he was fleeing and <idiom-start/>did not disclose it to me<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “did not reveal it to his ear”; the Masoretic Hebrew text (<i>Kethib</i>) reads “his,” but the reading tradition (<i>Qere)</i> has “my”</note> But the servants of the king <supplied>were</supplied> not willing to raise their hand to attack the priests of Yahweh. <verse-number id="1 Sa 22:18">18</verse-number>Then the king said to Doeg, “You turn and attack the priests!” So Doeg the Edomite turned and attacked the priests himself, and on that day he killed eighty-five men who wore <supplied>the</supplied> linen ephod. <verse-number id="1 Sa 22:19">19</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>he put to the sword<idiom-end/><note>Literally “he killed with <supplied>the</supplied> mouth of <supplied>the</supplied> sword”</note> Nob, the city of the priests, from man to woman, from child to infant, and ox and donkey and sheep;<note>Or “goats”; literally, “small livestock animals”</note> <supplied>all</supplied> <idiom-start/>to the sword<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “with <supplied>the</supplied> mouth of <supplied>the</supplied> sword”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 22:20">20</verse-number>But, one of the sons of Ahimelech the son of Ahitub, whose name was Abiathar, escaped and fled after David. <verse-number id="1 Sa 22:21">21</verse-number>Abiathar told David that Saul had killed the priests of Yahweh. <verse-number id="1 Sa 22:22">22</verse-number>Then David said to Abiathar, “I knew on that day that Doeg the Edomite was there, that he would certainly tell Saul. <idiom-start/>I am responsible for the deaths of all your father’s household<idiom-end/>!<note>Literally “I have turned against all the life of your father’s house”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 22:23">23</verse-number>Stay with me! Do not fear, because he who seeks my life seeks your life. You are in good care with me.” </p>
		</chapter>