<chapter id="1 Sa 23">
			<pericope>David Defeats the Philistines at Keilah</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 23:1">1</verse-number>Now they told David, “Look, <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines <supplied>are</supplied> fighting in Keilah and they <supplied>are</supplied> raiding the threshing floors.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 23:2">2</verse-number>So David inquired of Yahweh, saying, “Shall I go and attack these Philistines?” And Yahweh said to David, “Go and attack the Philistines and save<note>Or “deliver” or “rescue”</note> Keilah.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 23:3">3</verse-number>But David’s men said to him, “Look, we <supplied>are</supplied> afraid here in Judah. <idiom-start/>How much more<idiom-end/><note>Literally “also for”</note> <supplied>if</supplied> we go <supplied>to</supplied> Keilah to the battle lines of <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines?” <verse-number id="1 Sa 23:4">4</verse-number>So David again inquired of Yahweh, and Yahweh answered him and said, “Get up, go down <supplied>to</supplied> Keilah, for I <supplied>am</supplied> giving <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines into your hand.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 23:5">5</verse-number>So David and his men went to Keilah and fought with <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines. They drove off their livestock and <idiom-start/>dealt them a heavy blow<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “he struck them with a great smiting”</note> So David saved<note>Or “delivered” or “rescued”</note> the inhabitants of Keilah. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>David Flees from Saul at Keilah</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 23:6">6</verse-number><idiom-start/>Now when Abiathar the son of Ahimelech fled<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And it happened <supplied>that</supplied> at the fleeing of Abiathar son of Ahimelech”</note> to David <supplied>at</supplied> Keilah, he went down <supplied>with</supplied> an ephod in his hand. <verse-number id="1 Sa 23:7">7</verse-number>When it was told to Saul that David had gone to Keilah, Saul said, “God <idiom-start/>has given him<idiom-end/><note>Literally “has made him a stranger”</note> into my hand, because he has shut himself in by going into a city <supplied>with</supplied> <idiom-start/>two barred gates<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “two gates and a bar”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 23:8">8</verse-number>Saul then summoned all of the army for the battle, to go down <supplied>to</supplied> Keilah to lay a siege against David and his men. <verse-number id="1 Sa 23:9">9</verse-number>When David learned that Saul <supplied>was</supplied> plotting evil against him, he said to Abiathar the priest, “Bring the ephod here.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 23:10">10</verse-number>And David said, “O Yahweh, God of Israel, your servant has clearly heard that Saul <supplied>is</supplied> seeking to come to Keilah to destroy the city because of me. <verse-number id="1 Sa 23:11">11</verse-number>Will the rulers of Keilah deliver me into his hand? Will Saul come down as your servant has heard? O Yahweh, God of Israel, please tell your servant!” And Yahweh said, “He will come down.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 23:12">12</verse-number>Then David said, “Will the rulers of Keilah deliver me and my men into the hand of Saul?” And Yahweh said, “They will deliver <supplied>you</supplied>.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 23:13">13</verse-number>So David and his men got up, about six hundred men, and went out from Keilah and wandered wherever they could go. When it was told to Saul that David had escaped from Keilah, <idiom-start/>he stopped his pursuit<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “he ceased to go out”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>David Eludes Saul’s Pursuit</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 23:14">14</verse-number>David remained in the wilderness, in the strongholds, and in the hill country in the wilderness of Ziph. And Saul sought him <idiom-start/>continually<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “all the days”</note> but God did not give him into his hand. <verse-number id="1 Sa 23:15">15</verse-number>When David realized that Saul had gone out to seek his life, David was in the wilderness of Ziph at Horesh. <verse-number id="1 Sa 23:16">16</verse-number>So Jonathan the son of Saul got up and went to David <supplied>at</supplied> Horesh, and <idiom-start/>encouraged him<idiom-end/><note>Literally “he strengthened his hand”</note> through God. <verse-number id="1 Sa 23:17">17</verse-number>He said to him, “Do not be afraid, for the hand of my father Saul will not find you. You will be king over Israel, and <idiom-start/>I will be second to you<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “I shall be for you as second”</note> My father Saul knows <supplied>this</supplied> also.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 23:18">18</verse-number>Then the two of them <idiom-start/>made<idiom-end/><note>Literally “cut”</note> a covenant before Yahweh. David remained at Horesh, and Jonathan went to his house. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 23:19">19</verse-number>Then <supplied>the</supplied> Ziphites went up to Saul at Gibeah, saying, “<supplied>Is</supplied> not David hiding among us in the strongholds at Horesh on the hill of Hakilah, which <supplied>is</supplied> south of Jeshimon? <verse-number id="1 Sa 23:20">20</verse-number>So then, O king, <idiom-start/>whenever you want<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for all the wanting of your soul”</note> to come down, come down, and <supplied>it will be</supplied> for us to deliver him into the hand of the king.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 23:21">21</verse-number>And Saul said to them, “May you be blessed by Yahweh, for you have shown me compassion! <verse-number id="1 Sa 23:22">22</verse-number>Go, please, make certain again! Find out and see <idiom-start/>exactly where he is<idiom-end/><note>Literally “his place where his foot <supplied>is</supplied>”</note> and who has seen him there! For they have said to me, ‘He <supplied>is</supplied> very cunning.’ <verse-number id="1 Sa 23:23">23</verse-number>Look, find out all of the hiding places where he hides. Then return to me <idiom-start/>with dependable information<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to being established”</note> and I will go with you. And then if he <supplied>is</supplied> there in the land, then I will seek him among all the thousands of Judah.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 23:24">24</verse-number>Then they got up and went to Ziph before Saul. </p>
			<p>Now David and his men <supplied>were</supplied> in the wilderness of Maon in the Arabah, to the south of Jeshimon. <verse-number id="1 Sa 23:25">25</verse-number>And Saul and his men went to seek <supplied>him</supplied>, and they told David, so he went down <supplied>to</supplied> the rock and stayed in the wilderness of Maon. When Saul heard <supplied>this</supplied>, he pursued David <supplied>into</supplied> the wilderness of Maon. <verse-number id="1 Sa 23:26">26</verse-number>Saul went <idiom-start/>on one side of the mountain<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from the side of the mountain from this”</note> and David and his men <idiom-start/>went on the other side of the mountain<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “from the side of the mountain from this”</note> David was hurrying to get away from Saul, while Saul and his men <supplied>were</supplied> closing in on David and his men to capture them. <verse-number id="1 Sa 23:27">27</verse-number>But a messenger came to Saul, saying, “Hurry and come, because <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines have made a raid on the land!” <verse-number id="1 Sa 23:28">28</verse-number>So Saul returned from pursuing David, and he went to confront<note>Hebrew “to meet”</note> <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines. Therefore, they called that place the Rock of Division.<note>Hebrew “Sela’ Hammahlekot”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 23:29">29</verse-number><note><cite title="BibleLEB2: 1 Sa 23:29–24:22">1 Sam 23:29–24:22 </cite>in the English Bible is 24:1–23 in the Hebrew Bible</note> David went up from there and stayed in the strongholds of En Gedi. </p>
		</chapter>