<chapter id="1 Sa 24">
			<pericope>David Spares Saul in the Cave at En Gedi</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 24:1">1</verse-number>When Saul returned from <supplied>pursuing the</supplied> Philistines, they told him, “Look, David <supplied>is</supplied> in the wilderness of En Gedi.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 24:2">2</verse-number>So Saul took three thousand chosen men from all Israel, and he and his men went to search <supplied>for</supplied> David <idiom-start/>in the direction of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “on the face of”</note> the Rocks of the Mountain Goats.<note>Hebrew “of the Jael”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 24:3">3</verse-number>He came to the sheep pens beside the road, and a cave <supplied>was</supplied> there. Then Saul went in <idiom-start/>to relieve himself<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to cover his feet”</note> Now David and his men <supplied>were</supplied> sitting in the innermost part of the cave. <verse-number id="1 Sa 24:4">4</verse-number>And David’s men said to him, “Look, today <supplied>is</supplied> the day about which Yahweh said to you, ‘See, I am giving your enemy<note>The Masoretic Hebrew text (<i>Kethib</i>) reads “enemies,” but the reading tradition (<i>Qere)</i> has the singular “enemy”</note> into your hand, and you can do to him <idiom-start/>whatever seems good to you<idiom-end/>.’ ”<note>Literally “as that <supplied>which is</supplied> good in your eyes”</note> So David got up and secretly cut the hem of Saul’s robe. <verse-number id="1 Sa 24:5">5</verse-number><idiom-start/>And then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And it happened”</note> afterward David <idiom-start/>felt guilty<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the heart of David struck him”</note> because he had cut <idiom-start/>the hem of Saul’s robe<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the hem which <supplied>was</supplied> for Saul”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 24:6">6</verse-number>He said to his men, “Far be it from me in<note>Hebrew “from”</note> Yahweh, that I do this thing to my lord, to Yahweh’s anointed one, by stretching out my hand against him! For he <supplied>is</supplied> the anointed one of Yahweh.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 24:7">7</verse-number>So David rebuked his men with the words and did not allow them to rise against Saul. And Saul got up from the cave, and he went on his<note>Hebrew “the”</note> way. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 24:8">8</verse-number>Then David got up afterward and went out of the cave and called after Saul, “My lord the king!” When Saul looked after him, David knelt down <supplied>with his</supplied> face to the ground and bowed down. <verse-number id="1 Sa 24:9">9</verse-number>Then David said to Saul, “Why do you listen to the words of people who say: ‘Look, David <supplied>is</supplied> <idiom-start/>seeking to do you harm<idiom-end/>’?<note>Literally “seeking your evil”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 24:10">10</verse-number>Look, this day your eyes have seen that Yahweh gave you today into my hand in the cave, and some said to kill you. But <idiom-start/>I took pity<idiom-end/><note>Literally “she took pity,” with “she” = “my eye,” a common Hebrew expression</note> on you and said, ‘I will not stretch out my hand against my lord, because he <supplied>is</supplied> Yahweh’s anointed one.’ <verse-number id="1 Sa 24:11">11</verse-number>Now, my father, see, yes, see, the hem of your robe in my hand! For <idiom-start/>when I cut<idiom-end/><note>Literally “at my cutting”</note> the hem of your robe I did not kill you. Know and <idiom-start/>realize<idiom-end/><note>Literally “see”</note> that there is no evil or rebellion in my hand. I did not sin against you, but you <supplied>are</supplied> hunting down my life to take it. <verse-number id="1 Sa 24:12">12</verse-number>May Yahweh judge between me and you, and may Yahweh avenge me on you, but my hand will not be against you! <verse-number id="1 Sa 24:13">13</verse-number>Just as the ancient proverb says, ‘From the wicked, wickedness goes out,’ but my hand will not be against you! <verse-number id="1 Sa 24:14">14</verse-number>After whom did the king of Israel go out? After whom are you pursuing? After a dead dog? After one flea? <verse-number id="1 Sa 24:15">15</verse-number>May Yahweh be <supplied>the</supplied> judge, and let him judge between me and you, and may he see and plead my case. <idiom-start/>May he vindicate me against you<idiom-end/>!”<note>Literally “May he judge me from your hand”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 24:16">16</verse-number>When David finished speaking these words to Saul, Saul said, “<supplied>Is</supplied> this your voice, my son David?” And Saul lifted up his voice and wept. <verse-number id="1 Sa 24:17">17</verse-number>Then he said to David, “You are more righteous than I, for you have repaid me the good, but I have repaid you the evil. <verse-number id="1 Sa 24:18">18</verse-number>You have explained to me today that you have dealt well with me, how<note>Hebrew “that”</note> Yahweh delivered me into your hand but you did not kill me. <verse-number id="1 Sa 24:19">19</verse-number>For a man has found his enemy but sent him on <supplied>his</supplied> way safely. Now may Yahweh reward you with good in return for this day, for what you have done for me. <verse-number id="1 Sa 24:20">20</verse-number>So now then, look, I know that you will certainly be king and the kingdom of Israel will be established in your hand. <verse-number id="1 Sa 24:21">21</verse-number>So then, swear to me by Yahweh that you will not cut off my <idiom-start/>descendants<idiom-end/><note>Literally “seed”</note> after me and that you will not wipe out my name from my father’s house.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 24:22">22</verse-number>So David swore <supplied>this on oath</supplied> to Saul, and Saul went to his house, but David and his men went up to the stronghold. </p>
		</chapter>