<chapter id="1 Sa 25">
			<pericope>Samuel’s Death</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 25:1">1</verse-number>Now Samuel died, and all Israel assembled and mourned for him. They buried him at his house at Ramah. Then David got up and went down to the wilderness of Paran. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>David and Abigail</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 25:2">2</verse-number>Now there was a man in Maon, whose business <supplied>was</supplied> in Carmel. The man was very rich and <idiom-start/>owned<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<supplied>there were</supplied> for him”</note> three thousand sheep and a thousand goats. <idiom-start/>Now<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And it happened”</note> the shearing of his sheep <supplied>was taking place</supplied> in Carmel. <verse-number id="1 Sa 25:3">3</verse-number>The name of the man <supplied>was</supplied> Nabal,<note>The name “Nabal” means “foolish”</note> and the name of his wife <supplied>was</supplied> Abigail.<note>The name “Abigail” means “my father delights”</note> Now the woman <supplied>was</supplied> wise and beautiful, but the man <supplied>was</supplied> stubborn and <idiom-start/>mean<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “bad of deeds”</note> and he <supplied>was</supplied> as his heart.<note>The Masoretic Hebrew text (<i>Kethib</i>) reads “as his heart,” whereas the reading tradition (<i>Qere)</i> reads “Calebite”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 25:4">4</verse-number>David heard in the wilderness that Nabal <supplied>was</supplied> shearing his sheep. <verse-number id="1 Sa 25:5">5</verse-number>So David sent ten young men, and David said to the young men, “Go up to Carmel and go to Nabal; <idiom-start/>you will greet him in my name<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “you will ask for him in my name as far as peace”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 25:6">6</verse-number>Then you must say to him, ‘<supplied>Long</supplied> life <supplied>to you</supplied>, and <idiom-start/>may it go well with you, with your house, and with all that is yours<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “you <supplied>are</supplied> peace and your house <supplied>is</supplied> peace and all that <supplied>is</supplied> yours <supplied>is</supplied> peace”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 25:7">7</verse-number>Now I have heard that <idiom-start/>you have shearers<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “shearing <supplied>is</supplied> for you”</note> Now while your shepherds <supplied>were</supplied> with us, we did not mistreat them, and nothing of theirs <supplied>was</supplied> missing, all the days they were in Carmel. <verse-number id="1 Sa 25:8">8</verse-number>Ask your servants<note>Or “young men”</note> and they will tell you! Let the young men<note>Or “the servants”; “young men” is used here to connect with v. 5</note> find favor in your eyes because we have come on a feast day. Please give <idiom-start/>whatever you have on hand<idiom-end/><note>Literally “what your hand finds”</note> for your servants and for your son David.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 25:9">9</verse-number>So David’s young men came and they spoke all these words to Nabal in the name of David. Then they waited. <verse-number id="1 Sa 25:10">10</verse-number>But Nabal answered David’s servants and said, “Who <supplied>is</supplied> David? And who <supplied>is</supplied> the son of Jesse? Today, <supplied>there</supplied> are many servants breaking away from the presence of their masters. <verse-number id="1 Sa 25:11">11</verse-number>Should I take my bread and my water and my meat which I have slaughtered for my shearers and give <supplied>it</supplied> to men whom I do not know where they <supplied>are</supplied> from? <verse-number id="1 Sa 25:12">12</verse-number>So David’s young men turned on their way and returned and came and told him according to all these words. <verse-number id="1 Sa 25:13">13</verse-number>Then David said to his men, “Each man strap on his sword!” So each one strapped on his sword, and David also strapped on his sword. About four hundred men went up after David, while two hundred remained with the baggage. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 25:14">14</verse-number>But a young man of the servants told Abigail, Nabal’s wife, saying, “Look, David sent messengers from the desert to greet<note>Hebrew “bless”</note> our master, but he addressed them angrily, <verse-number id="1 Sa 25:15">15</verse-number>even though the men <supplied>were</supplied> very good to us; we were not mistreated and did not miss anything all the days we went about with them <idiom-start/>while we were<idiom-end/><note>Literally “at our being”</note> in the field. <verse-number id="1 Sa 25:16">16</verse-number>They were a wall to us both night and day, all <idiom-start/>the days we were<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the days of our being”</note> with them keeping the sheep. <verse-number id="1 Sa 25:17">17</verse-number>And so then, know and <idiom-start/>consider<idiom-end/><note>Literally “see”</note> what you should do, for evil has been decided against our master and against all his household, and he <supplied>is such</supplied> <idiom-start/>a wicked man<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “a son of uselessness”</note> <idiom-start/>nobody can reason with him<idiom-end/>!”<note>Literally “from speaking to him”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 25:18">18</verse-number>Then Abigail <idiom-start/>quickly took<idiom-end/><note>Literally “hastened and took”</note> two hundred loaves of bread, two skins of wine, five prepared sheep, five seahs of roasted grain, a hundred raisin cakes, and two hundred fig cakes, and she put <supplied>them</supplied> on the donkeys. <verse-number id="1 Sa 25:19">19</verse-number>Then she said to her servants, “Go ahead before me; look, I am coming after you,” but she did not tell her husband Nabal. <verse-number id="1 Sa 25:20">20</verse-number><idiom-start/>And then<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “And it happened”</note> <supplied>as</supplied> she <supplied>was</supplied> riding on the donkey and <supplied>was</supplied> going down the ravine of the mountain, David and his men <supplied>were</supplied> coming down to meet her, and she met them. <verse-number id="1 Sa 25:21">21</verse-number>Now David had said, “Surely <idiom-start/>in vain<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for the vanity”</note> I guarded all that this fellow had in the desert. And nothing was missed of all that <supplied>was</supplied> his, but he returned evil against me in place of good! <verse-number id="1 Sa 25:22">22</verse-number><idiom-start/>May God severely punish the enemies of David<idiom-end/><note>Literally “May God do so to the enemies of David”; following the LXX some English versions omit the words “the enemies of”</note> and again do thus if I leave behind <idiom-start/>anything that is his<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from all that <supplied>is</supplied> for him”</note> until the morning, <supplied>not even</supplied> <idiom-start/>one male<idiom-end/>!”<note>Literally “from one urinating against a wall”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 25:23">23</verse-number>When Abigail saw David, she hurried and got down from the donkey and fell on her face before <idiom-start/>David’s anger<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the nostrils of David”</note> and she bowed down to the ground. <verse-number id="1 Sa 25:24">24</verse-number>She fell at his feet and said, “On me, my lord, <supplied>be</supplied> the guilt! Please let your female servant speak <idiom-start/>to you personally<idiom-end/>!<note>Literally “in your ears”</note> Hear the words of your female servant! <verse-number id="1 Sa 25:25">25</verse-number>Please do not let my lord set his heart against <idiom-start/>this worthless man<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “this man of wickedness”</note> Nabal; for as his name, so <supplied>is</supplied> he. Nabal <supplied>is</supplied> his name, and stupidity <supplied>is</supplied> with him! But I, your female servant, did not see the young men<note>Or “the servants”</note> of my lord whom you sent. <verse-number id="1 Sa 25:26">26</verse-number>So then, my lord, <idiom-start/>as Yahweh lives and as your soul lives<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the life of Yahweh and <supplied>the</supplied> life of your soul”</note> since Yahweh restrained you from bloodguilt <idiom-start/>by taking matters into your own hand<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “saving your hand for you”</note> so then, may your enemies be like Nabal, even <idiom-start/>those who seek to do my lord harm<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the seeking to my lord evil”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 25:27">27</verse-number>So then, this gift which your female servant has brought to my lord, may it be given to the young men <idiom-start/>who follow my lord<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the <supplied>ones</supplied> going about at the feet of my lord”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 25:28">28</verse-number>Please forgive the transgression of your female servant, because Yahweh will certainly make a lasting house<note>That is, a lasting dynasty</note> for my lord, because my lord <supplied>is</supplied> fighting the battles of Yahweh, and evil will not be found in you <idiom-start/>as long as you live<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “from your days”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 25:29">29</verse-number>Should a man arise to pursue you and to seek your life, may the life of my lord be wrapped in the pouch<note>Or “bag”</note> of the living with Yahweh your God. But as for the life of your enemy, he will sling it from within<note>Hebrew “in the midst of”</note> the pocket of the sling! <verse-number id="1 Sa 25:30">30</verse-number><idiom-start/>And then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And it will happen”</note> when Yahweh has done for my lord according to all the good that he has spoken concerning you, and has appointed you as leader over Israel, <verse-number id="1 Sa 25:31">31</verse-number>then this will not be an obstacle for you or a stumbling block of conscience for my lord <supplied>either</supplied> by the shedding of blood without cause or by <idiom-start/>my lord taking matters into his own hands<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “<supplied>the</supplied> saving of my lord for himself”</note> And when Yahweh does good to my lord, then remember your female servant.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 25:32">32</verse-number>Then David said to Abigail, “Blessed be Yahweh the God of Israel who has sent you this day to meet me! <verse-number id="1 Sa 25:33">33</verse-number>And blessed be your discretion, and blessed be you who have prevented me this day from bloodguilt and <supplied>from</supplied> delivering myself by my own hand. <verse-number id="1 Sa 25:34">34</verse-number>But <idiom-start/>as Yahweh lives<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the life of Yahweh”</note> the God of Israel who has prevented me from harming you, if you had not hurried and come to meet me, surely there would not have been <idiom-start/>one male<idiom-end/><note>Literally “one urinating against a wall”</note> left alive for Nabal by the light of morning!” <verse-number id="1 Sa 25:35">35</verse-number>Then David took from her hand what she had brought for him, and he said to her, “Go up to your house in peace. See, I have listened to your voice, and I have <idiom-start/>granted your request<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “lifted up your face”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 25:36">36</verse-number>Then Abigail went to Nabal, and look, <idiom-start/>he was holding a feast<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a feast <supplied>was</supplied> for him”</note> in his house like the feast of the king. <idiom-start/>Nabal was enjoying himself<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the heart of Nabal <supplied>was</supplied> good on him”</note> and he <supplied>was</supplied> very drunk, so she did not tell him a thing, <idiom-start/>nothing at all<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “small or large”</note> until the light of morning. <verse-number id="1 Sa 25:37">37</verse-number><idiom-start/>And then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And it happened”</note> in the morning when the wine had gone out of Nabal, his wife told him these words. Then his heart died <idiom-start/>within him<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “in his midst”</note> and he became like a stone. <verse-number id="1 Sa 25:38">38</verse-number><idiom-start/>And then<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “And it happened”</note> about ten days later, Yahweh struck Nabal and he died. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 25:39">39</verse-number>When David heard that Nabal had died, he said, “Blessed be Yahweh who has vindicated the case of my reproach from the hand of Nabal, and he has kept back his servant from evil; but Yahweh has returned the evil of Nabal on his <supplied>own</supplied> head.” Then David sent and spoke with Abigail to take her for his wife. <verse-number id="1 Sa 25:40">40</verse-number>So the servants of David came to Abigail at Carmel, and they spoke to her, saying, “David has sent us to you to take you for his wife.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 25:41">41</verse-number>She got up and bowed down <supplied>with</supplied> her face to the ground and said, “Here is your female servant, as a slave to wash the feet of my lord’s servants.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 25:42">42</verse-number>Then Abigail <idiom-start/>quickly got up<idiom-end/><note>Literally “hastened and got up”</note> and rode on the donkey, <supplied>along with</supplied> five of her maidservants who <idiom-start/>attended her<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the <supplied>ones</supplied> going about at her feet”</note> and she went after the messengers of David and became his wife. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 25:43">43</verse-number>David had also taken Ahinoam from Jezreel, and both of them became his wives. <verse-number id="1 Sa 25:44">44</verse-number>(Now Saul had given his daughter Michal, David’s wife, to Palti the son of Laish, who <supplied>was</supplied> from Gallim.) </p>
		</chapter>