<chapter id="1 Sa 26">
			<pericope>David Again Spares Saul</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 26:1">1</verse-number>The Ziphites came to Saul at Gibeah, saying, “<supplied>Is</supplied> not David hiding on the hill of Hakilah opposite Jeshimon?” <verse-number id="1 Sa 26:2">2</verse-number>Then Saul got up and went down to the wilderness of Ziph, and three thousand chosen men of Israel with him, to seek David in the wilderness of Ziph. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 26:3">3</verse-number>Now Saul was on the hill of Hakilah, which <supplied>is</supplied> opposite Jeshimon by the road, but David was staying in the wilderness. When he realized that Saul had come to the wilderness after him, <verse-number id="1 Sa 26:4">4</verse-number>David sent spies, and he learned that Saul had come <idiom-start/>for certain<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to be established”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 26:5">5</verse-number>Then David got up and came to the place where Saul had encamped, and David saw the place where Saul <supplied>was</supplied> lying down, <idiom-start/>as well as<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and”</note> Abner the son of Ner, the commander of his army. (Now Saul <supplied>was</supplied> lying in the encampment, and the army <supplied>was</supplied> encamping around him.) </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 26:6">6</verse-number>David answered and said to Ahimelech the Hittite and to Abishai the son of Zeruiah the brother of Joab, saying, “Who will go down with me to Saul, in the camp?” And Abishai said, “I will go down with you.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 26:7">7</verse-number>So David and Abishai came to the army <supplied>by</supplied> night, and <idiom-start/>there was<idiom-end/><note>Literally “look” or “behold”</note> Saul lying asleep in the encampment with<note>Hebrew “and”</note> his spear thrust into the ground near his head, and Abner and the army <supplied>were</supplied> lying all around him. <verse-number id="1 Sa 26:8">8</verse-number>Then Abishai said to David, “God has handed over your enemy into your hand today! So then, <idiom-start/>please let me pin him to the ground with the spear<idiom-end/><note>Literally “let me strike him please with the spear and in the ground”</note> <idiom-start/>one time<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “one occurrence”</note> and <idiom-start/>I will not strike him twice<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “I will not repeat for him”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 26:9">9</verse-number>But David said to Abishai, “Do not destroy<note>Or “kill”</note> him! For who has stretched out his hand against Yahweh’s anointed one and remained blameless?” <verse-number id="1 Sa 26:10">10</verse-number>And David said, “<idiom-start/>As Yahweh lives<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “The life of Yahweh”</note> <idiom-start/>certainly<idiom-end/><note>Literally “if surely”</note> Yahweh will strike him, or his day will come and he will die, or he will go down in the battle and <idiom-start/>perish<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “will be carried away”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 26:11">11</verse-number><idiom-start/>Yahweh forbid me<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Far be it from me from Yahweh”</note> from stretching out my hand against Yahweh’s anointed one! So then, please take the spear that <supplied>is</supplied> near his head and the jar of water, and let us go.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 26:12">12</verse-number>So David took the spear and the jar of water from <supplied>near</supplied> Saul’s head, and they went <supplied>away</supplied>. <idiom-start/>No one saw, no one knew, and no one awakened<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “there was not <supplied>anyone</supplied> seeing and there was not <supplied>anyone</supplied> knowing and there was not <supplied>anyone</supplied> awakening”</note> for all of them <supplied>were</supplied> sleeping because a deep sleep of Yahweh had fallen upon them. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 26:13">13</verse-number>Then David went to the other side and stood on the top of the hill at a distance; the distance <supplied>was</supplied> great between them. <verse-number id="1 Sa 26:14">14</verse-number>David called out to the army and to Abner the son of Ner, “Will you not answer, Abner?” And Abner answered and said, “Who <supplied>are</supplied> you <supplied>that</supplied> you call to the king?” <verse-number id="1 Sa 26:15">15</verse-number>So David said to Abner, “<supplied>Are</supplied> you not a man? And who <supplied>is</supplied> like you in Israel? Why did you not keep watch over your lord the king? For one of the people came to destroy<note>Or “to kill”</note> your lord the king. <verse-number id="1 Sa 26:16">16</verse-number>This thing that you have done <supplied>is</supplied> not good. <idiom-start/>As Yahweh lives<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the life of Yahweh”</note> <idiom-start/>surely you people deserve to die<idiom-end/><note>Literally “you are sons of death”</note> since you have not kept watch over your lord, over Yahweh’s anointed one! So then, see where the king’s spear <supplied>is</supplied> and the jar of water that <supplied>was</supplied> near his head!” <verse-number id="1 Sa 26:17">17</verse-number>Then Saul recognized David’s voice and said, “<supplied>Is</supplied> this your voice, my son David?” And David said, “<supplied>It is</supplied> my voice, my lord the king.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 26:18">18</verse-number>Then he said, “Why <supplied>is</supplied> my lord pursuing after his servant? For what have I done? And what evil <supplied>is</supplied> in my hand? <verse-number id="1 Sa 26:19">19</verse-number>And so then, please let my lord the king listen to the words of his servant: If Yahweh has incited you against me, may he delight in an offering; but if <idiom-start/>it is mortals<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “<supplied>it is</supplied> the sons of humankind”</note> <supplied>may</supplied> they be accursed <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of”</note> Yahweh, for they have driven me away today from sharing in the inheritance of Yahweh, saying, ‘Go, serve other gods!’ <verse-number id="1 Sa 26:20">20</verse-number>And so then, do not let my blood fall to the ground <idiom-start/>away from<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from before”</note> the presence of Yahweh, for the king of Israel has gone out to seek a single flea, as one hunts a partridge in the mountains.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 26:21">21</verse-number>Then Saul said, “I have sinned! Come back, David my son, for I will not harm you again, because my life <supplied>was</supplied> precious in your eyes this day. Look, I have acted like a fool and <idiom-start/>have made a terrible mistake<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “have gone greatly astray”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 26:22">22</verse-number>David answered and said, “Here is the king’s spear; let one of the young men<note>Or “servants”</note> come over and take it. <verse-number id="1 Sa 26:23">23</verse-number>Yahweh repays to each <supplied>one</supplied> his righteousness and his faithfulness, for Yahweh gave you into my hand today, but I was not willing to stretch out my hand against Yahweh’s anointed. <verse-number id="1 Sa 26:24">24</verse-number>Look, as your life was precious in my eyes this day, may my life be great in the eyes of Yahweh, and may he rescue me from all trouble.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 26:25">25</verse-number>Then Saul said to David, “Blessed are you, my son David; <idiom-start/>you will not only do many things, but also will always succeed<idiom-end/>!”<note>Literally “you will do many things and also always you will prevail”</note> Then David went on his way and Saul returned to his place. </p>
		</chapter>