<chapter id="1 Sa 27">
			<pericope>David Returns to Achish</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 27:1">1</verse-number>Then David <idiom-start/>thought to himself<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “said to his heart”</note> “Now I will perish one day by the hand of Saul! There is nothing better for me but <supplied>that</supplied> I must certainly escape to the land of <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines. Then Saul will desist from searching for me further in all of the territories of Israel, and so I will escape from his hand.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 27:2">2</verse-number>So David got up and crossed over, he and the six hundred men who <supplied>were</supplied> with him, to Achish the son of Maoch, the king of Gath. <verse-number id="1 Sa 27:3">3</verse-number>David settled with Achish in Gath, he and his men, each with his household.<note>Or “family”</note> David <supplied>took along</supplied> his two wives Ahinoam <idiom-start/>from Jezreel<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the Jezreelitess”</note> and Abigail the wife of Nabal the Carmelite. <verse-number id="1 Sa 27:4">4</verse-number>And it was reported to Saul that David had fled <supplied>to</supplied> Gath, so <idiom-start/>he no longer searched for him<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “he does <supplied><i>Qere</i> did</supplied> not again to seek him longer”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 27:5">5</verse-number>Then David said to Achish, “Please, if I have found favor in your eyes, then let them give me a place in one of the <idiom-start/>country towns<idiom-end/><note>Literally “towns of the open field”</note> that I can live there. Why should your servant live in <idiom-start/>the royal city<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the city of the king”</note> with you?” <verse-number id="1 Sa 27:6">6</verse-number>So Achish gave him Ziklag on that day. (Therefore, Ziklag has belonged to the kings of Judah until this day.) <verse-number id="1 Sa 27:7">7</verse-number>The number of days that David lived in the countryside of the Philistines <supplied>was</supplied> one year and four months. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 27:8">8</verse-number>Now David and his men went up and raided the Geshurites and the Girzites and the Amalekites, for they had been living <supplied>in</supplied> the land for a long time <idiom-start/>in the direction of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<supplied>as</supplied> you come”</note> Shur and <idiom-start/>as far as<idiom-end/><note>Literally “up to”</note> the land of Egypt. <verse-number id="1 Sa 27:9">9</verse-number>So David struck the land and did not leave a man or a woman alive; he took the sheep,<note>Hebrew “flock,” referring to either sheep or goats or both</note> the cattle, the donkeys, the camels, and the clothing. Then he returned and came to Achish. <verse-number id="1 Sa 27:10">10</verse-number>And Achish said, “Against whom have you raided today?” David said, “Against the Negev of Judah and against the Negev of the Jerahmeelites and against the Negev of the Kenites.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 27:11">11</verse-number>And David did not leave alive a man or a woman to bring <supplied>them back</supplied> to Gath, thinking,<note>Hebrew “saying”</note> “So that they will not report about us, saying, ‘David did thus and so.’ ” Thus was his practice all the days that he lived in the countryside of <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines. <verse-number id="1 Sa 27:12">12</verse-number>And Achish trusted David, saying, “<idiom-start/>He has made himself utterly hated<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Stinking he stink” = “he really stinks”</note> among his people in Israel, and he will be my servant forever.” </p>
		</chapter>