<chapter id="1 Sa 28">
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 28">28</verse-number><verse-number id="1 Sa 28:1">1</verse-number> <idiom-start/>Now<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And it happened”</note> in those days <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines gathered their forces for war to fight against Israel. So Achish said to David, “Certainly you realize that you must go out with me in the army, you and your men.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 28:2">2</verse-number>David said to Achish, “Very well, you will know what your servant can do.” Achish said to David, “Very well, I will make you <idiom-start/>my bodyguard<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the keeper of my head”</note> for life.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Saul Inquires of the Medium at Endor</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 28:3">3</verse-number>(Now Samuel had died, and all Israel had mourned for him, and they had buried him in Ramah, his <supplied>own</supplied> city. And Saul had expelled the mediums<note>Or “necromancers”</note> and the soothsayers from the land.) <verse-number id="1 Sa 28:4">4</verse-number>Then <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines assembled and came and encamped at Shunem, so Saul assembled all Israel, and they encamped at Gilboa. <verse-number id="1 Sa 28:5">5</verse-number>When Saul saw the army of <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines, he was afraid and his heart trembled greatly. <verse-number id="1 Sa 28:6">6</verse-number>And Saul inquired of Yahweh, but Yahweh did not answer him, not by dreams or by the Urim<note>A device for revealing God’s decisions; see Exod 28:30; Num 27:21; Neh 7:65; Prov 16:33</note> or by the prophets. <verse-number id="1 Sa 28:7">7</verse-number>So Saul said to his servants, “Search for me <idiom-start/>a woman who is a medium<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a woman of an owner of a spirit of the dead” (= “a woman who owns a ritual pit for summoning spirits of the dead”)</note> so that I may go to her and inquire of her.” His servants said to him, “Look <supplied>there is</supplied> a woman who <supplied>is</supplied> a medium in Endor.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 28:8">8</verse-number>So Saul disguised himself and put on other clothes, and he went <idiom-start/>with two of his men<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “and two of <supplied>his</supplied> men with him”</note> And they came to the woman <supplied>by</supplied> night and he said, “Please consult a spirit for me through <idiom-start/>the ritual pit<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the spirit of the dead”</note> and bring up for me <supplied>the one</supplied> whom I tell you.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 28:9">9</verse-number>But the woman said to him, “Look, you know what Saul did, how he exterminated the mediums<note>Or “necromancers”</note> and the soothsayers from the land! Why <supplied>are</supplied> you setting a trap for my life to kill me?” <verse-number id="1 Sa 28:10">10</verse-number>Then Saul swore to her by Yahweh, “<idiom-start/>As Yahweh lives<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “The life of Yahweh”</note> <idiom-start/>you will not be punished<idiom-end/><note>Literally “guilt will not meet you”</note> for this thing.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 28:11">11</verse-number>So the woman asked, “Whom shall I bring up for you?” He said, “Bring up Samuel for me.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 28:12">12</verse-number>When the woman saw Samuel, she cried out with a loud voice, and the woman said to Saul, “Why did you deceive me? You <supplied>are</supplied> Saul!” <verse-number id="1 Sa 28:13">13</verse-number>The king said to her, “Do not be afraid! What do you see?” And the woman said to Saul, “I see a god<note>Or “a divine being”</note> coming up from the ground!” <verse-number id="1 Sa 28:14">14</verse-number>Then he said to her, “What <supplied>is</supplied> his appearance?” She said, “An old man <supplied>is</supplied> coming up, and <idiom-start/>he is wrapped in a robe<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “he <supplied>is</supplied> wrapping himself <supplied>with</supplied> a robe”</note> Then Saul realized that it was Samuel, and he knelt <supplied>with</supplied> his face to the ground and bowed down. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 28:15">15</verse-number>Then Samuel said to Saul, “Why have you disturbed me by bringing me up?” And Saul said, “<idiom-start/>I am in distress<idiom-end/>!<note>Literally “Great distress <supplied>is</supplied> for me”</note> For <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines <supplied>are about</supplied> to make war against me, but God has turned away from me, and he does not answer me any more, not <idiom-start/>by the prophets<idiom-end/><note>Literally “by the hand of the prophets”</note> or by the dreams. So I called to you to let me know what I should do.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 28:16">16</verse-number>Then Samuel said, “Why do you ask me, since Yahweh has turned away from you and has become your enemy? <verse-number id="1 Sa 28:17">17</verse-number>Yahweh has done to you just as he spoke by my hand! Yahweh has torn the kingdom from your hand and has given it to your neighbor, to David. <verse-number id="1 Sa 28:18">18</verse-number>Because you <idiom-start/>did not obey<idiom-end/><note>Literally “did not listen to”</note> Yahweh and did not carry out the fierce anger of his <idiom-start/>wrath<idiom-end/><note>Literally “face”</note> against Amalek, therefore Yahweh has done this thing to you today. <verse-number id="1 Sa 28:19">19</verse-number>And Yahweh will also give Israel with you into the hands of <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines, and tomorrow you and your sons <supplied>will be</supplied> with me, and Yahweh will also give the army of Israel into <supplied>the</supplied> hand of <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 28:20">20</verse-number><idiom-start/>Then Saul immediately fell prostrate<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Saul did at once and fell <supplied>with</supplied> the fullness of his height”</note> to the ground, and he was very afraid because of the words of Samuel; there was no more strength in him, for he had not eaten food all day and all night. <verse-number id="1 Sa 28:21">21</verse-number>Then the woman came to Saul and realized that he was absolutely<note>Hebrew “very”</note> terrified, so she said to him, “Look, your female servant <idiom-start/>has obeyed you<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “has listened to your voice”</note> and I have <idiom-start/>risked my life<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “I have put my life in my palm”</note> I have listened to your words that you have spoken to me. <verse-number id="1 Sa 28:22">22</verse-number>So then, you also please listen to the voice of your female servant, and let me set before you a morsel of bread, and <supplied>you</supplied> eat so that <idiom-start/>you will have strength<idiom-end/><note>Literally “it will be your strength”</note> in you when you go on your<note>Hebrew “the”</note> way.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 28:23">23</verse-number>But he refused and said, “I will not eat!” However, his servants urged him, and the woman also. So he listened <idiom-start/>to what they said<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “their voice”</note> and he got up from the ground and sat on the bed. <verse-number id="1 Sa 28:24">24</verse-number>Now the woman had a fattened bull calf in the house, <idiom-start/>so she quickly slaughtered it<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and she did quickly and she slaughtered it”</note> and took flour, kneaded <supplied>dough</supplied>, and baked him <supplied>some</supplied> unleavened bread. <verse-number id="1 Sa 28:25">25</verse-number>She brought it before Saul and his servants, and they ate. Then they got up and went away that <supplied>very</supplied> night. </p>
		</chapter>