<chapter id="1 Sa 30">
			<pericope>David Recovers His Loved Ones</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 30:1">1</verse-number><idiom-start/>Now<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And it happened”</note> when David and his men came <supplied>to</supplied> Ziklag on the third day, <supplied>the</supplied> Amalekites had raided <supplied>the</supplied> Negev and Ziklag. When they attacked Ziklag, they burned it with fire. <verse-number id="1 Sa 30:2">2</verse-number>They took captive the women<note>LXX adds “and all”</note> who were in it, <idiom-start/>from the youngest to the oldest<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “from small and up to great”</note> They did not kill anyone, but carried <supplied>them</supplied> off and went on their way. <verse-number id="1 Sa 30:3">3</verse-number>When David and his men came to the city, <idiom-start/>they saw<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “and look”</note> and <supplied>it</supplied> was burned with fire, and their wives, their sons, and their daughters had been taken captive. <verse-number id="1 Sa 30:4">4</verse-number>Then David and the people who <supplied>were</supplied> with him raised their voices and wept until there was not <supplied>enough</supplied> strength in them to weep. <verse-number id="1 Sa 30:5">5</verse-number>Two of David’s wives had been taken captive. Ahinoam <idiom-start/>from Jezreel<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the Jezreelitess”</note> and Abigail, the wife of Nabal the Carmelite. <verse-number id="1 Sa 30:6">6</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>David was in a very precarious situation<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “it was very pressed for David”</note> for the people spoke of stoning him, for the souls of all the people were bitter, each <supplied>one</supplied> over his sons and his daughters. But David strengthened himself in Yahweh his God. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 30:7">7</verse-number>Then David said to Abiathar the priest, the son of Ahimelech, “Please bring the ephod here for me.” So Abiathar brought the ephod to David. <verse-number id="1 Sa 30:8">8</verse-number>And David inquired of Yahweh, saying, “Should I pursue after this band <supplied>of raiders</supplied>? Will I overtake them?” He said to him, “Pursue <supplied>them</supplied>, for you will certainly overtake them, and you will certainly rescue them.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 30:9">9</verse-number>So David went, he and the six hundred men who were with him, and they came to the Wadi<note>A valley that is usually dry but contains a stream during the rainy season</note> Besor, but the rest remained. <verse-number id="1 Sa 30:10">10</verse-number>David pursued, he and four hundred men; but two hundred men stayed because they were too exhausted to pass over the Wadi Besor. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 30:11">11</verse-number>Then they found an Egyptian man in the open country and brought him to David, and they gave him food and he ate; they also gave him water. <verse-number id="1 Sa 30:12">12</verse-number>They gave him a slice of fig cake and two raisin cakes; he ate and <idiom-start/>this revived him<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “his spirit returned to him”</note> because he had not eaten food or drunk water <supplied>for</supplied> three days and three nights. <verse-number id="1 Sa 30:13">13</verse-number>Then David said to him, “<idiom-start/>To whom do you belong<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “To whom <supplied>are</supplied> you”</note> and from where <supplied>are</supplied> you? The young man said, “I am an Egyptian young man, a servant of an Amalekite man, but my master abandoned me because I became ill three days ago. <verse-number id="1 Sa 30:14">14</verse-number>We raided the Negev of the Kerethites and that <supplied>which belongs</supplied> to Judah and then the Negev of Caleb, and we burned Ziklag with fire.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 30:15">15</verse-number>So David asked him, “Will you take me down to this band <supplied>of raiders</supplied>?” He said, “Swear to me by God that you will not kill me and that you will not deliver me into my master’s hand! Then I will take you down to this band.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 30:16">16</verse-number>So he took him down, and <idiom-start/>there they were<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “look”</note> spread out over the surface of all the land, eating and drinking and dancing because of all of the abundant plunder which they had taken from the land of <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines and from the land of Judah. <verse-number id="1 Sa 30:17">17</verse-number>Then David attacked them from twilight until the evening of the next day. Not a man of them escaped <idiom-start/>except<idiom-end/><note>Literally “but if”</note> four hundred young men who rode <supplied>off</supplied> on camels and fled. <verse-number id="1 Sa 30:18">18</verse-number>So David recovered all that <supplied>the</supplied> Amalekites had taken; David also rescued his two wives. <verse-number id="1 Sa 30:19">19</verse-number>None of theirs <supplied>was</supplied> missing <idiom-start/>from the smallest to the greatest<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from the small and up to the great”</note> even sons and daughters, from <supplied>the</supplied> plunder up to everything they had taken for themselves; David brought back everything. <verse-number id="1 Sa 30:20">20</verse-number>And David took all of the sheep,<note>Hebrew “flock,” referring to either sheep or goats or both</note> and the cattle they drove along in front of that livestock, and they said, “This <supplied>is</supplied> David’s plunder.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 30:21">21</verse-number>Then David came to <supplied>the</supplied> two hundred men <idiom-start/>who had been too exhausted to follow<idiom-end/><note>Literally “who were exhausted from going after”</note> David; they had left them behind at the Wadi<note>A valley that is usually dry but contains a stream during the rainy season</note> Besor. They went out to meet David and to meet the people who were with him. David came near with the people and <idiom-start/>asked them how they were doing<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “asked for them as far as peace”</note> <verse-number id="1 Sa 30:22">22</verse-number>Then all the corrupt and useless men among the men who went with David reacted and said, “Because they did not go with us, we will not give them <supplied>anything</supplied> from the plunder which we recovered, <idiom-start/>except<idiom-end/><note>Literally “but if”</note> each <supplied>man may take</supplied> his own wife and children. They must take them along and go!” <verse-number id="1 Sa 30:23">23</verse-number>But David said to them, “You should not do so, my brothers, with what Yahweh has given to us! He has preserved us and has given the <supplied>raiding</supplied> band that came against us into our hand. <verse-number id="1 Sa 30:24">24</verse-number>And who would listen to you regarding this matter? For as the share of the one who went down into the battle, so the share of the one who remained with the baggage will be. They will share alike.” <verse-number id="1 Sa 30:25">25</verse-number>So<note>Or “And”</note> from that day and beyond, he made it a rule and a regulation for Israel until this day. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 30:26">26</verse-number>Then David came to Ziklag, and he sent some of the plunder to the elders of Judah, to his friends, saying, “<idiom-start/>Here is<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Look”</note> a gift for you from the plunder of the enemies of Yahweh!” <verse-number id="1 Sa 30:27">27</verse-number><supplied>It was</supplied> for those in Bethel, for those in Ramoth of the Negev, for those in Jattir, <verse-number id="1 Sa 30:28">28</verse-number>for those in Aroer, for those in Siphmoth, for those in Eshtemoa, <verse-number id="1 Sa 30:29">29</verse-number>for those in Racal, for those in the towns of the Jerahmeelites, for those in the towns of the Kenites, <verse-number id="1 Sa 30:30">30</verse-number>for those in Hormah, for those in Bor Ashan, for those in Athach, <verse-number id="1 Sa 30:31">31</verse-number>for those in Hebron, and for all the places <idiom-start/>where David and his men had roamed<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “where David had gone about there, he and his men”</note> </p>
		</chapter>