<chapter id="1 Sa 31">
			<pericope>Saul and Jonathan Die on Mount Gilboa</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 31:1">1</verse-number>Now <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines <supplied>were</supplied> fighting against Israel, and the men of Israel fled before <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines, and they fell slain on Mount Gilboa. <verse-number id="1 Sa 31:2">2</verse-number>And <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines overtook Saul and his sons, and <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines killed Jonathan and Abinadab and Malki-Shua, the sons of Saul. <verse-number id="1 Sa 31:3">3</verse-number><idiom-start/>Saul was in the thick of the battle<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “The battle weighed heavily on Saul”</note> and <idiom-start/>the archers<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the shooters, the men with the bow”</note> spotted<note>Hebrew “found”</note> him, and he <supplied>was</supplied> badly wounded by the archers. <verse-number id="1 Sa 31:4">4</verse-number>Then Saul said to <idiom-start/>his armor bearer<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the carrier of his weapons”</note> “Draw your sword and thrust me through with it, so that these uncircumcised do not come and thrust me through and make a fool of me!” But <idiom-start/>his armor bearer<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the carrier of his weapons”</note> <supplied>was</supplied> not willing <supplied>to do so</supplied> because he <supplied>was</supplied> very afraid. So Saul took the sword and fell on it. <verse-number id="1 Sa 31:5">5</verse-number>And when <idiom-start/>his armor bearer<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the carrier of his weapons”</note> saw that Saul <supplied>was</supplied> dead, he also fell on his sword and died with him. <verse-number id="1 Sa 31:6">6</verse-number>So Saul died, and his three sons, <idiom-start/>his armor bearer<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the carrier of his weapons”</note> <supplied>and</supplied> all his men together that <supplied>same</supplied> day. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 31:7">7</verse-number>And when the men of Israel who <supplied>were</supplied> on the other side of the valley and <supplied>those</supplied> who were beyond the Jordan saw that the men of Israel had fled and that Saul and his sons were dead, they abandoned the towns and fled. Thus <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines came and lived in them. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Sa 31:8">8</verse-number><idiom-start/>And then<idiom-end/><note>Literally, “And it happened”</note> the next day, <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines came to strip the dead and they found Saul and his three sons lying <supplied>dead</supplied> on Mount Gilboa. <verse-number id="1 Sa 31:9">9</verse-number>So they cut off his head and stripped off his armor. Then they sent <supplied>messengers</supplied> around in the land of <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines to proclaim <supplied>victory in</supplied> the temples<note>Or “houses”</note> of their idols and <supplied>to</supplied> the people. <verse-number id="1 Sa 31:10">10</verse-number>And they put his armor <supplied>in</supplied> the temple<note>Or “house”</note> of the Ashtoreth,<note>Hebrew plural “Ashtaroth” (Ashtoreth was the female consort of Ba’al)</note> and they fastened his corpse to the wall of Beth Shan. <verse-number id="1 Sa 31:11">11</verse-number>When the inhabitants of Jabesh Gilead heard about it, what <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines had done to Saul, <verse-number id="1 Sa 31:12">12</verse-number>all of <idiom-start/>the valiant men<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the men of ability”</note> set out and went all night and took the corpse of Saul and the corpses of his sons from the wall of Beth Shan, and they came to Jabesh and burned them there. <verse-number id="1 Sa 31:13">13</verse-number>Then they took their bones and buried <supplied>them</supplied> under the tamarisk in Jabesh, and they fasted <supplied>for</supplied> seven days. </p>
		</chapter>