<chapter id="Am 3">
			<pericope>Israel’s Guilt and Punishment</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Am 3:1">1</verse-number>Hear this word that Yahweh has spoken against you, O people of Israel, against the whole clan that I brought up from the land of Egypt:<note>Hebrew “Egypt, saying”</note> <verse-number id="Am 3:2">2</verse-number>“You only have I <idiom-start/>chosen<idiom-end/><note>Literally “known”</note> of all the clans of the earth. Therefore I will punish you for all your iniquities. <verse-number id="Am 3:3">3</verse-number>Do two walk together unless they have met? <verse-number id="Am 3:4">4</verse-number>Does a lion roar in the forest <idiom-start/>when he has no prey<idiom-end/>?<note>Literally “and there is no prey to him”</note> Does a fierce, young lion cry out from his den unless he has caught <supplied>something</supplied>? <verse-number id="Am 3:5">5</verse-number>Does a bird fall into a trapping net on the earth when there is no snare for it? Does a trapping net spring up from the ground unless it has certainly caught something? <verse-number id="Am 3:6">6</verse-number>Or is a horn blown in a city and people are not afraid? Or does a disaster occur in the city and Yahweh has not done <supplied>it</supplied>? <verse-number id="Am 3:7">7</verse-number>Surely my Lord does not do anything unless he has revealed his secret to his servants the prophets. <verse-number id="Am 3:8">8</verse-number>A lion has roared! Who is not afraid? My Lord Yahweh has spoken, who will not prophesy? <verse-number id="Am 3:9">9</verse-number>Proclaim to the citadel fortresses in Ashdod and the citadel fortresses in the land of Egypt and say: “Gather on the mountains of Samaria and see the great panic in her midst and the oppression in her midst!” <verse-number id="Am 3:10">10</verse-number>“They do not know <supplied>how</supplied> to do right,” <idiom-start/>declares Yahweh<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the declaration of Yahweh”</note> “those who store up violence and destruction in their citadel fortresses.” <verse-number id="Am 3:11">11</verse-number>Therefore, thus says my Lord Yahweh, “A foe shall surround the land and bring down your strongholds, and your citadel fortresses shall be plundered.” <verse-number id="Am 3:12">12</verse-number>Thus says Yahweh, “Just as the shepherd rescues two legs or a piece of an ear from the mouth of the lion, so shall the <idiom-start/>people<idiom-end/><note>Literally “children”</note> of Israel who dwell in Samaria, with the corner of a couch and the damask of a bed.” <verse-number id="Am 3:13">13</verse-number>“Listen and testify against the house of Jacob,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> my Lord Yahweh, the God of hosts. <verse-number id="Am 3:14">14</verse-number>“For on the day I punish Israel for <idiom-start/>its transgression<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the transgression of Israel upon it”</note> I will also punish the altars of Bethel and the horns of the altar will be cut off and fall to the ground. <verse-number id="Am 3:15">15</verse-number>I will ruin the winter house as well as the summer house, and the houses of ivory will perish and the great houses shall come to an end,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh. </p>
		</chapter>