<chapter id="Am 5">
			<pericope>A Lament and Call to Repentance</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Am 5:1">1</verse-number>Hear this word that I <supplied>am</supplied> going to intone over you <supplied>as</supplied> a lament, O house of Israel! <verse-number id="Am 5:2">2</verse-number>Virgin Israel has fallen and will not rise again. She is deserted on her land; there is no one to raise her up. <verse-number id="Am 5:3">3</verse-number>For thus says my Lord Yahweh, “The city that marches out <supplied>with</supplied> a thousand will <supplied>only</supplied> have a hundred left. And the one that marches out <supplied>with</supplied> a hundred will <supplied>only</supplied> have ten left for the house of Israel.” <verse-number id="Am 5:4">4</verse-number>For thus says Yahweh to the house of Israel, “Seek me so that you may live.” <verse-number id="Am 5:5">5</verse-number>But do not seek Bethel or go <supplied>to</supplied> Gilgal or cross over to Beersheba, for Gilgal will certainly go into exile and Bethel will come to disaster.” <verse-number id="Am 5:6">6</verse-number>Seek Yahweh so that you may live, so that he will not break out like a fire <supplied>against</supplied> the house of Joseph! And it will devour, <idiom-start/>with none to quench<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and there is not one to quench”</note> <supplied>it</supplied> for Bethel. <verse-number id="Am 5:7">7</verse-number><supplied>Ah,</supplied> you who turn justice into wormwood and hurl righteousness to the ground! <verse-number id="Am 5:8">8</verse-number>The one who made the Pleiades and Orion and who turns deep darkness into the morning and darkens day <supplied>into</supplied> night, the one who calls for the waters of the sea and pours them out on the surface of the earth, Yahweh <supplied>is</supplied> his name! <verse-number id="Am 5:9">9</verse-number>The one who makes destruction flash upon <supplied>the</supplied> fierce, <idiom-start/>so that<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and”</note> destruction comes upon <supplied>the</supplied> fortification. <verse-number id="Am 5:10">10</verse-number>They hate the one who reproves in the gate and they abhor the one who speaks honestly. <verse-number id="Am 5:11">11</verse-number>Therefore, because you trample on <supplied>the</supplied> poor and you take a grain tax from them, you built houses of dressed stone, but you will not live in them. You built vineyards of delightfulness, but you will not drink their wine. <verse-number id="Am 5:12">12</verse-number>For I know your transgressions <supplied>are</supplied> many and your sins <supplied>are</supplied> numerous, <supplied>you</supplied> foes of <supplied>the</supplied> righteous, those who take a bribe, and <idiom-start/>those who<idiom-end/><note>Literally “they”</note> push aside <supplied>the</supplied> poor <supplied>ones</supplied> in the gate! <verse-number id="Am 5:13">13</verse-number>Therefore, whoever has insight will keep silent in that time, for it <supplied>is</supplied> a time of evil. <verse-number id="Am 5:14">14</verse-number>Seek good and not bad in order that you may live, and so Yahweh, the God of hosts, will be with you, as you have said. <verse-number id="Am 5:15">15</verse-number>Hate evil and love good and establish justice in the gate; perhaps Yahweh, the God of hosts, will be gracious <supplied>to</supplied> the remnant of Joseph. <verse-number id="Am 5:16">16</verse-number>Therefore, thus says Yahweh, the God of hosts, my Lord, “In all <supplied>of</supplied> the public squares <supplied>there will be</supplied> wailing, and in all <supplied>of</supplied> the streets <supplied>they will say</supplied>, ‘Alas, alas, alas!’ They shall call <supplied>the</supplied> farmers to mourning and <supplied>to</supplied> wailing, to those who are skilled <supplied>in</supplied> lamentation. <verse-number id="Am 5:17">17</verse-number>And in all <supplied>of the</supplied> vineyards <supplied>there will be</supplied> wailing, because I will pass in your midst,” says Yahweh. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Day of Yahweh</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Am 5:18">18</verse-number>Alas, those who desire the day of Yahweh, why <supplied>is</supplied> this for you the day of Yahweh? It <supplied>will be</supplied> darkness and not light! <verse-number id="Am 5:19">19</verse-number><supplied>It will be</supplied> as <supplied>if</supplied> a man fled from a lion and a bear met him; or he went <supplied>into</supplied> the house and leaned his hand against the wall and a snake bit him. <verse-number id="Am 5:20">20</verse-number><supplied>Is</supplied> not the day of Yahweh darkness and not light, and pitch dark with no brightness in it? <verse-number id="Am 5:21">21</verse-number>“I hate, I despise your festivals, and I take no delight in your assemblies. <verse-number id="Am 5:22">22</verse-number>Yes, <supplied>even</supplied> if you offer me your burnt offerings and grain offerings, I will not accept <supplied>them</supplied>, and I will not look at the fellowship offerings of your fattened animals. <verse-number id="Am 5:23">23</verse-number>Remove from me the noise of your songs, and I do not want to hear the melody of your harps! <verse-number id="Am 5:24">24</verse-number>But let justice roll on like the water, and righteousness like an ever-flowing stream. <verse-number id="Am 5:25">25</verse-number>Did you bring to me sacrifices and offering<supplied>s</supplied> those forty years in the desert, O house of Israel? <verse-number id="Am 5:26">26</verse-number>And you will take up Sikkuth, your king, and Kaiwan, your images, the star of your gods which you made for yourselves. <verse-number id="Am 5:27">27</verse-number>And I will deport you beyond Damascus,” says Yahweh—the God of hosts <supplied>is</supplied> his name. </p>
		</chapter>