<chapter id="Am 6">
			<pericope>Woe to the Complacent</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Am 6:1">1</verse-number>Alas <supplied>for</supplied> those being at ease in Zion, and those who feel secure on Mount Samaria, the notables of the best of the nations! The house of Israel resorts to them. <verse-number id="Am 6:2">2</verse-number>Cross over <supplied>to</supplied> Calneh and see, and go from there <supplied>to</supplied> Hamath Rabbah and go down <supplied>to</supplied> Gath of the Philistines. <supplied>Are</supplied> you better than these kingdoms, or is their territory greater than your territory? <verse-number id="Am 6:3">3</verse-number>You that put off the day of disaster and bring near a reign of violence! <verse-number id="Am 6:4">4</verse-number><supplied>Alas for</supplied> those who lie on beds of ivory and lounge on their couches, and those eating young rams from <supplied>the</supplied> sheep and goats, and bull-calves from the middle of <supplied>the</supplied> animal stall. <verse-number id="Am 6:5">5</verse-number><supplied>Alas for those</supplied> who sing to the tune of the harp; like David they improvise on instruments of music. <verse-number id="Am 6:6">6</verse-number><supplied>Alas for those</supplied> who drink from sprinkling bowls of wine and anoint themselves with the best of olive oils and are not grieved over the ruin of Joseph. <verse-number id="Am 6:7">7</verse-number>Therefore, they shall now go into exile at the head of the exiles and the feast of lounging shall pass away. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Yahweh Abhors Israel’s Pride</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Am 6:8">8</verse-number>My Lord Yahweh has sworn by himself, <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh, the God of hosts: “I abhor the pride of Jacob and I hate his citadel fortresses and I will deliver <supplied>the</supplied> city and its fullness!” <verse-number id="Am 6:9">9</verse-number>And then if ten people remain in one house, they too will die. <verse-number id="Am 6:10">10</verse-number>And <supplied>if</supplied> one’s relative, who burns <supplied>the body</supplied>, lifts it up and brings the body out of the house and he will say to someone in the innermost part of the house, “<supplied>Are there</supplied> any more with you?” and he will say, “None,” then he will say, “Silence,” because <supplied>we</supplied> must not invoke the name of Yahweh. <verse-number id="Am 6:11">11</verse-number>Look, Yahweh <supplied>is</supplied> going to command and the great house will be destroyed <supplied>to</supplied> bits and the little house <supplied>to</supplied> pieces. <verse-number id="Am 6:12">12</verse-number>Do horses run on rocks, or does one plow the sea with oxen?<note>Or “does one plow them with oxen”</note> But you have turned justice into poison and <supplied>the</supplied> fruit of righteousness into wormwood! <verse-number id="Am 6:13">13</verse-number><supplied>You</supplied> who rejoice over Lo-Debar, who say, “Have we not taken Karnaim for ourselves by our strength?” <verse-number id="Am 6:14">14</verse-number>Indeed, I <supplied>am</supplied> going to raise up against you a nation, O house of Israel, <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh, the God of hosts. And they shall oppress you from Lebo-hamath up to the wadi of the Arabah. </p>
		</chapter>