<chapter id="1 Co 1">
			<pericope>Greeting</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 1:1">1</verse-number> Paul, called <supplied>to be</supplied> an apostle of Christ Jesus through the will of God, and Sosthenes our brother, <verse-number id="1 Co 1:2">2</verse-number>to the church of God sanctified in Christ Jesus that is in Corinth,<note>Some manuscripts have “to the church of God that is in Corinth, sanctified in Christ Jesus”</note> called <supplied>to be</supplied> saints, together with all those who call upon the name of our Lord Jesus Christ in every place, their <supplied>Lord</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “Lord” must be supplied to indicate the referent; otherwise this could be understood as “their place and ours”</note> and ours. <verse-number id="1 Co 1:3">3</verse-number>Grace to you and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Thanksgiving for the Corinthian Believers</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 1:4">4</verse-number>I give thanks to my God always concerning you, because of the grace of God which was given to you in Christ Jesus, <verse-number id="1 Co 1:5">5</verse-number>that<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Or “because”; the conjunction either (1) introduces a content clause (“that”) giving the content of Paul’s thanks, or (2) introduces a causal clause (“because”) giving the reason for Paul’s thanks</note> in everything you were made rich in him, in all speech and all knowledge, <verse-number id="1 Co 1:6">6</verse-number>just as the testimony about Christ has been confirmed in you, <verse-number id="1 Co 1:7">7</verse-number>so that you do not lack in any spiritual gift <supplied>as you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>as</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“eagerly await”) which is understood as temporal</note> eagerly await the revelation of our Lord Jesus Christ, <verse-number id="1 Co 1:8">8</verse-number>who will also confirm you until the end, blameless in the day of our Lord Jesus Christ. <verse-number id="1 Co 1:9">9</verse-number>God <supplied>is</supplied> faithful, by whom you were called to fellowship with his Son Jesus Christ our Lord. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Divisions in the Church at Corinth</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 1:10">10</verse-number>Now I exhort you, brothers, by the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, that you all say the same <supplied>thing</supplied> and there not be divisions among you, and that you be made complete in the same mind and with the same purpose. <verse-number id="1 Co 1:11">11</verse-number>For it has been made clear to me concerning you, my brothers, by <idiom-start/>Chloe’s people<idiom-end/><note>Literally “those of Chloe”</note>, that there are quarrels among you. <verse-number id="1 Co 1:12">12</verse-number>But I say this, that each of you is saying, “I am with Paul,” and “I <supplied>am</supplied> with Apollos,” and “I <supplied>am</supplied> with Cephas,” and “I <supplied>am</supplied> with Christ.” <verse-number id="1 Co 1:13">13</verse-number>Has Christ been divided? Paul was not crucified for you, was he?<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here</note> Or were you baptized in the name of Paul? <verse-number id="1 Co 1:14">14</verse-number>I give thanks<note>Some manuscripts have “I give thanks to God”</note> that I baptized none of you except Crispus and Gaius, <verse-number id="1 Co 1:15">15</verse-number>lest anyone should say that you were baptized in my name. <verse-number id="1 Co 1:16">16</verse-number>(Now I also baptized the household of Stephanas. Beyond that I do not know if I baptized anyone else.) <verse-number id="1 Co 1:17">17</verse-number>For Christ did not send me to baptize, but to proclaim the gospel, not with <idiom-start/>clever speech<idiom-end/><note>Literally “wisdom of word”</note>, lest the cross of Christ be emptied. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Christ Crucified, the Power and Wisdom of God</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 1:18">18</verse-number>For the message about the cross is foolishness to those who are perishing, but to us who are being saved it is the power of God. <verse-number id="1 Co 1:19">19</verse-number>For it is written, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“I will destroy the wisdom of the wise, </li1>
				<li2>and the intelligence of the intelligent I will confound.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 29:14">Isa 29:14</cite></note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 1:20">20</verse-number>Where <supplied>is</supplied> the wise person? Where <supplied>is</supplied> the scribe? Where <supplied>is</supplied> the debater of this age? Has not God made foolish the wisdom of the world? <verse-number id="1 Co 1:21">21</verse-number>For since, in the wisdom of God, the world through its wisdom did not know God, God was pleased through the foolishness of preaching to save those who believe. <verse-number id="1 Co 1:22">22</verse-number>For indeed, Jews ask for sign miracles and Greeks seek wisdom, <verse-number id="1 Co 1:23">23</verse-number>but we preach Christ crucified, to the Jews a cause for stumbling, but to the Gentiles foolishness, <verse-number id="1 Co 1:24">24</verse-number>but to those <supplied>who are</supplied> called, both Jews and Greeks, Christ <supplied>is</supplied> the power of God and the wisdom of God. <verse-number id="1 Co 1:25">25</verse-number>For the foolishness of God is wiser than human <supplied>wisdom</supplied>,<note>Literally “man”</note> and the weakness of God <supplied>is</supplied> stronger than human <supplied>strength</supplied>.<note>Literally “man”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Boast in the Lord</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 1:26">26</verse-number>For consider your calling, brothers, that not many <supplied>were</supplied> wise according to human standards,<note>Literally “according to flesh”</note> not many <supplied>were</supplied> powerful, not many <supplied>were</supplied> well born. <verse-number id="1 Co 1:27">27</verse-number>But the foolish <supplied>things</supplied> of the world God chose in order that he might put to shame the wise, and the weak <supplied>things</supplied> of the world God chose in order that he might put to shame the strong, <verse-number id="1 Co 1:28">28</verse-number>and the insignificant of the world, and the despised, God chose, the things that are not, in order that he might abolish the things that are, <verse-number id="1 Co 1:29">29</verse-number>so that all flesh may not boast before God. <verse-number id="1 Co 1:30">30</verse-number>But from him you are in Christ Jesus, who became wisdom to us from God, and righteousness and sanctification and redemption, <verse-number id="1 Co 1:31">31</verse-number>so that, just as it is written, “The one who boasts, let him boast in the Lord.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Je 9:24">Jer 9:24</cite></note> </p>
		</chapter>