<chapter id="1 Co 2">
			<pericope>Paul’s Approach to Ministry in Corinth</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 2:1">1</verse-number> And I, <supplied>when I</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“came”) which is understood as temporal</note> came to you, brothers, did not come with superiority of speech or of wisdom, proclaiming to you the testimony<note>Some manuscripts have “mystery”</note> of God. <verse-number id="1 Co 2:2">2</verse-number>For I decided not to know anything among you except Jesus Christ and him crucified. <verse-number id="1 Co 2:3">3</verse-number>And I came to you in weakness and in fear and with much trembling, <verse-number id="1 Co 2:4">4</verse-number>and my speech and my preaching <supplied>were</supplied> not with the persuasiveness<note>Some manuscripts have “with persuasive words”</note> of wisdom, but with a demonstration of the Spirit and power, <verse-number id="1 Co 2:5">5</verse-number>in order that your faith would not be in the wisdom of men, but in the power of God. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Wisdom Revealed by the Spirit</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 2:6">6</verse-number>Now we do speak wisdom among the mature, but wisdom not of this age or of the rulers of this age, who are perishing, <verse-number id="1 Co 2:7">7</verse-number>but we speak the hidden wisdom of God in a mystery, which God predestined before the ages for our glory, <verse-number id="1 Co 2:8">8</verse-number>which none of the rulers of this age knew. For if they had known <supplied>it</supplied>, they would not have crucified the Lord of glory. <verse-number id="1 Co 2:9">9</verse-number>But just as it is written, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“<supplied>Things</supplied> which eye has not seen and ear has not heard, </li1>
				<li2>and have not entered into the heart of man, </li2>
				<li1>all that<note>Some manuscripts have “which”</note> God has prepared for those who love him.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 64:4">Isa 64:4</cite></note> </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 2:10">10</verse-number>For<note>Some manuscripts have “But to us God has revealed <supplied>them</supplied>”</note> to us God has revealed <supplied>them</supplied> through the Spirit. For the Spirit searches all <supplied>things</supplied>, even the depths of God. <verse-number id="1 Co 2:11">11</verse-number>For who among men knows the things of a man, except the spirit of the man that <supplied>is</supplied> in him? Thus also no one knows the things of God except the Spirit of God. <verse-number id="1 Co 2:12">12</verse-number>Now we have received not the spirit of the world, but the Spirit who <supplied>is</supplied> from God, in order that we may know the things freely given to us by God, <verse-number id="1 Co 2:13">13</verse-number><supplied>things</supplied> which we also speak, not in words taught by human wisdom, but in <supplied>words</supplied> taught by the Spirit, explaining spiritual <supplied>things</supplied> to spiritual <supplied>people</supplied>.<note>Or “in spiritual <supplied>words</supplied>”</note> <verse-number id="1 Co 2:14">14</verse-number>But the natural man does not accept the things of the Spirit of God, for they are foolishness to him, and he is not able to understand <supplied>them</supplied>, because they are spiritually discerned. <verse-number id="1 Co 2:15">15</verse-number>Now the spiritual <supplied>person</supplied> discerns all <supplied>things</supplied>, but he himself is judged by no one. <verse-number id="1 Co 2:16">16</verse-number>“For who has known the mind of the Lord; who has advised him?”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 40:13">Isa 40:13</cite></note> But we have the mind of Christ. </p>
		</chapter>