<chapter id="1 Co 3">
			<pericope>Divisiveness and Immaturity</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 3:1">1</verse-number> And I, brothers, was not able to speak to you as to spiritual <supplied>people</supplied>, but as to fleshly <supplied>people</supplied>, as to infants in Christ. <verse-number id="1 Co 3:2">2</verse-number>I gave you milk to drink, not solid food, for you were not yet able <supplied>to eat it</supplied>. But now you are still not able, <verse-number id="1 Co 3:3">3</verse-number>for you are still fleshly. For where <supplied>there is</supplied> jealousy and strife among you, are you not fleshly, and do you not live like <supplied>unregenerate</supplied> people?<note>That is, like people who do not possess the Spirit at all</note> <verse-number id="1 Co 3:4">4</verse-number>For whenever anyone says, “I am with Paul,” and another, “I <supplied>am</supplied> with Apollos,” are you not <supplied>merely</supplied> human? </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 3:5">5</verse-number>Therefore, what is Apollos and what is Paul? Servants through whom you believed, and to each as the Lord gave. <verse-number id="1 Co 3:6">6</verse-number>I planted, Apollos watered, but God was causing <supplied>it</supplied> to grow. <verse-number id="1 Co 3:7">7</verse-number>So then, neither the one who plants nor the one who waters is anything, but God who is causing <supplied>it</supplied> to grow. <verse-number id="1 Co 3:8">8</verse-number>Now the one who plants and the one who waters are one, but each one will receive his own reward according to his own labor. <verse-number id="1 Co 3:9">9</verse-number>For we are God’s fellow workers; you are God’s field, God’s building. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 3:10">10</verse-number>According to the grace of God given to me, like a skilled master builder I laid a foundation, and another is building upon <supplied>it</supplied>. But each one must direct his attention to how he is building upon <supplied>it</supplied>. <verse-number id="1 Co 3:11">11</verse-number>For no one is able to lay another foundation than the one which is laid, which is Jesus Christ. <verse-number id="1 Co 3:12">12</verse-number>Now if anyone builds upon the foundation <supplied>with</supplied> gold, silver, precious stones, wood, grass, straw, <verse-number id="1 Co 3:13">13</verse-number>the work of each one will become evident. For the day will reveal <supplied>it</supplied>, because it will be revealed with fire, and the fire itself will test the work of each one, of what sort it is. <verse-number id="1 Co 3:14">14</verse-number>If anyone’s work that he has built upon <supplied>it</supplied> remains, he will receive a reward. <verse-number id="1 Co 3:15">15</verse-number>If anyone’s work is burned up, he will suffer loss, but he himself will be saved, but so as through fire. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 3:16">16</verse-number>Do you not know that you are God’s temple and the Spirit of God dwells in you? <verse-number id="1 Co 3:17">17</verse-number>If anyone destroys God’s temple, God will destroy this one. For God’s temple is holy, which you are. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 3:18">18</verse-number>Let no one deceive himself. If anyone thinks <supplied>himself</supplied> to be wise among you in this age, let him become a fool, in order that he may become wise. <verse-number id="1 Co 3:19">19</verse-number>For the wisdom of this world is foolishness with God, for it is written, “The one who catches the wise in their craftiness,”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Job 5:13">Job 5:13</cite></note> <verse-number id="1 Co 3:20">20</verse-number>and again, “The Lord knows the thoughts of the wise, that they are futile.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 94:11">Ps 94:11</cite></note> <verse-number id="1 Co 3:21">21</verse-number>So then, let no one boast in people. For all <supplied>things</supplied> are yours, <verse-number id="1 Co 3:22">22</verse-number>whether Paul or Apollos or Cephas or the world or life or death or things present or things to come, all <supplied>things</supplied> <supplied>are</supplied> yours, <verse-number id="1 Co 3:23">23</verse-number>and you <supplied>are</supplied> Christ’s, and Christ <supplied>is</supplied> God’s. </p>
		</chapter>