<chapter id="1 Co 5">
			<pericope>Immoral Behavior and Church Discipline</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 5:1">1</verse-number> It is reported everywhere <supplied>that there</supplied> is sexual immorality among you, and sexual immorality of such a kind which <supplied>does</supplied> not <supplied>even exist</supplied> among the Gentiles, so that someone has the wife of <supplied>his</supplied> father. <verse-number id="1 Co 5:2">2</verse-number>And you are inflated with pride, and should you not rather have mourned, so that the one who has done this deed would be removed from your midst? <verse-number id="1 Co 5:3">3</verse-number>For <supplied>although I</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>although</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“am absent”) which is understood as concessive</note> am absent in body but present in spirit, I have already passed judgment on the one who has done this in this way, as <supplied>if I</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>if</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“were present”) which is understood as conditional</note> were present. <verse-number id="1 Co 5:4">4</verse-number>In the name of our Lord Jesus, <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“are assembled”)</note> you are assembled, and my spirit, together with the power of our Lord Jesus, <verse-number id="1 Co 5:5">5</verse-number><supplied>I have decided</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The words “I have decided” are implied from the statement “I have already passed judgment” in v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:1 Co 5:3">3</cite></note> to hand over such a person to Satan for the destruction of the flesh, in order that his spirit may be saved in the day of the Lord. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 5:6">6</verse-number>Your boasting <supplied>is</supplied> not good. Do you not know that a little leaven leavens the whole batch of dough? <verse-number id="1 Co 5:7">7</verse-number>Clean out the old leaven in order that you may be a new batch of dough, just as you are unleavened. For Christ our Passover has been sacrificed. <verse-number id="1 Co 5:8">8</verse-number>So then, let us celebrate the feast, not with the old leaven or with the leaven of wickedness and sinfulness, but with the unleavened bread of sincerity and truth. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 5:9">9</verse-number>I wrote to you in the letter not to associate with sexually immoral people. <verse-number id="1 Co 5:10">10</verse-number>By no means <supplied>did I mean</supplied> the sexually immoral people of this world or the greedy people and swindlers or idolaters, since then you would have to depart out of the world. <verse-number id="1 Co 5:11">11</verse-number>But now I have written to you not to associate with any so-called brother, if he is a sexually immoral person or a greedy person or an idolater or an abusive person or a drunkard or a swindler—with such a person not even to eat. <verse-number id="1 Co 5:12">12</verse-number>For what <supplied>is it</supplied> to me to judge those outside? Should you not judge those inside? <verse-number id="1 Co 5:13">13</verse-number>But those outside God will judge. Remove the evil person <idiom-start/>from among yourselves<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from you of them”</note>. </p>
		</chapter>