<chapter id="1 Co 7">
			<pericope>Concerning Christian Marriage</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 7:1">1</verse-number> Now concerning <supplied>the things</supplied> about which you wrote: “<supplied>It is</supplied> good for a man not to touch<note>I.e., in a sexual sense</note> a woman.” <verse-number id="1 Co 7:2">2</verse-number>But because of sexual immorality, let each man have<note>I.e., in the sense of “have sexual relations with”</note> his own wife and let each woman have her own husband. <verse-number id="1 Co 7:3">3</verse-number>The husband must fulfill his obligation to his wife, and likewise also the wife to her husband. <verse-number id="1 Co 7:4">4</verse-number>The wife does not have authority over her own body, but her husband <supplied>does</supplied>. And likewise also the husband does not have authority over his own body, but his wife <supplied>does</supplied>. <verse-number id="1 Co 7:5">5</verse-number>Do not defraud one another, except perhaps by agreement, for a time, in order that you may devote yourselves to prayer, and <supplied>then</supplied> you should be <idiom-start/>together<idiom-end/><note>Literally “at the same”</note> again, lest Satan tempt you because of your lack of self control. <verse-number id="1 Co 7:6">6</verse-number>But I say this as a concession, not as a command. <verse-number id="1 Co 7:7">7</verse-number>I wish all people could be like myself, but each one has his own gift from God, one in this way and another in that way. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 7:8">8</verse-number>Now I say to the unmarried and to the widows: <supplied>It is</supplied> good for them if they remain as I <supplied>am</supplied>. <verse-number id="1 Co 7:9">9</verse-number>But if they cannot control themselves, they should marry, for it is better to marry than to burn <supplied>with sexual desire</supplied>. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 7:10">10</verse-number>To the married I command—not I, but the Lord—a wife must not separate from <supplied>her</supplied> husband. <verse-number id="1 Co 7:11">11</verse-number>But if indeed she does separate, she must remain unmarried or be reconciled to her husband. And a husband must not divorce <supplied>his</supplied> wife. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 7:12">12</verse-number>Now to the rest I say—not the Lord—if any brother has an unbelieving wife and she consents to live with him, he must not divorce her. <verse-number id="1 Co 7:13">13</verse-number>And if any wife has an unbelieving husband and he consents to live with her, she must not divorce her husband. <verse-number id="1 Co 7:14">14</verse-number>For the unbelieving husband is sanctified by his wife, and the unbelieving wife is sanctified by the brother, since otherwise your children are unclean, but now they are holy. <verse-number id="1 Co 7:15">15</verse-number>But if the unbeliever leaves, let him leave. The brother or the sister is not bound in such <supplied>cases</supplied>. But God has called us<note>Some manuscripts have “you” (plural)</note> in peace. <verse-number id="1 Co 7:16">16</verse-number>For how do you know, wife, whether you will save your husband? Or how do you know, husband, whether you will save your wife? </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 7:17">17</verse-number>But to each one as the Lord has apportioned. As God has called each one, thus let him live—and thus I order in all the churches. <verse-number id="1 Co 7:18">18</verse-number>Was anyone called <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“being circumcised”) which is understood as temporal</note> being circumcised? He must not undo his circumcision. Was anyone called in uncircumcision? He must not become circumcised. <verse-number id="1 Co 7:19">19</verse-number>Circumcision is nothing and uncircumcision is nothing, but the keeping of the commandments of God. <verse-number id="1 Co 7:20">20</verse-number>Each one in the calling in which he was called—in this he should remain. <verse-number id="1 Co 7:21">21</verse-number>Were you called <supplied>while</supplied> a slave? Do not let it be a concern to you. But if indeed you are able to become free, rather make use of <supplied>it</supplied>. <verse-number id="1 Co 7:22">22</verse-number>For the one who is called in the Lord <supplied>while</supplied> a slave is the Lord’s freedperson. Likewise the one who is called <supplied>while</supplied> free is a slave of Christ. <verse-number id="1 Co 7:23">23</verse-number>You were bought at a price; do not become slaves of men. <verse-number id="1 Co 7:24">24</verse-number>Each one in <supplied>the situation</supplied> in which he was called, brothers—in this he should remain with God. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Concerning the Unmarried</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 7:25">25</verse-number>Now concerning virgins I do not have a command from the Lord, but I am giving an opinion as one shown mercy by the Lord to be trustworthy. <verse-number id="1 Co 7:26">26</verse-number>Therefore, I consider this to be good because of the impending distress, that <supplied>it is</supplied> good for a man to be thus. <verse-number id="1 Co 7:27">27</verse-number>Are you bound to a wife? Do not seek release. Are you free from a wife? Do not seek a wife. <verse-number id="1 Co 7:28">28</verse-number>But if you marry, you have not sinned, and if the virgin marries, she has not sinned. But such people will have affliction in the flesh, and I would spare you. <verse-number id="1 Co 7:29">29</verse-number>But I say this, brothers: the time is shortened, that from now on even those who have wives should be as <supplied>if they</supplied> do not have <supplied>wives</supplied>, <verse-number id="1 Co 7:30">30</verse-number>and those who weep as <supplied>if they</supplied> do not weep, and those who rejoice as <supplied>if they</supplied> do not rejoice, and those who buy as <supplied>if they</supplied> do not possess, <verse-number id="1 Co 7:31">31</verse-number>and those who make use of the world as <supplied>if they</supplied> do not make full use of <supplied>it</supplied>. For the present form of this world is passing away. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 7:32">32</verse-number>But I want you to be free from care. The unmarried person cares for the things of the Lord, how he may please the Lord. <verse-number id="1 Co 7:33">33</verse-number>But the one who is married cares for the things of the world, how he may please his wife, <verse-number id="1 Co 7:34">34</verse-number>and he is divided. And the unmarried woman or the virgin cares for the things of the Lord, in order that she may be holy both in body and in spirit. But the married woman cares for the things of the world, how she may please her husband. <verse-number id="1 Co 7:35">35</verse-number>Now I am saying this for your own benefit, not that I may put a restriction on you, but to promote appropriate and devoted service to the Lord without distraction. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 7:36">36</verse-number>But if anyone thinks he is behaving dishonorably concerning his virgin, if she is past her prime<note>Or “if his passions are strong” (it is not clear in context whether this term refers to the man or to the woman)</note> and it ought to be thus, let him do what he wishes. He does not sin. Let them marry. <verse-number id="1 Co 7:37">37</verse-number>But he who stands firm in his heart, not having necessity, but has authority concerning his own will, and has decided this in his own heart, to keep his own virgin, he will do well. <verse-number id="1 Co 7:38">38</verse-number>So then, the one who marries<note>Or perhaps “the one who gives in marriage”</note> his own virgin does well, and the one who does not marry <supplied>her</supplied> will do better. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 7:39">39</verse-number>A wife is bound for as long a time <supplied>as</supplied> her husband lives. But if her husband <idiom-start/>dies<idiom-end/><note>Literally “falls asleep”</note>, she is free to marry whomever she wishes, only in the Lord. <verse-number id="1 Co 7:40">40</verse-number>But she is happier if she remains thus, according to my opinion—and I think I have the Spirit of God. </p>
		</chapter>