<chapter id="1 Co 8">
			<pericope>Concerning Food Sacrificed to Idols</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 8:1">1</verse-number> Now concerning food sacrificed to idols, we know that “we all have knowledge.”<note>Considered by many interpreters to be a slogan used by the Corinthians to justify their behavior</note> Knowledge puffs up, but love builds up. <verse-number id="1 Co 8:2">2</verse-number>If anyone thinks he knows anything, he has not yet known as it is necessary to know. <verse-number id="1 Co 8:3">3</verse-number>But if anyone loves God, this one is known by him. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 8:4">4</verse-number>Therefore, concerning the eating of food sacrificed to idols, we know that “an idol <supplied>is</supplied> nothing in the world” and that “<supplied>there is</supplied> no God except one.”<note>Considered by many interpreters to be slogans used by the Corinthians to justify their behavior</note> <verse-number id="1 Co 8:5">5</verse-number>For even if after all <supplied>there</supplied> are so-called gods, whether in heaven or on earth, just as <supplied>there</supplied> are many gods and many lords, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="1 Co 8:6">6</verse-number>yet to us <supplied>there is</supplied> one God, the Father, </li1>
				<li2>from whom <supplied>are</supplied> all <supplied>things</supplied>, and we <supplied>are</supplied> for him, </li2>
				<li1>and <supplied>there is</supplied> one Lord, Jesus Christ, </li1>
				<li2>through whom <supplied>are</supplied> all <supplied>things</supplied>, and we <supplied>are</supplied> through him. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 8:7">7</verse-number>But this knowledge <supplied>is</supplied> not in everyone. But some, being accustomed until now to the idol, eat <supplied>this food</supplied> as food sacrificed to idols, and their conscience, <supplied>because it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“is”) which is understood as causal</note> is weak, is defiled. <verse-number id="1 Co 8:8">8</verse-number>But food does not bring us close to God. For neither if we eat do we have more, nor if we do not eat do we lack.<note>Some manuscripts omit “For” and have “Neither if we do not eat do we lack, nor if we do eat do we have more”</note> <verse-number id="1 Co 8:9">9</verse-number>But watch out lest somehow this right of yours becomes a cause for stumbling to the weak. <verse-number id="1 Co 8:10">10</verse-number>For if someone should see you who has knowledge reclining for a meal in an idol’s temple, will not his conscience, <supplied>because it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“is”) which is understood as causal</note> is weak, be strengthened so that <supplied>he</supplied> eats the food sacrificed to idols? <verse-number id="1 Co 8:11">11</verse-number>For the one who is weak—the brother for whom Christ died—is destroyed by your knowledge. <verse-number id="1 Co 8:12">12</verse-number>Now <supplied>if you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>if</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“sin”) which is understood as conditional</note> sin in this way against the brothers and wound their conscience, which is weak, you sin against Christ. <verse-number id="1 Co 8:13">13</verse-number>Therefore, if food causes my brother to sin, I will never eat meat <idiom-start/>forever<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for the age”</note>, in order that I may not cause my brother to sin. </p>
		</chapter>