<chapter id="1 Co 9">
			<pericope>Paul Gives Up His Rights as an Apostle</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 9:1">1</verse-number> Am I not free? Am I not an apostle? Have I not seen Jesus our Lord? Are you not my work in the Lord? <verse-number id="1 Co 9:2">2</verse-number>If to others I am not an apostle, yet indeed I am to you, for you are my seal of apostleship in the Lord. <verse-number id="1 Co 9:3">3</verse-number>My defense to those who examine me is this: <verse-number id="1 Co 9:4">4</verse-number>Do we not have the right to eat and drink? <verse-number id="1 Co 9:5">5</verse-number>Do we not have the right to take along a sister <supplied>as</supplied> wife, like the rest of the apostles and the brothers of the Lord and Cephas? <verse-number id="1 Co 9:6">6</verse-number>Or do only I and Barnabas not have the right <idiom-start/>to refrain from working<idiom-end/><note>Literally “not to work”</note>? <verse-number id="1 Co 9:7">7</verse-number>Who ever serves as a soldier at his own expense? Who plants a vineyard and does not eat the fruit of it? Who<note>Some manuscripts have “Or who”</note> shepherds a flock and does not drink<note>Literally “eat”</note> from the milk of the flock? <verse-number id="1 Co 9:8">8</verse-number>I am not saying these <supplied>things</supplied> according to a human perspective. Or does the law not also say these <supplied>things</supplied>? <verse-number id="1 Co 9:9">9</verse-number>For in the law of Moses it is written, “You must not muzzle an ox <supplied>while it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“threshing”) which is understood as temporal</note> is threshing.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Dt 25:4">Deut 25:4</cite></note> It is not about oxen God is concerned, is it?<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here</note> <verse-number id="1 Co 9:10">10</verse-number>Or doubtless does he speak <idiom-start/>for our sake<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for the sake of us”</note>? For it is written <idiom-start/>for our sake<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for the sake of us”</note>, because the one who plows ought to plow in hope and the one who threshes <supplied>ought to do so</supplied> in hope of a share. <verse-number id="1 Co 9:11">11</verse-number>If we have sown spiritual <supplied>things</supplied> among you, <supplied>is it too</supplied> great <supplied>a thing</supplied> if we reap material <supplied>things</supplied> from you? <verse-number id="1 Co 9:12">12</verse-number>If others share this right over you, do we not <supplied>do so</supplied> even more? Yet we have not made use of this right, but we endure all <supplied>things</supplied>, in order that we may not cause any hindrance to the gospel of Christ. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 9:13">13</verse-number>Do you not know that those performing the holy services eat the things from the temple, <supplied>and</supplied> those attending to the altar have a share with the altar? <verse-number id="1 Co 9:14">14</verse-number>In the <supplied>same</supplied> way also the Lord ordered those who proclaim the gospel to live from the gospel. <verse-number id="1 Co 9:15">15</verse-number>But I have not made use of any of these <supplied>rights</supplied>. And I am not writing these <supplied>things</supplied> in order that it may be thus with me. For <supplied>it would be</supplied> better to me rather to die than <supplied>for</supplied> anyone to deprive me of my reason for boasting. <verse-number id="1 Co 9:16">16</verse-number>For if I proclaim the gospel, it is not to me a reason for boasting, for necessity is imposed on me. For woe is to me if I do not proclaim the gospel. <verse-number id="1 Co 9:17">17</verse-number>For if I do this voluntarily, I have a reward, but if <supplied>I do so</supplied> unwillingly, I have been entrusted with a stewardship. <verse-number id="1 Co 9:18">18</verse-number>What then is my reward? That <supplied>when I</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“proclaim the gospel”) which is understood as temporal</note> proclaim the gospel, I may offer the gospel free of charge, in order not to make full use of my right in the gospel. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 9:19">19</verse-number>For <supplied>although I</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>although</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“am”) which is understood as concessive</note> am free from all <supplied>people</supplied>, I have enslaved myself to all, in order that I may gain more. <verse-number id="1 Co 9:20">20</verse-number>I have become like a Jew to the Jews, in order that I may gain the Jews. To those under the law <supplied>I became</supplied> as under the law (<supplied>although I</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>although</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“am”) which is understood as concessive</note> myself am not under the law) in order that I may gain those under the law. <verse-number id="1 Co 9:21">21</verse-number>To those outside the law <supplied>I became</supplied> as outside the law (<supplied>although I</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>although</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“am”) which is understood as concessive</note> am not outside the law of God, but subject to the law of Christ) in order that I may gain those outside the law. <verse-number id="1 Co 9:22">22</verse-number>To the weak I became weak, in order that I may gain the weak. I have become all <supplied>things</supplied> to all <supplied>people</supplied>, in order that by all means I may save some. <verse-number id="1 Co 9:23">23</verse-number>I do all <supplied>this</supplied> for the sake of the gospel, in order that I may become a participant with it. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 9:24">24</verse-number>Do you not know that those who run in the stadium all run, but one receives the prize? Run in such a way that you may win. <verse-number id="1 Co 9:25">25</verse-number>And everyone who competes exercises self-control in all <supplied>things</supplied>. Thus those <supplied>do so</supplied> in order that they may receive a perishable crown, but we an imperishable <supplied>one</supplied>. <verse-number id="1 Co 9:26">26</verse-number>Therefore I run in this way, not as <supplied>running</supplied> aimlessly; I box in this way, not as beating the air. <verse-number id="1 Co 9:27">27</verse-number>But I discipline my body and subjugate <supplied>it</supplied>, lest somehow <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“preaching”) which is understood as temporal</note> preaching to others, <supplied>I</supplied> myself should become disqualified. </p>
		</chapter>