<chapter id="1 Co 10">
			<pericope>A History Lesson from Israel</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 10:1">1</verse-number> For I do not want you to be ignorant, brothers, that our fathers were all under the cloud and all went through the sea, <verse-number id="1 Co 10:2">2</verse-number>and all were baptized into Moses in the cloud and in the sea, <verse-number id="1 Co 10:3">3</verse-number>and all ate the same spiritual food, <verse-number id="1 Co 10:4">4</verse-number>and all drank the same spiritual drink. For they drank from the spiritual rock that followed <supplied>them</supplied>, and the rock was Christ. <verse-number id="1 Co 10:5">5</verse-number>But God was not pleased with the majority of them, for they were struck down in the desert. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 10:6">6</verse-number>Now these <supplied>things</supplied> happened <supplied>as</supplied> examples for us, so that we should not be desirers of evil <supplied>things</supplied>, just as those also desired <supplied>them</supplied>, <verse-number id="1 Co 10:7">7</verse-number>and not become idolaters, as some of them <supplied>did</supplied>, just as it is written, “The people sat down to eat and drink, and stood up to play,”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ex 32:6">Exod 32:6</cite></note> <verse-number id="1 Co 10:8">8</verse-number>nor commit sexual immorality, as some of them committed sexual immorality, and twenty-three thousand fell in one day, <verse-number id="1 Co 10:9">9</verse-number>nor put Christ to the test, as some of them tested <supplied>him</supplied>, and were destroyed by snakes, <verse-number id="1 Co 10:10">10</verse-number>nor grumble, just as some of them grumbled, and were destroyed by the destroyer. <verse-number id="1 Co 10:11">11</verse-number>Now these <supplied>things</supplied> happened to those <supplied>people</supplied> as an example, but are written for our instruction, on whom the ends of the ages have come. <verse-number id="1 Co 10:12">12</verse-number>Therefore, the one who thinks that he stands must watch out lest he fall. <verse-number id="1 Co 10:13">13</verse-number>Temptation has not come upon you except <supplied>what is</supplied> common to humanity. But God <supplied>is</supplied> faithful, who will not permit you to be tempted beyond what you are able, but will also make a way out together with the temptation, <supplied>so that you</supplied> may be able to endure <supplied>it</supplied>. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Warning Against Idolatry</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 10:14">14</verse-number>Therefore, my dear friends, flee from idolatry. <verse-number id="1 Co 10:15">15</verse-number>I am speaking as to sensible <supplied>people</supplied>; you judge what I am saying. <verse-number id="1 Co 10:16">16</verse-number>The cup of blessing which we bless, is it not a participation in the blood of Christ? The bread which we break, is it not a participation in the body of Christ? <verse-number id="1 Co 10:17">17</verse-number>Because <supplied>there is</supplied> one bread, <supplied>we</supplied> who <supplied>are</supplied> many are one body, for <supplied>we</supplied> all share from the one bread. <verse-number id="1 Co 10:18">18</verse-number>Consider Israel according to the flesh: are not the ones who eat the sacrifices sharers in the altar? <verse-number id="1 Co 10:19">19</verse-number>Therefore, what am I saying? That food sacrificed to idols is anything, or that an idol is anything? <verse-number id="1 Co 10:20">20</verse-number><supplied>No</supplied>, but that <supplied>the things</supplied> which they sacrifice, they sacrifice to demons and not to God, and I do not want you to become sharers with demons. <verse-number id="1 Co 10:21">21</verse-number>You are not able to drink the cup of the Lord and the cup of demons. You are not able to share the table of the Lord and the table of demons. <verse-number id="1 Co 10:22">22</verse-number>Or are we attempting to provoke the Lord to jealousy? We are not stronger than he <supplied>is, are we</supplied>?<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Freedom in Christ</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 10:23">23</verse-number>All <supplied>things</supplied> are permitted, but not all <supplied>things</supplied> are profitable. All <supplied>things</supplied> are permitted, but not all <supplied>things</supplied> build up. <verse-number id="1 Co 10:24">24</verse-number>Let no one seek <idiom-start/>his own good<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the <supplied>-</supplied> of himself”; “good” is implied</note> but the <supplied>good</supplied> of the other. <verse-number id="1 Co 10:25">25</verse-number>Eat everything that is sold in the meat market, <idiom-start/>asking no questions<idiom-end/><note>Literally “questioning nothing”</note> for the sake of the conscience, <verse-number id="1 Co 10:26">26</verse-number>for “the earth <supplied>is</supplied> the Lord’s, and its fullness.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 24:1">Ps 24:1, </cite>and an allusion to <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 50:12">Ps 50:12</cite>; <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 89:11">89:11</cite></note> <verse-number id="1 Co 10:27">27</verse-number>If any of the unbelievers invites you, and you want to go, eat everything that is set before you, <idiom-start/>asking no questions<idiom-end/><note>Literally “questioning nothing”</note> for the sake of the conscience. <verse-number id="1 Co 10:28">28</verse-number>But if someone says to you, “This is offered to idols,” do not eat <supplied>it</supplied>, for the sake of that one who informed <supplied>you</supplied> and the conscience. <verse-number id="1 Co 10:29">29</verse-number>Now I am not speaking about your own conscience, but the <supplied>conscience</supplied> of the other <supplied>person</supplied>. For why <supplied>is</supplied> my freedom judged by another’s conscience? <verse-number id="1 Co 10:30">30</verse-number>If I partake with thankfulness, why am I slandered concerning that for which I give thanks? </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 10:31">31</verse-number>Therefore, whether you eat or you drink or whatever you do, do all <supplied>things</supplied> for the glory of God. <verse-number id="1 Co 10:32">32</verse-number><idiom-start/>Give no offense<idiom-end/><note>Literally “be blameless”</note> both to Jews and to Greeks and to the church of God, <verse-number id="1 Co 10:33">33</verse-number>just as I also please all <supplied>people</supplied> in all <supplied>things</supplied>, not seeking my own benefit, but the <supplied>benefit</supplied> of the many, in order that they may be saved. </p>
		</chapter>