<chapter id="1 Co 11">
			<pericope>Concerning Head Coverings in Worship</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 11:1">1</verse-number> Become imitators of me, just as I also <supplied>am</supplied> of Christ. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 11:2">2</verse-number>Now I praise you that you remember me <supplied>in</supplied> all <supplied>things</supplied>, and just as I handed over to you the traditions, you hold fast to <supplied>them</supplied>. <verse-number id="1 Co 11:3">3</verse-number>But I want you to know that Christ is the head of every man, and the man <supplied>is the</supplied> head of the woman, and <supplied>the</supplied> head of Christ <supplied>is</supplied> God. <verse-number id="1 Co 11:4">4</verse-number>Every man who prays or prophesies <supplied>while</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“having”) which is understood as temporal</note> having <supplied>something</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object must be supplied from context, but the exact nature of the object is not clear from the context, so “<supplied>something</supplied>” is used in the English translation</note> on <supplied>his</supplied> head dishonors his head, <verse-number id="1 Co 11:5">5</verse-number>but every woman who prays or prophesies with uncovered head dishonors her head, for she is one and the same with the one whose <supplied>head</supplied> is shaved. <verse-number id="1 Co 11:6">6</verse-number>For if a woman does not cover herself, let her <supplied>hair</supplied> be shorn off. But if <supplied>it is</supplied> shameful for a woman to <supplied>have her head</supplied><note>Literally “to be”</note> shorn or shaved, let her cover her <supplied>head</supplied>.<note>Literally “herself”</note> <verse-number id="1 Co 11:7">7</verse-number>For indeed a man ought not to cover his head, <supplied>because he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“is”) which is understood as causal</note> is the image and glory of God, but the woman is the glory of the man. <verse-number id="1 Co 11:8">8</verse-number>For man is not from woman, but woman from man. <verse-number id="1 Co 11:9">9</verse-number>For indeed man was not created for the sake of the woman, but woman for the sake of the man. <verse-number id="1 Co 11:10">10</verse-number>Because of this, the woman ought to have <supplied>a symbol of</supplied> authority on her head, on account of the angels. <verse-number id="1 Co 11:11">11</verse-number>Nevertheless, neither <supplied>is</supplied> woman <supplied>anything</supplied> apart from man, nor <supplied>is</supplied> man <supplied>anything</supplied> apart from woman in the Lord. <verse-number id="1 Co 11:12">12</verse-number>For just as the woman <supplied>is</supplied> from the man, thus also the man <supplied>is</supplied> through the woman. But all <supplied>things</supplied> <supplied>are</supplied> from God. <verse-number id="1 Co 11:13">13</verse-number>You judge <idiom-start/>for yourselves<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in you yourselves”</note>: is it fitting for a woman to pray to God <supplied>with her head</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the words “<supplied>with her head</supplied>” have been supplied as a necessary clarification</note> uncovered? <verse-number id="1 Co 11:14">14</verse-number>And does not nature itself teach you that a man, if he wears long hair, it is a dishonor to him? <verse-number id="1 Co 11:15">15</verse-number>But a woman, if she wears long hair, it is her glory, because her hair is given<note>Some manuscripts have “is given to her”</note> for a covering. <verse-number id="1 Co 11:16">16</verse-number>But if anyone is disposed to be contentious, we have no such custom, nor do the churches of God. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Improper Conduct at the Lord’s Supper</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 11:17">17</verse-number>But in giving this instruction I do not praise <supplied>you</supplied>, because you come together not for the better but for the worse. <verse-number id="1 Co 11:18">18</verse-number>For in the first place, <supplied>when you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“come together”)</note> come together as a church, I hear there are divisions among you, and in part I believe it. <verse-number id="1 Co 11:19">19</verse-number>For indeed it is necessary that there be factions among you, in order that those who are approved may become evident among you. <verse-number id="1 Co 11:20">20</verse-number>Therefore, <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“come together”)</note> you come together in the same <supplied>place</supplied>, it is not to eat the Lord’s supper. <verse-number id="1 Co 11:21">21</verse-number>For <supplied>when you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “when” is supplied as a component of the temporal infinitive (“eat”)</note> eat <supplied>it</supplied>, each one of you goes ahead to take his own supper, and one is hungry and another is drunk. <verse-number id="1 Co 11:22">22</verse-number>For do you not have houses for eating and drinking? Or do you despise the church of God and humiliate those who do not have <supplied>anything</supplied>? What shall I say to you? Shall I praise you? In this I will not praise <supplied>you</supplied>! </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 11:23">23</verse-number>For I received from the Lord what I also passed on to you, that the Lord Jesus, on the night in which he was betrayed, took bread, <verse-number id="1 Co 11:24">24</verse-number>and <supplied>after he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had given thanks”) which is understood as temporal</note> had given thanks, he broke <supplied>it</supplied> and said, “This is my body which <supplied>is</supplied> for you. Do this in remembrance of me.” <verse-number id="1 Co 11:25">25</verse-number>Likewise also the cup, after they had eaten, saying, “This cup is the new covenant in my blood. Do this, as often as you drink <supplied>it</supplied>, in remembrance of me.” <verse-number id="1 Co 11:26">26</verse-number>For as often as you eat this bread and drink this cup, you proclaim the Lord’s death until he comes. <verse-number id="1 Co 11:27">27</verse-number>So then, whoever eats the bread or drinks the cup of the Lord in an unworthy manner will be guilty of the body and the blood of the Lord. <verse-number id="1 Co 11:28">28</verse-number>But let a person examine himself, and in this way let him eat from the bread and let him drink from the cup. <verse-number id="1 Co 11:29">29</verse-number>For the one who eats and drinks, <supplied>if he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>if</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“recognize”) which is understood as conditional</note> does not recognize the body, eats and drinks judgment against himself. <verse-number id="1 Co 11:30">30</verse-number>Because of this, many <supplied>are</supplied> weak and sick among you, and quite a few <idiom-start/>have died<idiom-end/><note>Literally “have fallen asleep”</note>. <verse-number id="1 Co 11:31">31</verse-number>But if we were evaluating ourselves, we would not be judged. <verse-number id="1 Co 11:32">32</verse-number>But <supplied>if we</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>if</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“are judged”) which is understood as conditional</note> are judged by the Lord, we are being disciplined, in order that we will not be condemned with the world. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 11:33">33</verse-number>So then, my brothers, <supplied>when you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“come together”) which is understood as temporal</note> come together in order to eat <supplied>the Lord’s supper</supplied>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the direct object (“the Lord’s supper”) is supplied from context in the English translation</note> wait for one another. <verse-number id="1 Co 11:34">34</verse-number>If anyone is hungry, let him eat at home, lest you come together for judgment. And I will give directions about the remaining <supplied>matters</supplied> whenever I come. </p>
		</chapter>