<chapter id="1 Co 12">
			<pericope>Varieties of Spiritual Gifts</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 12:1">1</verse-number> Now concerning spiritual <supplied>gifts</supplied>,<note>Or “spiritual <supplied>things</supplied>”; possibly “those who possess spiritual gifts”</note> brothers, I do not want you to be ignorant. <verse-number id="1 Co 12:2">2</verse-number>You know that when you were pagans, you were led astray to the speechless idols, however you were led. <verse-number id="1 Co 12:3">3</verse-number>Therefore I make known to you that no one speaking by the Spirit of God says, “Jesus <supplied>is</supplied> accursed,” and no one is able to say “Jesus <supplied>is</supplied> Lord” except by the Holy Spirit. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 12:4">4</verse-number>Now there are varieties of gifts, but the same Spirit, <verse-number id="1 Co 12:5">5</verse-number>and there are varieties of ministries, and the same Lord, <verse-number id="1 Co 12:6">6</verse-number>and there are varieties of activities, but the same God, who works all <supplied>things</supplied> in all <supplied>people</supplied>. <verse-number id="1 Co 12:7">7</verse-number>But to each one is given the manifestation of the Spirit for what is beneficial <supplied>to all</supplied>. <verse-number id="1 Co 12:8">8</verse-number>For to one is given a word of wisdom through the Spirit, and to another a word of knowledge by the same Spirit, <verse-number id="1 Co 12:9">9</verse-number>to another faith by the same Spirit, to another<note>Some manuscripts have “and to another”</note> gifts of healing by the one Spirit, <verse-number id="1 Co 12:10">10</verse-number>to another<note>Some manuscripts have “and to another”</note> <idiom-start/>miraculous powers<idiom-end/><note>Literally “activities of power”</note>, to another<note>Some manuscripts have “and to another”</note> prophecy, to another<note>Some manuscripts have “and to another”</note> distinguishing of spirits, to another kinds of tongues, to another<note>Some manuscripts have “and to another”</note> interpretation of tongues. <verse-number id="1 Co 12:11">11</verse-number>But in all these <supplied>things</supplied> one and the same Spirit is at work, distributing to each one individually just as he wishes. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Unity in the Midst of Diversity</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 12:12">12</verse-number>For just as the body is one and has many members, but all the members of the body, <supplied>although they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>although</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“are”) which is understood as concessive</note> are many, are one body, thus also Christ. <verse-number id="1 Co 12:13">13</verse-number>For by<note>Or “in”</note> one Spirit we were all baptized into one body, whether Jews or Greeks, whether slaves or free <supplied>persons</supplied>, and all were made to drink one Spirit. <verse-number id="1 Co 12:14">14</verse-number>For the body is not one member, but many. <verse-number id="1 Co 12:15">15</verse-number>If the foot should say, “Because I am not a hand, I am not <supplied>a part</supplied> of the body,” not because of this is it not <supplied>a part</supplied> of the body. <verse-number id="1 Co 12:16">16</verse-number>And if the ear should say, “Because I am not an eye, I am not <supplied>a part</supplied> of the body, not because of this is it not <supplied>a part</supplied> of the body. <verse-number id="1 Co 12:17">17</verse-number>If the whole body <supplied>were</supplied> an eye, where <supplied>would</supplied> the hearing <supplied>be</supplied>? If the whole <supplied>were</supplied> hearing, where <supplied>would</supplied> the sense of smell <supplied>be</supplied>? <verse-number id="1 Co 12:18">18</verse-number>But now God has placed the members, each one of them, in the body just as he wanted. <verse-number id="1 Co 12:19">19</verse-number>And if they all were one member, where <supplied>would</supplied> the body <supplied>be</supplied>? <verse-number id="1 Co 12:20">20</verse-number>But now <supplied>there are</supplied> many members, but one body. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 12:21">21</verse-number>Now the eye is not able to say to the hand, “I do not have need of you,” or again, the head to the feet, “I do not have need of you.” <verse-number id="1 Co 12:22">22</verse-number>But by much more the members of the body which are thought to be weaker are necessary, <verse-number id="1 Co 12:23">23</verse-number>and <supplied>the parts</supplied> of the body which we think to be less honorable, these we clothe with more abundant honor, and our unpresentable <supplied>parts</supplied> come to have more abundant presentability, <verse-number id="1 Co 12:24">24</verse-number>but our presentable <supplied>parts</supplied> do not have need <supplied>of this</supplied>. Yet God composed the body by giving more abundant honor to the part which lacked <supplied>it</supplied>, <verse-number id="1 Co 12:25">25</verse-number>in order that there not be a division in the body, but the members would have the same concern for one another. <verse-number id="1 Co 12:26">26</verse-number>And if one member suffers, all the members suffer together; if a member<note>Some manuscripts have “one member”</note> is honored, all the members rejoice with <supplied>it</supplied>. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 12:27">27</verse-number>Now you are the body of Christ, and members <idiom-start/>of it individually<idiom-end/><note>Literally “by part”</note>, <verse-number id="1 Co 12:28">28</verse-number>and whom God has appointed in the church: first, apostles, second, prophets, third, teachers, then miracles, then gifts of healing, helps, administrations, kinds of tongues. <verse-number id="1 Co 12:29">29</verse-number>Not all <supplied>are</supplied> apostles, <supplied>are they</supplied>?<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here</note> Not all <supplied>are</supplied> prophets, <supplied>are they</supplied>?<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here</note> Not all <supplied>are</supplied> teachers, <supplied>are they</supplied>?<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here</note> Not all <supplied>are workers of</supplied> miracles, <supplied>are they</supplied>?<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here</note> <verse-number id="1 Co 12:30">30</verse-number>Not all have gifts of healing, <supplied>do they</supplied>?<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here</note> Not all speak with tongues, <supplied>do they</supplied>?<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here</note> Not all interpret, <supplied>do they</supplied>?<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here</note> <verse-number id="1 Co 12:31">31</verse-number>But strive<note>Or “you are striving” (some understand the form of this verb to be indicative mood rather than imperative mood)</note> for the greater gifts. And I will show you a still more excellent way. </p>
		</chapter>