<chapter id="1 Co 13">
			<pericope>Love, the More Excellent Way</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 13:1">1</verse-number> If I speak with the tongues of men and of angels, but do not have love, I have become a ringing brass gong or a clashing cymbal. <verse-number id="1 Co 13:2">2</verse-number>And if I have <supplied>the gift of</supplied> prophecy and I know all mysteries and all knowledge, and if I have all faith so that <supplied>I can</supplied> remove mountains, but do not have love, I am nothing. <verse-number id="1 Co 13:3">3</verse-number>And if I parcel out all my possessions, and if I hand over my body in order that I will be burned,<note>Some manuscripts have “in order that I may boast”</note> but do not have love, it benefits <supplied>me</supplied> nothing. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 13:4">4</verse-number>Love is patient, love is kind, love is not jealous, <supplied>it</supplied> does not boast, <supplied>it</supplied> does not become conceited, <verse-number id="1 Co 13:5">5</verse-number><supplied>it</supplied> does not behave dishonorably, <supplied>it</supplied> <idiom-start/>is not selfish<idiom-end/><note>Literally “does not seek the things of itself”</note>, <supplied>it</supplied> does not become angry, <supplied>it</supplied> does not keep a record of wrongs, <verse-number id="1 Co 13:6">6</verse-number><supplied>it</supplied> does not rejoice at unrighteousness, but rejoices with the truth, <verse-number id="1 Co 13:7">7</verse-number>bears all <supplied>things</supplied>, believes all <supplied>things</supplied>, hopes all <supplied>things</supplied>, endures all <supplied>things</supplied>. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 13:8">8</verse-number>Love never ends. But if <supplied>there are</supplied> prophecies, they will pass away. If <supplied>there are</supplied> tongues, they will cease. If <supplied>there is</supplied> knowledge, it will pass away. <verse-number id="1 Co 13:9">9</verse-number>For we know in part and we prophesy in part, <verse-number id="1 Co 13:10">10</verse-number>but whenever the perfect comes, the partial will pass away. <verse-number id="1 Co 13:11">11</verse-number>When I was a child, I spoke like a child, I thought like a child, I reasoned like a child. When I became a man, I set aside the things of a child. <verse-number id="1 Co 13:12">12</verse-number>For now we see through a mirror <idiom-start/>indirectly<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in an indirect image”</note>, but then face to face. Now I know in part, but then I will know completely, just as I have also been completely known. <verse-number id="1 Co 13:13">13</verse-number>And now these three <supplied>things</supplied> remain: faith, hope, <supplied>and</supplied> love. But the greatest of these <supplied>is</supplied> love. </p>
		</chapter>