<chapter id="1 Co 14">
			<pericope>Appropriate Use of Prophecy and Tongues</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 14:1">1</verse-number> Pursue love, and strive for spiritual <supplied>gifts</supplied>, but especially that you may prophesy. <verse-number id="1 Co 14:2">2</verse-number>For the one who speaks in a tongue does not speak to people but to God, because no one understands, but by the Spirit<note>Or “in the Spirit”; or “in <supplied>his</supplied> spirit”</note> he speaks mysteries. <verse-number id="1 Co 14:3">3</verse-number>But the one who prophesies speaks to people edification and encouragement and consolation. <verse-number id="1 Co 14:4">4</verse-number>The one who speaks in a tongue edifies himself, but the one who prophesies edifies the church. <verse-number id="1 Co 14:5">5</verse-number>Now I want you all to speak with tongues, but even more that you may prophesy. The one who prophesies <supplied>is</supplied> greater than the one who speaks with tongues, unless he interprets, in order that the church may receive edification. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 14:6">6</verse-number>But now, brothers, if I come to you speaking with tongues, how do I benefit you, unless I speak to you either with a revelation or with knowledge or with a prophecy or with a teaching? <verse-number id="1 Co 14:7">7</verse-number>Likewise, the inanimate things which produce a sound, whether flute or lyre, if they do not produce a distinction in the tones, how will it be known what is played on the flute or on the lyre? <verse-number id="1 Co 14:8">8</verse-number>For indeed, if the trumpet produces an indistinct sound, who will prepare for battle? <verse-number id="1 Co 14:9">9</verse-number>And so you through the tongue, unless you produce a clear message, how will it be known what is spoken? For you will be speaking into the air. <verse-number id="1 Co 14:10">10</verse-number>There are probably so many kinds of languages in the world, and none without meaning. <verse-number id="1 Co 14:11">11</verse-number>Therefore, if I do not know the meaning of the language, I will be a barbarian to the one who is speaking, and the one who is speaking <supplied>will be</supplied> a barbarian in my <supplied>judgment</supplied>. <verse-number id="1 Co 14:12">12</verse-number>In this way also you, since you are zealous of spiritual <supplied>gifts</supplied>, seek for the edification of the church, in order that you may abound. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 14:13">13</verse-number>Therefore the one who speaks in a tongue must pray that he may interpret. <verse-number id="1 Co 14:14">14</verse-number>For if I pray in a tongue, my spirit prays but my mind is unproductive. <verse-number id="1 Co 14:15">15</verse-number><idiom-start/>Therefore what should I do<idiom-end/><note>Literally “what therefore is it”</note>? I will pray with my spirit, but I will also pray with my mind. I will sing praise with my spirit, but I will also sing praise with my mind. <verse-number id="1 Co 14:16">16</verse-number>For otherwise, if you praise in <supplied>your</supplied> spirit, how will the one who fills the place of the outsider say the “amen” at your thanksgiving, because he does not know what you are saying? <verse-number id="1 Co 14:17">17</verse-number>For indeed you are giving thanks well, but the other person is not edified. <verse-number id="1 Co 14:18">18</verse-number>I give thanks to God <supplied>that</supplied> I speak with tongues more than all of you, <verse-number id="1 Co 14:19">19</verse-number>but in the church I prefer to speak five words with my mind, in order that I may instruct other <supplied>people</supplied>, than ten thousand words in a tongue. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 14:20">20</verse-number>Brothers, do not become children in <supplied>your</supplied> understanding, but with respect to wickedness be as a child, and in <supplied>your</supplied> understanding be mature. <verse-number id="1 Co 14:21">21</verse-number>In the law it is written: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“By those who speak a foreign language </li1>
				<li2>and by the lips of others </li2>
				<li1>I will speak to this people, </li1>
				<li2>and not even in this way will they obey me,”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 28:11–12">Isa 28:11–12</cite></note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p>says the Lord. <verse-number id="1 Co 14:22">22</verse-number>So then, tongues are for a sign not to those who believe, but to unbelievers, but prophecy <supplied>is</supplied> not for unbelievers, but for those who believe. <verse-number id="1 Co 14:23">23</verse-number>Therefore, if the whole church comes together at the same <supplied>time</supplied> and all speak with tongues, and outsiders or unbelievers enter, will they not say that you are out of your minds? <verse-number id="1 Co 14:24">24</verse-number>But if all prophesy, and some unbeliever or outsider enters, he is convicted by all, he is judged by all, <verse-number id="1 Co 14:25">25</verse-number>the secret things of his heart become evident, and so, falling on <supplied>his</supplied> face, he will worship God, proclaiming, “God is truly among you!” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Specific Instructions for Orderly Worship Services</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 14:26">26</verse-number><idiom-start/>Therefore what should you do<idiom-end/><note>Literally “what therefore is it”</note>, brothers? Whenever you come together, each one of you has a psalm, has a teaching, has a revelation, has a tongue, has an interpretation. All <supplied>things</supplied> must be <supplied>done</supplied> for edification. <verse-number id="1 Co 14:27">27</verse-number>If anyone speaks in a tongue, <supplied>it must be</supplied> on one occasion two or at most three, and <idiom-start/>one after the other<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in turn”</note>, and one must interpret. <verse-number id="1 Co 14:28">28</verse-number>But if there is no interpreter, he must be silent in the church, but let him speak to himself and to God. <verse-number id="1 Co 14:29">29</verse-number>Let two or three prophets speak, and the others evaluate. <verse-number id="1 Co 14:30">30</verse-number>And if <supplied>something</supplied> is revealed to another who is seated, the first must be silent. <verse-number id="1 Co 14:31">31</verse-number>For you are all able to prophesy <idiom-start/>in turn<idiom-end/><note>Literally “one at a time</note>, in order that all may learn and all may be encouraged, <verse-number id="1 Co 14:32">32</verse-number>and the spirits of prophets are subject to prophets. <verse-number id="1 Co 14:33">33</verse-number>For God is not <supplied>a God of</supplied> disorder but of peace. </p>
			<p>As in all the churches of the saints, <verse-number id="1 Co 14:34">34</verse-number>the women must be silent in the churches, for it is not permitted for them to speak, but they must be in submission, just as the law also says. <verse-number id="1 Co 14:35">35</verse-number>But if they want to learn something, let them ask their own husbands at home, for it is shameful for a woman to speak in church. <verse-number id="1 Co 14:36">36</verse-number>Or has the word of God gone out from you, or has it come to you only? </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 14:37">37</verse-number>If anyone thinks he is a prophet or spiritual,<note>Or “or one who possesses the Spirit”</note> he should recognize that <supplied>the things</supplied> which I am writing to you are of the Lord.<note>Some manuscripts have “are a command of the Lord”</note> <verse-number id="1 Co 14:38">38</verse-number>But if anyone ignores <supplied>this</supplied>, he is ignored.<note>Or “if anyone is ignorant, let him be ignorant”</note> <verse-number id="1 Co 14:39">39</verse-number>So then, my brothers, desire to prophesy, and do not prevent speaking with tongues. <verse-number id="1 Co 14:40">40</verse-number>But let all <supplied>things</supplied> be <supplied>done</supplied> decently and according to proper procedure. </p>
		</chapter>