<chapter id="1 Co 15">
			<pericope>Paul’s Gospel and the Resurrection of Christ</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 15:1">1</verse-number> Now I make known to you, brothers, the gospel which I proclaimed to you, which you have also received, in which you also stand, <verse-number id="1 Co 15:2">2</verse-number>by which you are also being saved, if you hold fast to the message I proclaimed to you, unless you believed to no purpose. <verse-number id="1 Co 15:3">3</verse-number>For I passed on to you <idiom-start/>as of first importance<idiom-end/><note>Literally “among the first <supplied>things</supplied>”</note> what I also received, that Christ died for our sins according to the scriptures, <verse-number id="1 Co 15:4">4</verse-number>and that he was buried, and that he was raised up on the third day according to the scriptures, <verse-number id="1 Co 15:5">5</verse-number>and that he appeared to Cephas, then to the twelve, <verse-number id="1 Co 15:6">6</verse-number>then he appeared to more than five hundred brothers at once, the majority of whom remain until now, but some have fallen asleep. <verse-number id="1 Co 15:7">7</verse-number>Then he appeared to James, then to all the apostles, <verse-number id="1 Co 15:8">8</verse-number>and last of all, as it were to one born at the wrong time, he appeared also to me. <verse-number id="1 Co 15:9">9</verse-number>For I am the least of the apostles, not worthy to be called an apostle, because I persecuted the church of God. <verse-number id="1 Co 15:10">10</verse-number>But by the grace of God I am what I am, and his grace to me has not been in vain, but I labored even more than all of them, and not I, but the grace of God with me. <verse-number id="1 Co 15:11">11</verse-number>Therefore whether I or those, in this way we preached, and in this way you believed. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Concerning the Resurrection of the Dead</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 15:12">12</verse-number>Now if Christ is preached as raised up from the dead, how do some among you say that <supplied>there</supplied> is no resurrection of the dead? <verse-number id="1 Co 15:13">13</verse-number>But if <supplied>there</supplied> is no resurrection of the dead, Christ has not been raised <supplied>either</supplied>. <verse-number id="1 Co 15:14">14</verse-number>But if Christ has not been raised, then<note>Some manuscripts have “then both”</note> our preaching <supplied>is</supplied> in vain, and your faith <supplied>is</supplied> in vain. <verse-number id="1 Co 15:15">15</verse-number>And also we are found <supplied>to be</supplied> false witnesses of God, because we testified against God that he raised Christ, whom he did not raise if after all, then, the dead are not raised. <verse-number id="1 Co 15:16">16</verse-number>For if the dead are not raised, Christ has not been raised <supplied>either</supplied>. <verse-number id="1 Co 15:17">17</verse-number>But if Christ has not been raised, your faith <supplied>is</supplied> empty; you are still in your sins. <verse-number id="1 Co 15:18">18</verse-number>And as a further result, those who have fallen asleep in Christ have perished. <verse-number id="1 Co 15:19">19</verse-number>If <idiom-start/>we have put our hope<idiom-end/><note>Literally “we are having put our hope”</note> in Christ in this life only, we are of all people most pitiable. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 15:20">20</verse-number>But now Christ has been raised from the dead, the first fruits of those who have fallen asleep. <verse-number id="1 Co 15:21">21</verse-number>For since through a man <supplied>came</supplied> death, also through a man <supplied>came</supplied> the resurrection of the dead. <verse-number id="1 Co 15:22">22</verse-number>For just as in Adam all die, so also in Christ all will be made alive. <verse-number id="1 Co 15:23">23</verse-number>But each in his own group: Christ the first fruits, then those <supplied>who are</supplied> Christ’s at his coming, <verse-number id="1 Co 15:24">24</verse-number>then the end, when he hands over the kingdom to the God and Father, when he has abolished all rule and all authority and power. <verse-number id="1 Co 15:25">25</verse-number>For it is necessary for him to reign until he has put all his enemies under his feet. <verse-number id="1 Co 15:26">26</verse-number>The last enemy to be abolished <supplied>is</supplied> death. <verse-number id="1 Co 15:27">27</verse-number>For “he subjected all <supplied>things</supplied> under his feet.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 8:6">Ps 8:6</cite></note> But when it says “all <supplied>things</supplied>” are subjected, <supplied>it is</supplied> clear that the one who subjected all <supplied>things</supplied> to him <supplied>is</supplied> not included. <verse-number id="1 Co 15:28">28</verse-number>But whenever all <supplied>things</supplied> are subjected to him, then the Son himself will be subjected<note>Some manuscripts have “also will be subjected”</note> to the one who subjected all <supplied>things</supplied> to him, in order that God may be all in all. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 15:29">29</verse-number>Otherwise, why do they do <supplied>it</supplied>, those who are being baptized on behalf of the dead? If the dead are not raised at all, why indeed are they being baptized on behalf of them? <verse-number id="1 Co 15:30">30</verse-number>And why are we in danger every hour? <verse-number id="1 Co 15:31">31</verse-number>I die every day—yes indeed, by my boasting in you,<note>Some manuscripts have “in you, brothers,”</note> which I have in Christ Jesus our Lord! <verse-number id="1 Co 15:32">32</verse-number>If according to a human perspective I fought wild beasts at Ephesus, what benefit <supplied>is it</supplied> to me? If the dead are not raised, let us eat and drink, for tomorrow we die.<note>An allusion to <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 22:13">Isa 22:13</cite>; <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 56:12">56:12</cite></note> <verse-number id="1 Co 15:33">33</verse-number>Do not be deceived! “Bad company corrupts good morals.”<note>A quotation from the Greek poet Menander’s comedy <i>Thais</i>, 218</note> <verse-number id="1 Co 15:34">34</verse-number>Sober up correctly and <idiom-start/>stop sinning<idiom-end/><note>Literally “do not sin”</note>, for some have no knowledge of God—I say <supplied>this</supplied> to your shame. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Questions Concerning the Resurrection Body</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 15:35">35</verse-number>But someone will say, “How are the dead raised? And with what sort of body do they come?” <verse-number id="1 Co 15:36">36</verse-number>Foolish person! What you sow does not come to life unless it dies. <verse-number id="1 Co 15:37">37</verse-number>And what you sow <supplied>is</supplied> not the body which it will become, but you sow the bare seed, whether perhaps of wheat or of some of the rest. <verse-number id="1 Co 15:38">38</verse-number>But God gives to it a body just as he wishes, and to each one of the seeds its own body. <verse-number id="1 Co 15:39">39</verse-number>Not all flesh <supplied>is</supplied> the same, but <supplied>there is</supplied> one flesh of human beings, and another flesh of animals, and another flesh of birds, and another of fish, <verse-number id="1 Co 15:40">40</verse-number>and heavenly bodies and earthly bodies. But the glory of the heavenly <supplied>bodies</supplied> <supplied>is</supplied> of one kind, and the <supplied>glory</supplied> of the earthly <supplied>bodies</supplied> <supplied>is</supplied> of another kind. <verse-number id="1 Co 15:41">41</verse-number><supplied>There is</supplied> one glory of the sun, and another glory of the moon, and another glory of the stars, for star differs from star in glory. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 15:42">42</verse-number>Thus also <supplied>is</supplied> the resurrection of the dead. It is sown in corruption, it is raised in incorruptibility. <verse-number id="1 Co 15:43">43</verse-number>It is sown in dishonor, it is raised in glory. It is sown in weakness, it is raised in power. <verse-number id="1 Co 15:44">44</verse-number>It is sown a natural body, it is raised a spiritual body. If <supplied>there</supplied> is a natural body, <supplied>there</supplied> is also a spiritual <supplied>body</supplied>. <verse-number id="1 Co 15:45">45</verse-number>Thus also it is written, “The first man, Adam, became a living soul”;<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ge 2:7">Gen 2:7</cite></note> the last Adam <supplied>became</supplied> a life-giving spirit. <verse-number id="1 Co 15:46">46</verse-number>But the spiritual <supplied>is</supplied> not first, but the natural; then the spiritual. <verse-number id="1 Co 15:47">47</verse-number>The first man <supplied>is</supplied> from the earth, made of earth; the second man <supplied>is</supplied> from heaven. <verse-number id="1 Co 15:48">48</verse-number>As the one <supplied>who is</supplied> made of earth, so also <supplied>are</supplied> those <supplied>who are</supplied> made of earth, and as the heavenly, so also <supplied>are</supplied> those <supplied>who are</supplied> heavenly. <verse-number id="1 Co 15:49">49</verse-number>And just as we have borne the image of the <supplied>one who is</supplied> made of earth, we will also bear the image of the heavenly. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 15:50">50</verse-number>But I say this, brothers, that flesh and blood is not able to inherit the kingdom of God, nor can corruption inherit incorruptibility. <verse-number id="1 Co 15:51">51</verse-number>Behold, I tell you a mystery: we will not all fall asleep, but we will all be changed, <verse-number id="1 Co 15:52">52</verse-number>in a moment, in the blink of an eye, at the last trumpet. For the trumpet will sound, and the dead will be raised imperishable, and we will be changed. <verse-number id="1 Co 15:53">53</verse-number>For it is necessary <supplied>for</supplied> this perishable <supplied>body</supplied> to put on incorruptibility, and this mortal <supplied>body</supplied> to put on immortality. <verse-number id="1 Co 15:54">54</verse-number>But whenever this perishable <supplied>body</supplied> puts on incorruptibility and this mortal <supplied>body</supplied> puts on immortality, then the saying that is written will take place: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Death is swallowed up in victory. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="1 Co 15:55">55</verse-number>Where, O death, <supplied>is</supplied> your victory? </li1>
				<li1>Where, O death, <supplied>is</supplied> your sting? </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Co 15:56">56</verse-number>Now the sting of death <supplied>is</supplied> sin, and the power of sin <supplied>is</supplied> the law. <verse-number id="1 Co 15:57">57</verse-number>But thanks <supplied>be</supplied> to God, who gives us the victory through our Lord Jesus Christ! <verse-number id="1 Co 15:58">58</verse-number>So then, my dear brothers, be steadfast, immovable, always abounding in the work of the Lord, <supplied>because you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“know”) which is understood as causal</note> know that your labor is not <supplied>in</supplied> vain in the Lord. </p>
		</chapter>