<chapter id="2 Ki 1">
			<pericope>Elijah and the Messengers of Ahaziah</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ki 1:1">1</verse-number>Moab rebelled against Israel after the death of Ahab. <verse-number id="2 Ki 1:2">2</verse-number>Ahaziah had fallen through the lattice in his upper room, which <supplied>was</supplied> in Samaria, and he was injured. So he sent messengers, and he said to them, “Go, inquire of Baal-Zebub, the god of Ekron, if I will survive this injury.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ki 1:3">3</verse-number>Then the angel of Yahweh spoke to Elijah the Tishbite, “Get up, go up to meet the messengers of the king of Samaria and speak to them, ‘Is it because there is no God in Israel that you <supplied>are</supplied> going to inquire of Baal-Zebub, the god of Ekron?’ <verse-number id="2 Ki 1:4">4</verse-number>Therefore, thus says Yahweh, ‘The bed upon which you have gone, you will not come down from it, but you shall surely die.’ ” So Elijah went. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ki 1:5">5</verse-number>When the messengers returned to him, he asked them, “Why have you returned?” <verse-number id="2 Ki 1:6">6</verse-number>Then they said to him, “A man came up to meet us, and he said to us, ‘Go, return to the king who sent you and speak to him, “Thus says Yahweh, ‘Is it because there is no God in Israel that you <supplied>are</supplied> sending to inquire of Baal-Zebub the god of Ekron? Therefore the bed upon which you have gone, you will not come down from it, for you will surely die.’ ” ’ ” <verse-number id="2 Ki 1:7">7</verse-number>Then he spoke to them, “What <supplied>was</supplied> the manner of the man who came up to meet you and spoke to you all these things?” <verse-number id="2 Ki 1:8">8</verse-number>They answered him, “A <idiom-start/>hairy man<idiom-end/><note>Literally “an owner of hair”</note> with a leather belt girded around his waist.” And he said, “It <supplied>is</supplied> Elijah the Tishbite.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ki 1:9">9</verse-number>So <idiom-start/>Ahaziah<idiom-end/><note>Literally “he”</note> sent to him the commander of fifty with his fifty <supplied>men</supplied>, and he went up to him while he was sitting on the top of the hill. He said to him, “<supplied>O</supplied> man of God, the king says, ‘Come down.’ ” <verse-number id="2 Ki 1:10">10</verse-number>Then Elijah answered and said to the commander of the fifty, “If I <supplied>am</supplied> a man of God, let fire come down from heaven and consume you and your fifty!” Then fire came down from heaven and consumed him and his fifty. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ki 1:11">11</verse-number>So he <idiom-start/>again sent<idiom-end/><note>Literally “returned and sent”</note> another commander of fifty and his fifty <supplied>men</supplied>. He answered and said to him, “<supplied>O</supplied> man of God, thus says the king, ‘Come down quickly!’ ” <verse-number id="2 Ki 1:12">12</verse-number>Then Elijah answered and said to them, “If I <supplied>am</supplied> a man of God, then let fire come down from heaven and consume you and your fifty!” Then the fire of God came down from heaven and consumed him and his fifty. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ki 1:13">13</verse-number>So he <idiom-start/>again sent<idiom-end/><note>Literally “returned and sent”</note> a third <supplied>time</supplied> a commander of fifty and his fifty, and the commander of the third fifty went up and came and knelt down on his knees before Elijah and entreated him. He said to him, “<supplied>O</supplied> man of God, please let my life and the lives of your servants, these fifty, be precious in your eyes. <verse-number id="2 Ki 1:14">14</verse-number>Behold, fire from heaven came down and consumed the first two commanders of fifty and their fifties, so then let my life be precious in your eyes.” <verse-number id="2 Ki 1:15">15</verse-number>Then the angel of Yahweh spoke to Elijah, “Go down with him. Do not be afraid because of him.” So he got up and went down with him to the king, <verse-number id="2 Ki 1:16">16</verse-number>and he said to him, “Thus says Yahweh, ‘Because you have sent messengers to inquire of Baal-Zebub, the god of Ekron—is it because there is no God in Israel <supplied>from whom</supplied> to inquire his word?—therefore the bed upon which you went, you shall not come down from it, for you shall surely die.’ ” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Epitaph for Ahaziah</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ki 1:17">17</verse-number>So he died, according to the word of Yahweh which Elijah had spoken, and Joram became king in his place in the second year of Joram the son of Jehoshaphat, the king of Judah, because he had no son. <verse-number id="2 Ki 1:18">18</verse-number>The remainder of the acts of Ahaziah which he did, <supplied>are</supplied> they not written in the scroll of the events of the days of the kings of Israel? </p>
		</chapter>