<chapter id="2 Ki 7">
			<pericope>Elisha Prophesies Hope for Relief</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ki 7:1">1</verse-number>Elisha said, “Hear the word of Yahweh: ‘Thus says Yahweh, “At this time tomorrow a seah of wheat bread flour <supplied>will sell</supplied> for a shekel, and two seahs of barley for a shekel in the gate of Samaria.’ ” <verse-number id="2 Ki 7:2">2</verse-number>Then the officer <idiom-start/>on whom the king relied<idiom-end/><note>Literally “whom the king was leaning on his hand”</note> answered the man of God and said, “Look, <supplied>even if</supplied> Yahweh <supplied>is</supplied> making windows in heaven, could this thing happen?” And he said, “Look, you <supplied>will be</supplied> seeing <supplied>it</supplied> with your eyes, but you shall not eat from it there.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Four Lepers Report the Departure of the Arameans</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ki 7:3">3</verse-number>Now four men who had a skin disease were <supplied>at</supplied> the entrance of the gate, and they said <idiom-start/>to each other<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “each to his friend”</note> “Why <supplied>are</supplied> we sitting here until we die? <verse-number id="2 Ki 7:4">4</verse-number>If we say, ‘Let us go <supplied>into</supplied> the city,’ the famine <supplied>is</supplied> in the city, and we shall die there; but if we sit here, we shall die. So then, come, let us fall into the camp of <supplied>the</supplied> Arameans. If they let us live, we shall live; but if they kill us, then we shall die.” <verse-number id="2 Ki 7:5">5</verse-number>So they got up at dusk to go to the camp of <supplied>the</supplied> Arameans. They went up to the edge of the camp of <supplied>the</supplied> Arameans, and look, there was no man there! <verse-number id="2 Ki 7:6">6</verse-number>Now the Lord had caused the camp of <supplied>the</supplied> Arameans to hear the sound of chariots, the sound of horses, and the sound of a great army. So they said <idiom-start/>to one another<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “each to his brother”</note> “Look, the king of Israel has hired the kings of the Hittites and the kings of Egypt to come against us!” <verse-number id="2 Ki 7:7">7</verse-number>So they got up and fled at dusk and left their tents, their horses, their donkeys, and the camp as it was, and they fled for their lives. <verse-number id="2 Ki 7:8">8</verse-number>When these who had the skin disease came to the edge of the camp, they went into a certain tent and they ate, drank, and took from there silver and gold and clothes. Then they went and hid <supplied>them</supplied>, then returned and came to another tent, and they took from there and went and hid <supplied>them</supplied>. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ki 7:9">9</verse-number>Then they said <idiom-start/>to one another<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “each to his friend”</note> “We <supplied>are</supplied> not doing right. This day is a day of good news! If we <supplied>are</supplied> silent and wait until the light of morning, they will find us and <idiom-start/>we will be punished<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “guiltiness”</note> So then, come, let us go and tell the house of the king.” <verse-number id="2 Ki 7:10">10</verse-number>When they came, they called to the gatekeepers of the city and told them, saying, “We came to the camp of <supplied>the</supplied> Arameans, and behold, there was no man or the voice of a man there! Only the horses and the donkeys were tied up, and the tents <supplied>were left</supplied> as they <supplied>were</supplied>.” <verse-number id="2 Ki 7:11">11</verse-number>Then the gatekeepers called and told <supplied>it</supplied> inside the house of the king. <verse-number id="2 Ki 7:12">12</verse-number>The king got up in the night and said to his servants, “Please let me tell you what <supplied>the</supplied> Arameans have done to us. <supplied>The</supplied> Arameans know that we <supplied>are</supplied> hungry, so they went out from the camp to hide in the field, saying, ‘When they go out from the city, we shall seize them alive and go into the city.’ ” <verse-number id="2 Ki 7:13">13</verse-number>Then one of his servants replied and said, “Please let them take five of the remaining horses which remain in <supplied>the city</supplied>; behold, they <supplied>are</supplied> like all of the multitude of Israel that remain in it; they are like all the multitude of Israel who have perished. Let us send and see.” <verse-number id="2 Ki 7:14">14</verse-number>So he took two charioteer horsemen, and the king sent after the camp of <supplied>the</supplied> Arameans, saying, “Go, find out,” <verse-number id="2 Ki 7:15">15</verse-number>and they went after them to the Jordan. Look, all of the way <supplied>was</supplied> littered with clothes and equipment which <supplied>the</supplied> Arameans had thrown away in their haste. Then the messengers returned and told the king. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Prophecy Fulfilled</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ki 7:16">16</verse-number>So the people went out and plundered the camp of <supplied>the</supplied> Arameans. A seah of wheat flour <supplied>went</supplied> for a shekel and two seahs of barley <supplied>went</supplied> for a shekel according to the word of Yahweh. <verse-number id="2 Ki 7:17">17</verse-number>Then the king appointed the officer he was depending on over the gate, but the people trampled him and he died, according to that which the man of God had said which he spoke when the king came down to him. <verse-number id="2 Ki 7:18">18</verse-number>It happened as the man of God spoke to the king, saying, “Two seahs of barley <supplied>shall be sold</supplied> for a shekel and a seah of wheat flour for a shekel at this time tomorrow in the gate of Samaria.” <verse-number id="2 Ki 7:19">19</verse-number>Then the officer had replied to the man of God and said, “Look, even if Yahweh is opening the windows in heaven, could this thing happen?” And he had said, “Look you <supplied>are about to</supplied> see it with your eyes, but you will not eat from it.” <verse-number id="2 Ki 7:20">20</verse-number>So it had happened to him; the people trampled him in the gate and he died. </p>
		</chapter>