<chapter id="2 Ki 13">
			<pericope>Jehoahaz and Jehoash in Israel</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ki 13:1">1</verse-number>In the twenty-third year of Joash the son of Ahaziah, king of Judah, Jehoahaz the son of Jehu became king over Israel in Samaria, <supplied>reigning</supplied> seventeen years. <verse-number id="2 Ki 13:2">2</verse-number>But he did evil in the eyes of Yahweh, and he went after the sins of Jeroboam the son of Nebat with which he had caused Israel to sin, and he did not depart from it. <verse-number id="2 Ki 13:3">3</verse-number>So the <idiom-start/>anger of Yahweh was kindled<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the nose of Yahweh became hot”</note> against Israel, and he gave them into the hand of Hazael king of Aram and into the hand of Ben-Hadad the son of Hazael <idiom-start/>repeatedly<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “all the days”</note> <verse-number id="2 Ki 13:4">4</verse-number>Then Jehoahaz entreated Yahweh, and Yahweh listened to him, for he saw the oppression of Israel, because the king of Aram oppressed them. <verse-number id="2 Ki 13:5">5</verse-number>Yahweh gave Israel a savior, and they went out from under the hand of Aram. So the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> lived in their tents as <idiom-start/>formerly<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “as yesterday and the day before”</note> <verse-number id="2 Ki 13:6">6</verse-number>Yet they did not depart from the sins of the house of Jeroboam which he caused Israel to sin, but walked in it; and also, the pole of the Asherah worship was <supplied>still</supplied> standing in Samaria. <verse-number id="2 Ki 13:7">7</verse-number>For there was no army left over for Jehoahaz except for fifty horsemen, ten chariots, and ten thousand infantry, for the king of Aram had destroyed them and made them as the dust at threshing. <verse-number id="2 Ki 13:8">8</verse-number>Now the remainder of the acts of Jehoahaz and all that he did and his powerful <supplied>deeds, are</supplied> they not written in the scroll of the events of the days of the kings of Israel? <verse-number id="2 Ki 13:9">9</verse-number>Then Jehoahaz slept with his ancestors<note>Or “fathers”</note> and they buried him in Samaria, and Jehoash his son became king in his place. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ki 13:10">10</verse-number>In the thirty-seventh year of Joash king of Judah, Jehoash the son of Jehoahaz became king over Israel in Samaria, <supplied>reigning</supplied> sixteen years. <verse-number id="2 Ki 13:11">11</verse-number>He did evil in the eyes of Yahweh; he did not depart from all of the sins of Jeroboam the son of Nebat which he caused Israel to sin, <supplied>but</supplied> walked in it. <verse-number id="2 Ki 13:12">12</verse-number>The remainder of the acts of Joash<note>That is, the king of Israel rather than the king of Judah; “Jehoash” and “Joash” are variant spellings of one another</note> and all that he did, his powerful <supplied>deeds</supplied>, and how he fought with Amaziah king of Judah, <supplied>are</supplied> they not written in the scroll of the events of the days of the kings of Israel? <verse-number id="2 Ki 13:13">13</verse-number>Then Joash slept with his ancestors,<note>Or “fathers”</note> and Jeroboam sat on his throne. Joash was buried in Samaria with the kings of Israel. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Elisha Passes Away</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ki 13:14">14</verse-number>Elisha became ill with the illness with which he would die, so Jehoash king of Israel went down to him and wept before him, and said, “My father, my father; the chariot of Israel and its horsemen!” <verse-number id="2 Ki 13:15">15</verse-number>Elisha said to him, “Take a bow and arrows,” so he took him a bow and arrows. <verse-number id="2 Ki 13:16">16</verse-number>He said to the king of Israel, “<idiom-start/>Lay your hand on the bow<idiom-end/>,”<note>Literally “Let your hand climb upon the bow”</note> so he lay hold <supplied>of it</supplied>; then Elisha put his hand on the hands of the king. <verse-number id="2 Ki 13:17">17</verse-number>Then he said, “Open the window to the east,” so he opened <supplied>it</supplied>. Elisha said, “Shoot,” and he shot. Then he said, “An arrow of victory for Yahweh, and an arrow of victory against Aram; you shall fight the Arameans in Aphek until finishing <supplied>them</supplied>.” <verse-number id="2 Ki 13:18">18</verse-number>Then he said, “Take the arrows,” so he took <supplied>them</supplied>. He said to the king of Israel, “Strike the ground,” so he struck three times and stopped. <verse-number id="2 Ki 13:19">19</verse-number><supplied>Yet</supplied> the man of God became angry against him and said, “For striking five or six times, then you would have defeated Aram until finishing <supplied>them</supplied>, but now you will defeat Aram <supplied>only</supplied> three times.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ki 13:20">20</verse-number>Elisha died and they buried him. Now the raiding parties of Moab came <idiom-start/>in the spring<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “coming year”</note> <verse-number id="2 Ki 13:21">21</verse-number>And it happened that they <supplied>were</supplied> burying a man; suddenly they saw the marauding band, so they threw the man in the grave of Elisha. <supplied>As he</supplied> went <supplied>in</supplied>, the man touched the bones of Elisha, and became alive and got up on his feet! </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ki 13:22">22</verse-number>Hazael king of Aram oppressed Israel all the days of Jehoahaz. <verse-number id="2 Ki 13:23">23</verse-number>But Yahweh had mercy on them and showed compassion to them and turned to them because of his covenant with Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob. He was not willing to destroy them nor cast them from his presence up to now. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ki 13:24">24</verse-number>When Hazael king of Aram died, his son Ben-Hadad became king in his place. <verse-number id="2 Ki 13:25">25</verse-number>Jehoash the son of Jehoahaz returned and took the cities from the hand of Ben-Hadad the son of Hazael which he had taken from the hand of Jehoahaz his father in the war. Three times Jehoash defeated him and recovered the towns of Israel. </p>
		</chapter>