<chapter id="2 Ki 18">
			<pericope>Hezekiah Reigns in Judah</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ki 18:1">1</verse-number>It happened in the third year of Hoshea the son of Elah king of Israel, that Hezekiah the son of Ahaz king of Judah became king. <verse-number id="2 Ki 18:2">2</verse-number>He was twenty-five years old when he became king, and he reigned twenty-nine years in Jerusalem. The name of his mother was Abi, the daughter of Zechariah. <verse-number id="2 Ki 18:3">3</verse-number>He did right in the eyes of Yahweh according to all that David his ancestor<note>Or “father”</note> had done. <verse-number id="2 Ki 18:4">4</verse-number>He removed the high places, and he smashed the stone pillars; he cut down the poles of Asherah worship and demolished the bronze serpent which Moses had made, for up to those days the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> were offering incense to it and called it Nehushtan. <verse-number id="2 Ki 18:5">5</verse-number>He trusted in Yahweh the God of Israel; there was no one like him, before or after, among all the kings of Judah. <verse-number id="2 Ki 18:6">6</verse-number>He held on to Yahweh; he did not depart from following him, and he kept his commands that Yahweh had commanded Moses. <verse-number id="2 Ki 18:7">7</verse-number>Yahweh was with him; everywhere he went, he succeeded. He rebelled against the king of Assyria and did not serve him. <verse-number id="2 Ki 18:8">8</verse-number>He attacked <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines up to Gaza and its territory from the watchtower up to the fortified city. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ki 18:9">9</verse-number>It happened in the fourth year of King Hezekiah, that <supplied>is,</supplied> the seventh year of Hoshea the son of Elah king of Israel, Shalmaneser king of Assyria came against Samaria and laid siege against her. <verse-number id="2 Ki 18:10">10</verse-number>At the end of three years, he captured it in the sixth year of Hezekiah, that <supplied>is,</supplied> the ninth year of Hoshea king of Israel; Samaria was captured. <verse-number id="2 Ki 18:11">11</verse-number>Then the king of Assyria deported Israel to Assyria and settled them in Halah, in Habor, <supplied>in</supplied> the river <supplied>regions</supplied> of Gozan, and <supplied>in</supplied> the cities of the Medes, <verse-number id="2 Ki 18:12">12</verse-number>because they did not listen to the voice of Yahweh their God, and they transgressed his covenant; all that he had commanded Moses, the servant of Yahweh, they did not listen <supplied>to</supplied> nor did they obey. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Sennacherib of Assyria Invades Judah</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ki 18:13">13</verse-number>In the fourteenth year of King Hezekiah, Sennacherib king of Assyria came up against all of the fortified cities of Judah and captured them. <verse-number id="2 Ki 18:14">14</verse-number>So Hezekiah king of Judah sent <supplied>word</supplied> to the king of Assyria at Lachish, saying, “I have done wrong. Withdraw from me. What you impose on me I will bear.” So the king of Assyria imposed on Hezekiah king of Judah three hundred talents of silver and thirty talents of gold. <verse-number id="2 Ki 18:15">15</verse-number>Then Hezekiah gave all of the silver found <supplied>in</supplied> the temple of Yahweh and in the storerooms of the house of the king. <verse-number id="2 Ki 18:16">16</verse-number>At that time, Hezekiah cut off the doors of the temple of Yahweh and the doorposts which Hezekiah king of Judah had overlaid, and he gave them to the king of Assyria. <verse-number id="2 Ki 18:17">17</verse-number>So the king of Assyria sent the commander in chief, the chief eunuch, and the <idiom-start/>chief advisor<idiom-end/><note>Traditionally “Rabshekah”</note> from Lachish to King Hezekiah at Jerusalem with a heavy army. They went up and came <supplied>to</supplied> Jerusalem, then they went up and came and stood at the aqueduct of the upper pool which is on the main road of the <idiom-start/>washer’s<idiom-end/><note>Or “fuller’s”</note> field. <verse-number id="2 Ki 18:18">18</verse-number>Then they called to the king, so Eliakim the son of Hilkiah who <supplied>was</supplied> over the palace, Shebna the secretary, and Joah the son of Asaph the recorder, came out to them. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Assyrians Advise against Trust in Yahweh</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ki 18:19">19</verse-number>Then the chief advisor said to them, “Please say to Hezekiah: ‘Thus says the great king, the king of Assyria: “What <supplied>is</supplied> this confidence that you trust? <verse-number id="2 Ki 18:20">20</verse-number>You think only a word of lips, ‘<supplied>I have</supplied> advice and power for the war.’ Now, on whom do you trust that you have rebelled against me? <verse-number id="2 Ki 18:21">21</verse-number>Now, look! You <idiom-start/>rely<idiom-end/><note>Literally “trust for yourself”</note> on the staff of this broken reed, on Egypt, which <supplied>when</supplied> a man leans on it, it goes into his hand and pierces it! So <supplied>is</supplied> Pharaoh the king of Egypt for all who are trusting on him! <verse-number id="2 Ki 18:22">22</verse-number>But if you say to me, ‘On Yahweh our God we trust,’ <supplied>is</supplied> it not he whose high places and altars Hezekiah removed, and he had said to Judah and to Jerusalem, ‘In the presence of this altar you shall bow down <supplied>only</supplied> in Jerusalem?’ <verse-number id="2 Ki 18:23">23</verse-number>So then, please make a wager with my lord, with the king of Assyria, and I will give to you a thousand horses <idiom-start/>if you are able on your part to put riders on them.<idiom-end/><note>Literally “if you are able to give for yourself riders upon them”</note> <verse-number id="2 Ki 18:24">24</verse-number>How <idiom-start/>can you repulse a single captain among the least of the servants of my master<idiom-end/><note>Literally “can you return the face of the governor one of the servants of my master”</note>? <supplied>Yet</supplied> you rely for yourself on Egypt for chariots and horsemen! <verse-number id="2 Ki 18:25">25</verse-number>Have I now come up against this place without Yahweh to destroy it? Yahweh has said to me, ‘Go up against this land and destroy it!’ ” ’ ” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ki 18:26">26</verse-number>Then Eliakim the son of Hilkiah and Shebna and Joah said to the chief commander, “Please speak to your servants in Aramaic, for we <supplied>are</supplied> understanding, but you must not speak Judean with us in the ears of the people who <supplied>are</supplied> on the wall.” <verse-number id="2 Ki 18:27">27</verse-number>The chief commander said to them, “Is it <supplied>solely</supplied> to your master and to you my master has sent me to speak these words? <supplied>Is</supplied> it not for the men who sit on the wall to eat their feces and to drink their urine with you?” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ki 18:28">28</verse-number>Then the chief commander stood and called with a great voice in Judean, and he spoke and said, “Hear the word of the king, the great king of Assyria! <verse-number id="2 Ki 18:29">29</verse-number>Thus says the king, ‘Do not let Hezekiah deceive you, for he will not be able to rescue you from my<note>Hebrew “his”</note> hand. <verse-number id="2 Ki 18:30">30</verse-number>Do not let Hezekiah <supplied>make you</supplied> trust in Yahweh, saying, “Certainly Yahweh will rescue us, and this city shall not be given into the hand of the king of Assyria!” ’ <verse-number id="2 Ki 18:31">31</verse-number>Do not listen to Hezekiah; for thus says the king of Assyria, ‘Make with me a treaty of peace and come out to me that each <supplied>may</supplied> eat <supplied>from</supplied> his vine and each <supplied>from</supplied> his fig tree, and each <supplied>may</supplied> drink water <supplied>from</supplied> his cistern! <verse-number id="2 Ki 18:32">32</verse-number>Until I come and take you to a land like your land, a land of grain and new wine, a land of bread and vineyards, a land of olive trees, olive oil, and honey, that <supplied>you may</supplied> live and not die! You must not listen to Hezekiah, for he has misled you <supplied>by</supplied> saying, “Yahweh will deliver us!” <verse-number id="2 Ki 18:33">33</verse-number>Did the gods of each of the nations ever rescue the land from the hand of the king of Assyria? <verse-number id="2 Ki 18:34">34</verse-number>Where <supplied>are</supplied> the gods of Hamath and Arpad? Where <supplied>are</supplied> the gods of Sepharvaim, Hena, and Ivvah? For did they rescue Samaria from my hand? <verse-number id="2 Ki 18:35">35</verse-number>Who among all of the gods of the countries have rescued their countries from my hand that Yahweh should rescue Jerusalem from my hand?’ ” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ki 18:36">36</verse-number>The people were silent, and they did not answer him a word, for the command of that king was saying, “You shall not answer him.” <verse-number id="2 Ki 18:37">37</verse-number>Eliakim the son of Hilkiah who was over the palace, and Shebna the secretary, and Joah the son of Asaph the recorder came to Hezekiah <supplied>with</supplied> torn clothes, and they told him the words of the chief commander. </p>
		</chapter>