<chapter id="2 Ki 19">
			<pericope>Isaiah Sends Encouragement to Hezekiah</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ki 19:1">1</verse-number>It happened that when King Hezekiah heard, he tore his clothes and covered himself with sackcloth and went <supplied>to</supplied> the temple of Yahweh. <verse-number id="2 Ki 19:2">2</verse-number>He sent Eliakim who <supplied>was</supplied> over the palace, Shebna the secretary, the elders, and the priests, <supplied>all</supplied> clothed in sackcloth, to Isaiah the prophet the son of Amoz. <verse-number id="2 Ki 19:3">3</verse-number>They said to him, “Thus says Hezekiah, ‘A day of distress, rebuke, and disgrace is this day, for the children <idiom-start/>are about to be born<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “came up to the outer vagina”</note> but there is no strength to bear them. <verse-number id="2 Ki 19:4">4</verse-number>Perhaps Yahweh your God will hear all of the words of <supplied>the</supplied> chief commander whom his master the king of Assyria has sent to insult <supplied>the</supplied> living God, and he will rebuke the words which Yahweh your God has heard. Therefore lift up a prayer for the remainder who are left.’ ” <verse-number id="2 Ki 19:5">5</verse-number>So the servants of King Hezekiah came to Isaiah, <verse-number id="2 Ki 19:6">6</verse-number>and Isaiah said to them, “Thus you must say to your master, ‘Thus says Yahweh, “You must not be afraid because the face of the words which you have heard, <supplied>with</supplied> which the servants of the king of Assyria have reviled me. <verse-number id="2 Ki 19:7">7</verse-number>Look, I <supplied>am</supplied> putting in him a spirit. He will hear a rumor and return to his land. Then I will cause him to fall by the sword in his land.” ’ ” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Assyrians Defy God</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ki 19:8">8</verse-number>When <supplied>the</supplied> chief commander returned, he found the king of Assyria fighting against Libnah, for he had heard that he had departed from Lachish. <verse-number id="2 Ki 19:9">9</verse-number>He heard about Tirhakah, the king of Cush, saying, “Look, he has set out to fight with you,” so he again sent messengers to Hezekiah, saying, <verse-number id="2 Ki 19:10">10</verse-number>“Thus you shall say to Hezekiah the king of Judah, ‘Let not your God whom you <supplied>are</supplied> trusting deceive you, by his saying, “Jerusalem shall not be given into the hand of the king of Assyria!” <verse-number id="2 Ki 19:11">11</verse-number>Look, you have heard what the kings of Assyria have done to all the lands, by utterly destroying them, and shall you be delivered? <verse-number id="2 Ki 19:12">12</verse-number>Did the gods of the nations that my <idiom-start/>predecessors<idiom-end/><note>Literally “fathers”</note> destroyed deliver them? <supplied>Not</supplied> Gozan, Haran, Rezeph, <supplied>nor</supplied> the children of Eden who <supplied>were</supplied> in Tel Assar. <verse-number id="2 Ki 19:13">13</verse-number>Where are the king of Hamath, the king of Arpad, the king of the city of Sepharvaim, Hena, and Ivvah?’ ” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Hezekiah Prays to Yahweh</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ki 19:14">14</verse-number>Hezekiah took the letters from the hand of the messengers and read them. <supplied>Then</supplied> he went up to the temple of Yahweh, and Hezekiah spread them out before the presence of Yahweh. <verse-number id="2 Ki 19:15">15</verse-number>Then Hezekiah prayed before the face of Yahweh and said, “O Yahweh, God of Israel who lives <supplied>above</supplied> the cherubim. You <supplied>are</supplied> God, you alone, of all the kingdoms of the world; you have made the heavens and the earth. <verse-number id="2 Ki 19:16">16</verse-number>Incline your ears and hear; open, O Yahweh, your eyes and see and hear the words of Sennacherib which he has sent to insult the living God. <verse-number id="2 Ki 19:17">17</verse-number>Truly, O Yahweh, the kings of Assyria have utterly destroyed the nations and their land. <verse-number id="2 Ki 19:18">18</verse-number>He has hurled their gods in the fire because they <supplied>are</supplied> not gods, but the work of the hands of a human <supplied>made of</supplied> wood and stone, so they destroyed them. <verse-number id="2 Ki 19:19">19</verse-number>So then, O Yahweh our God, rescue us, please, from his hand, that all of the kingdoms of the earth may know that you, O Yahweh, you alone are God!” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Isaiah Brings a Prophetic Response</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ki 19:20">20</verse-number>Then Isaiah the son of Amoz sent to Hezekiah, saying, “Thus says Yahweh the God of Israel, ‘What you have prayed to me about Sennacherib king of Assyria I have heard. <verse-number id="2 Ki 19:21">21</verse-number>This is the word that Yahweh has spoken concerning him: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>She despises you, she scorns you, </li1>
				<li2>the virgin daughter of Zion. </li2>
				<li1>Behind you the daughter of Jerusalem </li1>
				<li2>shakes <supplied>her</supplied> head. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="2 Ki 19:22">22</verse-number>Whom have you mocked and reviled? </li1>
				<li2>And against whom have you have raised <supplied>your</supplied> voice </li2>
				<li1>and have haughtily lifted your eyes? </li1>
				<li2>Against the Holy One of Israel! </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="2 Ki 19:23">23</verse-number>By the hand of your messengers you have mocked the Lord, </li1>
				<li2>and you have said, </li2>
				<li1>‘With my many chariots I have gone up </li1>
				<li2><supplied>to</supplied> the height of the mountains. </li2>
				<li1><supplied>To</supplied> the remote areas of Lebanon, </li1>
				<li2>I have felled the tallest of its cedars, </li2>
				<li2>the choicest of its cypresses. </li2>
				<li1>I have entered the place of overnight lodging. </li1>
				<li2>Even <supplied>to</supplied> the edge of forest of its fertile land. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="2 Ki 19:24">24</verse-number>I dug <supplied>wells</supplied> and I drank foreign water, </li1>
				<li2>and I dried up with the sole of my steps </li2>
				<li2>all the canals of Egypt.’ </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="2 Ki 19:25">25</verse-number>Have you not heard? </li1>
				<li2>From long ago I have determined it, </li2>
				<li2>from the days of old I have planned it, </li2>
				<li2>and now I am bringing it to pass. </li2>
				<li1>It shall be turned into a pile of rocks; </li1>
				<li2>fortified cities are ruined. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="2 Ki 19:26">26</verse-number>Their inhabitants, short of hand, shall be dismayed; </li1>
				<li2>and they shall be ashamed. </li2>
				<li1>They have become green plants of the open field, </li1>
				<li2>and tender grass, </li2>
				<li2>green grass of the roof </li2>
				<li2>and blight before the standing grain. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="2 Ki 19:27">27</verse-number>Your sitting, your going out, and your coming <supplied>in</supplied> I know, </li1>
				<li2>and your raging against me. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="2 Ki 19:28">28</verse-number>Because you are raging against me, </li1>
				<li2>and your arrogance has come up in my ears, </li2>
				<li1>I will put my nose ring in your nose </li1>
				<li2>and my bridle in your mouth. </li2>
				<li1>And I will turn you back </li1>
				<li2>on the way that you have come. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ki 19:29">29</verse-number>“ ‘This will be the sign for you: Eat the volunteer plants for the year, and in the second year, the volunteer plants that spring up from that. But <supplied>in</supplied> the third year, sow and reap, plant vineyards and eat their fruit. <verse-number id="2 Ki 19:30">30</verse-number>The remainder of the house of Judah which survives will again <supplied>take</supplied> root below and bear fruit above. <verse-number id="2 Ki 19:31">31</verse-number>For from Jerusalem a remnant shall go out and survivors from Mount Zion; the zeal of Yahweh will do this. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ki 19:32">32</verse-number>“ ‘Therefore thus says Yahweh to the king of Assyria, “He shall not come to this city, nor shall he shoot an arrow there, nor shall he bring a small shield near her, nor shall he cast a siege ramp against her. <verse-number id="2 Ki 19:33">33</verse-number>By the way that he came to her he shall return; but to this city, he shall not come,” declares Yahweh. <verse-number id="2 Ki 19:34">34</verse-number>And I will defend this city to save her for my sake and for the sake of David my servant.’ ” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>An Angel Neutralizes the Assyrian Army</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ki 19:35">35</verse-number>It happened in that night that an angel of Yahweh went out, and he struck down one hundred and eighty-five thousand in the camp of Assyria. When they got up early in the morning, look! All of them <supplied>were</supplied> dead corpses. <verse-number id="2 Ki 19:36">36</verse-number>Then Sennacherib king of Assyria set out and went and returned and lived in Nineveh. <verse-number id="2 Ki 19:37">37</verse-number>It happened that he <supplied>was</supplied> worshiping in the temple of Nisroch his god, and Adrammelech and Sharezer<note>So <i>Kethib</i>; <i>Qere</i> adds “his sons”</note> struck him with the sword. Then they escaped <supplied>into</supplied> the land of Ararat, and Esarhaddon his son became king in his place. </p>
		</chapter>