<chapter id="2 Ki 20">
			<pericope>Hezekiah Loses Health and Regains It through Prayer</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ki 20:1">1</verse-number>In those days Hezekiah became <idiom-start/>deathly ill<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “ill to die”</note> and Isaiah the son of Amoz the prophet came to him and said to him, “Thus says Yahweh, ‘Command your house, for you <supplied>are about</supplied> to die; you will not recover.’ ” <verse-number id="2 Ki 20:2">2</verse-number>Then he turned his face to the wall and prayed to Yahweh, saying, <verse-number id="2 Ki 20:3">3</verse-number>“O Yahweh, please remember how I went about before you in faithfulness and with a whole heart, and <supplied>remember</supplied> the good that I have done in your eyes.” Then Hezekiah <idiom-start/>wept bitterly<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “wept a great weeping”</note> <verse-number id="2 Ki 20:4">4</verse-number>Isaiah had not gone out from the middle of the city when the word of Yahweh came to him, saying, <verse-number id="2 Ki 20:5">5</verse-number>“Return; you must say to Hezekiah, the leader of my people, ‘Thus says Yahweh the God of David your ancestor,<note>Or “father”</note> “I have heard your prayer and I have seen your tears. Look, I <supplied>am about to</supplied> heal you. On the third day you shall go up <supplied>to</supplied> the temple of Yahweh. <verse-number id="2 Ki 20:6">6</verse-number>I will add to your days fifteen years, and from the hand of the king of Assyria I will deliver you and this city. I will defend this city for my sake and for the sake of David my servant.” ’ ” <verse-number id="2 Ki 20:7">7</verse-number>Then Isaiah said, “Bring a lump of figs,” so they took and put it on the skin sores, and he lived. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ki 20:8">8</verse-number>Hezekiah said to Isaiah, “What is the sign that Yahweh will heal me that I shall go up on the third day <supplied>to</supplied> the temple of Yahweh?” <verse-number id="2 Ki 20:9">9</verse-number>Isaiah said, “This <supplied>is</supplied> the sign for you from Yahweh that Yahweh will do the thing that he has promised: Shall the shadow advance ten steps or shall it return ten steps?” <verse-number id="2 Ki 20:10">10</verse-number>Hezekiah answered, “It is easy for the shadow to lengthen ten steps. No, but let the shadow return backwards ten steps.” <verse-number id="2 Ki 20:11">11</verse-number>Isaiah the prophet called to Yahweh, and he brought back the shadow on the steps where it had gone down on the steps of Ahaz, backwards ten steps. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Hezekiah Reveals Too Much to a Babylonian Envoy</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ki 20:12">12</verse-number>At that time, Berodak-Baladan the son of Baladan king of <idiom-start/>Babylon<idiom-end/><note>Or “Babel.” Babel was the ancient name for Babylon, the capital of Babylonia. See also Genesis 11:9</note> sent letters and a gift to Hezekiah, for he had heard that Hezekiah had been ill. <verse-number id="2 Ki 20:13">13</verse-number>Hezekiah heard about them and showed them all of the house of his treasure, both the silver and the gold, the spices, the good olive oil, the room of his weapons, and all that could be found in his treasuries. There was nothing that he did not show them in his palace and in all of his kingdom. <verse-number id="2 Ki 20:14">14</verse-number>Then Isaiah the prophet came to King Hezekiah and said to him, “What did these men say, and from where have they come to you?” Hezekiah said, “From a far land; they have come from Babylon.” <verse-number id="2 Ki 20:15">15</verse-number>Then he asked, “What did they see in your palace?” And Hezekiah said, “All that is in my palace they have seen; there is nothing that I did not show them in my treasuries.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Ki 20:16">16</verse-number>Then Isaiah said to Hezekiah, “Hear the word of Yahweh! <verse-number id="2 Ki 20:17">17</verse-number>‘Look, days <supplied>are</supplied> coming when all that is in your palace will be carried off; <supplied>even</supplied> all that your ancestors<note>Or “fathers”</note> have stored up until this day, to Babylon; nothing shall be left,’ says Yahweh. <verse-number id="2 Ki 20:18">18</verse-number>‘Your sons who went out from you, whom you brought forth, will be taken, and they shall be eunuchs in the temple of the king of Babylon.’ ” <verse-number id="2 Ki 20:19">19</verse-number>Then Hezekiah said to Isaiah, “The word of Yahweh which you have spoken <supplied>is</supplied> good,” and he thought, “Is it not that peace and security shall be in my days?” <verse-number id="2 Ki 20:20">20</verse-number>Now the remainder of the acts of Hezekiah, all of his powerful <supplied>deeds</supplied>, and how he made the pool and the conduit and brought the water into the city, are they not written in the scroll of the events of the days of the kings of Judah? <verse-number id="2 Ki 20:21">21</verse-number>Then Hezekiah slept with his ancestors,<note>Or “fathers”</note> and Manasseh his son became king in his place. </p>
		</chapter>