<chapter id="Col 2">
			<pericope>Christ, the Mystery of God</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Col 2:1">1</verse-number> For I want you to know how great a struggle I have on behalf of you, and those in Laodicea, and all those who have not seen my face <idiom-start/>in person<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the flesh”</note>, <verse-number id="Col 2:2">2</verse-number>so that their hearts may be encouraged, united in love and into all the wealth of the full assurance of insight into the knowledge of the mystery of God, Christ, <verse-number id="Col 2:3">3</verse-number>in whom all the treasures of wisdom and knowledge are hidden. <verse-number id="Col 2:4">4</verse-number>I say this in order that no one will deceive you with persuasive speech, <verse-number id="Col 2:5">5</verse-number>for even if I am absent in the flesh, yet I am with you in spirit, rejoicing and seeing your good order and the steadfastness of your faith in Christ. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Made Alive in Christ</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Col 2:6">6</verse-number>Therefore as you have received Christ Jesus the Lord, live in him, <verse-number id="Col 2:7">7</verse-number>firmly rooted and built up in him and established in the faith, just as you were taught, abounding with thankfulness. <verse-number id="Col 2:8">8</verse-number>Beware lest <idiom-start/>anyone take you captive<idiom-end/><note>Literally “anyone be the one who takes captive you”</note> through philosophy and empty deceit, according to <idiom-start/>human tradition<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the tradition of men”</note>, according to the elemental spirits of the world and not according to Christ, <verse-number id="Col 2:9">9</verse-number>because in him all the fullness of deity dwells bodily, <verse-number id="Col 2:10">10</verse-number>and you are filled in him, who is the head over every ruler and authority, <verse-number id="Col 2:11">11</verse-number>in whom also you were circumcised with a circumcision not made by hands, by the removal of the body of the flesh, by the circumcision of Christ, <verse-number id="Col 2:12">12</verse-number>having been buried with him in baptism, in which also you were raised together with <supplied>him</supplied> through faith in the working of God, who raised him from the dead. <verse-number id="Col 2:13">13</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>although you were dead<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and you being dead”</note><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the participle (“being”) is understood as concessive</note> in the trespasses and the uncircumcision of your flesh, he made you alive together with him, having forgiven us all our trespasses, <verse-number id="Col 2:14">14</verse-number>having destroyed the certificate of indebtedness in ordinances against us, which was hostile to us, and removed it out of the way <supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “by” is supplied as a component of the participle (“nailing”) which is understood as means</note> nailing it to the cross. <verse-number id="Col 2:15">15</verse-number><supplied>When he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had disarmed”) which is understood as temporal</note> had disarmed the rulers and the authorities, he made a display of <supplied>them</supplied> in public, triumphing over them by it.<note>Or “in him”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Do Not Be Judged by Human Religious Rules</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Col 2:16">16</verse-number>Therefore do not let anyone judge you with reference to eating or<note>Some manuscripts have “and”</note> drinking or participation in a feast or a new moon or a Sabbath, <verse-number id="Col 2:17">17</verse-number>which are a shadow of what is to come, but the reality <supplied>is</supplied> Christ. <verse-number id="Col 2:18">18</verse-number>Let no one condemn you, taking pleasure in humility and the worship of angels, going into detail <supplied>about</supplied> <supplied>the things</supplied> which he has seen, inflated without cause by his fleshly mind, <verse-number id="Col 2:19">19</verse-number>and not holding fast to the head, from whom the whole body, supported and held together by the ligaments and sinews, grows with the growth of God. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Col 2:20">20</verse-number>If you have died with Christ to the elemental spirits of the world, why do you submit <supplied>to them</supplied> as <supplied>if</supplied> living in the world? <verse-number id="Col 2:21">21</verse-number>“Do not handle, do not taste, do not touch,” <verse-number id="Col 2:22">22</verse-number>which <supplied>things</supplied> are all <supplied>meant</supplied> for destruction by consuming according to human commandments and teachings, <verse-number id="Col 2:23">23</verse-number>which <supplied>things</supplied> <idiom-start/>although they have<idiom-end/><note>Literally “having”</note>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here the participle (“having”) is understood as concessive</note> to be sure, an appearance of wisdom in self-made religion and humility and unsparing treatment of the body, <idiom-start/>do not have any value<idiom-end/><note>Literally “are not with any value”</note> against the indulgence of the flesh. </p>
		</chapter>