<chapter id="Col 3">
			<pericope>Seek the Things Above</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Col 3:1">1</verse-number> Therefore, if you have been raised together with Christ, seek the things above, where Christ is, seated at the right hand of God. <verse-number id="Col 3:2">2</verse-number>Set your mind on the things above, not <supplied>on</supplied> the things on earth. <verse-number id="Col 3:3">3</verse-number>For you have died, and your life is hidden with Christ in God. <verse-number id="Col 3:4">4</verse-number>When Christ, <supplied>who is</supplied> your life, is revealed, then you also will be revealed with him in glory. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Put Off the Old Behavior</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Col 3:5">5</verse-number>Therefore put to death <idiom-start/>what is earthly in you<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the members on the earth”</note>: sexual immorality, uncleanness, lustful passion, evil desire, and greediness, which is idolatry, <verse-number id="Col 3:6">6</verse-number>because of which the wrath of God is coming upon the sons of disobedience, <verse-number id="Col 3:7">7</verse-number>in which also you once lived, when you used to live in them.<note>Or “among them” (the pronoun may refer either to people or to sins)</note> <verse-number id="Col 3:8">8</verse-number>But now you also lay aside all <supplied>these</supplied> things: anger, rage, wickedness, slander, abusive language from your mouth. <verse-number id="Col 3:9">9</verse-number>Do not lie to one another, <supplied>because you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“have taken off”) which is understood as causal</note> have taken off the old man together with his deeds, <verse-number id="Col 3:10">10</verse-number>and have put on the new <supplied>man</supplied> that is being renewed in knowledge according to the image of the one who created him, <verse-number id="Col 3:11">11</verse-number>where there is neither Greek nor Jew, circumcision nor uncircumcision, barbarian, Scythian, slave, <supplied>or</supplied> free, but Christ <supplied>is</supplied> all, and in all. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Appeal for New Behavior</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Col 3:12">12</verse-number>Therefore, as <supplied>the</supplied> chosen of God, holy and <supplied>dearly</supplied> loved, put on affection, compassion, kindness, humility, gentleness, patience, <verse-number id="Col 3:13">13</verse-number>putting up with one another and forgiving one another. If anyone should have a complaint against anyone, just as also the Lord forgave you, thus also you <supplied>do the same</supplied>. <verse-number id="Col 3:14">14</verse-number>And to all these <supplied>things</supplied> <supplied>add</supplied> love, which is <supplied>the</supplied> bond of perfection. <verse-number id="Col 3:15">15</verse-number>And the peace of Christ must rule in your hearts, to which also you were called in one body, and be thankful. <verse-number id="Col 3:16">16</verse-number>Let the word of Christ dwell in you richly, teaching and admonishing one another with all wisdom, with psalms, hymns, <supplied>and</supplied> spiritual songs, singing with thankfulness in your hearts to God, <verse-number id="Col 3:17">17</verse-number>and everything <idiom-start/>whatever<idiom-end/><note>Literally “if anything that”</note> you do in word or in deed, giving thanks <supplied>for</supplied> all <supplied>things</supplied> in the name of the Lord Jesus to God the Father through him. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Mutual Responsibilities in Christian Relationships</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Col 3:18">18</verse-number>Wives, be subject to your husbands, as is fitting in the Lord. <verse-number id="Col 3:19">19</verse-number>Husbands, love your wives and do not be embittered against them. <verse-number id="Col 3:20">20</verse-number>Children, obey your parents in everything, for this is pleasing in the Lord. <verse-number id="Col 3:21">21</verse-number>Fathers, do not provoke your children, so that they will not become discouraged. <verse-number id="Col 3:22">22</verse-number>Slaves, obey your <idiom-start/>human<idiom-end/><note>Literally “according to the flesh”</note> masters in everything, not <idiom-start/>while being watched<idiom-end/><note>Literally “with eye-service”</note>, as people pleasers, but with sincerity of heart, fearing the Lord. <verse-number id="Col 3:23">23</verse-number>Whatever you do, accomplish <supplied>it</supplied> from the soul, as to the Lord, and not to people, <verse-number id="Col 3:24">24</verse-number><supplied>because you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“know”) which is understood as causal</note> know that from the Lord you will receive the reward of the inheritance. Serve<note>Or “You serve”; the same Greek verb form can be understood as either imperative (“serve”) or indicative (“you serve”), so that commentators and Bible translations differ</note> the Lord Christ. <verse-number id="Col 3:25">25</verse-number>For the one who does wrong will receive back whatever wrong he has done, and there is no partiality. </p>
		</chapter>