<chapter id="Job 1">
			<pericope>Job’s Character and Greatness</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Job 1:1">1</verse-number><supplied>There</supplied> was a man in the land of Uz whose<note>Hebrew “his”</note> name <supplied>was</supplied> Job. That<note>Hebrew “And that”</note> man was blameless and upright and God-fearing and turning away from evil. <verse-number id="Job 1:2">2</verse-number>And seven sons and three daughters were born to him. <verse-number id="Job 1:3">3</verse-number>Then<note>Hebrew “And”</note> his livestock came to be seven thousand sheep and goats and three thousand camels and five hundred pairs<note>Hebrew “pair”</note> of oxen and five hundred female donkeys, and he had very many slaves, and that man was greater than all the people of the east. <verse-number id="Job 1:4">4</verse-number>And his sons used to go and hold a feast <idiom-start/>at each other’s house<idiom-end/><note>Literally “at the house of a man,” or “at the house of each”</note> on his day, and they would send, and they would invite their three sisters to eat and to drink with them. <verse-number id="Job 1:5">5</verse-number><idiom-start/>Then when<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And it would happen that,” or “And it would happen when”</note> the days of the feast had run their course, <idiom-start/>Job would send<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “and Job would send”</note> and he would sanctify them. Thus<note>Hebrew “And”</note> he would arise early in the morning and offer burnt offerings <supplied>according to</supplied> the number of all of them, because Job thought,<note>Or “said”</note> “Perhaps my children have sinned and <idiom-start/>cursed<idiom-end/><note>Literally “blessed”— negative meaning by context</note> God in their heart.” This is what Job used to do <idiom-start/>all the time<idiom-end/>.<note>Or “always”; literally “all the days”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Job 1:6">6</verse-number>And it happened <idiom-start/>one day<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the day”</note> <idiom-start/>that<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and”</note> the sons of God<note>Or “the heavenly beings,” or “the angels”</note> came to present themselves before Yahweh, and Satan<note>Hebrew “the accuser,” or “the adversary”</note> also came into their midst. <verse-number id="Job 1:7">7</verse-number>So<note>Hebrew “And”</note> Yahweh said to Satan,<note>Hebrew “the accuser,” or “the adversary”</note> “From where have you come?” </p>
			<p>Then<note>Hebrew “And”</note> Satan<note>Hebrew “the accuser,” or “the adversary”</note> answered Yahweh and said, “From roaming on the earth and from walking about in it.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Job 1:8">8</verse-number>So<note>Hebrew “And”</note> Yahweh said to Satan,<note>Hebrew “the accuser,” or “the adversary”</note> “Have you <idiom-start/>considered<idiom-end/><note>Literally “set your heart”</note> my servant Job? Indeed,<note>Or “For,” or “Because”</note> there is no one like him on the earth—a blameless man and upright and God-fearing and turning away from evil.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Job 1:9">9</verse-number>Then<note>Hebrew “And”</note> Satan<note>Hebrew “the accuser,” or “the adversary”</note> answered Yahweh and said, “Does Job fear God for nothing? <verse-number id="Job 1:10">10</verse-number>Have you<note>Emphatic personal pronoun could be translated “you yourself”</note> not put a fence around him and his household and around <idiom-start/>all that belongs to him<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all that <supplied>is</supplied> his”</note> <idiom-start/>on every side<idiom-end/>?<note>Literally “from around”</note> You have blessed the work of his hands, and his livestock<note>Or “possessions”</note> has increased in the land. <verse-number id="Job 1:11">11</verse-number>But,<note>Hebrew “And”</note> on the other hand, stretch out<note>Or “please”</note> your hand and touch <idiom-start/>all that belongs to him<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all that <supplied>is</supplied> his”</note> <supplied>and see</supplied> <idiom-start/>whether<idiom-end/><note>Literally “if not”</note> he will <idiom-start/>curse<idiom-end/><note>Literally “bless”— negative meaning by context</note> you to your face.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Job 1:12">12</verse-number>So<note>Hebrew “And”</note> Yahweh said to Satan,<note>Hebrew “the accuser,” or “the adversary”</note> “Look, <idiom-start/>all that belongs to him<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all that <supplied>is</supplied> his”</note> is in your <idiom-start/>power<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “hand”</note> Only do not stretch out your hand <idiom-start/>against<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to,” or “unto”</note> him.” So<note>Hebrew “And”</note> Satan<note>Hebrew “the accuser,” or “the adversary”</note> went out from Yahweh’s <idiom-start/>presence<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “faces of”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Adversary’s Attack on Job’s Possessions</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Job 1:13">13</verse-number>And then <supplied>there</supplied> was one day when<note>Hebrew “and”</note> his sons and his daughters were eating and drinking wine in their firstborn brother’s house. <verse-number id="Job 1:14">14</verse-number>And a messenger came to Job and said, “The oxen were plowing, and the female donkeys were feeding <idiom-start/>beside them<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “on their hands”</note> <verse-number id="Job 1:15">15</verse-number>Then<note>Hebrew “And”</note> the Sabeans <idiom-start/>attacked<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “fell <supplied>upon them</supplied>”</note> and they took them, and they slew the servants <idiom-start/>by the edge of the sword<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “with the mouth of <supplied>the</supplied> sword”</note> But<note>Hebrew “And”</note> I escaped, <supplied>even</supplied> I alone, to tell you.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Job 1:16">16</verse-number>While this one was still speaking, <idiom-start/>another<idiom-end/><note>Literally “this”</note> came and said, “The fire of God fell from the heavens, and it blazed up against the sheep and goats and against the servants, and it consumed them. But I escaped, <supplied>even</supplied> I alone, to tell you.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Job 1:17">17</verse-number>While this one was still speaking, <idiom-start/>another<idiom-end/><note>Literally “this”</note> came and said, “The Chaldeans formed three divisions, and they made a raid on the camels, and they carried them away, and they struck your servants <idiom-start/>by the edge of the sword<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “with the mouth of <supplied>the</supplied> sword”</note> but I escaped, <supplied>even</supplied> I alone, to tell you.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Job 1:18">18</verse-number>At the time<note>Hebrew “Until”</note> this one was speaking, <idiom-start/>another<idiom-end/><note>Literally “this”</note> came and said, “Your sons and your daughters were eating and drinking wine in their firstborn brother’s house. <verse-number id="Job 1:19">19</verse-number>And behold,<note>Or “Look”</note> a great wind came from across the desert, and it struck the four corners of the house <idiom-start/>so that<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and”</note> it fell upon the young people, and they died. But I escaped, <supplied>even</supplied> I alone, to tell you.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Job 1:20">20</verse-number>Then<note>Hebrew “And”</note> Job arose and tore his outer garment<note>Or “robe”</note> and shaved his head; <idiom-start/>then<idiom-end/><note>Hebrew “and”</note> he fell upon the ground and he worshiped. <verse-number id="Job 1:21">21</verse-number>Then<note>Hebrew “And”</note> he said, “Naked I came out from my mother’s womb, and naked I will return there. Yahweh gives, and Yahweh takes. Let Yahweh’s name be blessed.” <verse-number id="Job 1:22">22</verse-number>In all this, Job did not sin and did not <idiom-start/>charge God with wrongdoing<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “give unseemliness to God”</note> </p>
		</chapter>