<chapter id="Job 2">
			<pericope>The Adversary’s Attack on Job’s Person</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Job 2:1">1</verse-number><idiom-start/>And then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And it came to be,” or “and it happened”</note> one day the sons of God<note>Or “the heavenly beings,” or “the angels”</note> came to present themselves before Yahweh, and Satan<note>Hebrew “the accuser,” or “the adversary”</note> also came into their midst to present himself before Yahweh. <verse-number id="Job 2:2">2</verse-number>So<note>Hebrew “And”</note> Yahweh <idiom-start/>asked<idiom-end/><note>Literally “said to”</note> Satan,<note>Hebrew “the accuser,” or “the adversary”</note> “From where have you come?” </p>
			<p>And Satan<note>Hebrew “the accuser,” or “the adversary”</note> answered Yahweh and said, “From roaming on the earth and from walking about in it.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Job 2:3">3</verse-number>So<note>Hebrew “And”</note> Yahweh <idiom-start/>asked<idiom-end/><note>Literally “said to”</note> Satan,<note>Hebrew “the accuser,” or “the adversary”</note> “Have you <idiom-start/>considered<idiom-end/><note>Literally “set your heart”</note> my servant Job? Indeed,<note>Or “For” or “Because”</note> there is no one like him on the earth—a blameless man and upright and God-fearing and turning away from evil. And still he persists in his blamelessness <idiom-start/>even though<idiom-end/><note>Hebrew “and”</note> you incited me against him to destroy him for nothing.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Job 2:4">4</verse-number>Then<note>Hebrew “And”</note> Satan<note>Hebrew “the accuser,” or “the adversary”</note> answered him and said, “Skin for skin! All that <idiom-start/>that<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the”</note> man has he will give for his life. <verse-number id="Job 2:5">5</verse-number>But stretch out<note>Or “please”</note> your hand and touch his bones and his flesh, <supplied>and see</supplied> <idiom-start/>whether<idiom-end/><note>Literally “if not”</note> he will <idiom-start/>curse<idiom-end/><note>Literally “bless”—negative meaning by context</note> you to your face.”<note>Hebrew “your faces”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Job 2:6">6</verse-number>So<note>Literally “And it happened the/one day”</note> Yahweh said to Satan,<note>Hebrew “the accuser,” or “the adversary”</note> “<idiom-start/>All right<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “Look”</note> he <supplied>is</supplied> in your <idiom-start/>power<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “hand”</note> Only spare his life.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Job’s Blameless Behavior</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Job 2:7">7</verse-number>So<note>Hebrew “And”</note> Satan<note>Hebrew “the accuser,” or “the adversary”</note> went out from <idiom-start/>Yahweh’s presence<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the faces of Yahweh”</note> and he inflicted Job with loathsome skin sores from the sole of his foot up to the crown of his head. <verse-number id="Job 2:8">8</verse-number><idiom-start/>So<idiom-end/><note>Hebrew “And”</note> he took for himself a potsherd with which to scrape himself, and he sat in the midst of the ashes. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Job 2:9">9</verse-number>Then<note>Hebrew “And”</note> his wife said to him, “Are you still persisting in your blamelessness? <idiom-start/>Curse<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Bless”—negative meaning by context</note> God and die.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Job 2:10">10</verse-number>So<note>Hebrew “And”</note> he said to her, “You speak like one of the foolish women speaks. Indeed, should we receive the good from God, but<note>Or “and”</note> not receive the evil?” In all this, Job did not sin with his lips. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Job 2:11">11</verse-number>Thus<note>Hebrew “And”</note> Job’s three friends heard of this calamity that had come upon him. So<note>Hebrew “And”</note> each set out from his <supplied>own</supplied> place: Eliphaz the Temanite and Bildad the Shuhite and Zophar the Naamathite. And they met<note>Or “they agreed”</note> together to come to console him and to comfort him. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Job 2:12">12</verse-number>Thus<note>Hebrew “And”</note> they lifted up their eyes<note>Or “they gazed”</note> from afar, but<note>Hebrew “and”</note> they did not recognize him, so<note>Hebrew “and”</note> they raised their voice, and they wept, and each man tore his outer garment<note>Or “robe”</note> and threw dust on their heads <idiom-start/>toward the sky<idiom-end/>.<note>Or “in the air”; literally “to the heavens”</note> <verse-number id="Job 2:13">13</verse-number>Then<note>Hebrew “And”</note> they sat with him on the ground <supplied>for</supplied> seven days and seven nights, but<note>Hebrew “and”</note> no one spoke<note>Or “there was no speaking”</note> a word to him because they saw that <idiom-start/>his<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the”</note> suffering was very great. </p>
		</chapter>