<chapter id="Job 14">
			<pericope>Job Continues to Argue His Case with God</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 14:1">1</verse-number>“A human being born of a woman </li1>
				<li1><supplied>is</supplied> short of days and full of troubles.<note>Literally “trouble”</note> </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 14:2">2</verse-number>Like a flower he comes up, and he withers away; </li1>
				<li1>and he flees like a<note>Or “the”</note> shadow, but<note>Hebrew “and”</note> he does not last. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 14:3">3</verse-number>Even on such a one you fix your eyes, </li1>
				<li1>and you bring me into judgment with you. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 14:4">4</verse-number>“Who can bring a clean <supplied>thing</supplied> from an unclean <supplied>thing</supplied>? </li1>
				<li1>No one!<note>Or “Not one”</note> </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 14:5">5</verse-number>If his days <supplied>are</supplied> determined, the number of his months <supplied>is</supplied> with you; </li1>
				<li1>you have appointed his boundaries, and he cannot cross <supplied>them</supplied>. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 14:6">6</verse-number>Look away from him, and let him desist </li1>
				<li1>until he enjoys his days like a laborer. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 14:7">7</verse-number>“Indeed, there is hope for a tree: </li1>
				<li1>if it is cut down, then<note>Hebrew “and”</note> it will sprout again, </li1>
				<li1>and its new shoots will not cease; </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 14:8">8</verse-number>though its root grows old in the earth, </li1>
				<li1>and its stump dies in the dust, </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 14:9">9</verse-number>at<note>Hebrew “from”</note> the scent of water it will bud, </li1>
				<li1>and it will put forth branches like a young plant. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 14:10">10</verse-number>“But<note>Hebrew “And”</note> a man dies, and he dwindles away; </li1>
				<li1>thus<note>Hebrew “And”</note> a human being passes away, and where is he?<note>Or “where is he <supplied>then</supplied>?”</note> </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 14:11">11</verse-number><supplied>As</supplied> water disappears from a lake, </li1>
				<li1>and a river withers away and dries up,<note>Or “it dries up”</note> </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 14:12">12</verse-number><idiom-start/>so<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and”</note> a man lies down, and he does not arise. </li1>
				<li1><idiom-start/>Until the heavens are no more<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “Until not heavens”</note> they will not awaken, </li1>
				<li1>and they will not be roused out of their sleep. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 14:13">13</verse-number>“<idiom-start/>O that<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Who shall give”</note> you would conceal me in Sheol, </li1>
				<li1><supplied>that</supplied> you would hide me <idiom-start/>until your wrath is past<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “until the return of your nose”</note> </li1>
				<li1><supplied>that</supplied> you would appoint a set time for me and remember me. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 14:14">14</verse-number>If a man dies, will he live <supplied>again</supplied>? </li1>
				<li1>All the days of my compulsory service I will wait, </li1>
				<li1>until the coming of my relief. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 14:15">15</verse-number>You would call, and I myself<note>Emphatic personal pronoun</note> would answer you; </li1>
				<li1>you would long for the work of your hand. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 14:16">16</verse-number>For then<note>Hebrew “now”</note> you would count my steps, </li1>
				<li1><supplied>but</supplied> you would not keep watch over my sin. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 14:17">17</verse-number>My transgression would be sealed in a bag, </li1>
				<li1>and you would cover over my guilt. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 14:18">18</verse-number>“But<note>Or “And but”</note> a mountain falls; it crumbles away, </li1>
				<li1>and a rock moves away from its place. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 14:19">19</verse-number>Water wears away stones; </li1>
				<li1>its torrents wash away <supplied>the</supplied> soil of <supplied>the</supplied> earth; </li1>
				<li1>so<note>Hebrew “and”</note> you destroy the hope of human beings. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 14:20">20</verse-number>You overpower him forever, and he passes away; </li1>
				<li1><supplied>you</supplied> change <idiom-start/>his countenance<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “his faces”</note> <idiom-start/>then<idiom-end/><note>Hebrew “and”</note> you send him away. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 14:21">21</verse-number>His children may <supplied>come to</supplied> honor, but<note>Hebrew “and”</note> he does not know <supplied>it</supplied>; </li1>
				<li1>or<note>Hebrew “and”</note> they may become lowly, but<note>Hebrew “and”</note> he does not realize it.<note>Or “them”</note> </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 14:22">22</verse-number>He feels only the pain of his own body,<note>Hebrew “his body on him”</note> </li1>
				<li1>and his inner self<note>Or “soul”</note> mourns for him.”<note>Or “for himself”</note> </li1>
			</ul>
		</chapter>