<chapter id="Job 19">
			<pericope>Job’s Sixth Speech: A Response to Bildad</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Job 19:1">1</verse-number> Then<note>Hebrew “And”</note> Job answered and said, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 19:2">2</verse-number>“<idiom-start/>How long<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Until when”</note> will you<note>Plural</note> torment me<note>Hebrew “my soul,” or “my self”</note> </li1>
				<li1>and crush me with words? </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 19:3">3</verse-number>These ten times you<note>Plural</note> have disgraced me; </li1>
				<li1>you<note>Plural</note> are not ashamed <supplied>that</supplied> you<note>Plural</note> have attacked<note>Or “astonished”</note> me. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 19:4">4</verse-number>And what is more, <supplied>if</supplied> I have truly erred, </li1>
				<li1>my error remains with me. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 19:5">5</verse-number>If indeed you<note>Plural</note> must magnify yourselves against me, </li1>
				<li1>and you<note>Plural</note> must let my disgrace argue against me, </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 19:6">6</verse-number>know then that God has wronged me </li1>
				<li1>and has surrounded me <supplied>with</supplied> his net. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 19:7">7</verse-number>“Look, I cry out, ‘Violence!’ but<note>Or “and”</note> I am not answered; </li1>
				<li1>I cry out, but<note>Hebrew “and”</note> there is no justice. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 19:8">8</verse-number>He has walled up my way so that<note>Hebrew “and”</note> I cannot pass; </li1>
				<li1>and he has set darkness upon my paths. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 19:9">9</verse-number>He has taken my glory from me, </li1>
				<li1>and he has removed the crown of<note>Or “from”</note> my head. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 19:10">10</verse-number>He has broken me down all around, and I am gone. </li1>
				<li1>And he has uprooted my hope like a tree, </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 19:11">11</verse-number>and he has kindled his wrath against me, </li1>
				<li1>and <idiom-start/>he has counted me as one of his foes<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “he has counted me for him as his foes”</note> </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 19:12">12</verse-number>His troops have come together </li1>
				<li1>and have thrown up their rampart<note>Or “siege works”; compare NRSV</note> against me </li1>
				<li1>and have encamped around my tent. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 19:13">13</verse-number>“He has removed my kinsfolk from me, </li1>
				<li1>and my acquaintances have only<note>Or “completely”</note> turned aside from me. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 19:14">14</verse-number>My relatives have failed, </li1>
				<li1>and my close friends have forgotten me. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 19:15">15</verse-number>The sojourners in<note>Or “of”</note> my house and my slave women count me as a stranger; </li1>
				<li1>I have become a foreigner in their eyes. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 19:16">16</verse-number>I call to my servant, but<note>Hebrew “and”</note> he does not answer; </li1>
				<li1>I must <idiom-start/>personally<idiom-end/><note>Literally “with my mouth”</note> plead with him. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 19:17">17</verse-number>My breath is repulsive to my wife, </li1>
				<li1>and I am loathsome to <idiom-start/>my own family<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to the children of my womb”</note> </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 19:18">18</verse-number>Little boys also despise me; </li1>
				<li1><supplied>when</supplied> I rise, then<note>Hebrew “and”</note> they talk against me. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 19:19">19</verse-number>All <idiom-start/>my intimate friends<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the men of the circle of my confidants”</note> abhor me, </li1>
				<li1>and these <supplied>whom</supplied> I have loved have turned against me. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 19:20">20</verse-number>My bones<note>Collective singular</note> cling to my skin and to my flesh, </li1>
				<li1>and I have escaped by the skin of my teeth. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 19:21">21</verse-number>“Pity me, pity me, you my friends, </li1>
				<li1>for God’s hand has touched me. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 19:22">22</verse-number>Why do you<note>Plural</note> pursue me like God? </li1>
				<li1>And are not satisfied with my flesh? </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 19:23">23</verse-number>“<idiom-start/>O that<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Who then shall give and”</note> my words could be written down! </li1>
				<li1><idiom-start/>O that they could be inscribed in a scroll<idiom-end/>!<note>Literally “Who shall give in the scroll and they could be inscribed”</note> </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 19:24">24</verse-number><supplied>That</supplied> with a pen of iron and <supplied>with</supplied> lead </li1>
				<li1>they might be engraved on a rock forever! </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 19:25">25</verse-number>But<note>Hebrew “And”</note> I myself<note>Emphatic personal pronoun</note> know <supplied>that</supplied> my redeemer <supplied>is</supplied> alive, </li1>
				<li1>and <supplied>at the</supplied> last he will stand up upon <idiom-start/>the earth<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “dust”</note> </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 19:26">26</verse-number>And after my skin has been thus destroyed, </li1>
				<li1>but<note>Hebrew “and”</note> from<note>Or “without”</note> my flesh I will see God, </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 19:27">27</verse-number>whom <idiom-start/>I will see for myself<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “I myself will see for myself”; emphatic personal pronoun as subject to the singular verb</note> </li1>
				<li1>and <supplied>whom</supplied> my eyes will see and not a stranger.<note>Or “another”</note> </li1>
				<li1><idiom-start/>My heart faints within me<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “My kidneys fail in my lap”; see NRSV</note> </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 19:28">28</verse-number>“If you<note>Plural</note> say, ‘How will we persecute him?’ </li1>
				<li1>And ‘The root of the trouble is found’ in me,<note>Or “ ‘The root of the trouble is found’ in him”</note> </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 19:29">29</verse-number>be afraid for yourselves <idiom-start/>because of the sword<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from the faces of <supplied>the</supplied> sword”</note> </li1>
				<li1>for wrath <supplied>brings</supplied> punishment by<note>Literally “of”</note> <supplied>the</supplied> sword, </li1>
				<li1>so that you may know that <supplied>there is</supplied> judgment.” </li1>
			</ul>
		</chapter>