<chapter id="Job 42">
			<pericope>Job’s Repentance and Restoration</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Job 42:1">1</verse-number>Then<note>Hebrew “And”</note> Job answered Yahweh and said, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 42:2">2</verse-number>“I know that you can do all <supplied>things</supplied>, </li1>
				<li1>and <supplied>any</supplied> scheme from you will not be thwarted. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 42:3">3</verse-number>‘Who <supplied>is</supplied> this darkening counsel without knowledge?’ </li1>
				<li1>Therefore I uttered, but<note>Hebrew “and”</note> I did not understand; </li1>
				<li1><idiom-start/>things too wonderful for me<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “wonderful things from me”</note> but I did not know. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 42:4">4</verse-number>‘Hear and I will speak; </li1>
				<li1>I will question you, then<note>Hebrew “and”</note> inform me.’ </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 42:5">5</verse-number>By the ear’s hearing I heard <supplied>of</supplied> you, </li1>
				<li1>but<note>Hebrew “and”</note> now my eye has seen you. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Job 42:6">6</verse-number>Therefore I despise <supplied>myself</supplied> </li1>
				<li1>and repent in dust and ashes.” </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Job 42:7">7</verse-number><idiom-start/>And then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And it happened”</note> after Yahweh spoke these words to Job, Yahweh said to Eliphaz the Temanite, “<idiom-start/>My wrath has been kindled<idiom-end/><note>Literally “My nose became hot”</note> against you<note>Singular</note> and against <supplied>the</supplied> two of your friends, for you<note>Plural</note> have not spoken to me what is right as my servant Job <supplied>has</supplied>. <verse-number id="Job 42:8">8</verse-number><idiom-start/>So then<idiom-end/>,<note>Or “And now,” or “Therefore”</note> take for yourselves seven bulls and seven rams, and go to my servant Job and offer a burnt offering for yourselves. And my servant Job will pray for you,<note>Plural</note> for <idiom-start/>I will certainly accept his prayer<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “if his face I will lift up,” or “indeed his face I will lift up” (“if” used as an oath particle)</note> so that it will not be done with you<note>Plural</note> <supplied>according to your</supplied> folly, for you<note>Plural</note> have not spoken to me what is right as my servant Job <supplied>has</supplied>.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Job 42:9">9</verse-number>So<note>Hebrew “And”</note> Eliphaz the Temanite and Bildad the Shuhite <supplied>and</supplied> Zophar the Naamathite went and did just as Yahweh had told them, and <idiom-start/>Yahweh accepted Job’s prayer<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “Yahweh lifted up the face of Job”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Job 42:10">10</verse-number>Then<note>Hebrew “And”</note> Yahweh returned Job’s fortune when he prayed to him on behalf of his friends. Thus<note>Hebrew “And”</note> Yahweh increased <idiom-start/>all that Job had twice as much as before<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “all which for Job to twice”</note> <verse-number id="Job 42:11">11</verse-number>So<note>Hebrew “And”</note> all his brothers and all his sisters and all <supplied>those who</supplied> had known him <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to faces”</note> came to him, and they ate bread<note>Or “food”</note> with him in his house and showed sympathy to him and comforted him for all the disaster<note>Or “evil”</note> that Yahweh had brought upon him. Then<note>Hebrew “And”</note> each one gave to him one piece of money, and each one <supplied>gave to him</supplied> one ornamental ring of gold. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Job 42:12">12</verse-number>So<note>Hebrew “And”</note> Yahweh blessed Job’s latter days more than his beginning. <idiom-start/>Thus he had<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And it came to be for him,” or “And it was for him”</note> fourteen thousand sheep and goats and six thousand camels and a thousand pair of oxen and a thousand female donkeys. <verse-number id="Job 42:13">13</verse-number><idiom-start/>And he had<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And it came to be for him,” or “And it was for him”</note> seven sons and three daughters. <verse-number id="Job 42:14">14</verse-number>And he called the name of the first Jemimah and the name of the second Keziah and the name of the third Qeren-Happuk. <verse-number id="Job 42:15">15</verse-number>And beautiful women were not found in all the land like Job’s daughters, and their father gave to them an inheritance in the midst of their brothers. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Job 42:16">16</verse-number>And Job lived after this one hundred and forty years, and he saw his sons and his <idiom-start/>grandsons<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the sons of his sons”</note> <supplied>for</supplied> four generations. <verse-number id="Job 42:17">17</verse-number>Then<note>Hebrew “And”</note> Job died old and full of days. </p>
		</chapter>