<chapter id="Eph 1">
			<pericope>Greeting</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eph 1:1">1</verse-number> Paul, an apostle of Christ Jesus by the will of God, to the saints who are in Ephesus<note>A number of the earliest and most important manuscripts omit “in Ephesus,” though it is hard to make sense of the line without this phrase (cf. <sc>rsv</sc>, “to the saints who are also faithful”)</note> and faithful in Christ Jesus: <verse-number id="Eph 1:2">2</verse-number>Grace to you and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Praise to God for Spiritual Blessings</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eph 1:3">3</verse-number>Blessed <supplied>is</supplied><note>Or “blessed <supplied>be</supplied>”</note> the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, who has blessed us with every spiritual blessing in the heavenly <supplied>places</supplied> in Christ, <verse-number id="Eph 1:4">4</verse-number>just as he chose us in him before the foundation of the world, <supplied>that</supplied> we should be holy and blameless before him in love,<note>Or “before him, having predestined us in love” (the phrase “in love” could go either with v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Eph 1:4">4</cite> or v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Eph 1:5">5</cite>)</note> <verse-number id="Eph 1:5">5</verse-number>having predestined us to adoption through Jesus Christ to himself according to the good pleasure of his will, <verse-number id="Eph 1:6">6</verse-number>to the praise of the glory of his grace that he bestowed on us in the beloved, <verse-number id="Eph 1:7">7</verse-number>in whom we have redemption through his blood, the forgiveness of sins, according to the riches of his grace, <verse-number id="Eph 1:8">8</verse-number>that he caused to abound to us in all wisdom and insight, <verse-number id="Eph 1:9">9</verse-number>making known to us the mystery of his will, according to his good pleasure that he purposed in him, <verse-number id="Eph 1:10">10</verse-number>for the administration of the fullness of times, to bring together all things in Christ, the things in the heavens and the things on the earth, in him <verse-number id="Eph 1:11">11</verse-number>in whom also we were chosen, having been predestined according to the purpose of the One who works all <supplied>things</supplied> according to the counsel of his will, <verse-number id="Eph 1:12">12</verse-number><supplied>that</supplied> we who hoped beforehand in Christ should be for the praise of his glory, <verse-number id="Eph 1:13">13</verse-number>in whom also you, when you heard<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*This participle (“hearing”) and the following one (“believing”) are understood as temporal</note> the word of truth, the gospel of your salvation, in whom also when you believed you were sealed with the promised Holy Spirit, <verse-number id="Eph 1:14">14</verse-number>who is the down payment of our inheritance, until the redemption of the possession, to the praise of his glory. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Prayer for Spiritual Wisdom</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eph 1:15">15</verse-number>Because of this I also, hearing of <idiom-start/>your faith<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the according to you faith”</note> in the Lord Jesus and your love for all the saints, <verse-number id="Eph 1:16">16</verse-number>do not cease giving thanks for you, making mention in my prayers, <verse-number id="Eph 1:17">17</verse-number>that the God of our Lord Jesus Christ, <idiom-start/>the glorious Father<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the Father of glory”</note>,<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*Here “glorious” is an attributive genitive</note> may give you a spirit of wisdom<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Or “spiritual wisdom” (with “wisdom” is an attributive genitive)</note> and revelation in the knowledge of him <verse-number id="Eph 1:18">18</verse-number>(the eyes of your hearts having been enlightened), so that you may know what is the hope of his calling, what <supplied>are</supplied> the riches of the glory of his inheritance among the saints, <verse-number id="Eph 1:19">19</verse-number>and what <supplied>is</supplied> the surpassing greatness of his power toward us who believe, according to the working of his mighty strength <verse-number id="Eph 1:20">20</verse-number>which he has worked<note>Some manuscripts have “he worked”</note> in Christ, raising<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*These participles are either means (“by raising … and seating”) or temporal (“when he raised … and seated”)</note> him from the dead and seating <supplied>him</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> at his right hand in the heavenly <supplied>places</supplied>, <verse-number id="Eph 1:21">21</verse-number>above all rule and authority and power and lordship and every name named, not only in this age but also in the coming one, <verse-number id="Eph 1:22">22</verse-number>and he subjected all <supplied>things</supplied> under his feet<note>An allusion to <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 8:6">Ps 8:6</cite></note> and gave him <supplied>as</supplied> head over all <supplied>things</supplied> to the church, <verse-number id="Eph 1:23">23</verse-number>which is his body, the fullness of the one who fills all <supplied>things</supplied> in every <supplied>way</supplied>. </p>
		</chapter>