<chapter id="Eph 2">
			<pericope>Made Alive in Christ</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eph 2:1">1</verse-number> And you, <idiom-start/>although you were dead<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and you being dead”</note><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the participle (“being”) is understood as concessive</note> in your trespasses and sins, <verse-number id="Eph 2:2">2</verse-number>in which you formerly walked according to the course of this world, according to the ruler of the authority of the air, the spirit now working in the sons of disobedience, <verse-number id="Eph 2:3">3</verse-number>among whom also we all formerly lived in the desires of our flesh, doing the will<note>Or “desires”</note> of the flesh and of the mind, and we were children of wrath<note>This phrase is a Semitic idiom which can mean either (1) “children characterized by wrath” or (2) “children destined for wrath”</note> by nature, as also the rest of <supplied>them</supplied> were. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eph 2:4">4</verse-number>But God, being rich in mercy, because of his great love <supplied>with</supplied> which he loved us, <verse-number id="Eph 2:5">5</verse-number>and we being dead in trespasses, he made <supplied>us</supplied> alive together with Christ (by grace you are saved), <verse-number id="Eph 2:6">6</verse-number>and raised <supplied>us</supplied> together and seated <supplied>us</supplied> together in the heavenly <supplied>places</supplied> in Christ Jesus, <verse-number id="Eph 2:7">7</verse-number>in order that he might show in the coming ages the surpassing riches of his grace in kindness upon us in Christ Jesus. <verse-number id="Eph 2:8">8</verse-number>For by grace you are saved through faith, and this <supplied>is</supplied> not from yourselves, <supplied>it is</supplied> the gift of God; <verse-number id="Eph 2:9">9</verse-number><supplied>it is</supplied> not from works, so that no one can boast. <verse-number id="Eph 2:10">10</verse-number>For we are his creation, created in Christ Jesus for good works, which God prepared beforehand, so that we may walk in them. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jewish and Gentile Believers United in Christ</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eph 2:11">11</verse-number>Therefore remember that formerly you, the Gentiles in <supplied>the</supplied> flesh, the so-called uncircumcision by the so-called circumcision in <supplied>the</supplied> flesh, made by hands, <verse-number id="Eph 2:12">12</verse-number>that you were at that time apart from Christ, alienated from the citizenship of Israel, and strangers to the covenants of promise, not having hope, and without God in the world. <verse-number id="Eph 2:13">13</verse-number>But now in Christ Jesus you, the ones who once were far away, have become near by the blood of Christ. <verse-number id="Eph 2:14">14</verse-number>For he himself is our peace, who made both one and broke down the dividing wall of the partition, the enmity, in his flesh, <verse-number id="Eph 2:15">15</verse-number>invalidating the law of commandments in ordinances, in order that he might create the two in himself into one new man, <supplied>thus</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>thus</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“making”) which is understood as result</note> making peace, <verse-number id="Eph 2:16">16</verse-number>and might reconcile both in one body to God through the cross, killing the enmity in himself.<note>Or “by it” (referring to the cross)</note> <verse-number id="Eph 2:17">17</verse-number>And coming, he proclaimed the good news of peace to you who were far away and peace to the ones who were near, <verse-number id="Eph 2:18">18</verse-number>because through him <supplied>we</supplied> both have access in one Spirit to the Father. <verse-number id="Eph 2:19">19</verse-number>Consequently, therefore, you are no longer strangers and foreigners, but you are fellow citizens of the saints and members of the household of God, <verse-number id="Eph 2:20">20</verse-number>built on the foundation of the apostles and prophets, Christ Jesus himself being the cornerstone,<note>Or perhaps “capstone”</note> <verse-number id="Eph 2:21">21</verse-number>in whom the whole building, joined together, grows into a holy temple in the Lord, <verse-number id="Eph 2:22">22</verse-number>in whom you also are built up together into a dwelling place of God in <supplied>the</supplied> Spirit.<note>Or “are built up together in spirit <supplied>= spiritually</supplied> into a dwelling place of God” (cf. <sc>nrsv</sc>)</note> </p>
		</chapter>