<chapter id="Eph 3">
			<pericope>The Mystery of Christ Revealed</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eph 3:1">1</verse-number> On account of this I, Paul, the prisoner of Christ Jesus for the sake of you Gentiles <verse-number id="Eph 3:2">2</verse-number>—if indeed you have heard <supplied>about</supplied> the stewardship of God’s grace given to me for you. <verse-number id="Eph 3:3">3</verse-number>According to<note>Some manuscripts have “given to me for you, that according to”</note> revelation the mystery was made known to me, just as I wrote beforehand in brief, <verse-number id="Eph 3:4">4</verse-number>so that you may be able when you read<note>Or “by reading”</note> to understand my insight into the mystery of Christ <verse-number id="Eph 3:5">5</verse-number>(which in other generations was not made known to the sons of men as it has now been revealed to his holy apostles and prophets by the Spirit): <verse-number id="Eph 3:6">6</verse-number><supplied>that</supplied> the Gentiles are fellow heirs, and fellow members of the body, and fellow sharers of the promise in Christ Jesus through the gospel, <verse-number id="Eph 3:7">7</verse-number>of which I became a servant, according to the gift of God’s grace given to me, according to the working of his power. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eph 3:8">8</verse-number>To me, the least of all the saints, was given this grace: to proclaim the good news of the fathomless riches of Christ to the Gentiles, <verse-number id="Eph 3:9">9</verse-number>and to enlighten everyone <supplied>as to</supplied> what <supplied>is</supplied> the administration of the mystery hidden from the ages by God, who created all <supplied>things</supplied>, <verse-number id="Eph 3:10">10</verse-number>in order that the many-sided wisdom of God might be made known now to the rulers and the authorities in the heavenly <supplied>places</supplied> through the church, <verse-number id="Eph 3:11">11</verse-number>according to the purpose of the ages which he carried out in Christ Jesus our Lord, <verse-number id="Eph 3:12">12</verse-number>in whom we have boldness and access in confidence through faith in him.<note>Or “through his <supplied>i.e., Christ’s</supplied> faithfulness”</note> <verse-number id="Eph 3:13">13</verse-number>Therefore I ask <supplied>you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> not to be discouraged at my afflictions on behalf of you, which are your glory. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Prayer for Spiritual Strength</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eph 3:14">14</verse-number>On account of this, I bend my knees before the Father, <verse-number id="Eph 3:15">15</verse-number>from whom every<note>Or “the whole”</note> family in heaven and on earth is named, <verse-number id="Eph 3:16">16</verse-number>that he may grant you according to the riches of his glory to be strengthened with power through his Spirit in the inner person, <verse-number id="Eph 3:17">17</verse-number><supplied>that</supplied> Christ may dwell in your hearts through faith (you having been firmly rooted and established in love), <verse-number id="Eph 3:18">18</verse-number>in order that you may be strong enough to grasp together with all the saints what <supplied>is</supplied> the breadth, and length, and height, and depth, <verse-number id="Eph 3:19">19</verse-number>and to know the love of Christ that surpasses knowledge, in order that you may be filled up to all the fullness of God. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eph 3:20">20</verse-number>Now to the one who is able to do beyond all measure more than all that we ask or think, according to the power that is at work in us, <verse-number id="Eph 3:21">21</verse-number>to him <supplied>be</supplied> the glory in the church and in Christ Jesus to all generations forever and ever. Amen. </p>
		</chapter>