<chapter id="Eph 4">
			<pericope>Christians Should Live in Unity</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eph 4:1">1</verse-number> Therefore I, the prisoner in the Lord, exhort you to live in a manner worthy of the calling with which you were called: <verse-number id="Eph 4:2">2</verse-number>with all humility and gentleness, with patience, putting up with one another in love, <verse-number id="Eph 4:3">3</verse-number>being eager to keep the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace; <verse-number id="Eph 4:4">4</verse-number>one body and one Spirit (just as also you were called with one hope of your calling), <verse-number id="Eph 4:5">5</verse-number>one Lord, one faith, one baptism, <verse-number id="Eph 4:6">6</verse-number>one God and Father of all, who <supplied>is</supplied> over all, and through all, and in all. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Gifted Leaders Bring the Church to Maturity</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eph 4:7">7</verse-number>Now to each one of us was given this grace, according to the measure of Christ’s gift. <verse-number id="Eph 4:8">8</verse-number>Therefore it says, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Ascending on high he led captivity captive; </li1>
				<li1>he gave gifts to men.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 68:18">Ps 68:18</cite></note> </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Eph 4:9">9</verse-number>Now “he ascended,” what is <supplied>it</supplied>, except that he also descended<note>Some secondary manuscripts add “first”</note> to the lower regions of the earth? <verse-number id="Eph 4:10">10</verse-number>The one who descended himself is also the one who ascended above all the heavens, in order that he might fill all <supplied>things</supplied>. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eph 4:11">11</verse-number>And he himself gave some <supplied>as</supplied> apostles and some <supplied>as</supplied> prophets and some <supplied>as</supplied> evangelists and some <supplied>as</supplied> pastors and teachers <verse-number id="Eph 4:12">12</verse-number>for the equipping of the saints, for the work of the ministry, for building up the body of Christ, <verse-number id="Eph 4:13">13</verse-number>until we all reach the unity of the faith and the knowledge of the Son of God, to a mature man, to a measure of the maturity of the fullness of Christ, <verse-number id="Eph 4:14">14</verse-number>so that we may no longer be infants, tossed about by waves and carried about by every wind of teaching, by the trickery of people, by craftiness with reference to the scheming of deceit. <verse-number id="Eph 4:15">15</verse-number>But speaking the truth in love, we are to grow into him <supplied>with reference to</supplied> all <supplied>things</supplied>, who is the head, Christ, <verse-number id="Eph 4:16">16</verse-number>from whom the whole body, joined together and held together by every supporting ligament, according to the working by measure of each single part, the growth of the body makes for the building up of itself in love. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Appeal for New Behavior</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eph 4:17">17</verse-number>This therefore I say and testify in the Lord, <supplied>that</supplied> you no longer walk as the Gentiles walk: in the futility of their mind, <verse-number id="Eph 4:18">18</verse-number>being darkened in understanding, alienated from the life of God, because of the ignorance <supplied>that</supplied> is in them, because of the hardness of their heart, <verse-number id="Eph 4:19">19</verse-number>who, becoming callous, gave themselves over to licentiousness, for the pursuit of all uncleanness in greediness. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eph 4:20">20</verse-number>But you did not learn Christ in this way, <verse-number id="Eph 4:21">21</verse-number>if indeed you have heard <supplied>about</supplied> him, and you were taught by him (just as truth is in Jesus), <verse-number id="Eph 4:22">22</verse-number><supplied>that</supplied> you take off, according to your former way of life, the old man, who is being destroyed according to deceitful desires, <verse-number id="Eph 4:23">23</verse-number>be renewed in the spirit of your mind, <verse-number id="Eph 4:24">24</verse-number>and put on the new man (in accordance with God), who is created in righteousness and holiness from the truth. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Old Behavior, New Behavior, and Motivation</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eph 4:25">25</verse-number>Therefore, putting aside the lie, speak truth each one of you with his neighbor,<note>An allusion to <cite title="BibleLEB2: Zec 8:16">Zech 8:16</cite></note> because we are members of one another. <verse-number id="Eph 4:26">26</verse-number>Be angry and do not sin;<note>An allusion to <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 4:4">Ps 4:4</cite></note> do not let the sun set on your anger, <verse-number id="Eph 4:27">27</verse-number>nor give place to the devil. <verse-number id="Eph 4:28">28</verse-number>The one who steals must steal no longer, but instead must labor, working with his own hands <supplied>what is</supplied> good, so that he may have <supplied>something</supplied> to share with the one who has need. <verse-number id="Eph 4:29">29</verse-number><idiom-start/>No rotten word must proceed<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Every rotten word must not proceed”</note> from your mouth, but only something good for the building up of the need, in order that it may give grace to those who hear, <verse-number id="Eph 4:30">30</verse-number>and do not grieve the Holy Spirit of God, by whom you were sealed for the day of redemption. <verse-number id="Eph 4:31">31</verse-number>All bitterness, and rage, and wrath, and clamor, and abusive speech, must be removed from you, together with all wickedness. <verse-number id="Eph 4:32">32</verse-number>Become<note>Some manuscripts have “But become”</note> kind toward one another, compassionate, forgiving one another, just as also God in Christ has forgiven you. </p>
		</chapter>