<chapter id="Eph 6">
			<pericope>Children and Parents</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eph 6:1">1</verse-number> Children, obey your parents in the Lord, for this is right. <verse-number id="Eph 6:2">2</verse-number>“Honor your father and mother” (which is the first<note>Or “is a very important”</note> commandment with a promise), <verse-number id="Eph 6:3">3</verse-number>“in order that it may be well with you, and you may <idiom-start/>live a long time<idiom-end/><note>Literally “be long-lived”</note> on the earth.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ex 20:12">Exod 20:12 </cite>and/or <cite title="BibleLEB2: Dt 5:16">Deut 5:16</cite></note> <verse-number id="Eph 6:4">4</verse-number>And fathers, do not make your children angry, but bring them up in the discipline and instruction of the Lord. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Slaves and Masters</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eph 6:5">5</verse-number>Slaves, obey your earthly masters with fear and trembling, in the sincerity of your heart, as to Christ, <verse-number id="Eph 6:6">6</verse-number>not <idiom-start/>while being watched<idiom-end/><note>Literally “with eye service”</note>, as people pleasers, but as slaves of Christ doing the will of God from the heart, <verse-number id="Eph 6:7">7</verse-number>serving with goodwill as to the Lord and not to people, <verse-number id="Eph 6:8">8</verse-number><supplied>because you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“know”) which is understood as causal</note> know that each one of you, whatever good he should do,<note>Some manuscripts have “if he should do anything good”</note> this he will receive back from the Lord, whether slave or free. <verse-number id="Eph 6:9">9</verse-number>And masters, do the same <supplied>things</supplied> to them, giving up threats, knowing that both their Lord and yours is in heaven, and there is no partiality with him. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Spiritual Warfare</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eph 6:10">10</verse-number>Finally, become strong in the Lord and in the might of his strength. <verse-number id="Eph 6:11">11</verse-number>Put on the full armor of God, so that you may be able to stand against the stratagems of the devil, <verse-number id="Eph 6:12">12</verse-number>because our struggle is not against blood and flesh, but against the rulers, against the authorities, against the world rulers of this darkness, against the spiritual <supplied>forces</supplied> of wickedness in the heavenly <supplied>places</supplied>. <verse-number id="Eph 6:13">13</verse-number>Because of this, take up the full armor of God, in order that you may be able to resist in the evil day, and having done everything, to stand. <verse-number id="Eph 6:14">14</verse-number>Stand therefore, girding your waist with truth, and putting on the breastplate of righteousness, <verse-number id="Eph 6:15">15</verse-number>and binding <supplied>shoes</supplied> under your feet with the preparation of the good news of peace, <verse-number id="Eph 6:16">16</verse-number>in everything taking up the shield of faith, with which you are able to quench all the flaming arrows of the evil one, <verse-number id="Eph 6:17">17</verse-number>and receive the helmet of salvation, and the sword of the Spirit, which is the word of God, <verse-number id="Eph 6:18">18</verse-number>with all prayer and supplication praying at all times in the Spirit, and to this <supplied>end</supplied> being alert with all perseverance and supplication for all the saints, <verse-number id="Eph 6:19">19</verse-number>and for me, that a word may be given to me at the opening of my mouth, to make known with boldness the mystery of the gospel, <verse-number id="Eph 6:20">20</verse-number>for the sake of which I am an ambassador in chains, that <idiom-start/>in them<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in it” since “chain” is singular in the Greek text</note> I may speak freely, as it is necessary for me to speak. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Conclusion and Benediction</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eph 6:21">21</verse-number>Now, so that you also may know <idiom-start/>my circumstances<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the things with me”</note>, what I am doing, Tychicus, my dear brother and faithful servant in the Lord, will make known to you all <supplied>things</supplied>, <verse-number id="Eph 6:22">22</verse-number>whom I have sent<note>Or “whom I am sending”</note> to you for this very <supplied>reason</supplied>, that you may know <idiom-start/>our circumstances<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the things concerning us”</note>, and he may encourage your hearts. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eph 6:23">23</verse-number>Peace to the brothers and love with faith, from God the Father and the Lord Jesus Christ. <verse-number id="Eph 6:24">24</verse-number>Grace <supplied>be</supplied> with all who love our Lord Jesus Christ in incorruptibility.<note>Or “with undying love”</note> </p>
		</chapter>