<chapter id="Mal 1">
			<p><verse-number id="Mal 1">1</verse-number><verse-number id="Mal 1:1">1</verse-number> <idiom-start/>An oracle<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “A burden”</note> The word of Yahweh to Israel <idiom-start/>through<idiom-end/><note>Literally “by the hand of”</note> Malachi.<note>The name “Malachi” means “my messenger” in Hebrew</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>An Oracle Against Edom</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mal 1:2">2</verse-number>“I have loved you,” says Yahweh, but you say, “How have you loved us?” “<supplied>Is</supplied> Esau not Jacob’s brother?” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> Yahweh. “I have loved Jacob, <verse-number id="Mal 1:3">3</verse-number>but Esau I have hated. I have made his<note>That is, “Esau’s”</note> mountain ranges a desolation, and <supplied>given</supplied> his inheritance to the jackals of <supplied>the</supplied> desert.” <verse-number id="Mal 1:4">4</verse-number>If Edom says, “We are shattered, but we will return and rebuild <supplied>the</supplied> ruins,” Yahweh of hosts says this: “They may build, but I will tear down; and they will be called a territory of wickedness, and the people <supplied>with</supplied> whom Yahweh is angry forever.” <verse-number id="Mal 1:5">5</verse-number>Your eyes will see <supplied>this</supplied>, and you will say, “Yahweh is great beyond the borders<note>Hebrew “boundary”</note> of Israel.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>An Oracle Against the Temple Priesthood</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mal 1:6">6</verse-number>“A son honors <supplied>his</supplied> father, and a slave his master;<note>Hebrew “masters”</note> but if I <supplied>am</supplied> a father, where <supplied>is</supplied> my honor, and if I <supplied>am</supplied> a master,<note>Hebrew “masters”</note> where <supplied>is</supplied> my reverence?” says Yahweh of hosts to you, O priests, <idiom-start/>who despise<idiom-end/><note>Literally “despisers of”</note> my name. “But you say, ‘How have we despised your name?’ <verse-number id="Mal 1:7">7</verse-number><supplied>You are</supplied> presenting defiled food on my altar! But you ask, ‘How have we defiled you?’ By saying <supplied>that</supplied> the table of Yahweh is despised! <verse-number id="Mal 1:8">8</verse-number>When you offer a blind <supplied>animal</supplied> for sacrifice, is that not wrong?<note>Or “is there no wrong?”</note> And when you offer <supplied>the</supplied> lame and the one who is ill, is that not wrong?<note>Or “is there no wrong?”</note> Present it, please, to your governor! Will he be pleased with you? <idiom-start/>Will he show you favor<idiom-end/>?”<note>Literally “Will he lift your face?”</note> says Yahweh of hosts. <verse-number id="Mal 1:9">9</verse-number>So then, <idiom-start/>implore the favor of God<idiom-end/><note>Literally “appease, please, the face of God”</note> so that he will be gracious to us. “<idiom-start/>This is what you have done<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “From your hand was this”</note> <idiom-start/>Will he show favor to any of you<idiom-end/>?”<note>Literally “will he lift up from you a face”</note> says Yahweh of hosts. <verse-number id="Mal 1:10">10</verse-number>“Who also among you will shut <supplied>the temple</supplied> doors <supplied>so that</supplied> you will not kindle fire in vain <supplied>on</supplied> my altar? I take no pleasure in you,” says Yahweh of hosts, “and <idiom-start/>I will not accept<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I will not take pleasure in”</note> an offering from your hand. <verse-number id="Mal 1:11">11</verse-number>From the rising of the sun to its setting, my name <supplied>is</supplied> great among the nations, and in every place incense <supplied>is</supplied> being presented to my name, and a pure offering. For my name <supplied>is</supplied> great among the nations,” says Yahweh of hosts. <verse-number id="Mal 1:12">12</verse-number>“But you <supplied>are</supplied> profaning it by saying the table of the Lord <supplied>is</supplied> defiled, and its fruit—its food<note>The Hebrew here is difficult; “its food” may function to explain “its fruit”</note>—is despised! <verse-number id="Mal 1:13">13</verse-number>And you say, ‘Look! <supplied>This is</supplied> a weariness,’ and you sniff <supplied>with disdain</supplied> at it,” says Yahweh of hosts. “And you bring <supplied>the</supplied> stolen, the lame, and the one that is sick—<supplied>this</supplied> you bring as the offering! Should I <idiom-start/>accept it<idiom-end/><note>Literally “take pleasure in it”</note> from your hand?” says Yahweh. <verse-number id="Mal 1:14">14</verse-number>“Cursed is the one who cheats, who has in his flock a male and vows <supplied>it</supplied>, but <supplied>instead</supplied> sacrifices a blemished one to the Lord! For I <supplied>am</supplied> a great king,” says Yahweh of hosts, “and my name <supplied>is</supplied> awesome among the nations.” </p>
		</chapter>