<chapter id="Mal 2">
			<p><verse-number id="Mal 2">2</verse-number><verse-number id="Mal 2:1">1</verse-number> “And so then, O priests, this command <supplied>is</supplied> for you: <verse-number id="Mal 2:2">2</verse-number>If you will not listen, and if you will not <idiom-start/>take it to heart<idiom-end/><note>Literally, “place <supplied>it</supplied> on <supplied>your</supplied> heart”</note> to give glory to my name,” says Yahweh of hosts, “then I will send the curse on you, and I will curse your blessings; moreover I have <supplied>already</supplied> cursed them because <idiom-start/>you are not taking it to heart<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “you <supplied>are</supplied> not placing <supplied>it</supplied> on <supplied>your</supplied> heart”</note> <verse-number id="Mal 2:3">3</verse-number>Look! I <supplied>am</supplied> going to rebuke <idiom-start/>your offspring<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “for you the offspring”</note> and I will scatter offal on your faces, <supplied>the</supplied> offal of your religious feasts, and you will be carried to it.<note>The Hebrew is difficult. The subject is indefinite, and “it” likely refers to a refuse or waste pile</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Mal 2:4">4</verse-number>“Then you will know that I have sent to you this command, that my covenant with Levi <idiom-start/>continues<idiom-end/>,”<note>Literally “be”</note> says Yahweh of hosts. <verse-number id="Mal 2:5">5</verse-number>“My covenant with him was <supplied>one of</supplied> life and peace, and I gave them to him. <supplied>This required</supplied> reverence, and he revered<note>Or “feared”</note> me and stood in awe <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from the face of”</note> my name. <verse-number id="Mal 2:6">6</verse-number><supplied>The</supplied> instruction of truth<note>Or “law of truth”</note> was in his mouth, and wickedness was not found on his lips. In peace and in uprightness<note>Or “rectitude,” or “fairness”</note> he walked with me, and he brought back many from sin.<note>Or “iniquity”</note> <verse-number id="Mal 2:7">7</verse-number>For the lips of <supplied>the</supplied> priest should guard knowledge, and they should seek instruction<note>Or “law”</note> from his mouth, for he <supplied>is</supplied> the messenger of Yahweh of hosts. <verse-number id="Mal 2:8">8</verse-number>But you, you have turned from the way; you have caused many to stumble by <supplied>your</supplied> instruction;<note>Or “<supplied>the</supplied> law”</note> you have ruined the covenant of Levi,” says Yahweh of hosts. <verse-number id="Mal 2:9">9</verse-number>“And in turn I have made you despised and humbled before all the people, inasmuch as you <supplied>are</supplied> not keeping<note>Or “observing”</note> my way, but are <idiom-start/>favoring your own instruction<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “lifting faces in the instruction/law”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Yahweh Hates Faithlessness</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mal 2:10">10</verse-number><idiom-start/>Do we not all have<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<supplied>Is</supplied> for all of us not”</note> one father? Has not one God created us? Why <supplied>then</supplied> are we unfaithful <idiom-start/>to one another<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “each man to his brother”</note> profaning the covenant of our ancestors?<note>Or “fathers”</note> <verse-number id="Mal 2:11">11</verse-number>Judah has been faithless, and a detestable thing has been done in Israel and in Jerusalem. Judah has profaned the sanctuary of Yahweh which he loves, and has married the daughter of a foreign<note>Or “pagan”</note> god. <verse-number id="Mal 2:12">12</verse-number>May Yahweh cut off from the tents of Jacob the man who does this, <supplied>the</supplied> one who is awake and <supplied>who</supplied> answers, and <supplied>the one who</supplied> brings an offering to Yahweh of hosts! </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Mal 2:13">13</verse-number>And this you do <idiom-start/>as well<idiom-end/>:<note>Literally “a second time”</note> <supplied>you</supplied> cover the altar of Yahweh <supplied>with</supplied> tears, <supplied>with</supplied> weeping and <supplied>with</supplied> groaning, because he<note>Yahweh</note> <idiom-start/>no longer regards the offering<idiom-end/><note>Literally “there is no longer turning to the offering”</note> or accepts <supplied>it</supplied> <supplied>with</supplied> favor from your hand. <verse-number id="Mal 2:14">14</verse-number>But you ask, “<idiom-start/>For what reason<idiom-end/>?”<note>Literally “Because of what?”</note> Because Yahweh stands as a witness between you and the wife of your youth, against whom you have been unfaithful, even though she <supplied>is</supplied> your marriage partner and <idiom-start/>your wife by covenant<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the wife of your covenant”</note> <verse-number id="Mal 2:15">15</verse-number><idiom-start/>Did not one God make them?<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Not one did he make”</note> But a remnant of <supplied>the</supplied> spirit is his.<note>The meaning of this sentence is difficult; literally “And a remnant of the spirit to him”</note> And what does the one <supplied>God</supplied> desire? An offspring of God.<note>Or “a godly offspring”</note> <idiom-start/>You must be attentive to<idiom-end/><note>Literally “You must keep watch on”</note> your spirit, and you must not be unfaithful to the wife of your youth. <verse-number id="Mal 2:16">16</verse-number>“For <supplied>I</supplied> hate divorce,”<note>Hebrew “sending away”</note> says Yahweh, the God of Israel, “and he <supplied>who</supplied> covers his clothing <supplied>with</supplied> violence,” says Yahweh of hosts. “<idiom-start/>You must be attentive to<idiom-end/><note>Literally “You must keep watch on”</note> your spirit and you must not be unfaithful.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Mal 2:17">17</verse-number>You have wearied Yahweh with your words, but you ask, “With what have we wearied <supplied>him</supplied>?” <supplied>You have done so</supplied> <idiom-start/>when you say<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “at your saying”</note> “Everyone who does evil <supplied>is</supplied> good in the <idiom-start/>sight<idiom-end/><note>Literally “eyes”</note> of Yahweh, and in them he delights,” or “Where <supplied>is</supplied> the God of justice?” </p>
		</chapter>