<chapter id="Mal 3">
			<pericope>Yahweh’s Messenger is Coming</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mal 3:1">1</verse-number>“Look! I <supplied>am</supplied> going to send my messenger,<note>Or “my angel”</note> and he will prepare<note>Or “clear”</note> <supplied>the</supplied> way <idiom-start/>before me<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “before my face”</note> And the Lord whom you <supplied>are</supplied> seeking will come suddenly to his temple, and the messenger of the covenant, <supplied>in</supplied> whom you <supplied>are</supplied> taking pleasure—look!—<supplied>he is</supplied> about to come,” says Yahweh of hosts. <verse-number id="Mal 3:2">2</verse-number>And who <supplied>can</supplied> endure the day of his coming? And who <supplied>is</supplied> the one who can stand <idiom-start/>when he appears<idiom-end/>?<note>Literally “at his appearing”</note> For he <supplied>is</supplied> like a refiner’s fire, like launderers’ alkali.<note>Or “lye,” or “soap”</note> <verse-number id="Mal 3:3">3</verse-number>He will sit <supplied>as</supplied> a refiner and purifier of silver; he will purify the children of Levi, and he will refine them like gold and like silver, and they will present to Yahweh offerings<note>Hebrew “offering”</note> in righteousness. <verse-number id="Mal 3:4">4</verse-number>And the offering of Judah and Jerusalem will be pleasing to Yahweh, like <supplied>in the</supplied> days of old and like <supplied>in</supplied> former years. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Mal 3:5">5</verse-number>“Then I will approach you for judgment, and I will be a swift witness against the sorcerers and against the adulterers, and against those who swear <idiom-start/>falsely<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “as far as the falseness”</note> and against the oppressors of <supplied>the</supplied> hired worker <supplied>with his</supplied> wages, <supplied>the</supplied> widow and <supplied>the</supplied> orphan, and <idiom-start/>the abusers of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<supplied>those</supplied> pushing aside”</note> <supplied>the</supplied> alien,<note>Or “sojourner”</note> and <supplied>yet</supplied> do not fear me,” says Yahweh of hosts. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>An Overflowing Blessing</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mal 3:6">6</verse-number>“For I, Yahweh, have not changed,<note>Or “I do not change”</note> and you, O children of Jacob, have not perished.<note>Or “are not destroyed”</note> <verse-number id="Mal 3:7">7</verse-number>From the days of your ancestors<note>Or “fathers”</note> you have turned aside from my rules, and have not kept<note>Or “observed”</note> <supplied>them</supplied>! Return to me and I will return to you,” says Yahweh of hosts, “but you say, ‘How shall we return?’ </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Mal 3:8">8</verse-number>Will a human <supplied>dare to</supplied> rob God? Yet you <supplied>are</supplied> robbing me! And you say, ‘How have we robbed you?’ In the tithes and the contributions! <verse-number id="Mal 3:9">9</verse-number>You <supplied>are</supplied> being cursed with <supplied>a</supplied> curse, for you <supplied>are</supplied> robbing me, the whole nation <supplied>of you</supplied>! <verse-number id="Mal 3:10">10</verse-number>Bring the whole tithe to <idiom-start/>the storehouse<idiom-end/>,<note>Hebrew “the house of the treasure”</note> so that there will be food in my house, and test me please in this,” says Yahweh of hosts, “if I will not open for you the windows of heaven, and pour forth for you <idiom-start/>an overflowing blessing<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally, “a blessing up to not enough”</note> <verse-number id="Mal 3:11">11</verse-number>I will rebuke the devourer<note>NRSV, JPS interpret this word as “locust”</note> for you; it will not destroy the fruit of your soil; your vine in the field will not be unfruitful,” says Yahweh of hosts. <verse-number id="Mal 3:12">12</verse-number>“And all the nations will call you blessed, because you will be <idiom-start/>a land in which one takes joy<idiom-end/>,”<note>Literally “a land of desire”</note> says Yahweh of hosts. <verse-number id="Mal 3:13">13</verse-number>“Your words have been harsh<note>Hebrew “strong”</note> against me,” says Yahweh. “But you say, ‘How have we spoken together against you?’ <verse-number id="Mal 3:14">14</verse-number>You have said, ‘<supplied>It is</supplied> useless<note>Or “vain”</note> to serve God! What <supplied>is the</supplied> gain if we keep<note>Or “observe”</note> his requirements, and if we walk as mourners <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from the face of”</note> Yahweh of hosts? <verse-number id="Mal 3:15">15</verse-number>And now we <supplied>are</supplied> calling <supplied>the</supplied> arrogant blessed! Not only do those who do wickedness prosper; they also test God and they escape!’ ” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A Book of Remembrance is Written</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Mal 3:16">16</verse-number>Then those who revered<note>Or “fear”</note> Yahweh spoke <idiom-start/>with one another<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “each with his friend/companion”</note> And Yahweh listened attentively<note>Or “gave heed”</note> and heard, and a scroll of remembrance was written <idiom-start/>before him<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of him”</note> of those who revere<note>Or “fear”</note> Yahweh and ponder his name. <verse-number id="Mal 3:17">17</verse-number>“They will be mine,” says Yahweh of hosts, “on the day that I <supplied>am</supplied> acting, <supplied>my</supplied> treasured possession. I will have compassion on them as a man has compassion on his son who serves him. <verse-number id="Mal 3:18">18</verse-number>You will return and see <supplied>the difference</supplied> between <supplied>the</supplied> righteous and <supplied>the</supplied> wicked, between <supplied>the one who</supplied> serves God and the one who does not serve him. </p>
		</chapter>