<chapter id="Re 3">
			<pericope>The Letter to the Church in Sardis</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 3:1">1</verse-number> “And to the angel of the church in Sardis write: </p>
			<p>“This is what the one who has the seven spirits of God and the seven stars says: ‘I know your works, that you have a name that you are alive, and you are dead. <verse-number id="Re 3:2">2</verse-number>Be on the alert and strengthen the remaining <supplied>things</supplied> that are about to die, for I have not found your works completed before my God. <verse-number id="Re 3:3">3</verse-number>Therefore remember how you have received and heard, and observe <supplied>it</supplied>, and repent. If therefore you are not on the alert, I will come like a thief, and you will never know <supplied>at</supplied> what hour I will come against you. <verse-number id="Re 3:4">4</verse-number>But you have a few <idiom-start/>people<idiom-end/><note>Literally “names”</note> in Sardis who have not defiled their clothing, and they will walk with me in white, because they are worthy. <verse-number id="Re 3:5">5</verse-number>The one who conquers in this way will be dressed in white clothing, and I will never erase his name from the book of life, and I will declare his name before my Father and before his angels. <verse-number id="Re 3:6">6</verse-number>The one who has an ear, let him hear what the Spirit says to the churches.’ </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Letter to the Church in Philadelphia</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 3:7">7</verse-number>“And to the angel of the church in Philadelphia write: </p>
			<p>“This is what the holy one, the true one, the one who has the key of David, the one who opens and no one can shut, and who shuts and no one can open, says: <verse-number id="Re 3:8">8</verse-number>‘I know your works (behold, I have put before you an opened door that no one is able to shut<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “to shut it,” but the direct object is not translated here in keeping with English style</note>) that you have a little strength, and have kept my word, and did not deny my name. <verse-number id="Re 3:9">9</verse-number>Behold, I am causing <supplied>those</supplied> of the synagogue of Satan, the ones who call themselves Jews and are not, but are lying—behold, I will make them <idiom-start/>come<idiom-end/><note>Literally “that they will come”</note> and kneel down before your feet and acknowledge that I have loved you. <verse-number id="Re 3:10">10</verse-number>Because you have kept the word of my patient endurance, I also will keep you from the hour of testing that is about to come upon the whole inhabited world, to put to the test those who live on the earth. <verse-number id="Re 3:11">11</verse-number>I am coming quickly! Hold fast to what you have, so that no one may take away your crown. <verse-number id="Re 3:12">12</verse-number>The one who conquers, I will make him a pillar in the temple of my God, and he will never go outside again, and I will write on him the name of my God and the name of the city of my God, the new Jerusalem that comes down from heaven from my God, and my new name. <verse-number id="Re 3:13">13</verse-number>The one who has an ear, let him hear what the Spirit says to the churches.’ </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Letter to the Church in Laodicea</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 3:14">14</verse-number>“And to the angel of the church in Laodicea write: </p>
			<p>“This is what the Amen, the faithful and true witness, the originator<note>Or “the ruler”; or “the beginning”; or “the source”</note> of God’s creation, says: <verse-number id="Re 3:15">15</verse-number>‘I know your works, that you are neither cold nor hot. Would that you were cold or hot! <verse-number id="Re 3:16">16</verse-number>Thus, because you are lukewarm and neither hot nor cold, I am about to vomit you out of my mouth! <verse-number id="Re 3:17">17</verse-number>Because you are saying, “I am rich, and have become rich, and I have need of nothing,” and you do not know that you are wretched and pitiable and poor and blind and naked, <verse-number id="Re 3:18">18</verse-number>I advise you to buy from me gold refined by fire, in order that you may become rich, and white clothing, in order that you may be clothed and the shame of your nakedness may not be revealed, and eye salve to smear on your eyes, in order that you may see. <verse-number id="Re 3:19">19</verse-number>As many as I love, I reprove and discipline. Be zealous, therefore, and repent! <verse-number id="Re 3:20">20</verse-number>Behold, I stand at the door and knock! If anyone hears my voice and opens the door, indeed I will come in to him and dine with him, and he with me. <verse-number id="Re 3:21">21</verse-number>The one who conquers, I will grant to him to sit down with me on my throne, as I also have conquered and have sat down with my Father on his throne. <verse-number id="Re 3:22">22</verse-number>The one who has an ear, let him hear what the Spirit says to the churches.’ ” </p>
		</chapter>