<chapter id="Re 6">
			<pericope>The Opening of the First Six Seals</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 6:1">1</verse-number> And I watched when the Lamb opened one of the seven seals, and I heard one of the four living creatures saying like the sound of thunder, “Come!” <verse-number id="Re 6:2">2</verse-number>And I looked, and behold, a white horse, and the one seated on it had a bow, and a crown was given to him, and he went out conquering and in order that he might conquer. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 6:3">3</verse-number>And when he opened the second seal, I heard the second living creature saying, “Come!” <verse-number id="Re 6:4">4</verse-number>And another horse came out, fiery red, and it was granted to the one seated on it to take peace from the earth, and that they would slaughter one another, and a large sword was given to him. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 6:5">5</verse-number>And when he opened the third seal, I heard the third living creature saying, “Come!” And I looked, and behold, a black horse, and the one seated on it had a balance scale in his hand. <verse-number id="Re 6:6">6</verse-number>And I heard <supplied>something</supplied> like a voice in the midst of the four living creatures saying, “A quart of wheat for a denarius, and three quarts of barley for a denarius, and do not damage the olive oil and the wine!” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 6:7">7</verse-number>And when he opened the fourth seal, I heard a voice from the fourth living creature saying, “Come!” <verse-number id="Re 6:8">8</verse-number>And I looked, and behold, a pale green horse, and the one seated on it <idiom-start/>was named<idiom-end/><note>Literally “name to him”</note> Death, and Hades followed after him. And authority was granted to them over a fourth of the earth, to kill by the sword and by famine and by pestilence and by the wild beasts of the earth. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 6:9">9</verse-number>And when he opened the fifth seal, I saw under the altar the souls of those who had been slaughtered because of the word of God and because of the testimony which they had, <verse-number id="Re 6:10">10</verse-number>and they cried out with a loud voice, saying, “<idiom-start/>How long<idiom-end/><note>Literally “until when”</note>, holy and true Lord, will you not judge and avenge our blood from those who live on the earth?” <verse-number id="Re 6:11">11</verse-number>And to each one of them a white robe was given, and it was said to them that they should rest yet a short time, until <supplied>the number of</supplied> their fellow slaves and their brothers who were about to be killed as they <supplied>had been</supplied> were completed also. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 6:12">12</verse-number>And I watched when he opened the sixth seal, and a great earthquake took place, and the sun became black like sackcloth made of hair, and the whole moon became like blood, <verse-number id="Re 6:13">13</verse-number>and the stars of heaven<note>Or “of the sky”</note> fell to the earth like a fig tree throws down its unripe figs <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“shaken”) which is understood as temporal</note> shaken by a great wind. <verse-number id="Re 6:14">14</verse-number>And the sky was split apart like a scroll that is rolled up, and every mountain and island were moved from their place. <verse-number id="Re 6:15">15</verse-number>And the kings of the earth, and the most important people, and the military leaders, and the rich, and the powerful, and every slave and free person hid themselves in the caves and among the rocks of the mountains, <verse-number id="Re 6:16">16</verse-number>And they said to the mountains and to the rocks, “Fall on us and hide us from the face of the one who is seated on the throne, and from the wrath of the Lamb, <verse-number id="Re 6:17">17</verse-number>because the great day of their wrath has come, and who is able to stand?” </p>
		</chapter>