<chapter id="Re 7">
			<pericope>The Sealing of the 144,000</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 7:1">1</verse-number> After this I saw four angels standing at the four corners of the earth, holding back the four winds of the earth, so that no wind could blow on the earth or on the sea or on any tree. <verse-number id="Re 7:2">2</verse-number>And I saw another angel ascending <idiom-start/>from the east<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from the rising of the sun”</note>, holding the seal of the living God, and he cried out with a loud voice to the four angels <idiom-start/>who were given permission<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to whom was granted to them”</note> to damage the earth and the sea, <verse-number id="Re 7:3">3</verse-number>saying, “Do not damage the earth or the sea or the trees until we have sealed the slaves of our God on their foreheads.” <verse-number id="Re 7:4">4</verse-number>And I heard the number of the ones who were sealed, one hundred forty-four thousand sealed from every tribe of the sons of Israel: </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 7:5">5</verse-number>from the tribe of Judah, twelve thousand sealed, </p>
			<p>from the tribe of Reuben, twelve thousand, </p>
			<p>from the tribe of Gad, twelve thousand, </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 7:6">6</verse-number>from the tribe of Asher, twelve thousand, </p>
			<p>from the tribe of Naphtali, twelve thousand, </p>
			<p>from the tribe of Manasseh, twelve thousand, </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 7:7">7</verse-number>from the tribe of Simeon,<note>Or “Symeon,” an alternate spelling of the Greek form of the name</note> twelve thousand, </p>
			<p>from the tribe of Levi, twelve thousand, </p>
			<p>from the tribe of Issachar, twelve thousand, </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 7:8">8</verse-number>from the tribe of Zebulun, twelve thousand, </p>
			<p>from the tribe of Joseph, twelve thousand, </p>
			<p>from the tribe of Benjamin, twelve thousand were sealed. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Great Crowd before the Throne</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 7:9">9</verse-number>After these <supplied>things</supplied> I looked, and behold, a great crowd that no one was able to number, from every nation and tribe and people and language, standing before the throne and before the Lamb, dressed <supplied>in</supplied> white robes and <supplied>with</supplied> palm branches in their hands. <verse-number id="Re 7:10">10</verse-number>And they were crying out with a loud voice, saying, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Salvation to our God </li1>
				<li1>who is seated on the throne, </li1>
				<li1>and to the Lamb!” </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 7:11">11</verse-number>And all the angels stood around the throne and the elders and the four living creatures, and they fell down on their faces before the throne and worshiped God, <verse-number id="Re 7:12">12</verse-number>saying, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Amen! Praise and glory, </li1>
				<li1>and wisdom and thanksgiving, </li1>
				<li1>and honor and power and strength </li1>
				<li1><supplied>be</supplied> to our God <idiom-start/>forever and ever<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for the ages of the ages”</note>. Amen!” </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 7:13">13</verse-number>And one of the elders answered, saying to me, “These who are dressed <supplied>in</supplied> the white robes—who are <supplied>they</supplied>, and from where have they come?” <verse-number id="Re 7:14">14</verse-number>And I said to him, “My lord, you know.” And he said to me, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“These are the ones who have come out of the great tribulation, </li1>
				<li2>and have washed their robes </li2>
				<li2>and made them white in the blood of the Lamb. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Re 7:15">15</verse-number>Because of this, they are before the throne of God, </li1>
				<li2>and they serve<note>Or “worship”</note> him day and night in his temple, </li2>
				<li1>and the one who is seated on the throne <idiom-start/>will shelter<idiom-end/><note>Literally “will take up residence over”</note> them. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Re 7:16">16</verse-number>They will not be hungry <supplied>any</supplied> longer or be thirsty <supplied>any</supplied> longer, </li1>
				<li2>nor will the sun ever beat down on them, nor any heat,<note>An allusion to <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 49:10">Isa 49:10</cite></note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Re 7:17">17</verse-number>because the Lamb <supplied>who is</supplied> in the midst of the throne will shepherd them </li1>
				<li2>and will lead them to springs of living waters, </li2>
				<li1>and God will wipe away every tear from their eyes.”<note>An allusion to <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 25:8">Isa 25:8</cite></note> </li1>
			</ul>
		</chapter>