<chapter id="Re 8">
			<pericope>The Opening of the Seventh Seal</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 8:1">1</verse-number> And when he opened the seventh seal, there was silence in heaven <supplied>for</supplied> about half an hour. <verse-number id="Re 8:2">2</verse-number>And I saw the seven angels who stand before God, and seven trumpets were given to them. <verse-number id="Re 8:3">3</verse-number>And another angel who had a golden censer came and stood at the altar, and a large amount of incense was given to him, in order that he could offer the prayers of all the saints on the golden altar that <supplied>is</supplied> before the throne. <verse-number id="Re 8:4">4</verse-number>And the smoke of the incense went up before God with the prayers of the saints from the hand of the angel. <verse-number id="Re 8:5">5</verse-number>And the angel took the censer and filled it with the fire from the altar and threw <supplied>it</supplied> to the earth, and there were thunders and sounds and lightnings and an earthquake. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Blowing of the Trumpets</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 8:6">6</verse-number>And the seven angels who had the seven trumpets prepared themselves in order to blow them. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 8:7">7</verse-number>And the first blew the trumpet, and there was hail and fire mixed with blood, and it was thrown to the earth, and a third of the earth was burned up, and a third of the trees were burned up, and all the green grass was burned up. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 8:8">8</verse-number>And the second angel blew the trumpet, and <supplied>something</supplied> like a great mountain burning with fire was thrown into the sea, and a third of the sea became blood, <verse-number id="Re 8:9">9</verse-number>and a third of the creatures in the sea—the ones which had life—died, and a third of the ships were destroyed. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 8:10">10</verse-number>And the third angel blew the trumpet, and a great star burning like a torch fell from heaven, and it fell on a third of the rivers and on the springs of water. <verse-number id="Re 8:11">11</verse-number>And the name of the star was called Wormwood, and a third of the waters became wormwood, and many people died from the waters because they were made bitter. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 8:12">12</verse-number>And the fourth angel blew the trumpet, and a third of the sun was struck, and a third of the moon, and a third of the stars, so that a third of them were darkened, and the day did not shine <supplied>with respect to</supplied> a third of it, and the night likewise. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 8:13">13</verse-number>And I looked, and I heard one eagle flying <idiom-start/>directly overhead<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in midheaven,” i.e., “at the zenith”</note>, saying with a loud voice, “Woe, woe, woe to those who live on the earth, from the remaining sounds of the trumpets of the three angels who are about to blow the trumpet!” </p>
		</chapter>