<chapter id="Re 9">
			<pericope>Tormenting Locusts from the Abyss</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 9:1">1</verse-number> And the fifth angel blew the trumpet, and I saw a star that had fallen from heaven to the earth, and the key of the shaft of the abyss was given to him. <verse-number id="Re 9:2">2</verse-number>And he opened the shaft of the abyss, and smoke went up from the shaft like smoke from a great furnace, and the sun and the air were darkened by the smoke from the shaft. <verse-number id="Re 9:3">3</verse-number>And out of the smoke locusts came to the earth, and power was given to them like the scorpions of the earth have power. <verse-number id="Re 9:4">4</verse-number>And it was told to them that they should not damage the grass of the earth or any green <supplied>plant</supplied> or any tree, except those people who do not have the seal of God on their<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> foreheads. <verse-number id="Re 9:5">5</verse-number>And it was granted to them that they should not kill them, but that they would be tormented five months, and their torment <supplied>is</supplied> like the torment of a scorpion when it stings a person. <verse-number id="Re 9:6">6</verse-number>And in those days people will seek death and will never find it, and they will long to die, and death will flee from them. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 9:7">7</verse-number>And the appearance of the locusts <supplied>was</supplied> like horses prepared for battle, and on their heads <supplied>were something</supplied> like crowns similar in appearance to gold, and their faces <supplied>were</supplied> like men’s faces, <verse-number id="Re 9:8">8</verse-number>and they had hair like the hair of women, and their teeth were like <supplied>the teeth</supplied> of lions, <verse-number id="Re 9:9">9</verse-number>and they had breastplates like iron breastplates, and the sound of their wings <supplied>was</supplied> like the sound of many <idiom-start/>horse-drawn chariots<idiom-end/><note>Literally “chariots of horses”</note> running into battle. <verse-number id="Re 9:10">10</verse-number>And they have tails similar in appearance to scorpions, and stings, and their power to injure people <supplied>for</supplied> five months <supplied>is</supplied> in their tails. <verse-number id="Re 9:11">11</verse-number>They have <supplied>as</supplied> king over them the angel of the abyss, <idiom-start/>whose name<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the name to him”</note> in Hebrew <supplied>is</supplied> Abaddon, and in Greek he has the name Apollyon. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 9:12">12</verse-number>The first woe has passed. Behold, two woes are still coming after these <supplied>things</supplied>. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A Third of Humanity Killed by Plagues</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 9:13">13</verse-number>And the sixth angel blew the trumpet, and I heard one voice from the horns<note>Some manuscripts have “four horns”</note> of the golden altar <supplied>that is</supplied> before God <verse-number id="Re 9:14">14</verse-number>saying to the sixth angel, the one who had the trumpet, “Release the four angels who have been bound at the great river Euphrates!” <verse-number id="Re 9:15">15</verse-number>And the four angels who had been prepared for the hour and day and month and year were released, in order that they should kill a third of humanity. <verse-number id="Re 9:16">16</verse-number>And the number of the troops of the cavalry <supplied>was</supplied> <idiom-start/>two hundred million<idiom-end/><note>Literally “twenty thousands of ten thousands”</note>; I heard the number of them. <verse-number id="Re 9:17">17</verse-number>And in this way I saw the horses in the vision, and those seated on them, who had fiery <supplied>red</supplied> and hyacinth-colored and sulphurous <supplied>yellow</supplied> breastplates, and the heads of the horses <supplied>were</supplied> like the heads of lions, and out of their mouths came fire and smoke and sulphur. <verse-number id="Re 9:18">18</verse-number>By these three plagues a third of humanity was killed—by the fire and the smoke and the sulphur that came out of their mouths. <verse-number id="Re 9:19">19</verse-number>For the power of the horses is in their mouths and in their tails, for their tails <supplied>are</supplied> similar in appearance to snakes, having heads, and with them they cause injury.<note>Literally “they injure”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 9:20">20</verse-number>And the rest of humanity who were not killed by these plagues did not repent of the works of their hands, <idiom-start/>in order not to worship<idiom-end/><note>Literally “so that they did not worship”</note> the demons and the gold and silver and bronze and stone and wooden idols, which are able neither to see nor to hear nor to walk, <verse-number id="Re 9:21">21</verse-number>and they did not repent of their murders or of their magic spells or of their sexual immorality or of their thefts. </p>
		</chapter>