<chapter id="Re 10">
			<pericope>The Angel and the Little Scroll</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 10:1">1</verse-number> And I saw another powerful angel descending from heaven, wrapped in a cloud, and a rainbow over his head, and his face <supplied>was</supplied> like the sun, and his feet <supplied>were</supplied> like pillars of fire,<note>Or “like fiery pillars”</note> <verse-number id="Re 10:2">2</verse-number>and holding in his hand a little scroll that was opened. And he put his right foot on the sea and his<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> left on the land. <verse-number id="Re 10:3">3</verse-number>And he cried out with a loud voice like a lion roars, and when he cried out, the seven thunders sounded<note>Or “spoke”</note> their own voices. <verse-number id="Re 10:4">4</verse-number>And when the seven thunders spoke,<note>Or “sounded”</note> I was about to write, and I heard a voice from heaven saying, “Seal up <supplied>the things</supplied> which the seven thunders spoke, and do not write them!” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 10:5">5</verse-number>And the angel whom I saw standing on the sea and on the land raised his right hand to heaven <verse-number id="Re 10:6">6</verse-number>and swore by the one who lives <idiom-start/>forever and ever<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for the ages of the ages”</note>, who created heaven and the <supplied>things</supplied> in it, and the earth and the <supplied>things</supplied> in it, and the sea and the <supplied>things</supplied> in it, “There will be no more delay! <verse-number id="Re 10:7">7</verse-number>But in the days of the sound of the seventh angel, whenever he is about to blow the trumpet, then<note>Literally “and”</note> the mystery of God is completed, as he announced to his own slaves the prophets.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 10:8">8</verse-number>And the voice that I had heard from heaven <supplied>was</supplied> speaking with me again and saying, “Go, take the opened scroll in the hand of the angel who is standing on the sea and on the land.” <verse-number id="Re 10:9">9</verse-number>And I went to the angel and told him to give me the little scroll, and he said to me, “Take and eat it up, and it will make your stomach bitter, but in your mouth it will be sweet as honey.” <verse-number id="Re 10:10">10</verse-number>And I took the little scroll from the hand of the angel and ate it up, and it was sweet as honey in my mouth, and when I had eaten it, my stomach was made bitter. <verse-number id="Re 10:11">11</verse-number>And they said to me, “It is necessary for you to prophesy again about many peoples and nations and languages and kings.” </p>
		</chapter>