<chapter id="Re 12">
			<pericope>The Woman and Her Son Versus the Dragon</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 12:1">1</verse-number> And a great sign appeared in heaven: a woman clothed with the sun and <supplied>with</supplied> the moon under her feet, and on her head a crown of twelve stars, <verse-number id="Re 12:2">2</verse-number>and <idiom-start/>who was pregnant<idiom-end/><note>Literally “who was having in the belly”</note> and was crying out <supplied>because she</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was having birth pains”) which is understood as causal</note> was having birth pains, and was in torment to give birth. <verse-number id="Re 12:3">3</verse-number>And another sign appeared in heaven, and behold, a great fiery red dragon, having seven heads and ten horns, and on his heads <supplied>were</supplied> seven royal headbands.<note>Or “diadem crowns”</note> <verse-number id="Re 12:4">4</verse-number>And his tail swept away a third of the stars from heaven and threw them to the earth. And the dragon stood before the woman who was about to give birth, in order that whenever she gave birth to her child he could devour <supplied>it</supplied>. <verse-number id="Re 12:5">5</verse-number>And she gave birth to a son, a male <supplied>child</supplied>, who is going to shepherd all the nations with an iron rod,<note>An allusion to <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 2:9">Ps 2:9</cite></note> and her child was snatched away to God and to his throne. <verse-number id="Re 12:6">6</verse-number>And the woman fled into the wilderness, where she had a place prepared there by God, so that they could feed her there <supplied>for one</supplied> thousand two hundred sixty days. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Satan Thrown Down from Heaven to Earth</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 12:7">7</verse-number>And there was war in heaven; Michael and his angels <idiom-start/>fought against<idiom-end/><note>Literally “made war with”</note> the dragon, and the dragon and his angels <idiom-start/>fought back<idiom-end/><note>Literally “made war”</note>. <verse-number id="Re 12:8">8</verse-number>And they did not prevail, nor was a place found for them <supplied>any</supplied> longer in heaven. <verse-number id="Re 12:9">9</verse-number>And the great dragon was thrown down, the ancient serpent, who is called the devil and Satan, who deceives the whole world. He was thrown down to the earth, and his angels were thrown down with him. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 12:10">10</verse-number>And I heard a loud voice in heaven saying, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Now the salvation and the power </li1>
				<li2>and the kingdom of our God </li2>
				<li2>and the authority of his Christ have come, </li2>
				<li1>because the accuser of our brothers has been thrown down, </li1>
				<li2>the one who accuses them before our God day and night. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Re 12:11">11</verse-number>And they conquered him by the blood of the Lamb </li1>
				<li2>and by the word of their testimony, </li2>
				<li1>and they did not love their lives until death. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Re 12:12">12</verse-number>Because of this, rejoice, you heavens, </li1>
				<li2>and those who live in them! </li2>
				<li1>Woe <supplied>to</supplied> the earth and <supplied>to</supplied> the sea, </li1>
				<li2>because the devil has come down to you, </li2>
				<li1>having great anger, </li1>
				<li2><supplied>because he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“knows”) which is understood as causal</note> knows that he has little time!” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 12:13">13</verse-number>And when the dragon saw that he had been thrown down to the earth, he pursued the woman who had given birth to the male <supplied>child</supplied>. <verse-number id="Re 12:14">14</verse-number>And the two wings of a great eagle were given to the woman, in order that she could fly into the wilderness, to her place where she is fed there <supplied>for</supplied> a time, and times, and half a time, from the presence of the serpent. <verse-number id="Re 12:15">15</verse-number>And from his mouth the serpent spouted water like a river after the woman, in order that he could make her swept away by a river. <verse-number id="Re 12:16">16</verse-number>And the earth came to the aid of the woman, and the earth opened its mouth and swallowed up the river that the dragon had spouted out of his mouth. <verse-number id="Re 12:17">17</verse-number>And the dragon was angry at the woman, and went away to <idiom-start/>fight against<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to make war with”</note> the rest of her children, those who keep the commandments of God and who hold to the testimony about Jesus. <verse-number id="Re 12:18">18</verse-number>And he stood on the sand of the sea. </p>
		</chapter>