<chapter id="Re 18">
			<pericope>Lament Over Babylon the Great</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 18:1">1</verse-number> After these <supplied>things</supplied> I saw another angel descending from heaven, who had great authority, and the earth was illuminated by his splendor. <verse-number id="Re 18:2">2</verse-number>And he cried out with a powerful voice, saying, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Fallen, fallen <supplied>is</supplied> Babylon the great, </li1>
				<li1>and it has become a dwelling place of demons </li1>
				<li1>and a haunt of every unclean spirit </li1>
				<li1>and a haunt of every unclean bird </li1>
				<li1>and a haunt of every unclean and detested animal. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Re 18:3">3</verse-number>For all the nations have drunk<note>Some of the best manuscripts read “have fallen”</note> </li1>
				<li1>from the wine of the passion of her sexual immorality, </li1>
				<li1>and the kings of the earth have committed sexual immorality with her, </li1>
				<li1>and the merchants of the earth have become rich </li1>
				<li1>from the power of her sensuality.” </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 18:4">4</verse-number>And I heard another voice from heaven saying, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Come out from her, my people, </li1>
				<li1>so that you will not participate in her sins, </li1>
				<li1>and so that you will not receive her plagues, </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Re 18:5">5</verse-number>because her sins have reached up to heaven, </li1>
				<li1>and God has remembered her crimes. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Re 18:6">6</verse-number>Pay back to her as she herself also paid out, </li1>
				<li1>and <idiom-start/>pay back double<idiom-end/><note>Literally “double twofold”</note> according to her deeds; </li1>
				<li1>in the cup that she mixed, mix double for her. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Re 18:7">7</verse-number>As much as she glorified herself and lived in luxury, </li1>
				<li1>give to her so much torment and mourning, </li1>
				<li1>because in her heart she said, </li1>
				<li1>‘I sit as a queen, and am not a widow, </li1>
				<li1>and I will never see mourning!’ </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Re 18:8">8</verse-number>Because of this her plagues will come in one day— </li1>
				<li1>death and mourning and famine— </li1>
				<li1>and she will be burned up with fire, </li1>
				<li1>because the Lord God who passes judgment on her <supplied>is</supplied> powerful!” </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 18:9">9</verse-number>And the kings of the earth will weep and mourn over her, those who committed sexual immorality and lived sensually with her, when they see the smoke of her burning, <verse-number id="Re 18:10">10</verse-number>standing <idiom-start/>far off<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from afar”</note> because of the fear of her torment, saying, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Woe, woe, the great city, </li1>
				<li2>Babylon the powerful city, </li2>
				<li1>because in one hour your judgment has come!” </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 18:11">11</verse-number>And the merchants of the earth weep and mourn over her, because no one buys their cargo any more—<verse-number id="Re 18:12">12</verse-number>cargo of gold and silver and precious stones and pearls and fine linen and purple cloth and silk and scarlet cloth and all kinds of scented wood and all kinds of ivory goods and all kinds of goods of precious wood and bronze and iron and marble <verse-number id="Re 18:13">13</verse-number>and cinnamon and amomum<note>Or “spice”; the term can refer to “spice” in general, or specifically to <i>amomum</i>, a spice from India</note> and incense and ointment and frankincense and wine and olive oil and fine wheat flour and wheat and domesticated animals and sheep and horses and carriages and <idiom-start/>slaves<idiom-end/><note>Literally “bodies”</note> and human lives. </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Re 18:14">14</verse-number>“And <idiom-start/>the fruit your soul desires<idiom-end/><note>Literally “your fruit of desire”</note> has departed from you, </li1>
				<li1>and all the luxury and the splendor has perished from you, </li1>
				<li2>and they will never find them any more.” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 18:15">15</verse-number>The merchants of these <supplied>things</supplied>, who became rich from them, will stand <idiom-start/>far off<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from afar”</note>, weeping and mourning because of the fear of her torment, <verse-number id="Re 18:16">16</verse-number>saying, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Woe, woe, the great city, </li1>
				<li2>dressed in fine linen and purple cloth and scarlet cloth, </li2>
				<li2>and adorned with gold and precious stones and pearls, </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Re 18:17">17</verse-number>because in one hour such great wealth has been laid waste!” </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p>And every shipmaster and <idiom-start/>every seafarer<idiom-end/><note>Literally “everyone who sails to a place”</note> and sailors and all those who labor on the sea stood <idiom-start/>far off<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from afar”</note> <verse-number id="Re 18:18">18</verse-number>and began to cry out <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> saw the smoke of her burning, saying, “Who <supplied>is</supplied> like the great city?” <verse-number id="Re 18:19">19</verse-number>And they threw dust on their heads and were crying out, weeping and mourning, saying, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Woe, woe, the great city, </li1>
				<li2>in which all those who had ships on the sea </li2>
				<li3>became rich from her prosperity, </li3>
				<li1>because in one hour she has been laid waste!” </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Re 18:20">20</verse-number>Rejoice over her, heaven </li1>
				<li2>and the saints and the apostles and the prophets, </li2>
				<li1>because God has pronounced your judgment on her!” </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 18:21">21</verse-number>And one powerful angel picked up a stone like a great millstone and threw <supplied>it</supplied> into the sea, saying, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“In this way Babylon the great city will be thrown down with violence, </li1>
				<li2>and will never be found again! </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Re 18:22">22</verse-number>And the sound of harpists and musicians and flute players and trumpeters </li1>
				<li2>will never be heard in you again! </li2>
				<li1>And every craftsman of every trade </li1>
				<li2>will never be found in you again! </li2>
				<li1>And the sound of a mill </li1>
				<li2>will never be heard in you again! </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Re 18:23">23</verse-number>And the light of a lamp </li1>
				<li2>will never shine in you again! </li2>
				<li1>And the sound of a bridegroom and bride </li1>
				<li2>will never be heard in you again! </li2>
				<li1>For your merchants were the most important people of the earth, </li1>
				<li2>because with your sorcery they deceived all the nations. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Re 18:24">24</verse-number>And in her was found the blood of prophets and saints </li1>
				<li2>and all those who had been slaughtered on the earth. </li2>
			</ul>
		</chapter>