<chapter id="Re 19">
			<pericope>Rejoicing in Heaven</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 19:1">1</verse-number> After these <supplied>things</supplied> I heard <supplied>something</supplied> like the loud sound of a great crowd in heaven saying, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Hallelujah! </li1>
				<li1>Salvation and glory and power belong to our God, </li1>
				<li2><verse-number id="Re 19:2">2</verse-number>because his judgments <supplied>are</supplied> true and righteous, </li2>
				<li1>because he has passed judgment on the great prostitute </li1>
				<li2>who corrupted the earth with her sexual immorality, </li2>
				<li1>and has avenged the blood of his slaves <idiom-start/>shed by<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> her hand!” </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 19:3">3</verse-number>And a second time they said, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Hallelujah!” </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p>And her smoke goes up <idiom-start/>forever and ever<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for the ages of the ages”</note>. <verse-number id="Re 19:4">4</verse-number>And the twenty-four elders and the four living creatures fell down and worshiped God who is seated on the throne, saying, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Amen! Hallelujah!” </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 19:5">5</verse-number>And a voice came out from the throne, saying, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Praise our God </li1>
				<li2>all his slaves, </li2>
				<li1>and those who fear him, </li1>
				<li2>the small and the great!” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Wedding Celebration of the Lamb</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 19:6">6</verse-number>And I heard <supplied>something</supplied> like the sound of a great crowd and <supplied>something</supplied> like the sound of many waters and <supplied>something</supplied> like the sound of powerful thunder, saying, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Hallelujah! </li1>
				<li1>For the Lord God,<note>Some manuscripts have “the Lord our God, the All-Powerful”</note> the All-Powerful, reigns! </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Re 19:7">7</verse-number>Let us rejoice and be glad </li1>
				<li2>and give him the glory, </li2>
				<li1>because the wedding celebration of the Lamb has come, </li1>
				<li1>and his bride has prepared herself. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Re 19:8">8</verse-number>And it has been granted to her that she be dressed in bright, clean fine linen (for the fine linen is the righteous deeds of the saints). </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 19:9">9</verse-number>And he said to me, “Write: Blessed <supplied>are</supplied> those who are invited to the banquet of the wedding celebration of the Lamb!” And he said to me, “These are the true words of God.” <verse-number id="Re 19:10">10</verse-number>And I fell down before his feet to worship him, and he said to me, “<idiom-start/>Do not do that!<idiom-end/><note>Literally “do not see to it”</note> I am a fellow slave of you and of your brothers who hold to the testimony of Jesus. Worship God! For the testimony of Jesus is the spirit of prophecy.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Warrior on the White Horse</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 19:11">11</verse-number>And I saw heaven opened, and behold, a white horse, and the one seated on it was called “Faithful” and “True,” and with justice<note>Or “in righteousness”</note> he judges and makes war. <verse-number id="Re 19:12">12</verse-number>Now his eyes <supplied>were</supplied> a flame of fire, and on his head <supplied>were</supplied> many royal headbands having a name written that no one except he himself knows. <verse-number id="Re 19:13">13</verse-number>And <supplied>he was</supplied> dressed in an outer garment dipped in blood, and his name is called the Word of God. <verse-number id="Re 19:14">14</verse-number>And the armies <supplied>that are</supplied> in heaven, dressed in clean, white fine linen, were following him on white horses. <verse-number id="Re 19:15">15</verse-number>And out of his mouth came a sharp sword, so that with it he could strike the nations. And he will shepherd them with an iron rod,<note>An allusion to <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 2:9">Ps 2:9</cite></note> and he stomps the winepress of the wine of the furious wrath of God, the All-Powerful. <verse-number id="Re 19:16">16</verse-number>And he has a name written on his outer garment and on his thigh: “King of kings and Lord of lords.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 19:17">17</verse-number>And I saw one angel standing in the sun, and he cried out with a loud voice, saying to all the birds that fly <idiom-start/>directly overhead<idiom-end/><note>Literally, “in midheaven”</note>, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Come! Assemble for the great banquet of God, </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Re 19:18">18</verse-number>in order that you may eat the flesh of kings, </li1>
				<li1>and the flesh of military tribunes, </li1>
				<li1>and the flesh of the powerful, </li1>
				<li1>and the flesh of horses and those seated on them, </li1>
				<li1>and the flesh of all <supplied>people</supplied>, </li1>
				<li1>both free and slave, </li1>
				<li1>and small and great!” </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 19:19">19</verse-number>And I saw the beast and the kings of the earth and their armies assembled to make war with the one who is seated on the horse and with his army. <verse-number id="Re 19:20">20</verse-number>And the beast was seized, and with him the false prophet who performed the signs before him, by which he deceived those who received the mark of the beast and those who had worshiped his image. The two were thrown alive into the lake of fire that burns with sulphur. <verse-number id="Re 19:21">21</verse-number>And the rest were killed by the sword of the one who is seated on the horse—the <supplied>sword</supplied> that comes out of his mouth—and all the birds gorged themselves on their flesh. </p>
		</chapter>