<chapter id="Re 21">
			<pericope>The New Heaven, New Earth, and New Jerusalem</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 21:1">1</verse-number> And I saw a new heaven and a new earth, for the first heaven and the first earth had passed away, and the sea did not exist <supplied>any</supplied> longer. <verse-number id="Re 21:2">2</verse-number>And I saw the holy city, new Jerusalem, coming down out of heaven from God, prepared like a bride adorned for her husband. <verse-number id="Re 21:3">3</verse-number>And I heard a loud voice from the throne saying, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Behold, the dwelling of God <supplied>is</supplied> with humanity, </li1>
				<li1>and he will take up residence with them, </li1>
				<li1>and they will be his people </li1>
				<li1>and God himself will be with them.<note>Some manuscripts have “with them <supplied>as</supplied> their God”</note> </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Re 21:4">4</verse-number>And he will wipe away every tear from their eyes, </li1>
				<li1>and death will not exist <supplied>any</supplied> longer, </li1>
				<li1>and<note>Literally “or”</note> mourning or wailing or pain will not exist <supplied>any</supplied> longer. </li1>
				<li1>The former <supplied>things</supplied><note>Some manuscripts have “any longer, because the former <supplied>things</supplied>”</note> have passed away.” </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 21:5">5</verse-number>And the one seated on the throne said, “Behold, I am making all <supplied>things</supplied> new!” And he said, “Write, because these words are faithful and true.” <verse-number id="Re 21:6">6</verse-number>And he said to me, “It is done! I <supplied>am</supplied><note>Some manuscripts explicitly state “am”</note> the Alpha and the Omega, the beginning and the end. To the one who is thirsty I will give <supplied>water</supplied> from the spring of the water of life freely.<note>Or “without charge”</note> <verse-number id="Re 21:7">7</verse-number>The one who conquers will inherit these <supplied>things</supplied>, and I will be <idiom-start/>his God<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to him God”</note> and he will be <idiom-start/>my son<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to me a son”</note>. <verse-number id="Re 21:8">8</verse-number>But <supplied>as</supplied> for the cowards and unbelievers and detestable persons and murderers and sexually immoral people and sorcerers and idolaters and all liars, their share <supplied>is</supplied> in the lake that burns with fire and sulphur, which is the second death. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A Description of the New Jerusalem</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 21:9">9</verse-number>And one of the seven angels who had the seven bowls full of the seven last plagues came and spoke with me, saying, “Come, I will show you the bride, the wife of the Lamb.” <verse-number id="Re 21:10">10</verse-number>And he carried me away in the Spirit to a great and lofty mountain, and showed me the holy city, Jerusalem, coming down out of heaven from God, <verse-number id="Re 21:11">11</verse-number>that has the glory of God. Its radiance <supplied>is</supplied> like a precious stone, <supplied>something</supplied> like a jasper stone, shining like crystal. <verse-number id="Re 21:12">12</verse-number>It has<note>Literally “having,” referring back to the city mentioned in v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Re 21:11">11</cite></note> a great and high wall that has twelve gates, and at the gates twelve angels, and names written on <supplied>the gates</supplied> which are<note>Some manuscripts have “which are the names”</note> of the twelve tribes of the sons of Israel—<verse-number id="Re 21:13">13</verse-number>on the east, three gates, and on the north, three gates, and on the south, three gates, and on the west, three gates. <verse-number id="Re 21:14">14</verse-number>And the wall of the city has twelve foundations, and on them <supplied>are</supplied> twelve names of the twelve apostles of the Lamb. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 21:15">15</verse-number>And the one who spoke with me was holding a golden measuring rod in order that he could measure the city and its gates and its wall. <verse-number id="Re 21:16">16</verse-number>And the city is laid out as a square, and its length is the same as <supplied>its</supplied> width. And he measured the city with the measuring rod at twelve thousand stadia;<note>Or “two thousand two hundred kilometers”; or “fourteen hundred miles” (a <i>stade</i> was a unit of length about 185 meters or 607 feet)</note> the length and the width and the height of it are equal. <verse-number id="Re 21:17">17</verse-number>And he measured its wall, one hundred forty-four cubits<note>This number in cubits amounts to 12 times 12; it would be about 65 meters (216 feet)</note> <idiom-start/>according to human measure<idiom-end/><note>Literally “according to the measure of a man”</note>, which is the angel’s. <verse-number id="Re 21:18">18</verse-number>And the material of its wall <supplied>is</supplied> jasper, and the city <supplied>is</supplied> pure gold, similar in appearance to pure glass. <verse-number id="Re 21:19">19</verse-number>The foundations of the wall of the city are adorned with every kind of precious stone: the first foundation jasper, the second sapphire, the third chalcedony, the fourth emerald, <verse-number id="Re 21:20">20</verse-number>the fifth sardonyx, the sixth carnelian, the seventh chrysolite, the eighth beryl, the ninth topaz, the tenth chrysoprase, the eleventh jacinth, the twelfth amethyst. <verse-number id="Re 21:21">21</verse-number>And the twelve gates <supplied>are</supplied> twelve pearls, each one of the gates was from a single pearl. And the street of the city <supplied>is</supplied> pure gold, like transparent glass. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Re 21:22">22</verse-number>And I did not see a temple in it, for the Lord God All-Powerful is its temple, and the Lamb. <verse-number id="Re 21:23">23</verse-number>And the city has no need of the sun or of the moon, that they shine on it, for the glory of God illuminates it, and its lamp <supplied>is</supplied> the Lamb. <verse-number id="Re 21:24">24</verse-number>And the nations will walk by its light, and the kings of the earth will bring their glory into it. <verse-number id="Re 21:25">25</verse-number>And its gates will never be shut by day (for there will be no night there), <verse-number id="Re 21:26">26</verse-number>and they will bring the glory and the honor of the nations into it. <verse-number id="Re 21:27">27</verse-number>And every unclean thing and one who practices<note>Some manuscripts have “and the one who practices”</note> detestable things and falsehood will never enter into it, except those who are written in the book of life of the Lamb. </p>
		</chapter>