<chapter id="Es 3">
			<pericope>Haman is Promoted</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Es 3:1">1</verse-number>After these things King Ahasuerus promoted Haman son of Hammedatha the Agagite, and he exalted him and set <idiom-start/>his position<idiom-end/><note>Literally “his throne”</note> above all the officials who <supplied>were</supplied> with him. <verse-number id="Es 3:2">2</verse-number>And all of the king’s servants who <supplied>were</supplied> at the gate of the king <supplied>were</supplied> kneeling and bowing down to Haman; for so the king had commanded concerning him, but Mordecai did not kneel and bow down. <verse-number id="Es 3:3">3</verse-number>And the king’s servants who <supplied>were</supplied> at the gate of the king said to Mordecai, “Why <supplied>are</supplied> you transgressing the command of the king?” <verse-number id="Es 3:4">4</verse-number>They spoke to him day after day, but he did not listen to them, and they informed Haman to see if <idiom-start/>Mordecai’s resolve would prevail<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “the word’s of Mordecai would stand”</note> for he had told them that he <supplied>was</supplied> a Jew. <verse-number id="Es 3:5">5</verse-number>And Haman saw that Mordecai was not kneeling and bowing down to him, and he was filled <supplied>with</supplied> anger. <verse-number id="Es 3:6">6</verse-number>But <idiom-start/>he considered it beneath him<idiom-end/><note>Literally “he despised it in his eyes”</note> to lay hands on Mordecai only, for they told him of Mordecai’s people, and Haman sought to destroy all the Jews, the people of Mordecai, who <supplied>were</supplied> in the kingdom of Ahasuerus. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Es 3:7">7</verse-number>In the first month, that <supplied>is</supplied>, the month of Nisan, in the twelfth year of King Ahasurus, he cast pur—that <supplied>is</supplied>, the lot—before the presence of Haman <idiom-start/>for the day and for the month<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from day to day and from month to month”</note> until<note>The Septuagint adds, “and the lot fell on the thirteenth day of”</note> the twelfth month, that <supplied>is</supplied>, the month of Adar. <verse-number id="Es 3:8">8</verse-number>And Haman said to King Ahasuerus, “There is a certain people scattered and separated among the peoples in all of the provinces of your kingdom; their laws <supplied>are</supplied> different from every <supplied>other</supplied> people, and they do not <idiom-start/>observe<idiom-end/><note>Literally “do”</note> the laws of the king; it is not appropriate for the king to tolerate them. <verse-number id="Es 3:9">9</verse-number>If it pleases the king, let a <supplied>decree</supplied> be issued to destroy them, and I will pay<note>Or “I will weigh”</note> ten thousand talents<note>Hebrew “talent”</note> of silver to those who do the job, to bring to the treasury of the king.” <verse-number id="Es 3:10">10</verse-number>So the king removed his signet ring from his hand and gave it to Haman son of Hammedatha the Agagite, the enemy of the Jews. <verse-number id="Es 3:11">11</verse-number>And the king said to Haman, “The money <supplied>is</supplied> given to you and to the people to do with it <idiom-start/>as you see fit<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “as the good <supplied>is</supplied> in your eyes”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Es 3:12">12</verse-number>And the king’s secretaries were called in the first month on the thirteenth day, and <supplied>a decree</supplied> was issued, according to all that Haman commanded, to the satraps of the king and to the governors who <supplied>were</supplied> over all the provinces, and to <supplied>the</supplied> officials of all the people, to each province according to <supplied>its own</supplied> script and to all people according to their own language; <supplied>it was</supplied> written in the name of King Ahasuerus and <supplied>was</supplied> sealed with the king’s ring. <verse-number id="Es 3:13">13</verse-number>Letters <supplied>were</supplied> sent by couriers<note>Or “by runners”</note> to all the provinces of the king to destroy, to kill, and to annihilate all the Jews, <idiom-start/>both young and old<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from young to old”</note> women and children, on one day, the thirteenth day of the month, that <supplied>is</supplied> Adar, and to plunder their goods. <verse-number id="Es 3:14">14</verse-number>A copy of the edict <supplied>was</supplied> presented <supplied>as</supplied> law in every province making <supplied>it</supplied> known to all the people to be ready for that day. <verse-number id="Es 3:15">15</verse-number>The couriers went out quickly by order of the king, and the law was issued in the citadel of Susa. The king and Haman sat down to drink; and the city of Susa was bewildered.<note>Or “disturbed”</note> </p>
		</chapter>