<chapter id="Es 5">
			<pericope>Esther’s Banquet</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Es 5:1">1</verse-number>And it happened, on the third day, and Esther put on royal clothes, and she stood in the inner courtyard of the <idiom-start/>king’s palace<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “house of the king”</note> opposite the <idiom-start/>king’s palace<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “house of the king”</note> the king <supplied>was</supplied> sitting on his royal throne in the <idiom-start/>throne room<idiom-end/><note>Literally “house of the reign” or “house of the kingdom”</note> opposite the doorway of the palace. <verse-number id="Es 5:2">2</verse-number>When the king saw Queen Esther standing in the courtyard she found favor in his eyes, and the king held out the gold scepter that <supplied>was</supplied> in his hand to Esther, and Esther approached and touched the top of the scepter. <verse-number id="Es 5:3">3</verse-number>And the king said to her, “What <supplied>is</supplied> it, Queen Esther? What <supplied>is</supplied> your request? It will be given to you—even half the kingdom.” <verse-number id="Es 5:4">4</verse-number>And Esther said, “If it is good to the king, let the king and Haman come today to the banquet that I have prepared for him.” <verse-number id="Es 5:5">5</verse-number>And the king said, “Bring Haman quickly <idiom-start/>to fulfill<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to do”</note> the request of Esther.” So the king and Haman came to the banquet that Esther had prepared. <verse-number id="Es 5:6">6</verse-number>And the king said to Esther <idiom-start/>while they were drinking wine<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “at the meal of wine”</note> “What <supplied>is</supplied> your petition? It will be given to you. What <supplied>is</supplied> your request? Even half the kingdom, it will done. <verse-number id="Es 5:7">7</verse-number>And Esther answered and said, “<supplied>This is</supplied> my petition and my request. <verse-number id="Es 5:8">8</verse-number>If I have found favor in the eyes of the king,<note>Or “I have won the favor of the king</note> and if it is good to the king to grant my petition and fulfill my request, let the king and Haman come to the banquet that I will prepare for them tomorrow, and I will do according to the word of the king. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Es 5:9">9</verse-number>And Haman went out on that day rejoicing and <idiom-start/>feeling good<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “good of heart”</note> But when Haman saw Mordecai at the gate of the king, and he did not rise or tremble before him, Haman was filled <idiom-start/>with rage toward<idiom-end/><note>Literally “rage to”</note> Mordecai. <verse-number id="Es 5:10">10</verse-number>But Haman controlled himself and went to his house, and he sent <supplied>for</supplied> and brought his friends and Zeresh his wife. <verse-number id="Es 5:11">11</verse-number>And Haman recounted to them the splendor of his wealth and the number of his sons and all <supplied>the ways</supplied> that the king had honored him and promoted him above the officials and king’s servants. <verse-number id="Es 5:12">12</verse-number><idiom-start/>And Haman added<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “And Haman said also”</note> “Esther the Queen did not let <supplied>just anyone</supplied> come to the banquet that she prepared with the king except me, and I am also invited tomorrow to her <supplied>banquet</supplied> with the king. <verse-number id="Es 5:13">13</verse-number>But all this <idiom-start/>fails to satisfy me<idiom-end/><note>Literally “it is not sufficient for me”</note> <idiom-start/>when<idiom-end/><note>Literally “at every time”</note> I see Mordecai the Jew setting at the gate of the king.” <verse-number id="Es 5:14">14</verse-number>And Zeresh his wife and all of his friends said to him, “Let them make a gallows fifty cubits<note>Hebrew “cubit”</note> high, and in the morning tell the king, “Let them hang Mordecai on it; then go with the king to the banquet happily.” The advice pleased Haman, so he had the gallows made. </p>
		</chapter>