<chapter id="Es 7">
			<pericope>Esther’s Banquet</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Es 7:1">1</verse-number>So the king and Haman went <idiom-start/>to dine<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to drink”</note> with Queen Esther. <verse-number id="Es 7:2">2</verse-number>And the king again said to Esther, on the second day <idiom-start/>while they were drinking<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “at the meal of wine”</note> “What <supplied>is</supplied> your petition, Queen Esther? It will be given to you. What <supplied>is</supplied> your request? It will be given <supplied>to you</supplied>—even half the kingdom.” <verse-number id="Es 7:3">3</verse-number>Then Queen Esther answered, and she said, “If I have found favor in your eyes,<note>Or “If I have won your favor”</note> O king, and if it is good to the king, let my life be given to me at my petition and my people at my request; <verse-number id="Es 7:4">4</verse-number>I and my people have been sold to be destroyed and killed, to be annihilated. If we had been sold as male and female slaves I would have kept quiet, because this<note>Hebrew “there”</note> is not a need sufficient to trouble the king.”<note>See HALOT 1437, s.v. NRSV translates, “but no enemy can compensate for this damage to the king”</note> <verse-number id="Es 7:5">5</verse-number>And King Ahasuerus said to Queen Esther, “Who <supplied>is</supplied> he, and where <supplied>is</supplied> he, who <idiom-start/>gave himself the right to do this<idiom-end/>?”<note>Literally “has filled his heart to do so”</note> <verse-number id="Es 7:6">6</verse-number>And Esther said, “The adversary and enemy <supplied>is</supplied> this evil Haman!” And Haman was terrified before the king and queen. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Haman is Hanged</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Es 7:7">7</verse-number>The king rose in his anger <idiom-start/>from the banquet<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from the banquet of wine”</note> <supplied>and went</supplied> to the palace garden, and Haman stood to beg for his life from Queen Esther, for <idiom-start/>he realized that the king was determined to make an end to his life<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “that evil had been determined for him from the king”</note> <verse-number id="Es 7:8">8</verse-number>And the king returned from the palace garden to the <idiom-start/>banquet hall<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “house of the meal of wine”</note> <supplied>where</supplied> Haman <supplied>was</supplied> lying prostrate on the couch that Esther <supplied>was</supplied> on, and the king said, “Will he also molest the queen with me in the house?” As the words<note>Hebrew “word”</note> went from the king’s mouth they covered Haman’s face. <verse-number id="Es 7:9">9</verse-number>And Habrona, one of the eunuchs in the presence of the king, said, “Look, the same gallows that Haman had prepared for Mordecai who spoke good <supplied>for the sake</supplied> of the king stands at Haman’s house, fifty cubits high.” And the king said, “Hang him on it.” <verse-number id="Es 7:10">10</verse-number>And they hanged Haman on the gallows that he had prepared for Mordecai, and the anger of the king was abated. </p>
		</chapter>