<chapter id="Es 8">
			<pericope>Mordecai is Promoted</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Es 8:1">1</verse-number>On that day King Ahasuerus gave Queen Esther the house of Haman, the enemy of the Jews; and Mordecai came before the king, for Esther had told what he <supplied>was</supplied> to her. <verse-number id="Es 8:2">2</verse-number>And the king removed his signet ring that he had taken away from Haman, and he gave it to Mordecai. So Esther set Mordecai over the house of Haman. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Es 8:3">3</verse-number>And Esther again spoke before the king, and she fell before his feet and wept, pleading for his grace to avert Haman the Agagite’s evil <supplied>plan</supplied> and the plot that he devised against the Jews. <verse-number id="Es 8:4">4</verse-number>And the king held out to Esther the scepter of gold, and Esther rose and stood before the king, <verse-number id="Es 8:5">5</verse-number>and she said, “If it is good to the king, and if I have found favor before him,<note>Or “if I have won his favor”</note> and if the king is pleased with this matter, and <idiom-start/>I have his approval<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “I <supplied>am</supplied> good in his eyes”</note> let <supplied>an edict</supplied> be written to revoke the letters of the plans of Haman son of Hammedatha the Agagite, which he wrote to destroy the Jews that <supplied>are</supplied> in all the provinces of the king. <verse-number id="Es 8:6">6</verse-number>For <idiom-start/>how can I bear<idiom-end/><note>Literally “how am I able”</note> to look on the disaster that will find my people, and <idiom-start/>how can I bear<idiom-end/><note>Literally “how am I able”</note> to look on the destruction of my family?” <verse-number id="Es 8:7">7</verse-number>And King Ahasuerus said to Queen Esther and to Mordecai the Jew, “Look, I have given Haman’s house to Esther, and they have hanged him on the gallows because he <idiom-start/>plotted against<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sent his hand against”</note> the Jews. <verse-number id="Es 8:8">8</verse-number>Write <idiom-start/>as you see fit<idiom-end/><note>Literally “as it <supplied>is</supplied> good in your eyes”</note> concerning the Jews in the name of the king, and seal <supplied>it</supplied> with the king’s signet ring; for a decree that is written in the name of the king and sealed with the king’s signet ring cannot be revoked.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Es 8:9">9</verse-number>And the secretaries of the king were summoned<note>Or “called”</note> at that time, in the third month, which <supplied>is</supplied> in the month of Sivan on the twenty-third <supplied>day</supplied>, and <supplied>an edict</supplied> was written according to all that Mordecai commanded, to the Jews and to the governors and satraps and officials of the provinces from India to Cush<note>That is, “Ethiopia”</note>—one hundred and twenty-seven provinces<note>Hebrew “province”</note>—each province according to its own script and to every people in their own <idiom-start/>language<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “tongue”</note> and to the Jews in their own script and language. <verse-number id="Es 8:10">10</verse-number>And he wrote in the name of King Ahasuerus, and he sealed <supplied>the letters</supplied> with the king’s signet ring and sent them<note>Hebrew “the letters”</note> by couriers on horses, riding on royal horses <idiom-start/>bred by<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons of”</note> racing mares.<note>See HALOT 1244 s.v.</note> <verse-number id="Es 8:11">11</verse-number><supplied>In them</supplied> the king allowed the Jews who <supplied>were</supplied> in every city to assemble and <idiom-start/>defend their lives<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to stand for their live<supplied>s</supplied>”</note> to destroy and kill and annihilate any army of any people or province attacking them, including women and children, and to plunder their spoil, <verse-number id="Es 8:12">12</verse-number>in one day in all the provinces of King Ahasuerus, on the thirteenth <supplied>day</supplied> of the twelfth month, which is the month of Adar. <verse-number id="Es 8:13">13</verse-number>A copy of the <idiom-start/>edict<idiom-end/><note>Literally “writing”</note> <supplied>was</supplied> to be given <supplied>as</supplied> law in each province to inform all the people, so that the Jews would be ready<note>See HALOT 902 s.v.</note> on that day to avenge themselves from their enemies. <verse-number id="Es 8:14">14</verse-number>The mounted couriers on the royal horses went out without delay, urged by the king’s word. The law was given in the citadel of Susa. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Es 8:15">15</verse-number>Mordecai went out from the presence of the king in <idiom-start/>royal clothing<idiom-end/><note>Literally “clothing of the kingdom”</note> of blue cloth and white linen, and a great crown of gold and a robe of fine white linen and purple, and the city of Susa was shouting and rejoicing. <verse-number id="Es 8:16">16</verse-number>For the Jews, there was light and gladness, joy and honor. <verse-number id="Es 8:17">17</verse-number>In every province and city, wherever the king’s edict and his law came, there was gladness and joy for the Jews, a banquet and a <idiom-start/>holiday<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “day of good”</note> and many of the people from the country <supplied>were</supplied> posing as Jews because the fear of the Jews had fallen on them. </p>
		</chapter>