<chapter id="Es 9">
			<pericope>The Jews Destroy Their Enemies</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Es 9:1">1</verse-number>In the twelfth month, that <supplied>is</supplied> the month of Adar, on the thirteenth day, on which the edict of the king arrived and his law was enacted, on the day in which the enemies of the Jews had hoped to gain power over them but was overturned, <supplied>and</supplied> the Jews gained power against their enemies, <verse-number id="Es 9:2">2</verse-number>the Jews gathered in their cities in all the provinces of King Ahasuerus <idiom-start/>to strike against<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to send a hand against”</note> those who sought their destruction, and no one could withstand them,<note>Or “stand in their presence”</note> as the fear of them fell on all the people. <verse-number id="Es 9:3">3</verse-number>All the officials of the provinces, the satraps, governors, and <idiom-start/>those who did the work of the king<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the doers of the work who <supplied>were</supplied> for the king”</note> <supplied>were</supplied> supporting the Jews, because the fear of Mordecai had fallen on them. <verse-number id="Es 9:4">4</verse-number>For Mordecai <supplied>was</supplied> high-ranking in the <idiom-start/>king’s palace<idiom-end/><note>Literally “house of the king”</note> and his fame spread throughout all the provinces as <idiom-start/>Mordecai grew more and more powerful<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the man Mordecai <supplied>was</supplied> going and becoming great”</note> <verse-number id="Es 9:5">5</verse-number>The Jews struck down all their enemies with <idiom-start/>the sword<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the striking of <supplied>the</supplied> sword”</note> killing and destroying <supplied>them</supplied>; and they did as they pleased with those that hated them. <verse-number id="Es 9:6">6</verse-number>And in the citadel of Susa the Jews killed and destroyed five hundred men,<verse-number id="Es 9:7">7</verse-number>and Parshandatha, Dalphon, Aspatha, <verse-number id="Es 9:8">8</verse-number>Portha, Adalia, Aridatha, <verse-number id="Es 9:9">9</verse-number>Parmashta, Arisai, Aridai, and Vaizatha, <verse-number id="Es 9:10">10</verse-number>the ten sons of Haman, the son of Hammedatha, the enemy of the Jews; but they did not <idiom-start/>touch<idiom-end/><note>Literally “send their hand to”</note> the plunder. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Es 9:11">11</verse-number>On that day the number of those being killed in the citadel of Susa <idiom-start/>was reported to<idiom-end/><note>Literally “came before”</note> the king. <verse-number id="Es 9:12">12</verse-number>And the king said to Queen Esther, “In the citadel of Susa the Jews killed and destroyed five hundred men and the ten sons of Haman. What have they done in the rest of the king’s provinces? What <supplied>is</supplied> your petition? It will be granted to you. And what further <supplied>is</supplied> your request? It will be done.” <verse-number id="Es 9:13">13</verse-number>Esther replied, “If it is good to the king, let tomorrow also be granted to the Jews who <supplied>are</supplied> in Susa to do according to the edict of today; and let them hang Haman’s ten sons on the gallows.” <verse-number id="Es 9:14">14</verse-number>And the king said to do so. And a decree was issued in Susa and Haman’s ten sons were hanged. <verse-number id="Es 9:15">15</verse-number>And the Jews were gathered who <supplied>were</supplied> in Susa, and on the fourteenth day of the month of Adar and they killed in Susa three hundred men, but they did not <idiom-start/>touch<idiom-end/><note>Literally “send their hand to”</note> the plunder. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Es 9:16">16</verse-number>The rest of the Jews who <supplied>were</supplied> in the king’s provinces gathered and <idiom-start/>defended their lives<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to stand for their live<supplied>s</supplied>”</note> and <idiom-start/>found repose<idiom-end/><note>Literally “rested”</note> from their enemies. And they killed seventy-five thousand of those that hated them, but they did not <idiom-start/>touch<idiom-end/><note>Literally “send their hand to”</note> the plunder. <verse-number id="Es 9:17">17</verse-number><supplied>This was</supplied> on the thirteenth day of the month of Adar. <supplied>They</supplied> rested on the fourteenth <supplied>day</supplied> and made it a day of feasting and joy. <verse-number id="Es 9:18">18</verse-number>But the Jews who <supplied>were</supplied> in Susa gathered on the thirteenth and on the fourteenth day, and rested on the fifteenth day. And they made it a day of feasting and joy. <verse-number id="Es 9:19">19</verse-number>Therefore the Jews in the rural <supplied>areas</supplied>, living in the rural towns, made the fourteenth month of Adar a day of joy and feasting, a festive day of giving gifts to each other. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Feast of Purim</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Es 9:20">20</verse-number>Mordecai wrote down these things and he sent letters to all the Jews who <supplied>were</supplied> in all <supplied>of</supplied> the provinces of King Ahasuerus, <supplied>both</supplied> near and far, <verse-number id="Es 9:21">21</verse-number>to impose on them to keep the fourteenth day of the month of Adar, and the fifteenth <supplied>day</supplied>, <idiom-start/>every year<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “and every year and year”</note> <verse-number id="Es 9:22">22</verse-number>as the day that the Jews <idiom-start/>found relief<idiom-end/><note>Literally “rested”</note> from their enemies, and the month which changed for them from sorrow to joy, and from a mourning ceremony to a <idiom-start/>festive day<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “a day of good”</note> to make them days of feasting and joy, and giving gifts to each other and to the poor. <verse-number id="Es 9:23">23</verse-number>And the Jews adopted what they had begun to do and what Mordecai had written to them. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Es 9:24">24</verse-number>For Haman the son of Hammedatha the Agagite, the enemy of all the Jews had plotted against the Jews to destroy them, and he had cast pur, that <supplied>is</supplied> the lot, to rout them out and destroy them. <verse-number id="Es 9:25">25</verse-number>But when it came<note>Or “she came”</note> <idiom-start/>to the attention of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “before”</note> the king, he <idiom-start/>gave orders in writing<idiom-end/><note>Literally “said with a scroll”</note> <supplied>that</supplied> his evil plot that he had devised against the Jews should return on his head, and they hung him and his sons on the gallows. <verse-number id="Es 9:26">26</verse-number>Therefore they called these days Purim, because of the name Pur. Thus because of all the words of this letter, and of what they faced concerning this, and of what had happened to them, <verse-number id="Es 9:27">27</verse-number>the Jews established and adopted <supplied>it</supplied> for themselves and for their offspring, and for all who joined them. They did not neglect <idiom-start/>to observe<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to be doing”</note> these two days every year as it was written and appointed to them. <verse-number id="Es 9:28">28</verse-number>These days <supplied>are</supplied> to be remembered and <supplied>are</supplied> to be kept in every generation, and in family, province, and city; and these days of Purim are not <supplied>to be</supplied> neglected among the Jews, and their memory shall not come to an end among their offspring. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Es 9:29">29</verse-number>So Queen Esther the daughter of Abihail and Mordecai the Jew wrote in full authority to confirm this second letter of Purim. <verse-number id="Es 9:30">30</verse-number>He sent letters of words of peace and truth to all the Jews, to the one hundred and twenty-seven provinces<note>Hebrew “province”</note> of Ahasuerus’ kingdom, <verse-number id="Es 9:31">31</verse-number>to establish these days of Purim at their appointed times, just as Mordecai the Jew and Queen Esther had imposed, and just as they had imposed on themselves and their offspring regulations of the fast and their lament. <verse-number id="Es 9:32">32</verse-number>And the command of Esther established these practices of Purim, and <supplied>it was</supplied> written on the scroll. </p>
		</chapter>