<chapter id="Zec 1">
			<p><verse-number id="Zec 1">1</verse-number><verse-number id="Zec 1:1">1</verse-number> In the eighth month, in the second year of Darius, the word of Yahweh came<note>Literally “was”</note> to the prophet Zechariah son of Berekiah, son of Iddo, saying, <verse-number id="Zec 1:2">2</verse-number>“Yahweh <idiom-start/>was very angry with your ancestors<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “was angry against your ancestors <supplied>with</supplied> anger”</note> <verse-number id="Zec 1:3">3</verse-number>You must say to them: ‘Thus says Yahweh of hosts: “Return to me,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> Yahweh of hosts, “and I will return to you,” says Yahweh of hosts. <verse-number id="Zec 1:4">4</verse-number>“Do not be like your ancestors,<note>Or “fathers”</note> to whom the former prophets proclaimed, saying, ‘Thus says Yahweh of hosts: “Return from your evil ways and your evil deeds!” ’ But they did not hear<note>Or “listen”</note> and they did not pay attention<note>Or “give heed”</note> to me,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> Yahweh. <verse-number id="Zec 1:5">5</verse-number>“Your ancestors,<note>Or “fathers”</note> where are they? And the prophets, do they live forever? <verse-number id="Zec 1:6">6</verse-number>However, did not my words and my regulations which I commanded my servants the prophets overtake your ancestors?<note>Or “fathers”</note> And they repented and said, ‘Yahweh of hosts planned to do with us according to our ways, and according to our deeds so he has dealt with us.’ ” ’ ” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Zechariah’s First Vision</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Zec 1:7">7</verse-number>On the twenty-fourth day of <supplied>the</supplied> eleventh month, the month of Shebat, in the second year of Darius, the word of Yahweh came to Zechariah the prophet, son of Berekiah, son of Iddo, saying, <verse-number id="Zec 1:8">8</verse-number><idiom-start/>I had a vision in the night<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “I saw the night,” which means “I had a vision”</note> and look, a man riding on a red horse. And he <supplied>was</supplied> standing between the myrtle shrubs that <supplied>were</supplied> in the ravine, and behind him <supplied>were</supplied> red, reddish-brown, and white horses. <verse-number id="Zec 1:9">9</verse-number>And I asked, “What <supplied>are</supplied> these, my lord?” And the angel <supplied>who was</supplied> talking with me said, “I will show you what these are.” <verse-number id="Zec 1:10">10</verse-number>And the man standing between the myrtle shrubs answered and said, “These <supplied>are</supplied> those whom Yahweh has sent to patrol<note>Or “to go about,” or “to walk through”</note> <supplied>the</supplied> earth.” <verse-number id="Zec 1:11">11</verse-number>And they answered the angel of Yahweh who was standing between the myrtle shrubs, and they said, “We have patrolled<note>Or “have gone about,” or “have walked through”</note> the earth, and look, all the earth <idiom-start/>is dwelling in peace<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “<supplied>is</supplied> dwelling and <supplied>is</supplied> at rest”</note> <verse-number id="Zec 1:12">12</verse-number>The angel of Yahweh answered and said, “O Yahweh of hosts, <idiom-start/>how long<idiom-end/><note>Literally “until when”</note> will you have no compassion on Jerusalem and the cities of Judah, <supplied>with</supplied> which you showed fury these seventy years?”<note>Hebrew “year”</note> <verse-number id="Zec 1:13">13</verse-number><supplied>With</supplied> gracious<note>Or “kind”; literally “good”</note> and comforting words Yahweh answered the angel who was talking with me. <verse-number id="Zec 1:14">14</verse-number>And the angel who was talking with me said to me, “Proclaim, saying, ‘Thus says Yahweh of hosts: “<idiom-start/>I am very jealous<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I am jealous <supplied>with</supplied> a great jealousy”</note> for Jerusalem and for Zion! <verse-number id="Zec 1:15">15</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>I am extremely angry<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<supplied>With</supplied> a great anger I am angry”</note> with the nations that are at ease, for <supplied>while</supplied> I was a little angry, they <idiom-start/>furthered disaster<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “helped disaster”</note> <verse-number id="Zec 1:16">16</verse-number>Therefore, thus says Yahweh: “I have returned to Jerusalem with compassion. My temple<note>Or “house”</note> will be built in it,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh of hosts, “and a measuring line will be stretched out over Jerusalem.” ’ <verse-number id="Zec 1:17">17</verse-number>Proclaim again, saying, ‘Thus says Yahweh of hosts: “My cities shall again overflow from prosperity, and Yahweh will comfort Zion again, and he will choose Jerusalem again.” ’ ” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Zechariah’s Second Vision</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Zec 1:18">18</verse-number><note><cite title="BibleLEB2: Zec 1:18">Zechariah 1:18–2:17 </cite>in the English Bible is 2:1–13 in the Hebrew Bible</note> And I <idiom-start/>looked up<idiom-end/><note>Literally “lifted up my eyes”</note> and I saw, and look, <supplied>there were</supplied> four horns! <verse-number id="Zec 1:19">19</verse-number>And I said to the angel <supplied>who was</supplied> talking with me, “What <supplied>are</supplied> these?” And he said to me, “These <supplied>are</supplied> the horns that have scattered Judah, Israel, and Jerusalem.” <verse-number id="Zec 1:20">20</verse-number>Then Yahweh showed me four skilled craftsmen, <verse-number id="Zec 1:21">21</verse-number>and I asked, “What <supplied>are</supplied> these coming to do?” And he answered, saying, “These <supplied>are</supplied> the horns that scattered Judah, <idiom-start/>so that no man<idiom-end/><note>Literally “according to the mouth of a man”</note> lifted up his head; but these have come to frighten them, to strike down the horns of the nations that lifted a horn against the land of Judah to scatter it.” </p>
		</chapter>