<chapter id="Zec 2">
			<pericope>Zechariah’s Third Vision</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Zec 2:1">1</verse-number>And I <idiom-start/>looked up<idiom-end/><note>Literally “lifted up my eyes”</note> and I saw, and look, a man, and in his hand <supplied>was</supplied> a measuring rope! <verse-number id="Zec 2:2">2</verse-number>And I asked, “Where <supplied>are</supplied> you going?” And he answered me, “To measure Jerusalem to see what <supplied>is</supplied> its width and what <supplied>is</supplied> its length.” <verse-number id="Zec 2:3">3</verse-number>And look, the angel who was talking to me <supplied>was</supplied> coming forward, and another angel <supplied>was</supplied> coming forward to meet him. <verse-number id="Zec 2:4">4</verse-number>And he said to him, “Run, say to that young man, ‘Jerusalem shall be inhabited <idiom-start/>like villages without walls<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<supplied>like</supplied> open regions”</note> because of the multitude of people and animals in its midst. <verse-number id="Zec 2:5">5</verse-number>And I will be for it a wall of fire all around,’ <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh, ‘and I will be <supplied>the</supplied> glory in its midst.’ ” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Zec 2:6">6</verse-number>“Woe! Woe! Flee from <supplied>the</supplied> land of <supplied>the</supplied> north,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh, “for I have scattered you like <supplied>the</supplied> four winds of the heavens,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh. <verse-number id="Zec 2:7">7</verse-number>“Woe, Zion! Escape, you inhabitants of <supplied>the</supplied> daughter of Babylon!” <verse-number id="Zec 2:8">8</verse-number>For thus said Yahweh of hosts, after glory<note>The phrase “after glory” is difficult to interpret</note> he sent me against the nations plundering you: Truly, the one touching you <supplied>is</supplied> touching the apple<note>Hebrew “pupil,” but the expression “apple of his eye” has become well-established in English</note> of his eye. <verse-number id="Zec 2:9">9</verse-number>“Yes, look! I <supplied>am</supplied> going to wave my hand against them, and they will become plunder for their servants, and you will know that Yahweh of hosts has sent me. <verse-number id="Zec 2:10">10</verse-number>Sing and rejoice, O daughter of Zion, for look, I <supplied>am</supplied> coming and I will dwell in your midst,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh. <verse-number id="Zec 2:11">11</verse-number>“Many nations will join themselves to Yahweh on that day, and they will be my people, and I will dwell in your midst. And you will know that Yahweh of hosts has sent me to you. <verse-number id="Zec 2:12">12</verse-number>And Yahweh will inherit Judah <supplied>as</supplied> his portion <idiom-start/>in the holy land<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “upon <supplied>the</supplied> land of the holiness”</note> and he will again choose Jerusalem. <verse-number id="Zec 2:13">13</verse-number>Be silent, <idiom-start/>all people<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “all flesh”</note> before Yahweh, for he is roused from <idiom-start/>his holy dwelling<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “the dwelling place of his holiness”</note> </p>
		</chapter>