<chapter id="Zec 3">
			<pericope>Zechariah’s Fourth Vision</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Zec 3:1">1</verse-number>And he showed me Joshua the high priest standing <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of”</note> the angel of Yahweh; and Satan<note>Hebrew “the accuser,” or “the adversary”</note> was standing on his right to accuse him. <verse-number id="Zec 3:2">2</verse-number>But Yahweh said to Satan,<note>Hebrew “the accuser,” or “the adversary”</note> “Yahweh rebukes you, O Satan!<note>Hebrew “the accuser,” or “the adversary”</note> Yahweh who has chosen Jerusalem rebukes you! <supplied>Is</supplied> this not a stick snatched from the fire?” <verse-number id="Zec 3:3">3</verse-number>And Joshua was clothed <supplied>in</supplied> filthy garments and was standing <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of”</note> the angel. <verse-number id="Zec 3:4">4</verse-number>And he answered and said to the ones standing <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of”</note> him, saying, “Remove the filthy garments from him.” And he said to him, “See, I have taken away your guilt<note>The Hebrew term refers to guilt caused by sin (HALOT 800 s.v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Zec 3:2">2</cite>)</note> from you, and will clothe you <supplied>with</supplied> rich garments.” <verse-number id="Zec 3:5">5</verse-number>And I said, “Let them put a clean headband<note>Or “turban”</note> on his head.” And they put a clean headband on his head, and they clothed him <supplied>with</supplied> garments. And the angel of Yahweh <supplied>was</supplied> standing <supplied>by</supplied>. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Zec 3:6">6</verse-number>And the angel of Yahweh assured Joshua, saying, <verse-number id="Zec 3:7">7</verse-number>“Thus says Yahweh of hosts: ‘If you will walk in my ways, and if you will keep my requirements, then you will judge<note>Or “govern”</note> my house, and you will also guard my courtyards, and I will give to you passageways<note>Or “right of access”</note> among these that are standing here. <verse-number id="Zec 3:8">8</verse-number>Listen, please, O Joshua the high priest, you and your companions<note>Possibly his fellow priests</note> that are sitting <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of”</note> you. For <supplied>the</supplied> men <supplied>are</supplied> a sign that,<note>Hebrew “for”</note> look, I <supplied>am</supplied> going to bring my servant <supplied>the</supplied> Branch.<note>Hebrew “Sprout” or “Shoot” (“Branch” is a traditional rendering in English)</note> <verse-number id="Zec 3:9">9</verse-number>For consider, the stone that <idiom-start/>I set before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I gave to the face of, ”or “I gave in the presence of”</note> Joshua, on one stone <supplied>are</supplied> seven eyes.<note>Or “facets”</note> Look, <idiom-start/>I am going to engrave an inscription on it<idiom-end/>,’<note>Literally “I <supplied>am</supplied> going to engrave its engraving”</note> <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> Yahweh of hosts, ‘and I will remove the guilt of that land in a single day. <verse-number id="Zec 3:10">10</verse-number>On that day,’ <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> Yahweh of hosts, ‘you will invite <idiom-start/>one another<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a man to his friend”</note> under <supplied>the</supplied> vine and under <supplied>the</supplied> fig tree.’ ” </p>
		</chapter>