<chapter id="Zec 4">
			<pericope>Zechariah’s Fifth Vision</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Zec 4:1">1</verse-number>And the angel <supplied>who was</supplied> talking with me returned, and he wakened me as one who is wakened from his sleep. <verse-number id="Zec 4:2">2</verse-number>And he said to me, “What do you see?” And I said, “I see, and look, <idiom-start/>a lampstand all of gold<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “a lampstand of gold in its totality”</note> and a bowl <supplied>was</supplied> on its top, and its seven lamps on it, and seven lips on <supplied>each of</supplied> the lamps that <supplied>are</supplied> on its top. <verse-number id="Zec 4:3">3</verse-number>And <supplied>there are</supplied> two olive trees by it, one on the right of the bowl and the other on its left.” <verse-number id="Zec 4:4">4</verse-number>And I answered and said to the angel <supplied>who was</supplied> talking to me, “What <supplied>are</supplied> these, my lord?” <verse-number id="Zec 4:5">5</verse-number>And the angel <supplied>who was</supplied> talking with me answered and said to me, “Do you not know what these <supplied>are</supplied>?” And I said, “No, my lord.” <verse-number id="Zec 4:6">6</verse-number>And he answered and said to me, “This <supplied>is</supplied> the word of Yahweh to Zerubbabel, saying, ‘Not by strength and not by power, but <supplied>only</supplied> by my Spirit,’ says Yahweh of hosts. <verse-number id="Zec 4:7">7</verse-number>‘Who <supplied>are</supplied> you O great mountain? <idiom-start/>Before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “To the face of”</note> Zerubbabel <supplied>you will become</supplied> level ground, and he will bring out the top stone amid the shouts of “Grace, grace to it!” ’ ” <verse-number id="Zec 4:8">8</verse-number>And the word of Yahweh came to me, saying, <verse-number id="Zec 4:9">9</verse-number>“The hands of Zerubbabel have founded this house, and his hands will finish it. And you will know that Yahweh of hosts has sent me to you. <verse-number id="Zec 4:10">10</verse-number>For whoever has despised the day of small <supplied>things</supplied> will rejoice and will see the <idiom-start/>plumb line<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the tin stone”; this could refer to a plumb line or a plummet</note> in the hand of Zerubbabel.” </p>
			<p>These seven <supplied>are</supplied> the eyes of Yahweh which <supplied>are</supplied> ranging <idiom-start/>throughout the whole earth<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “in all the earth”</note> <verse-number id="Zec 4:11">11</verse-number>And I answered and said to him, “What <supplied>are</supplied> these two olive trees on the right of the lampstand and on its left?” <verse-number id="Zec 4:12">12</verse-number>And I replied a second <supplied>time</supplied> and asked him, “What <supplied>are</supplied> these two twigs of olive trees<note>Or “two clusters of olive branches”; literally “two ears of grain,” perhaps based on similarity of shape</note> on the right of the lampstand and on its left?” <verse-number id="Zec 4:13">13</verse-number>And he replied to me, “Do you not know what these <supplied>are</supplied>?” And I said, “No, my lord.” <verse-number id="Zec 4:14">14</verse-number>And he said, “These <supplied>are</supplied> the two <idiom-start/>anointed ones<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons of the olive oil”</note> standing by the Lord of the whole earth.” </p>
		</chapter>