<chapter id="Zec 5">
			<pericope>Zechariah’s Sixth Vision</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Zec 5:1">1</verse-number><idiom-start/>I looked up again<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “I did again, I lifted up my eyes”</note> and I saw, and look!—a flying scroll! <verse-number id="Zec 5:2">2</verse-number>And he asked me, “What <supplied>are</supplied> you seeing?” And I said, “I <supplied>am</supplied> seeing a flying scroll twenty cubits long and ten cubits wide.”<note>That is, thirty feet by fifteen feet</note> <verse-number id="Zec 5:3">3</verse-number>And he said to me, “This <supplied>is</supplied> the curse going out over the surface of the whole earth. For everyone who steals has gone unpunished<note>Many translations render this verb as “will be cut off”</note> according to it, and <supplied>likewise</supplied> everyone who swears <supplied>falsely</supplied> has gone unpunished according to it. <verse-number id="Zec 5:4">4</verse-number>‘I have sent it out,’ <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> Yahweh of hosts, ‘and it will go into the house of the thief and into the house of the one swearing <idiom-start/>falsely by my name<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “by my name to lie”</note> and it will spend the night in that<note>Hebrew “his”</note> house and will destroy it, with its timber and its stone.’ ” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Zechariah’s Seventh Vision</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Zec 5:5">5</verse-number>And the angel who was speaking to me went out, and he said to me, “<idiom-start/>Please look up<idiom-end/>!<note>Literally “Lift, please, your eyes!”</note> See what this <supplied>is</supplied> going out.” <verse-number id="Zec 5:6">6</verse-number>And I asked, “What <supplied>is</supplied> it?” And he said, “This <supplied>is</supplied> a basket<note>Or “an ephah,” a measure of grain</note> going out. And he said, “This <supplied>is</supplied> their iniquity<note>Hebrew “eye”; other ancient versions (LXX, Syriac) read “iniquity”</note> throughout all the earth. <verse-number id="Zec 5:7">7</verse-number>And look, the lead cover was lifted and a woman <supplied>was</supplied> sitting inside the basket.<note>Or “ephah,” a measure of grain</note> <verse-number id="Zec 5:8">8</verse-number>And he said, “This <supplied>is</supplied> Wickedness!” And he thrust her <supplied>back down</supplied> into the basket,<note>Or “ephah,” a measure of grain</note> and threw the lead cover on top of it.<note>That is, on top of the “basket” or “ephah”</note> <verse-number id="Zec 5:9">9</verse-number>And I <idiom-start/>looked up<idiom-end/><note>Literally “lifted up my eyes”</note> and saw, and look!—two women coming forward, and <supplied>the</supplied> wind <supplied>was</supplied> in their wings, and they had wings like those of a stork, and they lifted up the basket<note>Or “ephah,” a measure of grain</note> between the earth and the sky.<note>Or “heaven”</note> <verse-number id="Zec 5:10">10</verse-number>And I asked the angel who was talking to me, “Where <supplied>are</supplied> they taking the basket?”<note>Or “ephah,” a measure of grain</note> <verse-number id="Zec 5:11">11</verse-number>And he said to me, “To build for it a house<note>Or “temple”</note> in the land of Shinar,<note>That is, Babylon (<cite title="BibleLEB2: Ge 11:2">Gen 11:2</cite>)</note> and <supplied>when</supplied> it is put in place, it will be placed there on its site.” </p>
		</chapter>