<chapter id="Zec 6">
			<pericope>Zechariah’s Eighth Vision</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Zec 6:1">1</verse-number><idiom-start/>I looked up again<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “I did again, I lifted up my eyes”</note> and I saw, and look!—four chariots coming out from between two mountains, and the mountains <supplied>were</supplied> mountains of bronze. <verse-number id="Zec 6:2">2</verse-number>With the first chariot <supplied>there were</supplied> red horses, and with the second chariot <supplied>there were</supplied> black horses. <verse-number id="Zec 6:3">3</verse-number>And with the third chariot <supplied>there were</supplied> white horses, and with the fourth chariot <supplied>there were</supplied> strong<note>Other ancient versions read “grey” here</note> dappled horses. <verse-number id="Zec 6:4">4</verse-number>And I answered and said to the angel <supplied>that was</supplied> talking to me, “What <supplied>are</supplied> these, my lord?” <verse-number id="Zec 6:5">5</verse-number>And the angel answered and said to me, “These <supplied>are</supplied> the four winds<note>Or “spirits” (The same Hebrew word can be translated “wind” or “spirit” depending on the context)</note> of the heavens going out after presenting themselves before the Lord of all the earth. <verse-number id="Zec 6:6">6</verse-number><idiom-start/>The one with<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Her with which”</note> the black horses <supplied>is</supplied> going out to <supplied>the</supplied> north country, and the white <supplied>horses</supplied> go after them,<note>Some interpret the word “after” to indicate a westward direction</note> while the dappled <supplied>ones</supplied> go to the south country.” <verse-number id="Zec 6:7">7</verse-number>When the strong <supplied>horses</supplied> went out, they were anxious to go to patrol the earth. And he<note>That is, “Lord of all the earth”</note> said, “Go, patrol the earth.” And they patrolled the earth. <verse-number id="Zec 6:8">8</verse-number>And he cried out to me and said to me, “See those going out to <supplied>the</supplied> north country have set my spirit at rest in the north country.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Branch is Crowned</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Zec 6:9">9</verse-number>And the word of Yahweh came to me, saying, <verse-number id="Zec 6:10">10</verse-number>“Collect<note>The imperative “Collect” has no object; many translations supply “silver and gold” or “an offering”</note> from the exiles—from Heldai, Tobijah, and from Jedaiah, <supplied>all of</supplied> whom came from Babylon—and go on that day, go <supplied>to the</supplied> house of Josiah son of Zephaniah. <verse-number id="Zec 6:11">11</verse-number>Take <supplied>the</supplied> silver and gold and make a crown, and set <supplied>it</supplied> on the head of Joshua son of Jehozadak, the high priest. <verse-number id="Zec 6:12">12</verse-number>And say to him, ‘Thus says Yahweh of hosts: “Look, <supplied>here is</supplied> a man whose name <supplied>is</supplied> Branch,<note>Hebrew “Sprout” or “Shoot” (“Branch” is a traditional rendering in English)</note> and from his place he will sprout, and he will build the temple of Yahweh. <verse-number id="Zec 6:13">13</verse-number>And he will build the temple of Yahweh, and he will bear majesty and will sit and rule on his throne. And he shall be a priest on his throne, and the counsel of peace will be between the two of them.” ’<note>That is, between king and priest</note> <verse-number id="Zec 6:14">14</verse-number>And the crown will be for Helem,<note>“Helem” is probably another name for Heldai (v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Zec 6:10">10</cite>)</note> for Tobijah, for Jedaiah, and for Hen<note>“Hen” is frequently understood as a reference to Josiah (v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Zec 6:10">10</cite>)</note> son of Zephaniah, as a memorial in the temple of Yahweh. <verse-number id="Zec 6:15">15</verse-number>And those who are far off will come and build the temple of Yahweh, and you will know that Yahweh of hosts has sent me to you. And it will happen if you will listen diligently to the voice of Yahweh your God.” </p>
		</chapter>