<chapter id="Zec 7">
			<p><verse-number id="Zec 7">7</verse-number><verse-number id="Zec 7:1">1</verse-number> <idiom-start/>And then<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “and it happened”</note> in the fourth year of King Darius, the word of Yahweh came to Zechariah on <supplied>the</supplied> fourth <supplied>day</supplied> of the ninth month, <supplied>which is</supplied> Kislev. <verse-number id="Zec 7:2">2</verse-number>And <supplied>the people of</supplied> Bethel sent Sharezer and Regem-Melech, and their<note>Hebrew “his”</note> men, to entreat <idiom-start/>the favor<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the face”</note> of Yahweh, <verse-number id="Zec 7:3">3</verse-number>saying to the <idiom-start/>priests of the house of Yahweh of hosts<idiom-end/><note>Literally “priests who <supplied>are</supplied> for the house of Yahweh of hosts”</note> and to the prophets, “Should I mourn in the fifth month and keep myself separate<note>Or “abstain”; some interpret this as a reference to fasting</note> as I have done for these many years?” <verse-number id="Zec 7:4">4</verse-number>And the word of Yahweh of hosts came to me, saying, <verse-number id="Zec 7:5">5</verse-number>“Say to all the people of the land and to the priests: ‘When you fasted and lamented in the fifth and seventh months for these seventy years, did you really fast for me? <verse-number id="Zec 7:6">6</verse-number>And when you eat and drink, are you not eating and drinking <supplied>for yourselves</supplied>? <verse-number id="Zec 7:7">7</verse-number><supplied>Are</supplied> not <supplied>these</supplied> the words that Yahweh proclaimed <idiom-start/>through<idiom-end/><note>Literally “by the hand of”</note> the former prophets, when Jerusalem and <idiom-start/>its surrounding towns<idiom-end/><note>Literally “her towns around her”</note> were inhabited and at ease, and the Negev<note>The Negev is an arid region south of the Judean hills</note> and the Shephelah<note>The Shephelah is a geographical area on the western edge of the Judean hills</note> were inhabited?’ ” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Zec 7:8">8</verse-number>And the word of Yahweh came to Zechariah, saying, <verse-number id="Zec 7:9">9</verse-number>“Thus says Yahweh of hosts: ‘Judge <supplied>with</supplied> trustworthy justice, and show<note>Literally “do”</note> steadfast love and compassion <idiom-start/>to one another<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “a man his brother”</note> <verse-number id="Zec 7:10">10</verse-number>You must not oppress <supplied>the</supplied> widow, <supplied>the</supplied> orphan, <supplied>the</supplied> foreigner, and <supplied>the</supplied> needy. You must not devise evil in your heart <idiom-start/>against one another<idiom-end/>.’<note>Literally “a man his brother”</note> <verse-number id="Zec 7:11">11</verse-number>But they refused to listen, and turned<note>Hebrew “gave”</note> a stubborn shoulder and <idiom-start/>stopped their ears from listening<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “their ears were heavy from hearing”</note> <verse-number id="Zec 7:12">12</verse-number><idiom-start/>They made their hearts adamant<idiom-end/><note>Literally “They set their hearts <supplied>like</supplied> hard stone”</note> in order not to hear the law<note>Hebrew <i>torah</i></note> and the words that Yahweh of hosts had sent by his spirit through<note>Literally “by the hand of”</note> the former prophets; <supplied>therefore</supplied> great wrath came from Yahweh of hosts. <verse-number id="Zec 7:13">13</verse-number>‘Thus, just as I<note>Hebrew “he called” (but still referring to Yahweh)</note> called and they would not hear, so they will call and I will not hear,’ says Yahweh of hosts. <verse-number id="Zec 7:14">14</verse-number>‘And I scattered them with a wind among all the nations that they had not known; the land was made desolate behind them— no one crossing through <supplied>it</supplied> or returning—and they made the desirable land<note>Hebrew “land of desire,” but this could be understood as a land characterized by desire rather than a desirable land</note> a desolation.’ ” </p>
		</chapter>