<chapter id="Zec 9">
			<p><verse-number id="Zec 9">9</verse-number><verse-number id="Zec 9:1">1</verse-number> An oracle. The word of Yahweh <supplied>is</supplied> against the land of Hadrach, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>and Damascus <supplied>is</supplied> its resting place. </li1>
				<li2>For to Yahweh belongs the eye of humankind,<note>“Eye of humankind” is difficult to understand in this context; some scholars emend the phrase to “cities of Aram” or “capital of Aram”</note> </li2>
				<li3>and all the tribes of Israel, </li3>
				<li1><verse-number id="Zec 9:2">2</verse-number>and also Hamath, <supplied>which</supplied> borders on it; </li1>
				<li2>Tyre and Sidon—yes, they are very wise!<note>That is, wise in their own eyes (ironic)</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Zec 9:3">3</verse-number>Tyre has built a fortification for itself,<note>Hebrew “her”</note> </li1>
				<li2>and it heaped up silver like dust, </li2>
				<li2>and gold like <supplied>the</supplied> mud of <supplied>the</supplied> streets. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Zec 9:4">4</verse-number>Look! The Lord will drive it<note>Hebrew “her”</note> out </li1>
				<li2>and will hurl its<note>Hebrew “her”</note> outer ramparts into the sea, </li2>
				<li3>and it<note>Hebrew “she”</note> will be consumed by fire. </li3>
				<li1><verse-number id="Zec 9:5">5</verse-number>Ashkelon will see and will be afraid, </li1>
				<li2>and Gaza will writhe exceedingly, </li2>
				<li2>and Ekron <supplied>also</supplied>, because its hope is ruined.<note>Traditionally “ashamed”; some presuppose a different Hebrew form and translate “withered”</note> </li2>
				<li1>And the king from Gaza will perish, </li1>
				<li2>and Ashkelon will not be inhabited. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Zec 9:6">6</verse-number>A mongrel people<note>That is, a people of mixed marriage; “half-breeds”</note> will dwell in Ashdod, </li1>
				<li2>and I will cut down the pride of <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Zec 9:7">7</verse-number>I will remove its<note>Hebrew “his”</note> blood from its<note>Hebrew “his”</note> mouth, </li1>
				<li2>and its<note>Hebrew “his”</note> abominations from between its<note>Hebrew “his”</note> teeth. </li2>
				<li1>And it<note>Hebrew “he”</note> too will be a remnant for our God; </li1>
				<li2>and it<note>Hebrew “he”</note> will be like a tribal chief<note>This word is sometimes interpreted as “clan”</note> in Judah, </li2>
				<li2>and Ekron <supplied>will be</supplied> like <supplied>the</supplied> Jebusite. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Zec 9:8">8</verse-number>But I will encamp at my temple<note>Or “house”</note> <supplied>like a</supplied> guard, </li1>
				<li2>against those crossing through and returning; </li2>
				<li1>no oppressor will cross through them again, </li1>
				<li2>for now I have seen with my <supplied>own</supplied> eyes. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Zec 9:9">9</verse-number>Rejoice greatly, O daughter of Zion! </li1>
				<li2>Shout aloud, O daughter of Jerusalem! </li2>
				<li1>Look! Your king comes to you; </li1>
				<li2>he <supplied>is</supplied> righteous and victorious, </li2>
				<li1>humble and riding on a donkey, </li1>
				<li2>and on a male donkey, <idiom-start/>the foal of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the son of ”</note> a female donkey! </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Zec 9:10">10</verse-number>And I will cut off <supplied>the</supplied> chariot from Ephraim, </li1>
				<li2>and <supplied>the</supplied> horse from Jerusalem; </li2>
				<li1>the battle bow will be cut down, </li1>
				<li2>and he will announce peace to the nations. </li2>
				<li1>His dominion <supplied>will be</supplied> from sea to sea, </li1>
				<li2>and from <supplied>the</supplied> River<note>That is, the Euphrates</note> to <supplied>the</supplied> ends of <supplied>the</supplied> earth. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Zec 9:11">11</verse-number><supplied>As for</supplied> you also, because of the blood of your covenant, </li1>
				<li2>I will release your prisoners from <idiom-start/>the waterless pit<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “<supplied>the</supplied> cistern there is not water in him”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Zec 9:12">12</verse-number>Return to <supplied>the</supplied> fortress, </li1>
				<li2>O prisoners of hope; </li2>
				<li1>today <supplied>I am</supplied> declaring <supplied>that</supplied> I will repay you double. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Zec 9:13">13</verse-number>For I have bent Judah <supplied>as</supplied> my bow; </li1>
				<li2>I have set Ephraim <supplied>as an arrow</supplied>. </li2>
				<li1>I will set in motion your sons, O Zion, </li1>
				<li2>against your sons, O Javan.<note>That is, Greece</note> </li2>
				<li1>I will wield you like the sword of a warrior. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Zec 9:14">14</verse-number>Then Yahweh will appear over them, </li1>
				<li2>and his arrow will go forth like lightning; </li2>
				<li1>and my Lord Yahweh will blow the trumpet, </li1>
				<li2>and he shall go out in the storm winds of <supplied>the</supplied> south. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Zec 9:15">15</verse-number>Yahweh of hosts will defend them, </li1>
				<li2>and they will devour and subdue the slingstones;<note>Perhaps metonymy for the slingers of stones</note> </li2>
				<li1>they will drink, they will make noise<note>LXX reads “they will drink blood like wine”</note> like wine, </li1>
				<li2>and they will be full like the sacrificial basin,<note>That is, the ceremonial bowl used by the priest for sprinkling blood</note> </li2>
				<li2><supplied>drenched</supplied> like the corners of an altar. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Zec 9:16">16</verse-number>And Yahweh their God will save them on that day, </li1>
				<li2>as the flock of his people; </li2>
				<li1>for <supplied>they are like</supplied> the stones of a diadem, </li1>
				<li2>glittering on his land. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Zec 9:17">17</verse-number>For how <supplied>great is</supplied> his goodness, and how <supplied>great is</supplied> his beauty! </li1>
				<li2>Grain will make the young men thrive, </li2>
				<li1>and new wine <supplied>the</supplied> young women. </li1>
			</ul>
		</chapter>