<chapter id="Zec 10">
			<pericope>Yahweh Gives Rain</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Zec 10:1">1</verse-number>Ask rain from Yahweh in the season of <supplied>the</supplied> spring rain— </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>Yahweh, who makes storm clouds, </li1>
				<li1>and he gives showers of rain to them, </li1>
				<li2>to everyone vegetation in the field. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Zec 10:2">2</verse-number>Because the household gods<note>Hebrew <i>teraphim</i></note> speak deceit, </li1>
				<li2>and those who practice divination see a lie, </li2>
				<li1>and the dreamers of vanity speak in vain. </li1>
				<li2>Therefore <supplied>the people</supplied> wander like sheep;<note>Or “flocks”; the Hebrew term refers collectively to both sheep and goats (small livestock animals)</note> </li2>
				<li1>they are afflicted because there is no shepherd. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Zec 10:3">3</verse-number><idiom-start/>My anger burns<idiom-end/><note>Literally “My nose becomes hot”</note> against the shepherds, </li1>
				<li2>and I will punish the leaders,<note>Or “male goats”</note> </li2>
				<li1>because Yahweh of hosts watches over his flock,<note>Or “herd”</note> </li1>
				<li2>the house of Judah; </li2>
				<li3>and he will make them like his majestic horse in war. </li3>
				<li1><verse-number id="Zec 10:4">4</verse-number>From them<note>Hebrew “him” (or “it”), referring to the flock in v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Zec 10:3">3</cite></note> <supplied>the</supplied> cornerstone will go out, </li1>
				<li2>from them<note>Hebrew “him” (or “it”), referring to the flock in v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Zec 10:3">3</cite></note> <supplied>the</supplied> tent peg, </li2>
				<li1>from them<note>Hebrew “him” (or “it”), referring to the flock in v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Zec 10:3">3</cite></note> <supplied>the</supplied> battle bow, </li1>
				<li2>from them<note>Hebrew “him” (or “it”), referring to the flock in v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Zec 10:3">3</cite></note> every ruler, </li2>
				<li3><supplied>all</supplied> together. </li3>
				<li1><verse-number id="Zec 10:5">5</verse-number>And they will be like warriors, </li1>
				<li2>trampling in the mud of <supplied>the</supplied> streets in the battle. </li2>
				<li1>They will fight, because Yahweh <supplied>is</supplied> with them, </li1>
				<li2>and they will put to shame <supplied>the</supplied> riders on horses. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Zec 10:6">6</verse-number>And I will strengthen the house of Judah, </li1>
				<li2>and the house of Joseph I will save. </li2>
				<li1>And I will bring them back, because I have compassion on them, </li1>
				<li2>and they will be as if I had not rejected them, </li2>
				<li2>for I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh their God, and I will answer them. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Zec 10:7">7</verse-number>And <supplied>the people of</supplied> Ephraim will be like <supplied>a</supplied> warrior, </li1>
				<li2>and their heart will be glad as <supplied>with</supplied> wine. </li2>
				<li1>And their children will see and rejoice; </li1>
				<li2>their heart will shout in exultation in Yahweh. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Zec 10:8">8</verse-number>I will whistle to them and gather them, </li1>
				<li2>for I have redeemed them, </li2>
				<li2>and they will become numerous as they have been numerous <supplied>before</supplied>. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Zec 10:9">9</verse-number>Though I sow<note>Or “scatter”</note> them among the nations, </li1>
				<li2>in the distant places they will remember me, </li2>
				<li2>and they will stay alive with their children, and they will return. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Zec 10:10">10</verse-number>And I will bring them back from the land of Egypt, </li1>
				<li2>and from Assyria I will gather them. </li2>
				<li1>To the land of Gilead and Lebanon I will bring them, </li1>
				<li2>until no <supplied>room</supplied> will be found for them <supplied>there</supplied>. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Zec 10:11">11</verse-number>And he<note>LXX reads “they,” referring to the Israelites (so NIV, NRSV, NASB)</note> will pass through the sea of distress, </li1>
				<li2>and he will strike the waves of the sea, </li2>
				<li2>and all <supplied>the</supplied> depths of the Nile will dry up. </li2>
				<li1>The pride of Assyria will be brought low, </li1>
				<li2>and the scepter of Egypt will depart. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Zec 10:12">12</verse-number>I will make them strong in Yahweh, </li1>
				<li2>and in his name they will walk, </li2>
				<li3><idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> Yahweh. </li3>
			</ul>
		</chapter>