<chapter id="Zec 11">
			<p><verse-number id="Zec 11">11</verse-number><verse-number id="Zec 11:1">1</verse-number> Open your doors, <supplied>O</supplied> Lebanon, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>so that fire will devour your cedars! </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Zec 11:2">2</verse-number>Wail, O juniper,<note>Or “cypress”</note> for <supplied>the</supplied> cedar has fallen, </li1>
				<li2>for <supplied>the</supplied> magnificent <supplied>trees</supplied> are ruined! </li2>
				<li1>Wail, oaks of Bashan, </li1>
				<li2>for the impenetrable forest has come down! </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Zec 11:3">3</verse-number><supplied>Listen to</supplied> the wailing of the shepherds, </li1>
				<li2>for their splendor is ruined! </li2>
				<li1><supplied>Listen to</supplied> the roar of <supplied>the</supplied> young lions, </li1>
				<li2>for the thickets of the Jordan are ruined! </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Two Shepherds</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Zec 11:4">4</verse-number>Thus says Yahweh my God: “Shepherd the flock<note>The Hebrew term refers collectively to both sheep and goats (small livestock animals)</note> <supplied>doomed</supplied> to slaughter. <verse-number id="Zec 11:5">5</verse-number>The ones buying them kill them and go unpunished, and the ones selling them say, ‘Blessed <supplied>be</supplied> Yahweh, for I have become rich.’ Their own shepherds have no compassion for them. <verse-number id="Zec 11:6">6</verse-number>For I will no longer have compassion on the inhabitants of the land,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> Yahweh. “Look, I <supplied>am</supplied> going to cause humankind to fall, each into the hand of his neighbor, and into the hand of his king; and they will devastate the land, and I will not deliver <supplied>anyone</supplied> from their hand.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Zec 11:7">7</verse-number>And I shepherded the flock<note>The Hebrew term refers collectively to both sheep and goats (small livestock animals)</note> <supplied>doomed</supplied> to slaughter, even<note>Hebrew “therefore”</note> the afflicted<note>LXX reads “merchants <supplied>of the flock</supplied>” which is reflected in some English translations</note> of the flock.<note>The Hebrew term refers collectively to both sheep and goats (small livestock animals)</note> I took two staffs, one I called Kindness, and the other I called Unity, and I shepherded the flock.<note>The Hebrew term refers collectively to both sheep and goats (small livestock animals)</note> <verse-number id="Zec 11:8">8</verse-number>And I got rid of three shepherds in one month, for <idiom-start/>I grew impatient<idiom-end/><note>Literally “my soul became short”</note> with them, and <idiom-start/>they also became tired of me<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “also their soul detested me”</note> <verse-number id="Zec 11:9">9</verse-number>So I said, “I will not shepherd you! The <supplied>one</supplied> dying will die, and the <supplied>one</supplied> to be destroyed will be destroyed. And the <supplied>ones</supplied> remaining, let them devour <idiom-start/>the flesh of each other<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “each the flesh of her neighbor”</note> <verse-number id="Zec 11:10">10</verse-number>And I took my staff Kindness and broke it, to break my covenant that I <idiom-start/>had made<idiom-end/><note>Literally “had cut”</note> with all the peoples. <verse-number id="Zec 11:11">11</verse-number>And it was broken on that day. Then the afflicted<note>LXX reads “merchants (of the flock)” which is reflected in some English translations</note> of the flock,<note>The Hebrew term refers collectively to both sheep and goats (small livestock animals)</note> the <supplied>ones who were</supplied> watching me, knew that it <supplied>was</supplied> the word of Yahweh. <verse-number id="Zec 11:12">12</verse-number>And I said to them, “If <idiom-start/>it seems right to you<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “<supplied>it is</supplied> good in your eyes”</note> give <supplied>me</supplied> my wages, but if not, <idiom-start/>keep them<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “refrain”</note> And they weighed out my wages, thirty silver <supplied>shekels</supplied>. <verse-number id="Zec 11:13">13</verse-number>And Yahweh said to me, “Throw it to the potter,”<note>Syriac reads “treasury,” followed by NAB, NRSV, TEV</note> <idiom-start/>this noble price<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the price of honor”</note> <supplied>at</supplied> which I was valued by them!” So I took the thirty silver <supplied>shekels</supplied> and I threw them to the potter<note>Syriac reads “treasury,” followed by NAB, NRSV, TEV</note> <supplied>in</supplied> the house of Yahweh. <verse-number id="Zec 11:14">14</verse-number>Then I broke my second staff Unity to break the family ties between Judah and Israel. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Zec 11:15">15</verse-number>And Yahweh said to me, “Take again the implements<note>Hebrew “implement”</note> of a foolish shepherd. <verse-number id="Zec 11:16">16</verse-number>For look, I <supplied>am</supplied> raising up a shepherd in the land who will not attend to the <supplied>ones that are</supplied> perishing; he will not seek the young man,<note>Syriac and other ancient versions read “the wandering” or “the scattered,” as do several English translations</note> he will not heal the <supplied>ones that are</supplied> crushed and he will not sustain the healthy <supplied>ones</supplied>; he will devour the flesh of the <idiom-start/>fattened ones<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the stall-fed”</note> and tear apart <supplied>even</supplied> their hoofs. </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Zec 11:17">17</verse-number>“Woe, my worthless shepherd </li1>
				<li2>who deserts the flock!<note>The Hebrew term refers collectively to both sheep and goats (small livestock animals)</note> </li2>
				<li1><supplied>May</supplied> a sword <supplied>fall</supplied> on his arm </li1>
				<li2>and on <idiom-start/>his right eye<idiom-end/>!<note>Literally “the eye of his right”</note> </li2>
				<li1>May his arm wither completely </li1>
				<li2>and <idiom-start/>his right eye<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the eye of his right”</note> be utterly blinded!” </li2>
			</ul>
		</chapter>