<chapter id="2 Th 2">
			<pericope>The Man of Lawlessness Will Be Revealed</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Th 2:1">1</verse-number> Now we ask you, brothers, concerning the coming of our Lord Jesus Christ and our assembling to him, <verse-number id="2 Th 2:2">2</verse-number>that you not be easily shaken from your composure, nor be troubled either by a spirit or by a message or by a letter <idiom-start/>alleged to be from us<idiom-end/><note>Literally “as <supplied>if</supplied> by us”</note>, to the effect that the day of the Lord has arrived. <verse-number id="2 Th 2:3">3</verse-number>Do not let anyone deceive you in any way, for <supplied>that day will not come</supplied> unless the rebellion comes first, and the man of lawlessness is revealed, the son of destruction, <verse-number id="2 Th 2:4">4</verse-number>who opposes and who exalts himself over every so-called god or object of worship, so that he sits down in the temple of God, proclaiming that he himself is God. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Th 2:5">5</verse-number>Do you not remember that <supplied>while</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“were”) which is understood as temporal</note> we were still with you, we were saying these <supplied>things</supplied> to you? <verse-number id="2 Th 2:6">6</verse-number>And you know that which restrains <supplied>him</supplied> now, so that he will be revealed in his own time. <verse-number id="2 Th 2:7">7</verse-number>For the mystery of lawlessness is at work already; only the one who now restrains<note>Or “restrains it” (referring to the “mystery of lawlessness”; or “restrains him” (referring to the “man of lawlessness” in v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:2 Th 2:3">3</cite>)</note> <supplied>will do so</supplied> until he is out of the way,<note>Literally “out of the midst”</note> <verse-number id="2 Th 2:8">8</verse-number>and then the lawless one will be revealed, whom the Lord Jesus will slay with the breath of his mouth, and wipe out by the appearance of his coming, <verse-number id="2 Th 2:9">9</verse-number>whose coming is in accordance with the working of Satan, with all power and signs and lying wonders, <verse-number id="2 Th 2:10">10</verse-number>and with every unrighteous deception against those who are perishing, in place of which they did not accept the love of the truth, so that they would be saved. <verse-number id="2 Th 2:11">11</verse-number>And because of this, God sends them <idiom-start/>a powerful delusion<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a working of deceit”</note> so that they will believe the lie, <verse-number id="2 Th 2:12">12</verse-number>in order that all may be condemned who did not believe the truth, but delighted in unrighteousness. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Stand Firm and Hold Fast</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Th 2:13">13</verse-number>But we ought to give thanks to God always concerning you, brothers <supplied>dearly</supplied> loved by the Lord, because God has chosen you <supplied>as</supplied> first fruits for salvation by the sanctification of the Spirit and faith in the truth, <verse-number id="2 Th 2:14">14</verse-number>for which <supplied>purpose</supplied> he called<note>Some manuscripts have “he also called”</note> you through our gospel for the obtaining of the glory of our Lord Jesus Christ. <verse-number id="2 Th 2:15">15</verse-number>So then, brothers, stand firm and hold fast to the traditions which you were taught, whether by <supplied>spoken</supplied> word or by letter from us. <verse-number id="2 Th 2:16">16</verse-number>Now may our Lord Jesus Christ himself and God our Father, who has loved us and given <supplied>us</supplied> eternal encouragement and good hope by grace, <verse-number id="2 Th 2:17">17</verse-number>encourage your hearts and strengthen <supplied>you</supplied> in every good work and word. </p>
		</chapter>