<chapter id="Ne 1">
			<pericope>Nehemiah’s Prayer for the People</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ne 1:1">1</verse-number>The words of Nehemiah son of Hacaliah. </p>
			<p>It happened in the month of Kislev, in the twentieth year, that I myself was in the citadel in Susa, <verse-number id="Ne 1:2">2</verse-number>and one of my brothers, Hanani, came with some men from Judah. I asked them about the Jews who had escaped the captivity and about Jerusalem. <verse-number id="Ne 1:3">3</verse-number>They replied to me, “The survivors in the province who have survived the captivity are in great trouble and disgrace. The wall of Jerusalem is broken down, and its gates have been burned in the fire.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ne 1:4">4</verse-number>When I heard these words, I sat and wept and mourned for days, and I was fasting and praying before the God of the heavens. <verse-number id="Ne 1:5">5</verse-number>I said, “O Yahweh God of the heavens, the great and awesome one who keeps the covenant and loyal love for the ones who love him and for those who keep his commands. <verse-number id="Ne 1:6">6</verse-number>Please, let your ear be attentive and your eyes open to hear the prayer of your servant that I am praying before you by day and by night for your servants, the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and confessing the sins of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> that we have sinned against you. I and my father’s house have sinned. <verse-number id="Ne 1:7">7</verse-number>We have certainly offended you and have not kept the commands, regulations, and judgments that you have commanded your servant Moses. <verse-number id="Ne 1:8">8</verse-number>Please, remember the word that you have commanded to your servant Moses, saying, ‘If you act unfaithfully I will scatter you all among the nations. <verse-number id="Ne 1:9">9</verse-number>But if you return to me and keep my commandments and do them, even though all of your outcasts are at the furthest parts of heaven, I will gather them and bring them to the place which I have chosen to make my name dwell.’ <verse-number id="Ne 1:10">10</verse-number>They are your servants and your people whom you have redeemed by your great power and by your strong hand. <verse-number id="Ne 1:11">11</verse-number>O Lord, please let your ear be attentive to the prayer of your servant and to the prayer of your servants who delight to revere in your name. Please, let your servant be successful this day and give him compassion before this man.” </p>
			<p>I was cupbearer for the king. </p>
		</chapter>