<chapter id="Ne 7">
			<p><verse-number id="Ne 7">7</verse-number><verse-number id="Ne 7:1">1</verse-number> Now when the wall had been built and I had erected the doors and appointed the gatekeepers, singers, and the Levites, <verse-number id="Ne 7:2">2</verse-number>I gave command over Jerusalem to my brother Hanani and Hananiah the commander of the citadel. For he was a faithful man and feared God more than many. <verse-number id="Ne 7:3">3</verse-number>I said to them, “Do not open the gates of Jerusalem until the sun is hot. While they are standing guard let them shut and fasten the doors. And appoint guards from the inhabitants of Jerusalem, one at his post and another opposite his house.” <verse-number id="Ne 7:4">4</verse-number>The city <supplied>was</supplied> widespread and large, but the people in it were few and no houses were rebuilt. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Lists of the Exiles Who Returned</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ne 7:5">5</verse-number>Then my God put into my heart to assemble the nobles, the prefects, and the people to be enrolled. I found the book of the genealogy of those who first came back, and I found <supplied>this</supplied> written upon it: </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ne 7:6">6</verse-number>These are the people of the province who came up from captivity of the exiles whom Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon had carried into exile. They returned to Jerusalem and to Judah, each one to his city. <verse-number id="Ne 7:7">7</verse-number>These came with Zerubbabel, Joshua, Nehemiah, Azariah, Raamiah, Nahamani, Mordecai, Bilshan, Mispereth, Bigvai, Nehum, Baanah. </p>
			<p>The number of the men of the people of Israel: <verse-number id="Ne 7:8">8</verse-number>the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Parosh, two thousand one hundred and seventy-two. <verse-number id="Ne 7:9">9</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Shephatiah, three hundred and seventy-two. <verse-number id="Ne 7:10">10</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Arah, six hundred and fifty-two. <verse-number id="Ne 7:11">11</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Pahath-Moab, of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Jeshua and Joab, two thousand eight hundred and eighteen. <verse-number id="Ne 7:12">12</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Elam, one thousand two hundred and fifty-four. <verse-number id="Ne 7:13">13</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Zattu, eight hundred and forty-five. <verse-number id="Ne 7:14">14</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Zaccai, seven hundred and sixty. <verse-number id="Ne 7:15">15</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Binnui, six hundred and forty-eight. <verse-number id="Ne 7:16">16</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Bebai, six hundred and twenty-eight. <verse-number id="Ne 7:17">17</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Azgad, two thousand three hundred and twenty-two. <verse-number id="Ne 7:18">18</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Adonikam, six hundred and sixty-seven. <verse-number id="Ne 7:19">19</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Bigvai, two thousand and sixty-seven. <verse-number id="Ne 7:20">20</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Adin, six hundred and fifty-five. <verse-number id="Ne 7:21">21</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Ater, <supplied>namely</supplied> of Hezekiah, ninety-eight. <verse-number id="Ne 7:22">22</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Hashum, three hundred and twenty-eight. <verse-number id="Ne 7:23">23</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Bezai, three hundred and twenty-four. <verse-number id="Ne 7:24">24</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Hariph, one hundred and twelve. <verse-number id="Ne 7:25">25</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Gibeon, ninety-five. <verse-number id="Ne 7:26">26</verse-number>The men of Bethlehem and Netophah, one hundred and eighty-eight. <verse-number id="Ne 7:27">27</verse-number>The men of Anathoth, one hundred and twenty-eight. <verse-number id="Ne 7:28">28</verse-number>The men of Beth-azmaveth, forty-two. <verse-number id="Ne 7:29">29</verse-number>The men of Kiriath-Jearim, Kephirah, and Beeroth, seven hundred and forty-three. <verse-number id="Ne 7:30">30</verse-number>The men of Ramah and Geba, six hundred and twenty-one. <verse-number id="Ne 7:31">31</verse-number>The men of Micmash, one hundred and twenty-two. <verse-number id="Ne 7:32">32</verse-number>The men of Bethel and Ai, one hundred and twenty-three. <verse-number id="Ne 7:33">33</verse-number>The men of the other Nebo, fifty-two. <verse-number id="Ne 7:34">34</verse-number>The people<note>Or “sons”</note> of the other Elam, one thousand two hundred and fifty-four. <verse-number id="Ne 7:35">35</verse-number>The people<note>Or “sons”</note> of Harim, three hundred and twenty. <verse-number id="Ne 7:36">36</verse-number>The people<note>Or “sons”</note> of Jericho, three hundred and forty-five. <verse-number id="Ne 7:37">37</verse-number>The people<note>Or “sons”</note> of Lod, Hadid, and Ono, seven hundred and twenty-one. <verse-number id="Ne 7:38">38</verse-number>The people<note>Or “sons”</note> of Senaah, three thousand nine hundred and thirty. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ne 7:39">39</verse-number>The priests: The descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Jedaiah, of the house of Jeshua, nine hundred and seventy-three. <verse-number id="Ne 7:40">40</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Immer, one thousand and fifty-two. <verse-number id="Ne 7:41">41</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Pashhur, one thousand two hundred and forty-seven. <verse-number id="Ne 7:42">42</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Harim, one thousand and seventeen. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ne 7:43">43</verse-number>The Levites: the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Jeshua, <supplied>namely</supplied> of Kadmiel of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Hodaviah, seventy-four. <verse-number id="Ne 7:44">44</verse-number>The singers: the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Asaph, one hundred and forty-eight. <verse-number id="Ne 7:45">45</verse-number>The gatekeepers: the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Shallum, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Ater, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Talmon, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Akkub, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Hatita, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Shobai, one hundred and thirty-eight. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ne 7:46">46</verse-number>The temple servants: the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Ziha, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Hasupha, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Tabbaoth, <verse-number id="Ne 7:47">47</verse-number>the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Keros, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Siaha, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Padon, <verse-number id="Ne 7:48">48</verse-number>the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Lebanah, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Hagaba, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Shalmai, <verse-number id="Ne 7:49">49</verse-number>the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Hanan, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Giddel, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Gahar, <verse-number id="Ne 7:50">50</verse-number>the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Reaiah, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Rezin, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Nekoda, <verse-number id="Ne 7:51">51</verse-number>the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Gazzam, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Uzza, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Paseah, <verse-number id="Ne 7:52">52</verse-number>the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Besai, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Meunim, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Nephushesim, <verse-number id="Ne 7:53">53</verse-number>the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Bakbuk, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Hakupha, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Harhur, <verse-number id="Ne 7:54">54</verse-number>the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Bazlith, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Mehida, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Harsha, <verse-number id="Ne 7:55">55</verse-number>the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Barkos, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Sisera, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Temah, <verse-number id="Ne 7:56">56</verse-number>the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Neziah, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Hatipha. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ne 7:57">57</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Solomon’s servants: the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Sotai, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Sophereth, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Perida, <verse-number id="Ne 7:58">58</verse-number>the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Jaala, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Darkon, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Giddel, <verse-number id="Ne 7:59">59</verse-number>the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Shephatiah, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Hattil, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Pochereth-Hazzebaim, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Amon. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ne 7:60">60</verse-number>All the temple servants and the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Solomon’s servants were three hundred and ninety-two. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ne 7:61">61</verse-number>These were the ones who came up from Tel-melah, Tel-harsha, Cherub, Addon, and Immer, but they were not able to prove their ancestral houses or their descent, whether they were from Israel: <verse-number id="Ne 7:62">62</verse-number>the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Delaiah, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Tobiah, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Nekoda, six hundred and forty-two. <verse-number id="Ne 7:63">63</verse-number>And from the priests: the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Hobaiah, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Hakkoz, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Barzillai (who had taken as a wife from the daughters of Barzillai the Gileadite and was called by their name). <verse-number id="Ne 7:64">64</verse-number>These sought their record among those enrolled in the genealogy, but it was not found there, so they were excluded as unclean from the priesthood. <verse-number id="Ne 7:65">65</verse-number>So the governor said to them that they could not eat the most holy food until a priest could come with Urim and Thummim. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ne 7:66">66</verse-number>All of the assembly together was forty-two thousand three hundred and sixty, <verse-number id="Ne 7:67">67</verse-number>besides their servants and female slaves—these were seven thousand three hundred and thirty-seven. And the male and female singers were two hundred and forty-five,<note>After this verse, some versions add verse <cite title="BibleLEB2:Ne 7:68">68</cite>: “Their horses were seven hundred and thirty-six; their mules two hundred and forty-five”; compare <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ezr 2:66">Ezra 2:66</cite></note> <verse-number id="Ne 7:69">69</verse-number><note><cite title="BibleLEB2: Ne 7:69–73">Nehemiah 7:69–73 </cite>in the English Bible is 7:68–72 in the Hebrew Bible</note> <supplied>there were</supplied> four hundred and thirty-five camels and six thousand seven hundred and twenty male donkeys. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ne 7:70">70</verse-number>Now some from the heads of the <idiom-start/>families<idiom-end/><note>Literally “fathers”</note> gave to the work. The governor gave to the storehouse one thousand darics of gold, fifty basins, and five hundred and thirty priestly tunics. <verse-number id="Ne 7:71">71</verse-number>Now some of the heads of the <idiom-start/>families<idiom-end/><note>Literally “fathers”</note> gave to the storehouse of the work twenty thousand gold darics and two thousand two hundred silver minas. <verse-number id="Ne 7:72">72</verse-number>And what the rest of the people gave was twenty thousand darics of gold, and two thousand silver minas, and sixty-seven priestly tunics. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ne 7:73">73</verse-number>So the priests, the Levites, the gatekeepers, the singers, some of the people, the temple servants, and all Israel settled in their cities. When the seventh month came, the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> <supplied>were</supplied> in their cities. </p>
		</chapter>