<chapter id="Ne 8">
			<pericope>Ezra Reads the Law to the People</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ne 8:1">1</verse-number>All of the people gathered as one to the public square before the Water Gate. They asked Ezra the scribe to bring the book of the law<note>Hebrew <i>torah</i></note> of Moses that Yahweh had commanded Israel. <verse-number id="Ne 8:2">2</verse-number>So Ezra the priest brought the law<note>Hebrew <i>torah</i></note> before the assembly for <supplied>each</supplied> man and woman to hear with understanding, on the first day of the seventh month. <verse-number id="Ne 8:3">3</verse-number>He read from it facing the public square before the Water Gate from dawn until noon that day, opposite the men, women, and those with understanding. The ears of all the people <supplied>were attentive</supplied> to the book of the law.<note>Hebrew <i>torah</i></note> <verse-number id="Ne 8:4">4</verse-number>Then Ezra the scribe stood on a wooden podium that had been made for the occasion. And beside him stood Mattithiah, Shema, Anaiah, Uriah, Hilkiah, and Maaseiah on his right. On his left <supplied>was</supplied> Pedaiah, Mishael, Malkijah, Hashum, Hashbaddanah, Zechariah, and Meshullam. <verse-number id="Ne 8:5">5</verse-number>Ezra opened the book in the sight of all the people, because he was above all of the people. When he opened it all the people stood up. <verse-number id="Ne 8:6">6</verse-number>Then Ezra blessed Yahweh the great God, and all of the people answered, “Amen! Amen!” while lifting their hands. Then they bowed down and worshiped Yahweh <supplied>with their</supplied> noses to the ground. <verse-number id="Ne 8:7">7</verse-number>And Jeshua, Bani, Sherebiah, Jamin, Akkub, Shabbethai, Hodiah, Maaseiah, Kelita, Azariah, Jozabad, Hanan, Pelaiah, and the Levites were teaching the people from the law<note>Hebrew <i>torah</i></note> while the people were in their places. <verse-number id="Ne 8:8">8</verse-number>So they read the book from the law<note>Hebrew <i>torah</i></note> of God, making it clear and giving the meaning so that they could understand the reading. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ne 8:9">9</verse-number>Nehemiah the governor, Ezra the priest and scribe, and the Levites who taught the people said to all of the people, “This day is holy to Yahweh your God. Do not mourn nor weep.” For all of the people wept when they heard the words of the law.<note>Hebrew <i>torah</i></note> <verse-number id="Ne 8:10">10</verse-number>Then he said to them, “Go, eat festive food and drink sweet drinks, and send a share to those for whom nothing is prepared; for this day is holy to our lord. Do not be grieved because the joy of Yahweh is your refuge.” <verse-number id="Ne 8:11">11</verse-number>So the Levites silenced all of the people, saying, “Silence, for this day is holy. Do not be grieved.” <verse-number id="Ne 8:12">12</verse-number>All of the people went to eat, to drink, to send a share, and to have great joy because they understood the words that they had made known to them. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Festival of Booths</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ne 8:13">13</verse-number>On the second day the heads of the <idiom-start/>families<idiom-end/><note>Literally “fathers”</note> of all the people, the priests, and the Levites gathered together to Ezra the scribe to study the words of the law.<note>Hebrew <i>torah</i></note> <verse-number id="Ne 8:14">14</verse-number>They found written in the law,<note>Hebrew <i>torah</i></note> which Yahweh had commanded by the hand of Moses, that the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> should live in booths during the festival of the seventh month, <verse-number id="Ne 8:15">15</verse-number>and that they should proclaim and give voice in all of their cities in Jerusalem, saying, “Go out to the hill and bring olive tree branches, olive oil wood branches, myrtle shrub branches, palm tree branches, and other leafy tree branches to make booths, as it is written.” <verse-number id="Ne 8:16">16</verse-number>So the people went out and brought them and made booths for themselves, each on his roof, in their courtyards, in the courtyards of the house of God, in the public square of the Water Gate, and in the public square of the Gate of Ephraim. <verse-number id="Ne 8:17">17</verse-number>And all of the assembly of those who returned from captivity made booths and lived in the booths because the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> had not done it from the days of Jeshua son of Nun until that day. And there was very great joy. <verse-number id="Ne 8:18">18</verse-number>And he read from the scroll of the law<note>Hebrew <i>torah</i></note> of God day by day from the first day up to the last day. They celebrated the festival for seven days, and on the eighth day there was an assembly according to the rule. </p>
		</chapter>