<chapter id="Ne 11">
			<pericope>The Leaders and Servants in Jerusalem</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ne 11:1">1</verse-number>Now the commanders of the people lived in Jerusalem, but the remainder of the people cast lots to bring one out of ten to live in the holy city of Jerusalem, the <supplied>other</supplied> nine’s place <supplied>was in</supplied> the <supplied>other</supplied> cities. <verse-number id="Ne 11:2">2</verse-number>And the people blessed all the men who willingly offered to live in Jerusalem. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ne 11:3">3</verse-number>These are the heads of the province who lived in Jerusalem, but in the cities of Judah each one lived on his property in their cities: Israel, the priests, the Levites, the temple servants, and the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Solomon’s servants. <verse-number id="Ne 11:4">4</verse-number>And <supplied>some</supplied> from the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Judah and Benjamin lived in Jerusalem. From the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Judah: Athaiah son of Uzziah, son of Zechariah, son of Amariah, son of Shephatiah, son of Mahalalel, from the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Perez; <verse-number id="Ne 11:5">5</verse-number>and Maaseiah son of Baruch, son of Col-Hozeh, son of Hazaiah, son of Adaiah, son of Jehoiarib, son of Zechariah, son<note>Or “descendant”</note> of the Shilonite. <verse-number id="Ne 11:6">6</verse-number>All of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Perez who were living in Jerusalem <supplied>were</supplied> four hundred and sixty-eight able-bodied men. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ne 11:7">7</verse-number>These are the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Benjamin: Sallu son of Meshullam, son of Joed, son of Pedaiah, son of Kolaiah, son of Maaseiah, son of Ithiel, son of Jeshaiah. <verse-number id="Ne 11:8">8</verse-number>And <supplied>following</supplied> after him Gabbai, Sallai, nine hundred and twenty-eight. <verse-number id="Ne 11:9">9</verse-number>And Joel son of Zicri, their chief officer; and Judah son of Hassenuah, second <supplied>in command</supplied> over the city. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ne 11:10">10</verse-number>From the priests: Jedaiah son of Jehoiarib, Jakin, <verse-number id="Ne 11:11">11</verse-number>Seraiah son of Hilkiah, son of Meshullam, son of Zadok, son of Meraioth, son of Ahitub—the leader of the house of God— <verse-number id="Ne 11:12">12</verse-number>and their brothers who did the work of the house, eight hundred and twenty-two. And Adaiah son of Jeroham, son of Pelaliah, son of Amzi, son of Zechariah, son of Pashhur, son of Malkijah, <verse-number id="Ne 11:13">13</verse-number>and his brothers, heads of the <idiom-start/>families<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “fathers”</note> two hundred and forty-two. And Amashai son of Azarel, son of Ahzai, son of Meshillemoth, son of Immer, <verse-number id="Ne 11:14">14</verse-number>and their brothers; mighty warriors of strength, one hundred and twenty-eight. The chief officer over them <supplied>was</supplied> Zabdiel son of Hagedolim. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ne 11:15">15</verse-number>Now from the Levites: Shemaiah son of Hasshub, son of Azrikam, son of Hashabiah, son of Bunni; <verse-number id="Ne 11:16">16</verse-number>and Shabbethai and Jehozabad, leaders over the work of the Levites outside of the house of God; <verse-number id="Ne 11:17">17</verse-number>Mattaniah son of Micah, son of Zabdi, son<note>Or “descendant”</note> of Asaph, <supplied>who was</supplied> the leader to begin the thanksgiving prayer, and Bakbukiah the second of his brothers; Abda son of Shammua, son of Galal, son of Jeduthun. <verse-number id="Ne 11:18">18</verse-number>All of the Levites in the holy city <supplied>were</supplied> two hundred and eighty-four. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ne 11:19">19</verse-number>The gatekeepers: Akkub, Talmon, and their brothers, the keepers of the gates, one hundred and seventy-two. <verse-number id="Ne 11:20">20</verse-number>And the remainder of Israel, the priests and the Levites, in all of the cities of Judah, each in his inheritance. <verse-number id="Ne 11:21">21</verse-number>But the temple servants were living on the Ophel; Ziha and Gishpa <supplied>were</supplied> over the temple servants. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ne 11:22">22</verse-number>The chief officer of the Levites in Jerusalem <supplied>was</supplied> Uzzi son of Bani, son of Hashabiah, son of Mattaniah, son of Mica, from the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Asaph, the singers over the work of the house of God. <verse-number id="Ne 11:23">23</verse-number>For <supplied>there was</supplied> a command of the king concerning them and a regulation concerning the singers, required <idiom-start/>day by day<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “a word for a day on his day”</note> <verse-number id="Ne 11:24">24</verse-number>And Pethahiah son of Meshezabel, from the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Zerah the son of Judah, <supplied>was</supplied> at the hand of the king in all matters concerning the people. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Villages Outside of Jerusalem</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ne 11:25">25</verse-number>As for the villages in their territories, <supplied>some</supplied> from the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Judah lived in Kiriath-Arba and <idiom-start/>its settlements<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “its daughters”</note> Dibon and <idiom-start/>its settlements<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “its daughters”</note> Jekabzeel and <idiom-start/>its settlements<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “its daughters”</note> <verse-number id="Ne 11:26">26</verse-number>Jeshua, Moladah, Beth Pelet, <verse-number id="Ne 11:27">27</verse-number>Hazar Shual, Beersheba and <idiom-start/>its settlements<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “its daughters”</note> <verse-number id="Ne 11:28">28</verse-number>Ziklad, Meconah and <idiom-start/>its settlements<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “its daughters”</note> <verse-number id="Ne 11:29">29</verse-number>En-Rimmon, Zorah, Jarmuch, <verse-number id="Ne 11:30">30</verse-number>Zanoah, Adullam and <idiom-start/>their settlements<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “their daughters”</note> Lachish and its fields, and Azekah and <idiom-start/>its settlements<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “its daughters”</note> So they camped from Beersheba up to <supplied>the</supplied> Valley <supplied>of</supplied> Hinnom. <verse-number id="Ne 11:31">31</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Benjamin from Geba, Micmash, Aija, Bethel and <idiom-start/>their settlements<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “their daughters”</note> <verse-number id="Ne 11:32">32</verse-number>Anathoth, Nob, Ananiah, <verse-number id="Ne 11:33">33</verse-number>Hazor, Ramah, Gittaim, <verse-number id="Ne 11:34">34</verse-number>Hadid, Zeboim, Neballat, <verse-number id="Ne 11:35">35</verse-number>Lod, and Ono the valley of the artisans. <verse-number id="Ne 11:36">36</verse-number>And from the Levites the working groups of Judah <supplied>were assigned</supplied> to Benjamin. </p>
		</chapter>