<chapter id="Eze 1">
			<pericope>Date of Vision of Living Creatures and Glory of the Throne of Yahweh</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 1:1">1</verse-number>And it was in <supplied>the</supplied> thirtieth year, in the fourth <supplied>month</supplied>, on the fifth <supplied>day</supplied> of the month, and I <supplied>was</supplied> in the midst of<note>Or “among”</note> the exiles<note>Hebrew “exile”</note> by the <idiom-start/>Kebar River<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “river of Kebar”</note> The heavens were opened, and I saw visions of God. <verse-number id="Eze 1:2">2</verse-number>On the fifth <supplied>day</supplied> of the month—it was the fifth year of the exile of the king Jehoiachin— <verse-number id="Eze 1:3">3</verse-number>the word of Yahweh <idiom-start/>came<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was”</note> clearly<note>Or “certainly”</note> to Ezekiel the son of Buzi, the priest, in the land of <supplied>the</supplied> Chaldeans at the <idiom-start/>Kebar River<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “river of Kebar”</note> and the hand of Yahweh was on him there. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 1:4">4</verse-number>And I looked,<note>Or “saw”</note> and look! A storm wind <supplied>was</supplied> coming from the north, a great cloud, and fire flashing back and forth, and brightness around <supplied>and</supplied> <idiom-start/>within it<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “for it”</note> and from its midst<note>Or “middle”</note> <supplied>it was</supplied> like <supplied>the</supplied> outward appearance of amber stone from the midst<note>Or “middle”</note> of the fire. <verse-number id="Eze 1:5">5</verse-number>And from its midst<note>Or “middle”</note> <supplied>was</supplied> the likeness of four living creatures, and this <supplied>was</supplied> their appearance: <idiom-start/>a human form<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “this their appearance the likeness of a human to them”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 1:6">6</verse-number>and <idiom-start/>each had four faces<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “and four faces to each”</note> and <idiom-start/>each of them had four wings<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “and four wings to each for them”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 1:7">7</verse-number>And their legs <supplied>were</supplied> straight legs, and the sole of their feet <supplied>was</supplied> like the sole of <supplied>the</supplied> foot of a calf, and <supplied>they</supplied> were sparkling like the outward appearance of polished bronze. <verse-number id="Eze 1:8">8</verse-number>And under their wings <supplied>were</supplied> <idiom-start/>human hands<idiom-end/><note>Literally “hand his a man”</note> on their four sides. And their faces and their wings for the four of them <supplied>were as follows</supplied>: <verse-number id="Eze 1:9">9</verse-number><idiom-start/>their wings were touching one another<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “their wings <supplied>were</supplied> touching each her sister”</note> <idiom-start/>each of them went straight forward<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “they did not turn at their going”</note> <idiom-start/>without turning right or left<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “each toward the side of his face they went”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 1:10">10</verse-number>The likeness of their faces <supplied>was the</supplied> face of a human <supplied>in front</supplied>, and <supplied>the</supplied> face of a lion on the right <idiom-start/>of each of them<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “of the four of them”</note> and the face of an ox on the left <idiom-start/>of each of them<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “of the four of them”</note> and <supplied>the</supplied> face of an eagle <idiom-start/>for each of them<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “of the four of them”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 1:11">11</verse-number>So <supplied>were</supplied> their faces; their wings <supplied>were</supplied> spread out <idiom-start/>upward<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “from to above”</note> each <supplied>had</supplied> two touching one another and two covering their bodies. <verse-number id="Eze 1:12">12</verse-number>And each <idiom-start/>went straight forward<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “toward the side of his face they went”</note> <idiom-start/>wherever the spirit went<idiom-end/><note>Literally “towards which it was there the spirit”</note> they went, <supplied>and</supplied> <idiom-start/>they did not turn as they went<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “they did not turn at their going”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 1:13">13</verse-number>As for<note>Or “And”</note> the likeness of the living creatures, their appearance <supplied>was</supplied> like burning coals of fire, like the appearance of torches. It<note>That is, the fire</note> <supplied>was</supplied> moving to and fro between the living creatures, and <idiom-start/>the fire was very bright<idiom-end/><note>Literally “brightness <supplied>was</supplied> for the fire”</note> and lightning <supplied>was</supplied> going out from the fire. <verse-number id="Eze 1:14">14</verse-number>And the living creatures <idiom-start/>were speeding to and fro<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sped forth and returned”</note> like the appearance of lightning. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 1:15">15</verse-number>And I saw the living creatures, and look! A wheel was on the earth<note>Or “ground”</note> beside <idiom-start/>each of the living creatures that had four faces<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the living creatures for the four of his/its faces.” The LXX has “for the four of them.”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 1:16">16</verse-number>The appearance of the wheels and their construction <supplied>was</supplied> like <supplied>the</supplied> appearance of beryl,<note>Or “chrysolite,” or “topaz”; this stone is difficult to identify exactly</note> and <idiom-start/>they all looked alike<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “likeness <supplied>was</supplied> one for the four of them”</note> and their appearance and their construction <supplied>was</supplied> <idiom-start/>like a wheel within a wheel<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “as that it was a wheel in the midst of a wheel”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 1:17">17</verse-number>When they moved, they went toward their four sides; they did not <idiom-start/>veer at all as they went<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “turn away when they went”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 1:18">18</verse-number>And their rims <idiom-start/>were high and awesome<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “height <supplied>was</supplied> for them and awesomeness <supplied>was</supplied> for them”</note> and <idiom-start/>all four of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “of the four of them”</note> their rims <supplied>were</supplied> full of eyes <supplied>all</supplied> around. <verse-number id="Eze 1:19">19</verse-number>And at the going of the living creatures, the wheels next to them <supplied>also</supplied> went, and <idiom-start/>when the creatures were lifted from the ground<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and at the lifting up of the creatures from the earth”</note> the wheels <supplied>also</supplied> rose. <verse-number id="Eze 1:20">20</verse-number><idiom-start/>Wherever<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Toward which”</note> the spirit went they would go there, and the wheels rose, for the spirit of the living creatures<note>Hebrew “creature”</note> <supplied>was</supplied> in the wheels. <verse-number id="Eze 1:21">21</verse-number>At their<note>That is, the living creatures</note> going, they<note>That is, the wheels</note> go, and at their standing, they stood, and at their being lifted up from on the earth,<note>Or “ground”</note> the wheels rose,<note>Or “were lifted up”</note> for the spirit of the living creatures<note>Hebrew “creature”</note> <supplied>was</supplied> in the wheels. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 1:22">22</verse-number>Now<note>Or “And”</note> <supplied>the</supplied> likeness above the heads of the living creatures <supplied>was</supplied> an expanse like the outward appearance of <idiom-start/>awesome<idiom-end/><note>Literally “terrible”</note> <idiom-start/>ice<idiom-end/><note>Literally “frozen water”</note> spread out above their heads <idiom-start/>upward<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “from to upward”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 1:23">23</verse-number>And under the expanse their wings <supplied>were stretched out</supplied> straight <idiom-start/>one toward the other<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “each towards its sister”</note> each had two <supplied>wings</supplied> covering them, and each had two <supplied>wings</supplied> covering their bodies. <verse-number id="Eze 1:24">24</verse-number>And I heard the sound of their wings like <supplied>the</supplied> sound of many waters, like the voice of Shaddai,<note>Often translated “Almighty”</note> <supplied>and</supplied> <idiom-start/>when they moved<idiom-end/><note>Literally “at their going”</note> <supplied>there was</supplied> a sound of tumult like <supplied>the</supplied> sound of an army; <idiom-start/>when they stood still<idiom-end/><note>Literally “at their standing”</note> they lowered their wings. <verse-number id="Eze 1:25">25</verse-number>And there was<note>Or “it was”</note> a sound from above the expanse that <supplied>was</supplied> above their heads, <idiom-start/>and when they stood<idiom-end/><note>Literally “at their standing”</note> they lowered their wings. <verse-number id="Eze 1:26">26</verse-number>And from above the expanse that <supplied>was</supplied> above their heads <supplied>there was</supplied> the likeness of a throne, <idiom-start/>looking like a sapphire<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “<supplied>the</supplied> appearance of a stone of sapphire”</note> and above the likeness of the throne <supplied>was</supplied> a likeness similar to<note>Or “like”</note> <supplied>the</supplied> appearance of a human on it, <supplied>but</supplied> <idiom-start/>above it<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “from to above”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 1:27">27</verse-number>And I saw <supplied>something</supplied> like <supplied>the</supplied> outward appearance of amber, <supplied>something</supplied> like <supplied>the</supplied> appearance of fire, <supplied>with</supplied> a covering around <supplied>it</supplied>, from the likeness of his loins and <idiom-start/>upward<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to above”</note> And from the likeness of his loins and <idiom-start/>downward<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to down”</note> I saw <supplied>something</supplied> like <supplied>the</supplied> appearance of fire, and <idiom-start/>it was radiant all around<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “brightness <supplied>was</supplied> for it around”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 1:28">28</verse-number>Like the appearance<note>Or “likeness”</note> of a bow that is in the cloud on <idiom-start/>a rainy day<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the day of the rain”</note> such <supplied>was</supplied> the radiance<note>Or “brightness”</note> around it; <supplied>thus was</supplied> the appearance of the likeness of the glory of Yahweh. And I saw, and I fell on my face, and I heard a voice speaking. </p>
		</chapter>