<chapter id="Eze 2">
			<pericope>The Call of Ezekiel to Speak God’s Words</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 2:1">1</verse-number>And he said to me, “Son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> stand on your feet, so that I can speak with you.” <verse-number id="Eze 2:2">2</verse-number>And <supplied>the</supplied> Spirit<note>Or “<supplied>a</supplied> spirit”</note> came into me as he was speaking to me, and it set me on my feet, and I heard the one speaking to me. <verse-number id="Eze 2:3">3</verse-number>And he said to me, “Son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> I am sending you to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> to nations<note>Or “a people”</note> <supplied>who are</supplied> rebelling, who rebelled against me, they and their ancestors,<note>Hebrew “fathers”</note> they transgressed against me <idiom-start/>until this very day<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “until the day the this”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 2:4">4</verse-number>And the children<note>Or “sons”</note> <supplied>are</supplied> <idiom-start/>impudent<idiom-end/><note>Literally “hard of face”</note> and <idiom-start/>stubborn<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “strong of heart”</note> <supplied>and so</supplied> I am sending you to them, and you must say to them, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh!’ <verse-number id="Eze 2:5">5</verse-number>And they, whether they listen or whether they fail <supplied>to listen</supplied>, for they <supplied>are</supplied> a rebellious house, they will know that a prophet was in their midst. <verse-number id="Eze 2:6">6</verse-number>And you, son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> you must not be afraid of them, and you must not be afraid of their words, because<note>Or “although”</note> briers and thorns <supplied>are</supplied> with you, and you <supplied>are</supplied> sitting among scorpions. You must not be afraid of their words, and you must not be dismayed because of their <idiom-start/>looks<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “faces”</note> for they <supplied>are</supplied> a rebellious house. <verse-number id="Eze 2:7">7</verse-number>And you must speak my words to them whether they listen or whether they fail <supplied>to listen</supplied>, for they <supplied>are</supplied> rebellious. <verse-number id="Eze 2:8">8</verse-number>And you, son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> hear what I <supplied>am</supplied> speaking to you: you must not be rebellious like <supplied>the</supplied> house of rebellion. Open your mouth and eat what I <supplied>am</supplied> giving to you.” <verse-number id="Eze 2:9">9</verse-number>And I looked,<note>Or “saw”</note> and look! There was a hand stretched out to me, and look! In it <supplied>was</supplied> <idiom-start/>a scroll with writing<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “a scroll of a book”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 2:10">10</verse-number>And he rolled it out<note>Or “he spread it out”</note> <idiom-start/>before me<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to the face of me”</note> and it <supplied>was</supplied> written <supplied>on the</supplied> front and back, and there <supplied>were</supplied> written on it laments and mourning and wailing.<note>Or “woe”</note> </p>
		</chapter>