<chapter id="Eze 3">
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 3">3</verse-number><verse-number id="Eze 3:1">1</verse-number> And he said to me, “Son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> what you find, eat! Eat this scroll, and go, speak to the house of Israel.” <verse-number id="Eze 3:2">2</verse-number>And I opened my mouth, and he gave me this scroll to eat, <verse-number id="Eze 3:3">3</verse-number>and he said to me, “Son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> you must give your stomach <supplied>this</supplied> to eat, and you must fill your belly <supplied>with</supplied> this scroll that I <supplied>am</supplied> giving to you.” And I ate, and it became <idiom-start/>like sweet honey<idiom-end/><note>Literally “like honey for sweetness”</note> in my mouth. <verse-number id="Eze 3:4">4</verse-number>And he said to me, “Son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> come! Go to the house of Israel, and you must speak to them with my words. <verse-number id="Eze 3:5">5</verse-number>For you are sent to the house of Israel, not to a people <idiom-start/>of obscure speech<idiom-end/><note>Literally “obscure of lip”</note> and <idiom-start/>of a difficult language<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “heavy/thick of tongue”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 3:6">6</verse-number><supplied>and</supplied> not to many nations <idiom-start/>of obscure speech<idiom-end/><note>Literally “obscure of tongue”</note> and <idiom-start/>a difficult language<idiom-end/><note>Literally “heavy/thick of tongue”</note> <idiom-start/>whose words<idiom-end/><note>Literally “their words”</note> you do not understand, <supplied>for</supplied> if I had sent you to them they would have listened to you. <verse-number id="Eze 3:7">7</verse-number>And the house of Israel, they are not willing to listen to you, for they <supplied>are</supplied> not willing to listen to me, for all of the house of Israel is hard of forehead, and they <supplied>are</supplied> hard of heart. <verse-number id="Eze 3:8">8</verse-number><supplied>But</supplied> look, I have made<note>Or “set”</note> your face hard <idiom-start/>against<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to correspond <supplied>to</supplied>”</note> their faces and your forehead hard <idiom-start/>against<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to correspond <supplied>to</supplied>”</note> their forehead. <verse-number id="Eze 3:9">9</verse-number>Like a diamond <idiom-start/>harder than flint<idiom-end/><note>Literally “hard more than flint”</note> I have made your forehead; you must not fear them, and you must not be dismayed <idiom-start/>on account of them<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from the face of them”</note> for they <idiom-start/>are a rebellious house<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “<supplied>are</supplied> a house of rebellion”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 3:10">10</verse-number>And he said to me, “Son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> all of my words that I shall speak to you, receive into<note>Hebrew “in”</note> your heart and hear with your ears. <verse-number id="Eze 3:11">11</verse-number>And come, go to the exiles,<note>Hebrew “exile”</note> to the children<note>Or “sons”</note> of your people, and you must speak to them, and say to them, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh!’ whether they listen or whether they fail <supplied>to listen</supplied>.” <verse-number id="Eze 3:12">12</verse-number>And the Spirit lifted me up, and I heard behind me the sound of a great earthquake when the glory of Yahweh rose from its place. <verse-number id="Eze 3:13">13</verse-number>And <supplied>it was</supplied> the sound of the wings of the living creatures touching lightly<note>Or “brushing against”</note> <idiom-start/>one against the other<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “each against each <supplied>its sister</supplied></note> and the sound of the wheels beside them and <supplied>the</supplied> sound of a great earthquake. <verse-number id="Eze 3:14">14</verse-number>And <supplied>the</supplied> Spirit lifted me and took me, and I went <supplied>in</supplied> bitterness in the heat of my spirit, and the hand of Yahweh <supplied>was</supplied> strong on me. <verse-number id="Eze 3:15">15</verse-number>And I went to the exiles<note>Hebrew “exile”</note> <supplied>at</supplied> Tel Abib, who <supplied>were</supplied> dwelling near the <idiom-start/>Kebar River<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “river of Kebar”</note> and I sat <supplied>where</supplied> they <supplied>were</supplied> dwelling. I sat there seven days in the midst of them, stunned. <verse-number id="Eze 3:16">16</verse-number>And then it happened<note>Or “was”</note> at <supplied>the</supplied> end of seven days, <idiom-start/>the word of Yahweh came<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and it was the word of Yahweh to me to say <supplied>saying</supplied>”</note> to me, saying, <verse-number id="Eze 3:17">17</verse-number>“Son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> I have appointed you <supplied>as</supplied> a watchman for the house of Israel. When you hear a word from my mouth, then you must warn them from me. <verse-number id="Eze 3:18">18</verse-number><idiom-start/>When I say<idiom-end/><note>Literally “at/in my saying”</note> to the wicked, ‘Surely you will die,’ and you do not warn him and you do not speak to warn <supplied>the</supplied> wicked from his wicked way <idiom-start/>so that he may live<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “so that <supplied>you</supplied> let him live”</note> that wicked <supplied>person</supplied> will die because of his guilt, and from your hand I will seek his blood. <verse-number id="Eze 3:19">19</verse-number>And you, if you do warn <supplied>the</supplied> wicked and he does not turn from his wickedness and from his wicked way, on account of his guilt he will die, and you yourself will have saved your life.<note>Or “soul,” or “self”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 3:20">20</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>when the righteous turns from his righteousness<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and at <supplied>the</supplied> to turn of <supplied>the</supplied> righteous from his righteousness”</note> and does injustice, and I place<note>Or “give”</note> a stumbling block <idiom-start/>before him<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to the face of him”</note> he will die, for you did not warn him. Because of his sin he will die, and his righteousness<note>Or “righteous deeds”</note> that he did will not be remembered, and his blood I shall seek from your hand. <verse-number id="Eze 3:21">21</verse-number>And if you warn him, the righteous, not to sin, and <supplied>the</supplied> righteous does not sin, surely he will live, for he heeded a warning. And you will have saved your life.”<note>Or “soul,” or “self”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 3:22">22</verse-number>And the hand of Yahweh was on me there, and he said to me, “Rise up, go out to the valley, and there I will speak with you.” <verse-number id="Eze 3:23">23</verse-number>And I rose up, and I went to the valley, and, look, there the glory of Yahweh <supplied>was</supplied> standing, like the glory that I saw near the <idiom-start/>Kebar River<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “river of Kebar”</note> and I fell on my face. <verse-number id="Eze 3:24">24</verse-number>And <supplied>the</supplied> Spirit<note>Or “<supplied>a</supplied> spirit”</note> came into me, and it made me stand on my feet, and he spoke with me and said to me, “Come, shut yourself <idiom-start/>inside your house<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “in the midst of your house”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 3:25">25</verse-number>and you, son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> look, they will place<note>Or “give”</note> cords on you, and they will tie you up with them. Then you will not go out into the midst of them. <verse-number id="Eze 3:26">26</verse-number>And I will make your tongue cling to the roof of your mouth, and you will be silenced, and you will not be a reproving man for them, for they <idiom-start/>are a rebellious house<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “a house of rebellion”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 3:27">27</verse-number>And when I speak with you, I will open your mouth, and you must say to them, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “The <supplied>one</supplied> hearing him, let him hear, and the <supplied>one</supplied> failing <supplied>to hear</supplied>, let him fail,” ’ for they <idiom-start/>are a rebellious house<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “a house of rebellion”</note> </p>
		</chapter>