<chapter id="Eze 4">
			<pericope>Siege of Jerusalem Illustrated on a Brick</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 4:1">1</verse-number>“Now,<note>Or “And”</note> son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> take for yourself a brick, and you must put it <idiom-start/>before you<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to the face of you”</note> and you must portray on it a city, Jerusalem. <verse-number id="Eze 4:2">2</verse-number>And you must build against it siege works, and you must build against it <supplied>a</supplied> bulwark, and you must heap against it a siege ramp, and you must set up against it camps and put against it a battering ram all around. <verse-number id="Eze 4:3">3</verse-number>And take for yourself a plate of iron, and you must place it <supplied>as</supplied> a wall of iron between you and the city, and you must set your face against it, and it must be <idiom-start/>under siege<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “in the siege”</note> and you must lay the siege against it; it is a sign for the house of Israel. <verse-number id="Eze 4:4">4</verse-number>And you, lie down on your left side, and you must put<note>Or “you will put”</note> the guilt of the house of Israel on it. You will carry their guilt the number of days that you will lie on it. <verse-number id="Eze 4:5">5</verse-number>And I will give to you the years of their guilt according to <supplied>the</supplied> number of <supplied>the</supplied> days, three hundred and ninety days, and you must bear the guilt<note>Or “punishment”</note> of the house of Israel. <verse-number id="Eze 4:6">6</verse-number>When you have completed these, then you must lie a second <supplied>time</supplied> on your right side; and you must bear the guilt<note>Or “punishment”</note> of the house of Judah forty days, a day for each year, a day for each year I give it to you. <verse-number id="Eze 4:7">7</verse-number>And toward the siege of Jerusalem you must set your face and your bared arm; then you must prophesy against it. <verse-number id="Eze 4:8">8</verse-number>Now<note>Or “and”</note> look! I <supplied>will</supplied> put on you cords, and you may not turn yourself from <supplied>one</supplied> side to your <supplied>other</supplied> side until you complete the days of your siege. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Ezekiel’s Strange Defiled Meal</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 4:9">9</verse-number>“And you, take for yourself<note>Hebrew “you”</note> wheat and barley and beans and lentils and millet<note>Or “sorghum”</note> and spelt, and you must put them in one vessel, and you must make them for yourself<note>Hebrew “you”</note> into a food <supplied>during</supplied> the number of days that you <supplied>are</supplied> lying on your side; three hundred and ninety days you shall eat it. <verse-number id="Eze 4:10">10</verse-number>And your food that you will eat<note>Hebrew “will eat it”</note> <supplied>will be</supplied> according to weight; twenty shekels for each day <idiom-start/>at fixed times<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from time to time”</note> you shall eat it. <verse-number id="Eze 4:11">11</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>an amount of water<idiom-end/><note>Literally “water by amount”</note> you shall drink, a sixth of a hin; <idiom-start/>at fixed times<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from time to time”</note> you shall drink <supplied>it</supplied>. <verse-number id="Eze 4:12">12</verse-number>And <supplied>as a</supplied> bread-cake of barley you shall eat it, and <idiom-start/>with human excrement<idiom-end/><note>Literally “with human dung of the excrement of the human”</note> you shall bake it before their eyes.” <verse-number id="Eze 4:13">13</verse-number>And Yahweh said, “Thus shall the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> eat their unclean food among the nations <idiom-start/>where I will scatter them<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “which I will scatter them there”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 4:14">14</verse-number>And I said, “Ah, Lord Yahweh! Look! I have not been defiling myself, and a dead body and mangled carcass I have not eaten from my childhood until now, and <idiom-start/>unclean meat<idiom-end/><note>Literally “flesh of unclean meat”</note> has not come into my mouth!” <verse-number id="Eze 4:15">15</verse-number>And he said to me, “See I will give you <idiom-start/>cattle manure<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the manure of cattle”</note> in the place of the feces of a human, and you may prepare your food on it.” <verse-number id="Eze 4:16">16</verse-number>And he said to me, “Son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> look, I <supplied>am</supplied> going to break the <idiom-start/>supply<idiom-end/><note>Literally “staff”</note> of bread in Jerusalem, and they will eat bread by weight, <idiom-start/>anxiously<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “and with worry”</note> and <idiom-start/>rationed water<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “and water by amount”</note> and they will drink with horror, <verse-number id="Eze 4:17">17</verse-number>so that they will lack food and water, and they will be appalled <idiom-start/>with one another<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “a man and his brother”</note> and they will waste away because of their guilt.<note>Or “punishment”</note> </p>
		</chapter>