<chapter id="Eze 5">
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 5">5</verse-number><verse-number id="Eze 5:1">1</verse-number> “And you, son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> take for yourself<note>Hebrew “you”</note> a sword, sharp <supplied>as</supplied> <idiom-start/>a barber’s razor<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the razor of the barbers”</note> Take it for yourself, and you must cause <supplied>it</supplied> to pass over your head and over your beard, and you must take for yourself a set of scales for weighing, and you must divide them.<note>That is, the hairs</note> <verse-number id="Eze 5:2">2</verse-number>A third you must burn with fire in the midst<note>Or “middle”</note> of the city at <idiom-start/>the completion<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the completing”</note> of the days of the siege, and you must take a third, and you must strike <supplied>it</supplied> with the sword around it, and a third you must scatter to the wind, and I will draw a sword behind them. <verse-number id="Eze 5:3">3</verse-number>And you must take from these a few in number, and you must tuck them in your hem. <verse-number id="Eze 5:4">4</verse-number>And from them again you shall take <supplied>some</supplied>, and you must throw them in the middle of the fire, and you must burn them with fire; from it a fire will go out to all of the house of Israel. <verse-number id="Eze 5:5">5</verse-number>Thus says the Lord Yahweh: This <supplied>is</supplied> Jerusalem in the midst of the nations <supplied>where</supplied> I have put her, and countries <supplied>are</supplied> around her. <verse-number id="Eze 5:6">6</verse-number>But she has rebelled against my regulations to the point of wickedness more than the nations, and my statutes more than the countries that <supplied>are</supplied> around her; for they rejected my regulations, and <supplied>as for</supplied> my statutes, they did not walk in them. <verse-number id="Eze 5:7">7</verse-number>Therefore, thus says the Lord Yahweh: Because of your commotion more than the nations that <supplied>are</supplied> around you—you did not walk in my statutes, and you did not do my regulations, and according to the regulations of the nations that <supplied>are</supplied> around you, you did not do. <verse-number id="Eze 5:8">8</verse-number>Therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh: Look! I, <idiom-start/>even I<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “surely I”</note> am against you, and I will execute judgment in the midst of you before the eyes of the nations, <verse-number id="Eze 5:9">9</verse-number>and I will do with you <supplied>that</supplied> which I have not done, and which I will not do again, because of all of your detestable things. <verse-number id="Eze 5:10">10</verse-number>Therefore<note>Literally “to thus”</note> parents<note>Or “fathers”</note> will eat children<note>Or “sons”</note> in the midst of you, and children<note>Or “sons”</note> will eat their parents,<note>Or “fathers”</note> and I will execute judgment in you, and I will scatter your entire remnant to every wind. <verse-number id="Eze 5:11">11</verse-number>Therefore <idiom-start/>as surely as I live<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “alive I <supplied>am</supplied>”</note> <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh, <idiom-start/>Surely<idiom-end/><note>Literally “If not”</note> because you have defiled my sanctuary with all of your vile idols and with all of your detestable things, <idiom-start/>now indeed I<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and also I”</note> will reduce, and my eye will not take pity, and surely I will show no compassion. <verse-number id="Eze 5:12">12</verse-number>A third of you will die because of the plague, and because of the famine they will perish in the midst of you, and a third will fall through the sword around you, and a third I will scatter to every direction of the wind, and I will draw <supplied>the</supplied> sword behind them. <verse-number id="Eze 5:13">13</verse-number>And my anger will come to an end, and I will place my rage on them, and I will relent, and they will know that I, Yahweh, have spoken in my passion <idiom-start/>when I fully vent my rage against them<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “at my finishing my anger against them”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 5:14">14</verse-number>And I will make you into a desolate place and into a disgrace among the nations that surround you before the eyes of <idiom-start/>every one who passes by<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “every one of passing by”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 5:15">15</verse-number>And it will be<note>Or “and you will be”</note> <supplied>an</supplied> object of taunting<note>Hebrew “taunt”</note> and <supplied>an</supplied> object of mockery, a warning and a horror to the nations that <supplied>are</supplied> around you whenever I execute judgments against you in anger and in wrath and in furious punishments! I, Yahweh, have spoken! <verse-number id="Eze 5:16">16</verse-number>When I send my arrows of deadly famine against them, which will be as destruction that I will send <supplied>in order</supplied> to destroy you, I will increase famine against you, and I will break <idiom-start/>the supply of food<idiom-end/><note>Literally “staff of bread”</note> for you. <verse-number id="Eze 5:17">17</verse-number>And I will send against you famine and fierce animals,<note>Hebrew “animal”</note> and they will make you childless; and plague and blood will pass through you, and I will bring <supplied>the</supplied> sword upon you. I, Yahweh, I have spoken!” </p>
		</chapter>