<chapter id="Eze 6">
			<pericope>Idolatrous Worship and Idolatrous Objects Denounced</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 6:1">1</verse-number>And the word of Yahweh <idiom-start/>came<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was”</note> to me, saying, <verse-number id="Eze 6:2">2</verse-number>“Son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> set your face to the mountains of Israel and prophesy against them, <verse-number id="Eze 6:3">3</verse-number>and you must say, ‘Mountains of Israel, hear the word of the Lord Yahweh, thus says the Lord Yahweh to the mountains and to the hills, to the ravines and to the valleys: “Look, I <supplied>am</supplied> bringing upon you <supplied>the</supplied> sword, and I will destroy your high places, <verse-number id="Eze 6:4">4</verse-number>and your altars will be desolate, and your incense altars will be broken, and I will throw down your slain ones <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of”</note> your idols, <verse-number id="Eze 6:5">5</verse-number>and I will place<note>Or “give”</note> the corpses of the children of Israel <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of”</note> their idols, and I will scatter your bones around your altars. <verse-number id="Eze 6:6">6</verse-number>In all of your dwellings, the cities will be desolate and the high places will be ruined, so that your altars will be desolate and will suffer punishment. Your idols will be broken and will come to an end, and your incense altars will be cut down, and your works will be destroyed, <verse-number id="Eze 6:7">7</verse-number>and the slain one will fall in the midst of you, and <supplied>then</supplied> you will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh. <verse-number id="Eze 6:8">8</verse-number>But<note>Or “And”</note> I will spare <supplied>some</supplied>, <idiom-start/>so there will be<idiom-end/><note>Literally “at their being”</note> for you fugitives from <supplied>the</supplied> sword among the nations <idiom-start/>when you are scattered<idiom-end/><note>Literally “at you to be scattered”</note> in the countries. <verse-number id="Eze 6:9">9</verse-number>And your fugitives will remember me among the nations <supplied>to</supplied> which they were taken captive, that I was shattered by <idiom-start/>their adulterous heart<idiom-end/><note>Literally “heart their which <supplied>was</supplied> prostituting <supplied>itself</supplied>”</note> which departed from me, and by <idiom-start/>their adulterous eyes<idiom-end/><note>Literally “eyes their which <supplied>were</supplied> prostituting”</note> which <supplied>went</supplied> after their idols, and they will feel loathing <idiom-start/>for themselves<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “for their face”</note> for the evil that they did, for all of their detestable things. <verse-number id="Eze 6:10">10</verse-number>And they will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh; not <idiom-start/>in vain<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to nothing”</note> I spoke to bring to them this evil.” ’ <verse-number id="Eze 6:11">11</verse-number>Thus says the Lord Yahweh: ‘Clap your hand and stamp with your foot, and say, “Alas, for all of the detestable things of the evil of the house of Israel, <idiom-start/>because of which<idiom-end/><note>Literally “which”</note> they will fall with the sword, with the famine, and with the plague. <verse-number id="Eze 6:12">12</verse-number>The one who is far <supplied>away</supplied> will die by the plague, and the one who is near will fall by the sword, and the one who is being left behind and being spared will die by the famine, and I will complete my rage on<note>Or “toward”</note> them. <verse-number id="Eze 6:13">13</verse-number>And you will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh <idiom-start/>when their slain ones are in the midst of their idols<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the being of their slain ones in the midst of their idols”</note> around their altars at every high hill, on the tops of all the mountains and under every green tree and under every leafy oak—the place <supplied>at</supplied> which they gave <supplied>a</supplied> pleasing scent for all of their idols. <verse-number id="Eze 6:14">14</verse-number>And I will stretch out my hand against them, and I will make the land a desolation and a wasteland from the desert to Riblah in all of their dwellings, and they will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh.” ’ ” </p>
		</chapter>