<chapter id="Eze 7">
			<pericope>Punishment for Abominations Throughout the Land</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 7:1">1</verse-number>And the word of Yahweh <idiom-start/>came<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was”</note> to me, saying, <verse-number id="Eze 7:2">2</verse-number>“And you, son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> thus says the Lord Yahweh to the land of Israel: ‘<supplied>The</supplied> end comes, the end on the four corners of the land. <verse-number id="Eze 7:3">3</verse-number>Now the end <supplied>is</supplied> on you, and I will send my anger on you, and I will judge you according to your ways, and I will bring on you all your detestable things. <verse-number id="Eze 7:4">4</verse-number>And my eye will not take pity on you, and I will not show compassion for your ways; on you I will bring your detestable things; they will be in the midst of you, and you will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh.’ <verse-number id="Eze 7:5">5</verse-number>Thus says the Lord Yahweh: ‘Look! Disaster after disaster <supplied>is</supplied> coming! <verse-number id="Eze 7:6">6</verse-number><supplied>The</supplied> end comes, comes the end! It has awakened against you! Look! <supplied>It</supplied> comes! <verse-number id="Eze 7:7">7</verse-number>Doom is coming against you, the dweller<note>Or “inhabitant”</note> of the land; the time comes, the day <supplied>is</supplied> near, panic and not joy <supplied>is</supplied> on the mountains. <verse-number id="Eze 7:8">8</verse-number><idiom-start/>Soon<idiom-end/><note>Literally “now from near”</note> I will pour out my rage on you, and I will fully vent my anger on you, and I will judge you according to your ways, and I will bring on you all of your detestable things. <verse-number id="Eze 7:9">9</verse-number>And my eye will not take pity, and I will not show compassion. According to your ways I will <idiom-start/>deal with you<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “on you I will bring”</note> and your detestable things will be in the midst of you, and you will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh <supplied>who</supplied> strikes.<note>Or “smites”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 7:10">10</verse-number>Look! The day is coming; doom goes out, the staff blossoms, pride sprouts. <verse-number id="Eze 7:11">11</verse-number>Violence has grown to <supplied>become</supplied> a staff of wickedness; <idiom-start/>none<idiom-end/><note>Literally “not <supplied>any</supplied>”</note> from them <supplied>will remain</supplied>, and <idiom-start/>none<idiom-end/><note>Literally “not <supplied>any</supplied>”</note> from their abundance nor from their wealth;<note>Or “noise,” or “multitude”; the same word appears in each of the next three verses</note> and prominence <supplied>will</supplied> not <supplied>be</supplied> among them. <verse-number id="Eze 7:12">12</verse-number>The time has come, the day has arrived; let not the buyer rejoice, and let the seller not mourn, for anger <supplied>is</supplied> on all their multitude. <verse-number id="Eze 7:13">13</verse-number>For the seller will not return to the merchandise <idiom-start/>while they are still alive<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “while still <supplied>is</supplied> in the life, their life”</note> for the vision <supplied>is</supplied> about all of its multitude; it will not change, and a man because of his guilt will not be able to hold onto his life. <verse-number id="Eze 7:14">14</verse-number>They shall blow on the trumpet and prepare <idiom-start/>everything<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the all”</note> but <supplied>there is</supplied> no <supplied>one</supplied> going to the battle, for my anger <supplied>is</supplied> on all of their multitude. <verse-number id="Eze 7:15">15</verse-number>The sword <idiom-start/>is outside<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “<supplied>is</supplied> in the outside place”</note> and the plague and the famine <idiom-start/>are inside<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “<supplied>are</supplied> from <supplied>the</supplied> house</note> <supplied>the one</supplied> who <supplied>is</supplied> in the field will die by the sword, and <supplied>the one</supplied> who <supplied>is</supplied> in the city, famine and plague will devour him. <verse-number id="Eze 7:16">16</verse-number>And <supplied>if</supplied> their survivors will escape, they will be on the mountains, like the doves of the valley, all of them groaning, each because of his guilt. <verse-number id="Eze 7:17">17</verse-number>All of the hands will hang limp, and all of <idiom-start/>the knees will be wet with urine<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “<supplied>the</supplied> knees will flow <supplied>with</supplied> water”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 7:18">18</verse-number>And they will wear sackcloth, and horror will cover them, and on all of <supplied>the</supplied> faces <supplied>will be</supplied> shame, and baldness on all of their heads. <verse-number id="Eze 7:19">19</verse-number>Their silver they will discard on the streets, and filth will be their gold; their silver and their gold will not be able to rescue them on the day of the wrath of Yahweh. They will not satisfy their <idiom-start/>hunger<idiom-end/><note>Literally “selves,” or “desire”</note> and their stomachs they will not fill, for their guilt will be their<note>Hebrew “the”</note> stumbling block. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Judgment for the Profanation of the Temple and Sanctuary</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 7:20">20</verse-number>“ ‘And the beauty of its<note>Or “their”</note> ornament <idiom-start/>he made into a prideful thing<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to <supplied>a</supplied> prideful <supplied>thing</supplied> he made it”</note> and made with it their detestable things and their vile idols; therefore I will make it into an impure thing for them. <verse-number id="Eze 7:21">21</verse-number>And I will give it into the hand of strangers as plunder and to the wicked people of the earth as spoil, and they will defile it. <verse-number id="Eze 7:22">22</verse-number>And I will turn my face from them, and they will defile my treasured <supplied>place</supplied>, and violent ones will enter and defile it. <verse-number id="Eze 7:23">23</verse-number>Make a chain for the land; it is full of <idiom-start/>bloody crimes<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<supplied>the</supplied> judgment of blood”</note> and the city is full of violence. <verse-number id="Eze 7:24">24</verse-number>And I will bring <supplied>the</supplied> worst of <supplied>the</supplied> nations, and they will take possession of their houses, and I will put to an end <supplied>the</supplied> pride of <supplied>the</supplied> mighty ones, and their sanctuaries will be defiled. <verse-number id="Eze 7:25">25</verse-number>Anguish comes, and they will seek peace, and <supplied>there will be</supplied> none. <verse-number id="Eze 7:26">26</verse-number>Calamity upon calamity will come, and rumor will be upon rumor. And they will seek a vision from a prophet, but instruction will perish from <supplied>the</supplied> priest and counsel from <supplied>the</supplied> elders. <verse-number id="Eze 7:27">27</verse-number>The king will mourn, and <supplied>the</supplied> prince will be dressed with despair, and the hands of the people of the land will tremble. According to their way I will do to<note>Or “deal with”</note> them, and according to their judgments I will judge them, and they will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh.’ ” </p>
		</chapter>