<chapter id="Eze 8">
			<pericope>Abominations in the Temple and in Jerusalem</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 8:1">1</verse-number><idiom-start/>And then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and it happened”</note> in the sixth year, in the sixth <supplied>month</supplied>, on the fifth <supplied>day</supplied> of the month, I <supplied>was</supplied> sitting in my house, and the elders of Judah <supplied>were</supplied> sitting <idiom-start/>before me<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to the face of me”</note> And the hand of the Lord Yahweh fell on me there, <verse-number id="Eze 8:2">2</verse-number>and I saw,<note>Or “looked”</note> and look! A figure like <supplied>the</supplied> appearance of a man;<note>Hebrew “fire”; but reading the BHS note 2b, “a man.”</note> from the appearance of his waist and below <supplied>was</supplied> fire, and from his waist and <idiom-start/>upward<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to above”</note> <supplied>was</supplied> like <supplied>the</supplied> appearance of brightness,<note>Or “shining metal”</note> like the <idiom-start/>outward appearance of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “eye”</note> amber. <verse-number id="Eze 8:3">3</verse-number>And he sent out <supplied>the</supplied> form of a hand, and he took me by a lock of hair of my head, and <supplied>the</supplied> Spirit lifted me between earth and heaven, and it brought me to Jerusalem in visions of God to the doorway of <supplied>the</supplied> inner gate <idiom-start/>that faced north<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the <supplied>one</supplied> facing north”</note> <supplied>at</supplied> which there <supplied>was</supplied> the seat of the image of jealousy, which was making jealous. <verse-number id="Eze 8:4">4</verse-number>And look! There <supplied>was</supplied> the glory of the God of Israel like the vision that I saw in the valley. <verse-number id="Eze 8:5">5</verse-number>And he said to me, “Son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> lift up now<note>Particle of entreaty, “please/ please now”</note> your eyes <idiom-start/>toward the north<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “<supplied>to</supplied> the way of the north”</note> And I lifted up my eyes <idiom-start/>toward the north<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “<supplied>to</supplied> the way of the north”</note> and, look, <supplied>there was</supplied> to the north of the gate of the altar this image of jealousy at the entrance. <verse-number id="Eze 8:6">6</verse-number>And he said to me, “Son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> “<idiom-start/>Do you see<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<supplied>Are</supplied> you seeing?”</note> what they <supplied>are</supplied> doing—great detestable things that the house of Israel <supplied>is</supplied> committing<note>Or “doing”</note> here <supplied>so as</supplied> to drive <supplied>me</supplied> from<note>Hebrew “from upon”</note> my sanctuary, and yet <idiom-start/>you will see again<idiom-end/><note>Literally “you will return you will see”</note> greater<note>Or “worse”</note> detestable things.” <verse-number id="Eze 8:7">7</verse-number>And he brought me to the doorway of the courtyard, and I saw, and look! A hole in the wall. <verse-number id="Eze 8:8">8</verse-number>And he said to me, “Son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> dig now<note>Or “please”</note> through the wall.” And I dug through the wall, and look! There was a doorway. <verse-number id="Eze 8:9">9</verse-number>And he said to me, “Come and see the detestable things, the evil that they are doing<note>Or “making”</note> here. <verse-number id="Eze 8:10">10</verse-number>And I came, and I saw, and look, all kinds of creatures<note>Hebrew “creature”</note> and detestable beasts;<note>Hebrew “beast”</note> <supplied>and</supplied> all of the idols of the house of Israel <supplied>were</supplied> carved on the wall <idiom-start/>all around<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “around around”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 8:11">11</verse-number>And seventy men from the elders of the house of Israel, and Jaazaniah, the son of Shaphan, <supplied>was</supplied> standing in the midst of them, <supplied>and</supplied> <supplied>they were</supplied> standing <idiom-start/>before them<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to the face of them”</note> Each <supplied>one</supplied> <supplied>had</supplied> his censer in his hand, and the fragrance of the cloud of the incense <supplied>was</supplied> going up. <verse-number id="Eze 8:12">12</verse-number>And he said to me, “Have you seen, son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> what the elders of the house of Israel <supplied>are</supplied> doing in the dark, each in the inner rooms of his idol, for <supplied>they are</supplied> saying, ‘Yahweh <supplied>is</supplied> not seeing us; Yahweh has abandoned the land.’ ” <verse-number id="Eze 8:13">13</verse-number>And he said to me, “Still <idiom-start/>you will see again<idiom-end/><note>Literally “you will return, you will see”</note> greater detestable things that they <supplied>are</supplied> doing.” <verse-number id="Eze 8:14">14</verse-number>And he brought me to the doorway of the gate of the house of Yahweh that <supplied>is</supplied> toward the north, and look! There <supplied>were</supplied> the women sitting weeping for Tammuz. <verse-number id="Eze 8:15">15</verse-number>And he said to me, “Have you seen, son of man?<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> Still <idiom-start/>you will see again<idiom-end/><note>Literally “you will return, you will see”</note> greater detestable things than these.” <verse-number id="Eze 8:16">16</verse-number>And he brought me to the inner courtyard of the house of Yahweh, and look, <supplied>at</supplied> the doorway of the temple of Yahweh, between the portico and the altar, <supplied>there were</supplied> about twenty-five men <supplied>with</supplied> their backs to the temple of Yahweh and their faces toward the east, and they <supplied>were</supplied> bowing down toward the east before the sun. <verse-number id="Eze 8:17">17</verse-number>And he said to me, “Have you seen, son of man?<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> <idiom-start/>Was it too small a thing<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was it <supplied>too</supplied> little”</note> for the house of Judah <idiom-start/>to do<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from doing”</note> the detestable things that they did here? For they filled up the land <supplied>with</supplied> violence, and <idiom-start/>they provoked me to anger again<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “they returned to provoke me to anger”</note> and look! They <supplied>are</supplied> putting the branch to their nose. <verse-number id="Eze 8:18">18</verse-number>And so I will act in rage, and my eye will not take pity, and I will not have compassion, and they will cry in my ear <supplied>with</supplied> a loud voice, and I will not hear them.” </p>
		</chapter>