<chapter id="Eze 9">
			<pericope>Yahweh’s Avenging Messenger Destroys the Wicked in the City</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 9:1">1</verse-number>And he called in my ears <supplied>with</supplied> a loud voice, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> “<supplied>They</supplied> have come near,<note>Or “Come near” (imperative)</note> the punishers of the city, and each <supplied>with</supplied> his weapon of destruction in his hand. <verse-number id="Eze 9:2">2</verse-number>And look! Six men coming from the way of <idiom-start/>the upper gate<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the gate of the upper”</note> that faced <idiom-start/>northward<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “faced north + directive”</note> and each <supplied>with</supplied> his weapon for<note>Or “of”</note> shattering in his hand; and one man <supplied>was</supplied> in the midst of them, dressed in linen, and the<note>Or “his”</note> writing case of the scribe <supplied>was</supplied> at his side. And they came and stood beside the bronze altar. <verse-number id="Eze 9:3">3</verse-number>And the glory of the God of Israel lifted itself up from upon the cherub that he was on<note>Hebrew “which he was on it”</note> <supplied>and went</supplied> to the threshold of the house,<note>That is, the temple</note> and he called to the man who <supplied>was</supplied> clothed in linen <idiom-start/>with a scribal writing case at his side<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “whom a writing case of a scribe <supplied>was</supplied> at his side”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 9:4">4</verse-number>And Yahweh said to him, “Go through in the midst of the city, in the midst of Jerusalem, and you must place a mark on the foreheads of the men <idiom-start/>who are groaning and lamenting<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the men the groaning and the lamenting”</note> about all of the detestable things <idiom-start/>that are being done<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the being done”</note> in the midst of her.” <verse-number id="Eze 9:5">5</verse-number>And to the others he said in my hearing, “Go through the city behind him and kill! Your eyes shall not take pity, and you shall not have compassion. <verse-number id="Eze 9:6">6</verse-number>You must kill <idiom-start/>totally<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to destruction”</note> old man, young man and young woman, and little children and women, but <idiom-start/>concerning<idiom-end/><note>Literally “upon”</note> every man <idiom-start/>with the mark on him<idiom-end/><note>Literally “which is on him the mark”</note> you must not approach; and from my sanctuary you must begin.” And they began with the old men who <idiom-start/>were before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<supplied>were</supplied> to the face of”</note> the house.<note>That is, the temple</note> <verse-number id="Eze 9:7">7</verse-number>And he said to them, “Defile the house<note>Or “temple”</note> and fill the courtyards <supplied>with</supplied> the dead; go out! And they went out, and they killed in the city. <verse-number id="Eze 9:8">8</verse-number><idiom-start/>And then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and it was”</note> <idiom-start/>as they were striking<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “in their striking”</note> and I <supplied>was</supplied> left behind, I fell on my face, and I cried out, and I said, “Ah, Lord Yahweh! “<supplied>Will</supplied> you <supplied>be</supplied> destroying all of the remnant of Israel <idiom-start/>while you pour out your rage<idiom-end/><note>Literally “when pouring out your rage”</note> on Jerusalem?” <verse-number id="Eze 9:9">9</verse-number>And he said to me, “The guilt of the house of Israel and Judah <supplied>is</supplied> <idiom-start/>exceedingly<idiom-end/><note>Literally “with very very”</note> great, and the land is filled with bloodguilt, and the city is full of injustice. For they say Yahweh abandoned the land, and <idiom-start/>Yahweh does not see<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “not Yahweh <supplied>is</supplied> seeing</note> <verse-number id="Eze 9:10">10</verse-number>And I, my eye will not take pity, and I will not have compassion; their way I will bring on their head.” <verse-number id="Eze 9:11">11</verse-number>And look! The man clothed in linen <supplied>and</supplied> <idiom-start/>with a writing case at his side<idiom-end/><note>Literally “which/whom the writing-case <supplied>was</supplied> at his side”</note> <supplied>was</supplied> bringing back a word, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> “I have done all that you commanded me.” </p>
		</chapter>