<chapter id="Eze 10">
			<pericope>God’s Presence Leaves the Temple</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 10:1">1</verse-number>And I looked, and look! On the expanse that <supplied>was</supplied> above the head of the cherubim <supplied>something</supplied> like a stone of sapphire,<note>Or “lapis lazuli”</note> <supplied>and</supplied> like <supplied>the</supplied> appearance of <supplied>the</supplied> shape of a throne it appeared above them. <verse-number id="Eze 10:2">2</verse-number>And he spoke<note>Or “said”</note> to the man clothed in linen and said, “Go <idiom-start/>in among the wheel area under the cherubim<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to between to the wheel to under the cherub”</note> and fill the hollow of your hands <supplied>with</supplied> coals of fire from among the cherubim, and toss <supplied>them</supplied> on the city.” And he went <supplied>right</supplied> before my eyes. <verse-number id="Eze 10:3">3</verse-number>Now<note>Or “And”</note> the cherubim <supplied>were</supplied> standing on <supplied>the</supplied> south of the temple <idiom-start/>when the man went<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “at his coming the man”</note> and the cloud filled the inner courtyard. <verse-number id="Eze 10:4">4</verse-number>And the glory of Yahweh rose up from on the cherub toward<note>Or “onto”</note> the threshold of the house,<note>Or “temple”</note> and the house<note>Or “temple”</note> was filled with the cloud, and the courtyard was filled with the brightness of the glory of Yahweh. <verse-number id="Eze 10:5">5</verse-number>And the sound of the wings of the cherubim was heard <idiom-start/>as far as<idiom-end/><note>Literally “up to”</note> the outer courtyard; <supplied>it was</supplied> like the voice of God Shaddai<note>Often translated “Almighty”</note> <idiom-start/>when he speaks<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “in his speaking”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 10:6">6</verse-number>And then at his command<note>Or “when he commanded”</note> to the man clothed in linen, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> “Take fire from among the wheel area from among the cherubim,” he went and stood beside the wheel. <verse-number id="Eze 10:7">7</verse-number>Then the cherub stretched out his hand from among<note>Or “between”</note> the cherubim toward the fire that <supplied>was</supplied> among<note>Or “between”</note> the cherubim, and he lifted up and gave<note>Or “placed”</note> <supplied>it</supplied> into the hollow of the hand of <supplied>the man</supplied> clothed with linen, and he took <supplied>it</supplied>, and he went out. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 10:8">8</verse-number>And <supplied>there</supplied> appeared for<note>Literally “to”</note> the cherubim <supplied>the</supplied> form of <idiom-start/>a human hand<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a hand of a man”</note> under their wings. <verse-number id="Eze 10:9">9</verse-number>And I saw, and look, four wheels beside the cherubim, <idiom-start/>one wheel beside each cherub<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “wheel one beside the cherub one, and wheel one beside the cherub one”</note> and the appearance of the wheels <supplied>was</supplied> like <supplied>the</supplied> outward appearance of <idiom-start/>turquoise stone<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “stone of turquoise”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 10:10">10</verse-number>Their appearance<note>That is, of the wheels</note> <idiom-start/>was the same for each of the four of them<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “likeness one <supplied>was</supplied> for the four of them”</note> as if the wheel was in the midst of a wheel. <verse-number id="Eze 10:11">11</verse-number><idiom-start/>When they went<idiom-end/><note>Literally “In their going”</note> to the four of their directions <supplied>that</supplied> they went, they did not change direction <idiom-start/>when they went<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “At their going”</note> for the place <supplied>to</supplied> which the head<note>Or “first” or “lead wheel”</note> turned, they went behind him; they did not change direction at their going. <verse-number id="Eze 10:12">12</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>their whole body<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the whole of their body”</note> and their rims, and their spokes, and their wings, and the wheels <supplied>were</supplied> full of eyes <supplied>all</supplied> around—<idiom-start/>the wheels for the four of them<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “for the four of them their wheels”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 10:13">13</verse-number>Concerning the wheels, he <supplied>was</supplied> calling them “the wheelwork” <idiom-start/>in my hearing<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “in my ears”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 10:14">14</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>each one had four faces<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “four faces <supplied>were</supplied> to each”</note> the face of the one <supplied>was</supplied> the face of a cherub, and the face of the second <supplied>was the</supplied> face of a human, and the face of the third <supplied>was the</supplied> face of a lion, and the fourth <supplied>was the</supplied> face of an eagle. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 10:15">15</verse-number>And the cherubim rose; that is, the living creatures<note>Hebrew “creature”</note> that I saw at the <idiom-start/>Kebar River<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “river of Kebar”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 10:16">16</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>when the cherubim went<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “at the going of the cherubim”</note> the wheels beside them went; and <idiom-start/>when the cherubim lifted their wings to rise up from the earth<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “and at the lifting of the cherubim wings their to rise from on the earth”</note> the wheels also did not turn aside from beside them. <verse-number id="Eze 10:17">17</verse-number><idiom-start/>When they stood<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “at their standing”</note> they stood, and at their rising, they rose with them, for the spirit of the living creatures <supplied>was</supplied> in them. <verse-number id="Eze 10:18">18</verse-number>And the glory of Yahweh went out from<note>Hebrew “from on”</note> the threshold of the temple, and it stood above the cherubim. <verse-number id="Eze 10:19">19</verse-number>And the cherubim lifted up their wings, and they rose from the earth before my eyes. At their going out, the wheels <supplied>were</supplied><note>Hebrew “to”</note> beside them. And he stood <supplied>at</supplied> the doorway of the eastern gate of the temple<note>Or “house”</note> of Yahweh, and the glory of the God of Israel <idiom-start/>was over them<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “on them from to above”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 10:20">20</verse-number>This <supplied>was</supplied><note>Or “these were”</note> the living creature that I saw under the God of Israel at the <idiom-start/>Kebar River<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “river of Kebar”</note> and I knew that they <supplied>were</supplied> cherubim. <verse-number id="Eze 10:21">21</verse-number><idiom-start/>Each one had four faces<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “four faces <supplied>were</supplied> for one/each”</note> and <supplied>there were</supplied> four wings for each, and <supplied>the</supplied> likeness of <idiom-start/>human hands<idiom-end/><note>Literally “hands of a man”</note> <supplied>was</supplied> under their wings. <verse-number id="Eze 10:22">22</verse-number>And the likeness of their faces, they <supplied>were</supplied> the faces that I saw at the <idiom-start/>Kebar River<idiom-end/>;<note>Litearlly “river of Kebar”</note> <supplied>thus was</supplied> their appearance, and they each went <idiom-start/>straight ahead<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to the opposite of face his”</note> </p>
		</chapter>