<chapter id="Eze 11">
			<pericope>Judgment On Evil Rulers</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 11:1">1</verse-number>And <supplied>the</supplied> Spirit lifted me up, and it brought me to the eastern gate, the one facing east, of the temple<note>Or “house”</note> of Yahweh. And look, there were twenty-five men in the doorway of the gate, and I saw Jaazaniah the son of Azzur in the midst of them, and Pelatiah the son of Benaiah, the commanders of the people. <verse-number id="Eze 11:2">2</verse-number>And he said to me, “Son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> these <supplied>are</supplied> the men <idiom-start/>who devise mischief<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the ones devising mischief”</note> and <supplied>who are</supplied> offering bad counsel in this city, <verse-number id="Eze 11:3">3</verse-number>who <supplied>are</supplied> saying, “The building of houses <supplied>is</supplied> not near; <supplied>the city</supplied> is the pot, and we <supplied>are</supplied> the flesh. <verse-number id="Eze 11:4">4</verse-number>Therefore prophesy against them! Prophesy, son of man!”<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 11:5">5</verse-number>And the Spirit of Yahweh fell on me, and he said to me, “Say, ‘thus says Yahweh: “This is what you think, house of Israel, and I myself know them,<note>Hebrew “it”</note> the thoughts of your spirit. <verse-number id="Eze 11:6">6</verse-number>You made your slain ones numerous in this city, and you have filled its streets <supplied>with</supplied> slain ones.” ’<note>Hebrew “slain one”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 11:7">7</verse-number>Therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Your slain ones whom you put in its midst, they <supplied>are</supplied> the flesh, and it is <supplied>the</supplied> pot, and I<note>Hebrew “he”</note> will bring you out from its midst. <verse-number id="Eze 11:8">8</verse-number><supplied>The</supplied> sword you have feared, and <supplied>the</supplied> sword I will bring against you!” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh. <verse-number id="Eze 11:9">9</verse-number>“And I will bring you out from its midst, and I will give you into <supplied>the</supplied> hand of strangers, and I will execute judgments against you. <verse-number id="Eze 11:10">10</verse-number>By the sword you will fall at the border of Israel; I will judge you, and you will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh. <verse-number id="Eze 11:11">11</verse-number>It will not be as a pot to you, and <supplied>so</supplied> you would be<note>Or “will be”</note> in the midst of it as flesh, <supplied>for</supplied> at the border of Israel I will judge you. <verse-number id="Eze 11:12">12</verse-number>And you will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh, whose<note>Hebrew “which”</note> rules you did not follow, and whose<note>Hebrew “my”</note> regulations you did not do, but according to the regulations of the nations that <supplied>are</supplied> around you, you acted.” ’<note>Or “did”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 11:13">13</verse-number>And it happened <supplied>that</supplied> <idiom-start/>as I was prophesying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “at my prophesying”</note> Pelatiahu the son of Benaiahu died! And I fell on my face, and I cried <supplied>with</supplied> a loud voice, and I said, “Ah, Lord Yahweh, you <supplied>are</supplied> making <supplied>a</supplied> complete destruction <supplied>of</supplied> the remnant of Israel!” <verse-number id="Eze 11:14">14</verse-number>And the word of Yahweh <idiom-start/>came<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was”</note> to me, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Or “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 11:15">15</verse-number>“Son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> your brothers, your brothers, the men of your redemption, and all of the house of Israel, all of it, <idiom-start/>who said concerning the inhabitants of Jerusalem<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “which they said concerning them the inhabitants of Jerusalem”</note> ‘They are far from Yahweh, <supplied>therefore</supplied> to us this land was given as a possession.’ <verse-number id="Eze 11:16">16</verse-number>Therefore say, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Though I have removed them <supplied>far away</supplied> among the nations and though I have scattered them among the countries, yet I was a sanctuary to them <supplied>for a</supplied> little while in the countries <idiom-start/>to which they have gone<idiom-end/>.’ ”<note>Literally “which they came there”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 11:17">17</verse-number>Therefore say, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “And I will assemble you from the peoples, and I will gather you from the countries <supplied>to</supplied> which you were scattered among them, and I will give the land of Israel to you. <verse-number id="Eze 11:18">18</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied> they come there, then they will remove all of its vile idols and all of its detestable things from it. <verse-number id="Eze 11:19">19</verse-number>And I will give to them one heart, and a new spirit I will give<note>Or “put”</note> in their inner parts. And I will remove their<note>Hebrew “the”</note> heart of stone from their body, and I will give to them a heart of flesh, <verse-number id="Eze 11:20">20</verse-number>so that they may walk in my statutes, and they will keep my regulations, and they will do them, and they will be to me a people, and I myself will be to them as God. <verse-number id="Eze 11:21">21</verse-number>But to<note>Or “and to”</note> the heart of their abominations and the detestable things their heart is going. I will bring their way on their head,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh.’ ” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 11:22">22</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> the cherubim lifted up their wings, and their<note>Or “the”</note> wheels <supplied>were</supplied> beside them, and the glory of the God of Israel <idiom-start/>was over them<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “from to above”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 11:23">23</verse-number>And the glory of Yahweh went up from the midst of the city, and it stood <supplied>still</supplied> on the mountain that <supplied>is</supplied> to the east of the city. <verse-number id="Eze 11:24">24</verse-number>And <supplied>the</supplied> Spirit lifted me up, and it brought me to Chaldea, to the exiles,<note>Hebrew “exile”</note> in the vision by the spirit of God; and the vision that I had seen <idiom-start/>left me<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “went up from <supplied>being</supplied> upon me”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 11:25">25</verse-number>And I spoke to the exiles<note>Hebrew “exile”</note> all of the words of Yahweh that he had shown me. </p>
		</chapter>