<chapter id="Eze 13">
			<pericope>Condemnation of False Prophets</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 13:1">1</verse-number>And the word of Yahweh <idiom-start/>came<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was”</note> to me, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Or “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 13:2">2</verse-number>“Son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> prophesy to<note>Or “against”</note> the prophets of Israel <idiom-start/>who are prophesying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the <supplied>ones</supplied> prophesying”</note> and you must say to <supplied>those who are</supplied> prophets out of their own <idiom-start/>imagination<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “heart”</note> ‘Hear the word of Yahweh!’ <verse-number id="Eze 13:3">3</verse-number>Thus says the Lord Yahweh: ‘Alas, for the foolish prophets who <supplied>are</supplied> going after their <supplied>own</supplied> spirit, <idiom-start/>and they did not see anything<idiom-end/>!<note>Literally “and not they saw”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 13:4">4</verse-number>Your prophets have been like foxes<note>Or “jackals”</note> among ruins. <verse-number id="Eze 13:5">5</verse-number>You did not go up into<note>Hebrew “in”</note> the breaches and repair a wall for the house of Israel to stand <supplied>firm</supplied> in the battle on the day of Yahweh. <verse-number id="Eze 13:6">6</verse-number>They saw falseness and <idiom-start/>a lying divination<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “a divination of a lie”</note> the ones saying, ‘Declaration of Yahweh!’ and Yahweh did not send them, and they wait <idiom-start/>for the confirmation of their word<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to confirm a word”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 13:7">7</verse-number>Have you not seen <idiom-start/>a false vision<idiom-end/><note>Literally “vision of falseness”</note> and spoken <supplied>a</supplied> <idiom-start/>lying divination<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “divination of a lie”</note> and <supplied>you</supplied> said, ‘Declaration of Yahweh!’ but <idiom-start/>I myself did not speak<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “I not I spoke”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 13:8">8</verse-number>Therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh: ‘Because of your speaking falseness and <supplied>because</supplied> you envisioned a lie, therefore, look! I <supplied>am</supplied> against you!” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh. <verse-number id="Eze 13:9">9</verse-number>“And it will be my hand against the prophets who <supplied>are</supplied> seeing falseness and who <supplied>are</supplied> practicing lying divination. They will not be in the council of my people, and they will not be written <supplied>down</supplied> in the record <supplied>book</supplied> of the house of Israel, and into<note>Hebrew “in”</note> the land of Israel they will not come, and <supplied>then</supplied> you will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> the Lord Yahweh. <verse-number id="Eze 13:10">10</verse-number>Because, yes, because they led my people astray, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to say”</note> ‘Peace!’ And <supplied>there is</supplied> not peace. And <supplied>when</supplied> anyone<note>Hebrew “he”</note> builds a flimsy wall, look, they coat it <supplied>with</supplied> whitewash. <verse-number id="Eze 13:11">11</verse-number>Say to <supplied>those</supplied> covering <supplied>it</supplied> <supplied>with</supplied> whitewash that it will fall; there will be <idiom-start/>a torrent of rain<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “rain flooding”</note> and I will give stones of hail; they will fall! <note>Or “and I will give great hailstones. They will fall”</note> And a <idiom-start/>windstorm<idiom-end/><note>Literally “wind of a storm”; or “with respect/concerning you stones of hail, they will fall”</note> will burst forth! <verse-number id="Eze 13:12">12</verse-number>And look! <supplied>When</supplied> the wall falls, will it not be said to you, ‘Where <supplied>is</supplied> the whitewash <supplied>with</supplied> which you covered <supplied>it</supplied>?’ <verse-number id="Eze 13:13">13</verse-number>Therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh: ‘And <supplied>so</supplied> I will let burst forth a <idiom-start/>windstorm<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a wind of storm”</note> in my rage, and <idiom-start/>there will be a torrent of rain<idiom-end/><note>Literally “rain flooding there will be”</note> in my anger, and hailstones in <supplied>my</supplied> rage <idiom-start/>for complete destruction<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to complete destruction”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 13:14">14</verse-number>And I will break down the wall that you covered <supplied>with</supplied> whitewash, and I will knock it to the ground, and its foundation will be revealed, and it will fall, and you will come to an end in the midst of it, and you will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh! <verse-number id="Eze 13:15">15</verse-number>And I will fully vent my rage against the wall and against those covering it <supplied>with</supplied> whitewash, and I will say to you, “<idiom-start/>The wall is no more<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “not <supplied>is</supplied> the wall”</note> and <idiom-start/>the people covering it are no more<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “not <supplied>are</supplied> the <supplied>people</supplied> whitewashing him”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 13:16">16</verse-number><supplied>that is</supplied>, the prophets of Israel, the ones prophesying concerning Jerusalem and the ones seeing visions of peace, and there is not peace!’ ” ” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 13:17">17</verse-number>“And you, son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> place your face toward the daughters of your people who prophesy from their <idiom-start/>imagination<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “heart”</note> and prophesy against them! <verse-number id="Eze 13:18">18</verse-number>And you must say, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Woe to <idiom-start/>those who sew<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<supplied>the</supplied> sewers of”</note> magic charm bands on all the wrists<note>Or “joints”</note> of the hands of my <supplied>people</supplied> and <idiom-start/>those who make the veils<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the makers of the veils”</note> <supplied>that are</supplied> on the head of <supplied>people of</supplied> every height, to ensnare <supplied>people’s</supplied> lives!<note>Or “souls”</note> Will you ensnare <supplied>the</supplied> lives<note>Or “souls”</note> of my people <idiom-start/>and keep yourselves alive<idiom-end/>?<note>Literally “and lives/souls for you, you keep alive”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 13:19">19</verse-number>And you defiled me among my people for a handful of barley and for morsels of bread to kill persons who should not die and to keep alive persons who should not live by <supplied>means of</supplied> your lies to my people <supplied>who are</supplied> listening to <supplied>your</supplied> lies.” ’<note>Hebrew “lie”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 13:20">20</verse-number>Therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh: ‘Look! I am against your magic charm bands <idiom-start/>with which you are ensnaring persons<idiom-end/><note>Literally “which you <supplied>are</supplied> ensnaring with them the souls/individuals”</note> as birds; I will tear them from your arms, and I will release the persons that you <supplied>are</supplied> ensnaring, <supplied>treating</supplied> persons as birds. <verse-number id="Eze 13:21">21</verse-number>And I will tear off your veils, and I will deliver my people from your hand, and they will not any longer be in your hand as prey, and you will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh. <verse-number id="Eze 13:22">22</verse-number>Because <supplied>you</supplied> disheartened <supplied>the</supplied> heart of <supplied>the</supplied> righteous <supplied>by</supplied> deception, and I have not<note>Or “did not”</note> caused him pain, and strengthened <supplied>the</supplied> hands of <supplied>the</supplied> wicked <supplied>so that he did</supplied> not turn<note>Or “not to turn”</note> from his wicked way to save his life. <verse-number id="Eze 13:23">23</verse-number>Therefore falseness<note>Or “vanity” or “vain/false visions”</note> you will not see,<note>Or “observe”</note> and divination you will not practice<note>Or “you will indeed not practice divination”</note> any longer, and I will rescue my people from your hand, and you will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh!’ ” </p>
		</chapter>