<chapter id="Eze 14">
			<pericope>Condemnation of Israel’s Idolatrous Elders</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 14:1">1</verse-number>And men from the elders of Israel came to me, and they sat <idiom-start/>before me<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to the face of me”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 14:2">2</verse-number>And the word of Yahweh <idiom-start/>came<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was”</note> to me, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 14:3">3</verse-number>“Son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> these men took up their idols into their heart and <idiom-start/>they placed before themselves<idiom-end/><note>Literally “they gave before their faces”</note> a stumbling block of their guilt.<note>Or “iniquity”</note> <idiom-start/>Should I really let myself be consulted by them<idiom-end/>?<note>Literally “Surely I will let me be consulted by them?”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 14:4">4</verse-number>Therefore speak with them, and you must say to them, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Every person from the house of Israel who brings up his idols into his heart and <idiom-start/>places before himself<idiom-end/><note>Literally “they gave before their faces”</note> a stumbling block of his guilt<note>Or “iniquity”</note> and <supplied>yet</supplied> he comes to the prophet, I Yahweh, I will respond to him through this act<note>Hebrew “it”</note> with <supplied>respect to</supplied> the multitude<note>According to the <i>Kethib</i>; the <i>Qere</i> reads “I will respond to him, he who comes with the multitude of his idols”</note> of his idols, <verse-number id="Eze 14:5">5</verse-number>so that <supplied>I may</supplied> take hold of the house of Israel by their heart, <supplied>those</supplied> who are estranged from me, all of them, through their idols.’ <verse-number id="Eze 14:6">6</verse-number>Therefore say to the house of Israel, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Return,<note>Or “Repent”</note> and turn away from your idols and from all of your detestable things! Turn away your faces!” ’ <verse-number id="Eze 14:7">7</verse-number>For <idiom-start/>each person<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a man, a man” or “each one, each one”</note> from the house of Israel, and from the alien who dwells as an alien in Israel, who separates himself <idiom-start/>from following me<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from behind me”</note> and brings up his idols into his heart and <idiom-start/>places before himself<idiom-end/><note>Literally “he puts beside his face”</note> a stumbling block of his guilt<note>Or “iniquity”</note>, and <supplied>yet</supplied> he comes to the prophet to consult him concerning me, I Yahweh will answer<note>Or “am answering”</note> him myself. <verse-number id="Eze 14:8">8</verse-number>And I will set my face against that person, and I will make him to<note>Or “as”</note> <supplied>be</supplied> a sign and <supplied>make him</supplied> into<note>Hebrew “to”</note> <supplied>the subject of</supplied> proverbs; and I will cut him off from the midst of my people, and you will know I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh. <verse-number id="Eze 14:9">9</verse-number>And the prophet, if he is deceived and he speaks a word, I Yahweh, I have deceived that prophet, and I will stretch out my hand against him, and I will destroy him from the midst of my people Israel. <verse-number id="Eze 14:10">10</verse-number>And they will bear their guilt, like<note>Or “as”</note> the guilt of the inquirer so<note>Or “like”</note> the guilt of the prophet will be, <verse-number id="Eze 14:11">11</verse-number>so that the house of Israel will not go astray again <idiom-start/>from me<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from behind me”</note> and they will not make themselves unclean again with all of their transgressions, and they will be for me a people, and I will be for them as God,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jerusalem will not be Spared</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 14:12">12</verse-number>And the word of Yahweh <idiom-start/>came<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was”</note> to me, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 14:13">13</verse-number>“Son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> when a land sins against me by <idiom-start/>acting very unfaithfully<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “acting unfaithfully doing infidelity”</note> then I will stretch out my hand against it, and I will break for it <supplied>the</supplied> <idiom-start/>supply of food<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “staff of bread”</note> and I will send against it famine, and I will cut it off, <supplied>both</supplied> human and animal. <verse-number id="Eze 14:14">14</verse-number>And if <supplied>even</supplied> the three of these men were in the midst of it—Noah, Daniel, and Job—they, through their righteousness, would save <supplied>only</supplied> <idiom-start/>themselves<idiom-end/>!”<note>Literally “their souls”</note> <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh. <verse-number id="Eze 14:15">15</verse-number>“If a fierce animal I <supplied>should</supplied> let cross through the land, and it <supplied>should</supplied> make it childless and it will be <supplied>a</supplied> desolation, so that <supplied>there will</supplied> not <supplied>be</supplied> one crossing over <supplied>the land</supplied> <idiom-start/>due to<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from the face of”</note> the presence of the animal, <verse-number id="Eze 14:16">16</verse-number><supplied>even if</supplied> these three men <supplied>were</supplied> in the midst of it, <idiom-start/>as surely as I live<idiom-end/>,”<note>Literally “live I”</note> <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh, “surely they will not save sons and daughters; <idiom-start/>they themselves alone<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “they to alone them”</note> they will be saved, but the land will be <supplied>a</supplied> desolation. <verse-number id="Eze 14:17">17</verse-number>Or, if I bring a sword over that land, and I say, ‘Sword, let it cross over into<note>Hebrew “in”</note> the land!’ And I will cut off from it <supplied>both</supplied> human and animal. <verse-number id="Eze 14:18">18</verse-number>And <supplied>if</supplied> these three men <supplied>were</supplied> in the midst of it, <idiom-start/>as surely as I live<idiom-end/>,”<note>Literally “live I”</note> <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh, “they will not save sons and daughters, but <idiom-start/>they alone<idiom-end/><note>Literally “they to alone them”</note> will be saved. <verse-number id="Eze 14:19">19</verse-number>And if I <supplied>were to</supplied> send a plague to that land, and I pour out my rage on it with blood to cut it off, <supplied>both</supplied> human and animal, <verse-number id="Eze 14:20">20</verse-number>and <supplied>if</supplied> Noah, Daniel, and Job <supplied>were</supplied> in the midst of her, <idiom-start/>as surely as I live<idiom-end/>,”<note>Literally “live I”</note> <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh, “surely not <supplied>a</supplied> son, surely not <supplied>a</supplied> daughter will they save by their righteousness; they would save <idiom-start/>themselves<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “their souls”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 14:21">21</verse-number>For thus says the Lord Yahweh: “How much more when I send my four punishments—the evil sword, and famine, and <supplied>a</supplied> fierce animal, and a plague—to Jerusalem to cut it off, <supplied>both</supplied> human and animal! <verse-number id="Eze 14:22">22</verse-number>But<note>Or “And”</note> look! A remnant will be left over in it, sons and daughters <idiom-start/>who will be brought out<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the ones being brought out”</note> Look! They are coming out to you, and you will see their way, and with their deeds you will be consoled with respect to<note>Hebrew “for”</note> the evil that I brought over Jerusalem, all of <supplied>it</supplied> that I brought over<note>Or “upon”</note> it. <verse-number id="Eze 14:23">23</verse-number>And they will console you when you see their way and their deeds, and you will know that not for nothing I did all that I did in it,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh. </p>
		</chapter>