<chapter id="Eze 15">
			<pericope>Jerusalem a Useless Vine</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 15:1">1</verse-number>And the word of Yahweh <idiom-start/>came<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was”</note> to me, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 15:2">2</verse-number>“Son of man, how will the wood of the vine be <idiom-start/>better than<idiom-end/><note>Literally “more than”</note> <idiom-start/>any of the wood of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all of the wood of”</note> the branch which is among the trees of the forest?<note>Or “wood”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 15:3">3</verse-number>Can wood be taken from it to make anything, or can they take a tent peg from it to hang on it any object?<note>Or “vessel”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 15:4">4</verse-number>Look! It is given to the fire as fuel. The fire will consume two of its ends, and its middle will be charred. Is it useful for anything? <verse-number id="Eze 15:5">5</verse-number>Look! <idiom-start/>When it is in perfect condition<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “In being it perfect”</note> it will not be used for anything, <idiom-start/>how much less<idiom-end/><note>Literally “indeed”</note> <idiom-start/>when the fire has consumed it<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for <supplied>if</supplied> fire has consumed it”</note> and it is charred; and <supplied>then</supplied> can it be used again for anything? <verse-number id="Eze 15:6">6</verse-number>Therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh: <idiom-start/>Just like<idiom-end/><note>Literally “As that”</note> the wood of the vine among the trees of the forest<note>Or “wood”</note> which I gave to the fire for fuel, so I have given the inhabitants of Jerusalem. <verse-number id="Eze 15:7">7</verse-number>And I will set my face against them. From the fire they <supplied>may</supplied><idiom-start/>escape<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “go out”</note> but the fire will <supplied>yet</supplied> consume them, and they will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh <idiom-start/>when I set my face against them<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “in to set me my face against them”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 15:8">8</verse-number>And I will make the land <supplied>a</supplied> desolation because <idiom-start/>they acted very unfaithfully<idiom-end/>!”<note>Literally “they displayed infidelity”</note> <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh. </p>
		</chapter>