<chapter id="Eze 17">
			<pericope>Parable of Two Eagles and a Vine</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 17:1">1</verse-number>And the word of Yahweh <idiom-start/>came<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was”</note> to me, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 17:2">2</verse-number>“Son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> tell a riddle and quote a proverb to the house of Israel, <verse-number id="Eze 17:3">3</verse-number>and you must say, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “<idiom-start/>The great eagle with great wings and long feathers<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the eagle the great great of <supplied>the</supplied> wings long of <supplied>the</supplied> feather”</note> <supplied>and</supplied> <idiom-start/>full of variegated plumage<idiom-end/><note>Literally “full of <supplied>the</supplied> plumage which <supplied>is</supplied> for him <supplied>the</supplied> variegated”</note> came to Lebanon and he took the treetop of the cedar. <verse-number id="Eze 17:4">4</verse-number>He plucked the top of its new plant shoot, and he brought it to the land of Canaan <supplied>and</supplied> put it in a city of merchants, <verse-number id="Eze 17:5">5</verse-number>and he took from the seed of the land and placed it in <idiom-start/>fertile soil<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a field of seed”</note> on<note>Or “by”</note> many waters; <supplied>like</supplied> a willow he planted it. <verse-number id="Eze 17:6">6</verse-number>And it sprouted, and <idiom-start/>it became a vine spreading out<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “he was to vine spreading out”</note> low of height, turning its branches to him, and its roots were under it, and <idiom-start/>it became a vine<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “and it was to a vine”</note> and it made<note>Or “sprouted”</note> branches, and it sent out foliage. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 17:7">7</verse-number>“ ‘ “And there was another great eagle, great of wings and <supplied>with</supplied> abundant plumage, and look! This vine stretched out its roots toward him and extended its branches to him to water it from the garden bed <idiom-start/>where it was planted<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “from the garden bed of its planting”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 17:8">8</verse-number>It was planted in<note>Or “to”</note> <supplied>a</supplied> good field by<note>Or “to”</note> many waters<note>Hebrew “water”</note> to produce branches<note>Hebrew “branch”</note> and to bear fruit to become<note>Hebrew “be”</note> <idiom-start/>a beautiful vine<idiom-end/>.” ’<note>Literally “to a vine of splendor”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 17:9">9</verse-number>Say, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Will it prosper? Will he not tear out its roots, and will he not make its fruit scaly, and it will wither, and all of the freshness of its vegetation will dry up? And to lift it from its roots <idiom-start/>will not require great strength or many people<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “not with strong arm and with many people”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 17:10">10</verse-number>And look! <supplied>Though</supplied> it is planted, will it prosper? <idiom-start/>When the east wind strikes it<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “at striking her/it the wind of the east”</note> will it not dry up completely? On the garden bed of its vegetation it will dry up!” ’ ” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 17:11">11</verse-number>And the word of Yahweh <idiom-start/>came<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was”</note> to me, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>, <verse-number id="Eze 17:12">12</verse-number>“Say now to the rebellious house of Israel, ‘Do you not know what these <supplied>are</supplied>?’<note>Or “mean”</note> Say, ‘Look! The king of Babylon will come <supplied>to</supplied> Jerusalem, and he will take its king and its officials, and he will bring<note>Or “take”</note> them to himself,<note>Hebrew “him”</note> <supplied>to</supplied> Babylon. <verse-number id="Eze 17:13">13</verse-number>And he took from the seed of the kingship, and he made with him a covenant, and <idiom-start/>he brought him under oath<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “and he brought him in<supplied>to</supplied> oath”</note> and he took the rulers of the land, <verse-number id="Eze 17:14">14</verse-number>so that <supplied>they would</supplied> be a humble kingdom and not lift itself up to keep his covenant <idiom-start/>in order for it to stand<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to standing her”; or “to let her stand”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 17:15">15</verse-number>But he rebelled against him by sending his messengers <supplied>to</supplied> Egypt to give to him horses and a large army. Will he succeed? Will he escape doing these <supplied>things</supplied>, and can he break <supplied>the</supplied> covenant and escape? <verse-number id="Eze 17:16">16</verse-number><idiom-start/>As I live<idiom-end/>,’<note>Literally “live I”</note> <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh, ‘<idiom-start/>surely<idiom-end/><note>Literally “if not”</note> in the place of the king <idiom-start/>who made<idiom-end/><note>Literally “who <supplied>he was</supplied> making”</note> him king, who despised his oath and who broke his covenant with him—in the midst of Babylon he will die. <verse-number id="Eze 17:17">17</verse-number>And not with a great army and with a great crowd will Pharaoh work<note>Or “help/aid”</note> with him in the war, at the pouring out of a siege ramp and the building of siege works to destroy many lives. <verse-number id="Eze 17:18">18</verse-number>And he despised <supplied>the</supplied> oath to break covenant. And, look, he gave his hand <supplied>in pledge</supplied>, and <supplied>yet</supplied> he did all of these <supplied>things</supplied>. He will not escape.’ <verse-number id="Eze 17:19">19</verse-number>Therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh: ‘<idiom-start/>As I live<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “live I”</note> <idiom-start/>surely<idiom-end/><note>Literally “if not”</note> my oath that he despised and my covenant that he broke I will return upon his head. <verse-number id="Eze 17:20">20</verse-number>And I will spread my net over him, and he will be caught in my hunting net, and I will bring him <supplied>to</supplied> Babylon, and I will enter into judgment with him there <supplied>about</supplied> his infidelity that he displayed against me. <verse-number id="Eze 17:21">21</verse-number>And all of his choice troops, among all of his troops, they will fall by the sword, and <supplied>those who</supplied> <supplied>are</supplied> remaining,<note>Or “left over”</note> they will be scattered to all <supplied>the directions of the</supplied> wind, and you will know that I, Yahweh, I have spoken.’ <verse-number id="Eze 17:22">22</verse-number>Thus says the Lord Yahweh: ‘And I will take, <supplied>even</supplied> I, from the treetop of the high cedar, and I will plant <supplied>it</supplied>, from the head of its new plant shoot I will pluck a tender one, and I will plant <supplied>it</supplied>, <supplied>even</supplied> I, on a high and lofty mountain. <verse-number id="Eze 17:23">23</verse-number>On the height of the mountain of Israel I will plant <supplied>it</supplied>, and it will carry<note>Or “bear”</note> branches,<note>Hebrew “branch”</note> and it will bear fruit, and <idiom-start/>it will become a noble cedar<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “he will be to a cedar noble”</note> and all of the birds of all wings<note>Or “kinds”</note> will dwell under it in the shade of its branches. <verse-number id="Eze 17:24">24</verse-number>And all of the trees of the field will know that I, Yahweh, I will bring low a high tree, <supplied>and</supplied> I will exalt a low, fresh tree, and I will make a dry tree flourish. I, Yahweh, I have spoken, and I will do <supplied>it</supplied>.’ ” </p>
		</chapter>