<chapter id="Eze 18">
			<pericope>God’s Just Treatment of Individuals, Both Righteous and Wicked</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 18:1">1</verse-number>And the word of Yahweh <idiom-start/>came<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was”</note> to me, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 18:2">2</verse-number>“<idiom-start/>What do you mean by<idiom-end/><note>Literally “What <supplied>is</supplied> to you”</note> quoting this proverb about the land of Israel, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> ‘The fathers, they ate unripe fruit, and the teeth of the child became blunt.’<note>Or “dull,” set on edge”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 18:3">3</verse-number><idiom-start/>As I live<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “life I”</note> <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh, it will surely not any longer be <idiom-start/>appropriate for you<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to you”</note> to quote this proverb in Israel! <verse-number id="Eze 18:4">4</verse-number>Look! <idiom-start/>All lives are mine<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “all of the lives <supplied>are</supplied> for me they”</note> <idiom-start/>The lives of father and son alike are mine<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “Like the life of the father and like the life of the son <supplied>is</supplied> to me look”</note> The person<note>Or “life,” or “soul”</note> sinning will die. <verse-number id="Eze 18:5">5</verse-number>And if a man is righteous and does justice and righteousness, <verse-number id="Eze 18:6">6</verse-number>and on the mountains he <supplied>does</supplied> not eat and he <supplied>does</supplied> not lift up his eyes to the idols of the house of Israel, and the wife of his neighbor he <supplied>does</supplied> not defile and he <supplied>does</supplied> not approach a woman of<note>Or “in”</note> menstruation, <verse-number id="Eze 18:7">7</verse-number>and he oppresses <idiom-start/>no one<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a person not”</note> <supplied>and</supplied> he returns <supplied>a</supplied> pledge for his loan <idiom-start/>and he commits no robbery<idiom-end/><note>Literally “robbed things not he seized”</note> <supplied>and</supplied> he gives<note>Or “shares”</note> his bread to <supplied>the</supplied> hungry and he covers a naked person <supplied>with</supplied> a garment, <verse-number id="Eze 18:8">8</verse-number><supplied>and</supplied> <idiom-start/>he does not charge interest<idiom-end/><note>Literally “with the interest not he gives”</note> and he takes no usury, <supplied>and</supplied> he holds back<note>Or “brings back”</note> his hand from injustice <supplied>and</supplied> he executes <supplied>a</supplied> judgment of fairness between <idiom-start/>persons<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “man and man”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 18:9">9</verse-number><supplied>and</supplied> in my statutes he goes about and my regulations he keeps,<note>Or “watches”</note> <idiom-start/>performing faithfully<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to do with <supplied>with</supplied> faithfulness”</note> —<supplied>then</supplied> he is righteous, <supplied>and</supplied> certainly he will live,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 18:10">10</verse-number>“And <supplied>now</supplied> he has a son, a violent one, <idiom-start/>who sheds blood<idiom-end/><note>Literally “shedding of blood”</note> <idiom-start/>and does any of these things<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and he does like from one from these”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 18:11">11</verse-number>(though<note>Hebrew “And”</note> he<note>That is, the father</note> did not do all of these <supplied>things</supplied>), for <supplied>the son</supplied> also<note>Or “even”</note> eats on the mountains and he defiles the wife of his neighbor. <verse-number id="Eze 18:12">12</verse-number>He oppresses <supplied>the</supplied> needy and <supplied>the</supplied> poor, <supplied>and</supplied> <idiom-start/>he commits robbery<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “robbed things he seized”</note> <supplied>and</supplied> he <supplied>does</supplied> not return <supplied>a</supplied> pledge for a loan, <supplied>and</supplied> he lifts his eyes to the idols <supplied>so</supplied> he does a detestable thing. <verse-number id="Eze 18:13">13</verse-number><idiom-start/>He charges interest<idiom-end/><note>Literally “with the interest he gives”</note> and takes usury. Then, shall he live? He shall not live, <supplied>for</supplied> he did all of these detestable things. Surely he will die! His blood will be on him. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 18:14">14</verse-number>“And look! He has a son, and he sees all of the sin of his father that he did, and he sees <supplied>it</supplied>, but he does not <supplied>do</supplied> it. <verse-number id="Eze 18:15">15</verse-number>On the mountains he does not eat, and he does not lift <supplied>up</supplied> his eyes to the idols of the house of Israel, <supplied>and</supplied> the wife of his neighbor he does not defile. <verse-number id="Eze 18:16">16</verse-number>And he oppresses no one; he requires no pledge for a loan, and <idiom-start/>he does not commit robbery<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “robbed things not does he seize”</note> he gives his bread to <supplied>the</supplied> hungry, and he covers the naked person <supplied>with</supplied> a garment. <verse-number id="Eze 18:17">17</verse-number>He brings back<note>Or “holds back”</note> his hand from iniquity;<note>Cf. verse <cite title="BibleLEB2:Eze 18:8">8</cite></note> he does not take interest and usury; he does my regulations; he goes<note>Or “walks”</note> in my statutes. He will not die because of the guilt of his father; he will surely live! <verse-number id="Eze 18:18">18</verse-number>Because his father <idiom-start/>oppressed severely<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “he oppressed oppression”</note> <idiom-start/>he stole from his brother<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “he seized robbed things of a brother”</note> <supplied>that</supplied> which <supplied>is</supplied> not good he did in the midst of his people, and look! He will die through<note>Or “in”</note> his guilt. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 18:19">19</verse-number>“Yet<note>Or “And”</note> you say, ‘Why <supplied>does</supplied> the son not bear the guilt of the father?’ And <supplied>since</supplied> the son does justice and righteousness and he keeps all of my statutes and does them, he shall surely live! <verse-number id="Eze 18:20">20</verse-number>The person,<note>Or “soul,” or “life”</note> the <supplied>one</supplied> sinning, will die. A son shall not bear the guilt of the father, and a father shall not bear the guilt of the son. The righteousness of the righteous shall be on him; the wickedness of the wicked<note>According to the reading tradition (<i>Qere</i>)</note> shall be on him. <verse-number id="Eze 18:21">21</verse-number>But if the wicked returns from all of his sins<note>According to the reading tradition (<i>Qere</i>)</note> that he has done and he keeps all of my statutes and he does justice and righteousness, he shall surely live; he shall not die! <verse-number id="Eze 18:22">22</verse-number>All of his transgressions that he committed will not be remembered against<note>Or “for”</note> him. Through<note>Or “By means of”</note> his righteousness that he has done he shall live. <verse-number id="Eze 18:23">23</verse-number>Have I delight by any means<note>Or “in any way”</note> <supplied>in the</supplied> death of <supplied>the</supplied> wicked, <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh, <supplied>and</supplied> not at his turning from his way, <idiom-start/>so that<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and”</note> he lives? <verse-number id="Eze 18:24">24</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>when the righteous turns<idiom-end/><note>Literally “at turning of <supplied>the</supplied> righteous”</note> from his righteousness, so that<note>Literally “and”</note> he does injustice, and does all of the detestable things that the wicked do, then<note>Or “and”</note> will he live <supplied>because of</supplied> all of his righteousness<note>According to the reading tradition (<i>Qere</i>)</note> that he did? <supplied>Those things</supplied> will not be remembered because of his infidelity that he displayed, and because of his <idiom-start/>sin that he committed<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sin that he sinned”</note> Through<note>Or “in/by”</note> them he shall die. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 18:25">25</verse-number>“Yet<note>Or “And”</note> you say, ‘The way of the Lord is not fair!’ Listen, now, house of Israel, is my way not fair? <supplied>Is it</supplied> not your ways <supplied>that</supplied> are not fair? <verse-number id="Eze 18:26">26</verse-number>When the righteous turns from his righteousness, and he does injustice, then<note>Or “and”</note> he will die because of them; because of his injustice that he did he will die! <verse-number id="Eze 18:27">27</verse-number>And when the wicked turns from his wickedness that he did and he does justice and righteousness, <idiom-start/>he will preserve his life<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “his soul/life he will keep alive”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 18:28">28</verse-number>And if he sees and he returns from all of his transgressions that he did, surely he will live; he will not die! <verse-number id="Eze 18:29">29</verse-number>And <supplied>yet</supplied> they, the house of Israel, say, ‘The way of the Lord is not fair!’ <supplied>Are</supplied> not my ways fair, house of Israel? <idiom-start/>Are not your ways unfair?<idiom-end/><note>Literally “not ways your not are right”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 18:30">30</verse-number>“Therefore I will judge you, house of Israel, each one<note>Hebrew “man”</note> according to his ways,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh. “Repent<note>Or “Turn/Return”</note> and turn around from all of your transgression, and it will not be as a stumbling block of iniquity to you. <verse-number id="Eze 18:31">31</verse-number>Throw <idiom-start/>away from yourselves<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from on you”</note> all of your transgressions that you committed,<note>Hebrew “committed with them”</note> and make <idiom-start/>for yourselves<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to you”</note> a new heart and new spirit, and <supplied>so</supplied> why will you die, house of Israel? <verse-number id="Eze 18:32">32</verse-number>For I have no pleasure in the death of the dying,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh. “And <supplied>so</supplied> repent<note>Or “turn/return”</note> and live!” </p>
		</chapter>