<chapter id="Eze 20">
			<pericope>God’s Dealings with Israel for His Name’s Sake</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 20:1">1</verse-number>And then in the seventh year, in the fifth <supplied>month</supplied>, on the tenth <supplied>day</supplied> of the month, men from the elders of Israel came to consult Yahweh, and they sat <idiom-start/>before me<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to the face of”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 20:2">2</verse-number>And the word of Yahweh <idiom-start/>came<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was”</note> to me, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 20:3">3</verse-number>“Son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> speak with the elders of Israel, and you must say to them, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “<supplied>Are</supplied> you coming to consult me? <idiom-start/>As I live<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “live I”</note> I will surely not allow myself<note>Or “me”</note> to be consulted by you!” ’ <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh. <verse-number id="Eze 20:4">4</verse-number>Will you judge them? Will you judge <supplied>them</supplied>, son of man?<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> Make known to them the detestable things of their ancestors.<note>Or “fathers”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 20:5">5</verse-number>And you must say to them, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “On the day of my choosing Israel <idiom-start/>I swore<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and I raised my hand”</note> to the offspring of the house of Jacob, and I made myself known to them in the land of Egypt, and <idiom-start/>I swore<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and I raised my hand”</note> to them, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> ‘I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh your God.’ <verse-number id="Eze 20:6">6</verse-number>On that day <idiom-start/>I swore<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I raised my hand”</note> to them to bring them out from the land of Egypt to <supplied>the</supplied> land that I had searched out for them, flowing with milk and honey—it <supplied>is the most</supplied> beautiful of all of the lands. <verse-number id="Eze 20:7">7</verse-number>Then I said to them, ‘<supplied>Let</supplied> each <supplied>one</supplied> throw away the detestable things of his eyes, and you must not make yourselves unclean with the idols of Egypt! I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh your God.’ <verse-number id="Eze 20:8">8</verse-number>But they rebelled against me, and they were not willing to listen to me; each <supplied>one</supplied> <idiom-start/>did not throw away<idiom-end/><note>Literally “not they threw away”</note> the detestable things of their eyes; and <idiom-start/>they did not abandon<idiom-end/><note>Literally “not they abandoned”</note> the idols of Egypt, and I decided to pour out my rage on them, to fully vent my anger against them in the midst of the land of Egypt. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 20:9">9</verse-number>“But<note>Or “And”</note> I acted for the sake of my name <idiom-start/>to keep it from being profaned<idiom-end/><note>Literally “not to be profaned before the eyes of”</note> before the eyes of the nations <idiom-start/>among whom they lived<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “which they <supplied>were</supplied> in their midst”</note> where I made known to them before their eyes, to bring them out from the land of Egypt. <verse-number id="Eze 20:10">10</verse-number>And I brought them out from the land of Egypt, and I brought them to the desert, <verse-number id="Eze 20:11">11</verse-number>and I gave my statutes to them, and my regulations I made known to them, which, if a person does them, then he will live by them. <verse-number id="Eze 20:12">12</verse-number>And also my Sabbaths I gave to them to be a sign between me and between them <idiom-start/>so they would know<idiom-end/><note>Literally “know”</note> that I, Yahweh, <supplied>am</supplied> <supplied>the one</supplied> sanctifying them. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 20:13">13</verse-number>“But<note>Or “And”</note> in the desert the house of Israel rebelled against me; <idiom-start/>they did not walk in my statutes<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “in my statutes not they went”</note> and they rejected my regulations, which, if a person does them, he will live by them, and they greatly profaned my Sabbaths, and I decided to pour out my rage on them in the desert to destroy them, <verse-number id="Eze 20:14">14</verse-number>and I acted for the sake of my name, <supplied>that it</supplied> not be profaned before the eyes of the nations <idiom-start/>before whom I brought them out<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “which I brought out them before their eyes”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 20:15">15</verse-number>And also <idiom-start/>I myself swore<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I, I raised my hand”</note> to them in the desert not to bring them into the land that I had given <supplied>to them</supplied>, flowing with milk and honey—it <supplied>is the most</supplied> beautiful of all of the lands— <verse-number id="Eze 20:16">16</verse-number>because they despised my judgments, and <idiom-start/>they did not walk in my statutes<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “and my statutes not they went in them”</note> and my Sabbaths they profaned, for their heart was going after their idols. <verse-number id="Eze 20:17">17</verse-number>But my eye took pity on them by not destroying them, and <idiom-start/>I did not completely destroy them<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and not I make them complete destruction”</note> in the desert. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 20:18">18</verse-number>“And I said to their children in the desert, ‘You must not go in the statutes of your parents;<note>Or “fathers”</note> you must not keep their regulations, and you must not make yourself unclean with their idols. <verse-number id="Eze 20:19">19</verse-number>I, Yahweh, <supplied>am</supplied> your God, <supplied>so</supplied> go in my statutes and keep my regulations and do them. <verse-number id="Eze 20:20">20</verse-number>And treat my Sabbaths as holy, and they will be a sign between me and between you <idiom-start/>that you may know<idiom-end/><note>Literally “know”</note> that I, Yahweh, <supplied>am</supplied> your God.’ <verse-number id="Eze 20:21">21</verse-number>But the children rebelled against me; <idiom-start/>they did not walk in my statutes<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “in statutes my not they went”</note> and <idiom-start/>they did not observe my regulations<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “my regulations not they kept to do them”</note> which <supplied>if</supplied> a person does them, then he will live by them. My Sabbaths they desecrated, and I decided to pour out my rage on them, to finish my anger against them in the desert. <verse-number id="Eze 20:22">22</verse-number>But I withheld my hand, and I acted for the sake of my name not to be profaned before the eyes of the nations <supplied>before</supplied> whom I <supplied>had</supplied> brought them out before their eyes. <verse-number id="Eze 20:23">23</verse-number>What is more, <idiom-start/>I swore<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I will raise my hand”</note> to them in the desert to scatter them among the nations and to disperse them in the lands, <verse-number id="Eze 20:24">24</verse-number>because they did not <supplied>do</supplied> my regulations, and my statutes they despised, and my Sabbaths they profaned, and their eyes were after the idols of their ancestors.<note>Or “fathers”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 20:25">25</verse-number>And in turn I gave to them rules <supplied>that were</supplied> not good and regulations <idiom-start/>by which they will not live<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “regulations not they will live by them”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 20:26">26</verse-number>And I defiled them through their gifts in sacrificing all of <supplied>the</supplied> first offspring of <supplied>the</supplied> womb, in order that<note>Or “so that”</note> I will cause them to be stunned, so that they will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 20:27">27</verse-number>“Therefore speak to the house of Israel, son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> and you must say to them, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Again <supplied>in</supplied> this your ancestors blasphemed me <idiom-start/>at<note>Or “by”</note> their display of infidelity toward me<idiom-end/>.” ’<note>Literally “at/in acting unfaithfully they against me in/by unfaithfulness”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 20:28">28</verse-number>And I brought them to the land that <idiom-start/>I swore<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I raised my hand”</note> to give<note>Hebrew “give it”</note> to them, and they saw every high hill and every leafy tree, and they offered their sacrifices, and they presented there the provocation of their offering, and they gave there their fragrant incense offering, and they poured out their libations there. <verse-number id="Eze 20:29">29</verse-number>And I said to them, ‘What <supplied>is</supplied> the high place<note>Hebrew Bamah, which became its name</note> to which you are going?’ And <idiom-start/>it is called<idiom-end/><note>Literally “it is called name its”</note> Bamah until this day. <verse-number id="Eze 20:30">30</verse-number>Therefore thus say to the house of Israel, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “In the way of your ancestors<note>Or “fathers”</note> <supplied>will</supplied> you defile yourself, and after their vile idols <supplied>will</supplied> you prostitute <supplied>yourselves</supplied>? <verse-number id="Eze 20:31">31</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>when you lift up your gifts, sacrificing your children<idiom-end/><note>Literally “at to lift up your gifts at causing to pass over your children”</note> through the fire, you are defiling yourself through all of your idols until <idiom-start/>today<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the day”</note> and will I let myself<note>Hebrew “me”</note> be consulted by you, house of Israel?” ’ <idiom-start/>As I live<idiom-end/>,”<note>Literally “Live I”</note> <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh, “I will not let myself<note>Hebrew “me”</note> be consulted by you! <verse-number id="Eze 20:32">32</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>what you are planning<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “what is going up on your spirit”</note> surely it will not be—that you are saying, ‘Let us be like the nations, like the clans<note>Or “tribes”</note> of the lands, <idiom-start/>serving wood and stone<idiom-end/>!’<note>Literally “to serve wood and stone”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 20:33">33</verse-number>“<idiom-start/>As I live<idiom-end/>,”<note>Literally “live I”</note> <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh, “<idiom-start/>surely<idiom-end/><note>Literally “if not”</note> with <supplied>a</supplied> strong hand and with <supplied>an</supplied> outstretched arm and with <idiom-start/>rage pouring forth<idiom-end/><note>Literally “rage poured out”</note> I will reign as king over you! <verse-number id="Eze 20:34">34</verse-number>And I will bring you from the peoples, and I will gather you from the countries <supplied>to</supplied> which you were scattered with <supplied>a</supplied> strong hand and with an outstretched arm and with rage poured out. <verse-number id="Eze 20:35">35</verse-number>Then I will bring you to the desert of the peoples, and I will execute justice on you there face to face. <verse-number id="Eze 20:36">36</verse-number><idiom-start/>Just as<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Like what”</note> I executed justice on your ancestors<note>Or “fathers”</note> in the desert of the land of Egypt, likewise I will execute justice on you!” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh. <verse-number id="Eze 20:37">37</verse-number>“And I will make you pass under the rod, and I will bring you into the bond of the covenant. <verse-number id="Eze 20:38">38</verse-number>And I will purge the rebels from <supplied>among</supplied> you and the <supplied>ones</supplied> transgressing against me; I will bring them out from the land <idiom-start/>where they are living as aliens<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from the land of living as an alien there”</note> but into the land of Israel they will not come, and <supplied>then</supplied> you will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 20:39">39</verse-number>And you, house of Israel, thus says the Lord Yahweh: “<supplied>Let</supplied> each one go serve his idols <supplied>now</supplied> and after, if you <supplied>are</supplied> not listening to me, but <idiom-start/>my holy name<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the name of my holiness”</note> you will not profane <supplied>any</supplied> longer with your gifts and with your idols. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 20:40">40</verse-number>“For on <idiom-start/>my holy mountain<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the mountain of my holiness”</note> on the mountain of the height of Israel,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh, “there all of the house of Israel will serve me, all of them,<note>Hebrew “it/him”</note> in the land. I will take pleasure in them, and there I will accept your contributions and the best of your portions with all of your holy objects. <verse-number id="Eze 20:41">41</verse-number>I will accept you as <idiom-start/>a fragrant incense offering<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a fragrance of an incense offering”</note> when I bring you out from the peoples and I gather you from the lands <supplied>to</supplied> which you were scattered, and I will show myself holy among you before the eyes of the nations. <verse-number id="Eze 20:42">42</verse-number>And you will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh <idiom-start/>when I bring you<idiom-end/> to the land of Israel, to the land that <idiom-start/>I swore<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I raised my hand”</note> to give to your ancestors. <verse-number id="Eze 20:43">43</verse-number>And you will remember there your ways, and all of your deeds <idiom-start/>by which you were made unclean<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “which you were made unclean by them”</note> and you will feel a loathing <idiom-start/>for yourself<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for your face”</note> for all of your evils that you have done. <verse-number id="Eze 20:44">44</verse-number>And you will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh <idiom-start/>when I deal with you<idiom-end/><note>Literally “at/in doing my with you”</note> for the sake of my name and <idiom-start/>not according to your evil ways<idiom-end/><note>Literally “not like your ways the evil”</note> or <idiom-start/>according to<idiom-end/><note>Literally “like”</note> your corrupted deeds, house of Israel,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 20:45">45</verse-number><note><cite title="BibleLEB2: Eze 20:45–21:32">Ezekiel 20:45–21:32 </cite>in the English Bible is 21:1–37 in the Hebrew Bible</note> And the word of Yahweh <idiom-start/>came<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was”</note> to me, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 20:46">46</verse-number>“Son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> set your face <supplied>toward</supplied> the way of <supplied>the</supplied> south,<note>Or “Teman”</note> and preach to <supplied>the</supplied> south, and prophesy against the forest of the territory of the Negev. <verse-number id="Eze 20:47">47</verse-number>And you must say to the forest of the Negev, ‘Hear the word of Yahweh, thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Look! I am kindling against you a fire, and it will devour in you every fresh tree and every dry tree; <supplied>the</supplied> blaze of <supplied>the</supplied> flame will not be quenched, and all the surfaces from <supplied>the</supplied> south <supplied>to</supplied> <supplied>the</supplied> north will be scorched by it. <verse-number id="Eze 20:48">48</verse-number>And all creatures will see that I, Yahweh, I kindled it—it will not be quenched!” ’ ” <verse-number id="Eze 20:49">49</verse-number>Then I said, “Ah, Lord Yahweh, they are saying about me, ‘<supplied>Is</supplied> he not posing a parable?’ ” </p>
		</chapter>