<chapter id="Eze 21">
			<pericope>A Vision of the Avenging Sword of Yahweh</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 21:1">1</verse-number>And the word of Yahweh <idiom-start/>came<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was”</note> to me, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 21:2">2</verse-number>“Son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> set your face toward Jerusalem, and preach to <supplied>the</supplied> sanctuaries, and prophesy to the land of Israel. <verse-number id="Eze 21:3">3</verse-number>And you must say to the land of Israel, ‘Thus says Yahweh: “Look! I <supplied>am</supplied> against you, and I will draw out my sword from its sheath, and I will cut <supplied>off</supplied> from you <supplied>the</supplied> righteous and <supplied>the</supplied> wicked. <verse-number id="Eze 21:4">4</verse-number>Because<note>Hebrew “Because that”</note> I will cut <supplied>off</supplied> from you <supplied>both</supplied> righteous and wicked, therefore my sword will go out from its sheath to<note>Or “against”</note> all creatures<note>Hebrew “creature”</note> from south <supplied>to</supplied> north. <verse-number id="Eze 21:5">5</verse-number>And they will know, all creatures, that I, Yahweh, I will bring out my sword from its sheath; it will not return again!” ’ <verse-number id="Eze 21:6">6</verse-number>And you, son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> groan <idiom-start/>with shaking hips<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “with destruction of loins”</note> and you must groan with bitterness before their eyes. <verse-number id="Eze 21:7">7</verse-number><idiom-start/>And then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and it will be”</note> when they say to you, ‘On account of what <supplied>are</supplied> you groaning?’ then you must say, ‘On account of <supplied>the</supplied> report, for it <supplied>is</supplied> coming, and every heart will be weak and all hands will hang limp and every spirit will be disheartened, and all knees will go <supplied>like</supplied> water.’ Look! It <supplied>is</supplied> coming, and it will happen!” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 21:8">8</verse-number>And the word of Yahweh <idiom-start/>came<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was”</note> to me, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 21:9">9</verse-number>“Son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> prophesy, and you must say, ‘Thus says the Lord,’ say, ‘A sword, a sword <supplied>is</supplied> sharpened and <supplied>is</supplied> also polished. <verse-number id="Eze 21:10">10</verse-number>It is sharpened to slaughter a slaughter, <idiom-start/>polished to flash like lightning<idiom-end/>!<note>Literally “so that there be for her lightning”</note> Or will we rejoice?<note>Or “be pleased”</note> A rod, my son, <supplied>is</supplied> despising every tree.<note>Or “stick” of correction; Hebrew is uncertain in meaning here</note> <verse-number id="Eze 21:11">11</verse-number>And he gives it to be polished, <idiom-start/>to be seized by the hand<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to take hold of in the palm of the hand”</note> It is sharpened—a sword—and it <supplied>is</supplied> polished to give it into <supplied>the</supplied> hand of <supplied>the</supplied> killer. <verse-number id="Eze 21:12">12</verse-number>Cry and wail, son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> for it is against my people; it is against all of the princes of Israel. They are thrown to <supplied>the</supplied> sword with my people; therefore <idiom-start/>strike your thigh<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “strike on <supplied>the</supplied> thigh”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 21:13">13</verse-number>For <idiom-start/>examine<idiom-end/>!<note>Literally “it was tested”</note> And what if also <supplied>the</supplied> rod will not be despising?’ <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh. <verse-number id="Eze 21:14">14</verse-number>And you, son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> prophesy <idiom-start/>and clap your hands<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “strike hand to hand”</note> And the sword will <idiom-start/>strike twice<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “be doubled”</note> let it happen a third time. It <supplied>is</supplied> a sword of the dead, <supplied>the</supplied> sword of the great dead that <supplied>is</supplied> surrounding them, <verse-number id="Eze 21:15">15</verse-number>so that a heart melts, and the fallen <idiom-start/>multiply<idiom-end/><note>Literally “be made many”</note> at all of their gates. I gave a sword for slaughter, <supplied>and</supplied> alas! It is made for flashing, it is grasped<note>Or “polished”</note> for slaughtering. <verse-number id="Eze 21:16">16</verse-number>Gather together, strike to the right; cause <supplied>to</supplied> go to the left, where your <idiom-start/>edge<idiom-end/><note>Literally “face”</note> <supplied>is</supplied> directed. <verse-number id="Eze 21:17">17</verse-number>And also <idiom-start/>I myself<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I, I”</note> will <idiom-start/>clap my hands<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “strike my hand to my hand”</note> and I will satisfy my rage! I, Yahweh, I have spoken.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 21:18">18</verse-number>And the word of Yahweh <idiom-start/>came<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was”</note> to me, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 21:19">19</verse-number>“And you, son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> mark <supplied>out</supplied> for yourself<note>Hebrew “you”</note> two roads for the coming of the sword of the king of Babylon; they must <idiom-start/>both<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the two of them”</note> go out from the same land. And hew <supplied>out</supplied> a <idiom-start/>signpost<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “hand”</note> hew <supplied>it</supplied> at <supplied>the</supplied> head of <supplied>the</supplied> road of <supplied>the</supplied> city. <verse-number id="Eze 21:20">20</verse-number>You must mark a road for <supplied>the</supplied> coming of <supplied>the</supplied> sword <supplied>to</supplied> Rabbah of the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons of Ammon”</note> and <supplied>to</supplied> Judah, in Jerusalem <supplied>the</supplied> fortified. <verse-number id="Eze 21:21">21</verse-number>For the king of Babylon stands at the fork of the road at the head of the two roads to practice divination. <idiom-start/>He shakes the arrows<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “he casts the lot with the arrows” (cf. NASB, NRSV)</note> he inquires with the teraphim, he <idiom-start/>examines<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sees with”</note> the liver. <verse-number id="Eze 21:22">22</verse-number>In his right hand is the divination for Jerusalem, to put <supplied>up</supplied> battering rams, to open <supplied>a</supplied> mouth for slaughter,<note>Or “open the mouth of Sheol”; or “give the command to slaughter” (cf. NRSV, NASB)</note> <idiom-start/>to raise the battle cry<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to raise a voice in shouting”</note> to put <supplied>up</supplied> battering rams against gates, to build a siege ramp, to build siege works.<note>Hebrew “siege work”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 21:23">23</verse-number>And it will be to them like practicing divination falsely<note>Or “in vain”</note> in their eyes; <idiom-start/>they have sworn oaths for themselves<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “swearers of oaths <supplied>will be</supplied> for them”</note> But<note>Or “And”</note> he <supplied>will</supplied> bring <supplied>their</supplied> guilt to remembrance <supplied>so as</supplied> to seize them. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 21:24">24</verse-number>“Therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh: ‘Because you have brought to remembrance your guilt by the uncovering of your transgressions, so that your sins in all of your deeds appear—because of your being remembered, you will be captured in the hand.’ <verse-number id="Eze 21:25">25</verse-number>And <supplied>as for</supplied> you, profane one, wicked prince of Israel, whose day has come with <supplied>the</supplied> time of <supplied>the</supplied> punishment of <supplied>the</supplied> end, <verse-number id="Eze 21:26">26</verse-number>thus says the Lord Yahweh: ‘Remove the turban and lift off the crown; things <supplied>are</supplied> no longer the same. Exalt the low and bring low the high. <verse-number id="Eze 21:27">27</verse-number>A ruin, a ruin, a ruin I will make it! Also<note>Or “indeed”</note> this has not <supplied>ever</supplied> happened;<note>Or “will not happen until” (cf. NASB and NRSV)</note> <supplied>it will remain</supplied> until the coming of <supplied>the one</supplied> <supplied>to</supplied> whom the judgment belongs and I have given it <supplied>to him</supplied>.’ <verse-number id="Eze 21:28">28</verse-number>And you, son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> prophesy, and you must say, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh to the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons of Ammon”</note> and concerning their disgrace,’ and you must say, ‘A sword, a sword <supplied>is</supplied> drawn for slaughtering; <supplied>it is</supplied> polished for holding, <idiom-start/>for flashing like lightning<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “for the sake of lightening”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 21:29">29</verse-number>when seeing a false vision for you in vain, when practicing divination for you falsely, to give<note>Or “place”</note> you on <supplied>the</supplied> neck of <supplied>the</supplied> profane ones of <supplied>the</supplied> wicked, <idiom-start/>whose day has come<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “who has come their day”</note> <idiom-start/>the time of final punishment<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “in <supplied>the</supplied> time of <supplied>the</supplied> punishment of <supplied>the</supplied> end”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 21:30">30</verse-number>Return it to its sheath in <supplied>the</supplied> place where you were created. In the land of your origin I will judge you! <verse-number id="Eze 21:31">31</verse-number>And I will pour out my anger on you; I will blow on you with the fire of my wrath, and I will give you into <supplied>the</supplied> hand of brutal men, skilled craftsmen of destruction. <verse-number id="Eze 21:32">32</verse-number>You will be as fuel for the fire; your blood will be in the midst of the earth. You will not be remembered, for I, Yahweh, I have spoken.’ ” </p>
		</chapter>