<chapter id="Eze 22">
			<pericope>Highlighting the Sins and the Judgments of Israel</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 22:1">1</verse-number>And the word of Yahweh <idiom-start/>came<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was”</note> to me, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 22:2">2</verse-number>“And you, son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> will you judge? Will you judge the <idiom-start/>bloody city<idiom-end/>?<note>Literally “city of blood”</note> Then you must make known <supplied>to</supplied> her all of her detestable things! <verse-number id="Eze 22:3">3</verse-number>And you must say, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “A city pouring out blood in the midst of her; <idiom-start/>its time has come<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to come time her its”</note> and it made idols for itself, becoming unclean. <verse-number id="Eze 22:4">4</verse-number>By your blood that you poured out you have become guilty, and by your idols that you made you have become unclean, and you have brought your days near, <idiom-start/>and your appointed years have come<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “and it came to years your”</note> Therefore I have made you a disgrace for the nations and a laughingstock to all of the countries. <verse-number id="Eze 22:5">5</verse-number>The <supplied>people</supplied> near and the <supplied>people</supplied> far from you will make fun of you, <idiom-start/>the unclean and the terrified<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the unclean of the name the great of the panic”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 22:6">6</verse-number>Look! The princes of Israel, each <supplied>one</supplied> according to his strength,<note>Or “influence”</note> they are in you <idiom-start/>for the shedding of blood<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to shedding of blood”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 22:7">7</verse-number>They have treated father and mother with contempt in you; <idiom-start/>they violated<idiom-end/><note>Literally “they did with extortion”</note> the alien with<note>Or “by”</note> extortion; in the midst of you they mistreated <supplied>the</supplied> orphan and widow. <verse-number id="Eze 22:8">8</verse-number>You despised my holy objects; my Sabbaths you profaned. <verse-number id="Eze 22:9">9</verse-number>Slanderous men are <idiom-start/>among you<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in you”</note> to shed blood, and they, <idiom-start/>among you<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “in you”</note> eat upon the mountains; they do wickedness in the midst of you. <verse-number id="Eze 22:10">10</verse-number>They uncover <supplied>the</supplied> nakedness of <supplied>a</supplied> father among<note>Hebrew “in”</note> you; they violate <supplied>a woman</supplied> unclean of menstruation among<note>Hebrew “in”</note> you. <verse-number id="Eze 22:11">11</verse-number>And a man does a detestable thing <supplied>with</supplied> the wife of his neighbor, and a man defiles his daughter-in-law in wickedness, and a man sexually violates among<note>Hebrew “in”</note> you his sister, the daughter of his father. <verse-number id="Eze 22:12">12</verse-number>They take a bribe among<note>Hebrew “in”</note> you in order to shed blood; and you take usury, and you make gain <supplied>from</supplied> your neighbors by extortion, and <supplied>so</supplied> you have forgotten me, <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh. <verse-number id="Eze 22:13">13</verse-number>And look! I strike my hand for your ill-gotten gain that you <supplied>have</supplied> made and at your blood that was in the midst of you. <verse-number id="Eze 22:14">14</verse-number>Can your heart endure,<note>Or “hold up”</note> or can your hands be strong at the days <supplied>in</supplied> which I <supplied>am</supplied> dealing with you? I, Yahweh, I have spoken, and I will act! <verse-number id="Eze 22:15">15</verse-number>I will scatter you among the nations, and I will disperse you through the countries, and I will purge your uncleanness from you. <verse-number id="Eze 22:16">16</verse-number>And I will be profaned by you before <supplied>the</supplied> eyes of <supplied>the</supplied> nations, and you will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh.” ’ ” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 22:17">17</verse-number>And the word of Yahweh <idiom-start/>came<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was”</note> to me, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 22:18">18</verse-number>“Son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> the house of Israel has become as silver dross to me; all of them <supplied>are as</supplied> bronze and tin and iron and lead in the midst of a furnace, <supplied>even</supplied> <supplied>as</supplied> silver dross, silver <supplied>dross</supplied> they became! <verse-number id="Eze 22:19">19</verse-number>Therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh: ‘Because all of you have become <supplied>as</supplied> silver dross, therefore look! I <supplied>am</supplied> gathering you to the midst of Jerusalem, <verse-number id="Eze 22:20">20</verse-number>like the gathering of silver and bronze and iron and lead and tin to the middle of a furnace to blow fire on it for melting. Thus I will gather in my anger and in my rage, and I will <idiom-start/>deposit<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I will put/place”</note> you, and I will melt you. <verse-number id="Eze 22:21">21</verse-number>And I will gather you, and I will blow on you with the fire of my wrath, and <supplied>so</supplied> I will melt <supplied>you</supplied> in the midst of her. <verse-number id="Eze 22:22">22</verse-number>Thus you will be melted like <supplied>the</supplied> melting of silver in the midst of a furnace, and you will know that I, Yahweh, I have poured out my rage on you.’ ” <verse-number id="Eze 22:23">23</verse-number>And the word of Yahweh <idiom-start/>came<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was”</note> to me, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 22:24">24</verse-number>“Son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> say to her, ‘You <supplied>are</supplied> a land not cleansed; it is not rained upon <supplied>in</supplied> <supplied>the</supplied> day of indignation.’ <verse-number id="Eze 22:25">25</verse-number>The conspiracy of its prophets in the midst of her <supplied>is</supplied> like a roaring lion <supplied>that</supplied> is tearing prey. They devour people, and they take wealth and treasure; they make its widows numerous in the midst of her. <verse-number id="Eze 22:26">26</verse-number>Its priests treat my law violently, and they profane my holy objects; they do not distinguish between <supplied>a</supplied> holy object and what is unholy, or between the clean and the unclean. They do not teach the difference, and they hide their eyes from my Sabbaths, and <supplied>so</supplied> I am profaned in the midst of them. <verse-number id="Eze 22:27">27</verse-number>Its officials <supplied>are</supplied> like wolves tearing prey in its midst, to pour out blood, to destroy people, to make dishonest gain. <verse-number id="Eze 22:28">28</verse-number>And for them its prophets plaster whitewash; <supplied>they are</supplied> seeing falseness and <supplied>are</supplied> practicing divination for them <supplied>by</supplied> lying, saying, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh,’ and Yahweh has not spoken. <verse-number id="Eze 22:29">29</verse-number>They severely oppress the people of the land, and <idiom-start/>they committed robbery<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “and they seized <supplied>a</supplied> robbed thing<supplied>s</supplied>”</note> and they mistreated <supplied>the</supplied> needy and <supplied>the</supplied> poor, and they oppressed the alien <idiom-start/>without<idiom-end/><note>Literally “with not”</note> justice. <verse-number id="Eze 22:30">30</verse-number>And <supplied>so</supplied> I sought for them somebody, one repairing <supplied>the</supplied> wall and standing in the breach <idiom-start/>before me<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of me”</note> on behalf of the land not to destroy it, but I did not find <supplied>anyone</supplied>, <verse-number id="Eze 22:31">31</verse-number>and <supplied>so</supplied> I poured out my indignation on them. With the fire of my wrath I destroyed them; I returned their way upon their head,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh. </p>
		</chapter>