<chapter id="Eze 23">
			<pericope>Oholah and Oholibah as Symbols of God’s Corrupt People</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 23:1">1</verse-number>And the word of Yahweh <idiom-start/>came<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was”</note> to me, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 23:2">2</verse-number>“Son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> there were two women, <supplied>the</supplied> daughters of one mother, <verse-number id="Eze 23:3">3</verse-number>and they prostituted <supplied>themselves</supplied> in Egypt in their childhood; they were prostituting <supplied>themselves</supplied> there, <supplied>and</supplied> their breasts were fondled, and there they caressed the bosoms of their virginity. <verse-number id="Eze 23:4">4</verse-number>Now <supplied>as for</supplied> their names, the older <supplied>was</supplied> Oholah, and Oholibah <supplied>was</supplied> her sister. And <idiom-start/>they became mine<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “they were for me”</note> and they bore sons and daughters, and their names<note>Hebrew “name”</note> <supplied>are</supplied> Samaria <supplied>for</supplied> Oholah, and Jerusalem <supplied>for</supplied> Oholibah. <verse-number id="Eze 23:5">5</verse-number>And Oholah prostituted <supplied>herself</supplied> <idiom-start/>while she was still mine<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “under me”</note> and she lusted for her lovers, for Assyria <supplied>who was</supplied> nearby, <verse-number id="Eze 23:6">6</verse-number>clothed in blue cloth, governors and prefects, <idiom-start/>handsome young men<idiom-end/><note>Literally “young men of handsomeness/beauty”</note> <supplied>and</supplied> all of them horsemen, <idiom-start/>experts on horseback<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “riders <supplied>of</supplied> horsemen”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 23:7">7</verse-number>And she bestowed her fornication on them, <supplied>on</supplied> the choice <supplied>ones</supplied> of the <idiom-start/>Assyrians<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons of Assyria”</note> all of them, and with every one <supplied>after</supplied> which she lusted; with all of their idols she defiled herself. <verse-number id="Eze 23:8">8</verse-number>And her whorings from <supplied>the time of</supplied> Egypt she <supplied>did</supplied> not abandon, for they slept with her in her childhood, and they caressed the bosoms of her virginity, and they poured out their fornication on her. <verse-number id="Eze 23:9">9</verse-number>Therefore I gave her into the hand of her lovers, into the hand of the <idiom-start/>Assyrians<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons of Assyria”</note> <idiom-start/>after whom she lusted<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “which she lusted for them”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 23:10">10</verse-number>They uncovered her nakedness; they took her sons and her daughters, and they killed her with the sword. And she became a name for the women, and they executed judgments against her. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 23:11">11</verse-number>“And though Oholibah her sister saw, yet in her lust <idiom-start/>she behaved more corruptly than her<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “she behaved corruptly <supplied>in</supplied> lust from her”</note> and her whoring <supplied>was</supplied> more than the prostitution of her sister. <verse-number id="Eze 23:12">12</verse-number>She lusted after the <idiom-start/>Assyrians<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons of Assyria”</note> governors and prefects, warriors<note>Hebrew uncertain</note> clothed in<note>Or “to”</note> perfection,<note>Or “in full armor” or “wonderfully dressed”</note> <idiom-start/>expert horsemen<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “horsemen, riders of horses”</note> all of them <idiom-start/>handsome young men<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “young men of handsomeness”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 23:13">13</verse-number>And I saw that she was defiled; <idiom-start/>they had both taken the same path<idiom-end/>!<note>Literally “way one <supplied>was</supplied> for the two of them”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 23:14">14</verse-number>And she increased her whorings, and she saw men carved<note>Or “portrayed”</note> on the wall, images of Chaldeans<note>According to the reading tradition (<i>Qere</i>)</note> carved in red, <verse-number id="Eze 23:15">15</verse-number>belted with a belt at<note>Or “around”</note> their waist with turbans on their heads, all of them <supplied>giving</supplied> <supplied>the</supplied> appearance of adjutants,<note>Or “officers”</note> the image<note>Or “likeness”</note> of the <idiom-start/>Babylonians<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “sons of Babylon”</note> Chaldea <supplied>was</supplied> the land of their birth. <verse-number id="Eze 23:16">16</verse-number>And she lusted for them <idiom-start/>when her eyes saw them<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “at the sight of her eyes”</note> and she sent messengers to them <supplied>at</supplied> Chaldea. <verse-number id="Eze 23:17">17</verse-number>And so the <idiom-start/>Babylonians<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons of Babylon”</note> came to her <supplied>for the</supplied> bed of lovemaking; and they defiled her with their fornication, and she was defiled by them, and she turned from them. <verse-number id="Eze 23:18">18</verse-number>And she revealed her whorings, and she revealed her nakedness, and so I turned from her <idiom-start/>just as<idiom-end/><note>Literally “as that”</note> I turned from her sister. <verse-number id="Eze 23:19">19</verse-number>Yet<note>Or “And”</note> she increased her whorings, <idiom-start/>recalling<idiom-end/><note>Or “remembering”</note> the days of her childhood when she was prostituted<note>Or “prostituted <supplied>herself</supplied>”</note> in the land of Egypt. <verse-number id="Eze 23:20">20</verse-number>And she lusted after her male lovers whose genitalia <supplied>were the</supplied> genitalia of male donkeys and <supplied>their</supplied> seminal emission <supplied>was the</supplied> seminal emission of horses. <verse-number id="Eze 23:21">21</verse-number>And you longed <supplied>after</supplied> the obscene conduct of your youth when your bosom was caressed by Egypt, fondling your young breasts. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 23:22">22</verse-number>“Therefore, Oholibah, thus says the Lord Yahweh: ‘Look! I <supplied>am</supplied> stirring up your lovers against you <supplied>concerning</supplied> whom you turned away, and I will bring them against you from all around: <verse-number id="Eze 23:23">23</verse-number>the <idiom-start/>Babylonians<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons of Babylon”</note> and all of the Chaldeans, Pekod and Shoa and Koa, all of the <idiom-start/>Assyrians<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons of Assyria”</note> <supplied>along</supplied> with them, <idiom-start/>handsome young men<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “young men of beauty/handsomeness”</note> governors and prefects, all of them adjutants<note>Or “officers”</note> <idiom-start/>and excellent horsemen<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “ones called riders of horses”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 23:24">24</verse-number>And they will come against you <supplied>with</supplied> an army chariot and wagon and with a crowd<note>Or “horde” or “host of”</note> of peoples; they will set <supplied>themselves</supplied> against you <supplied>from</supplied> all around <supplied>with</supplied> large shield and small shield and helmet. And I will give <idiom-start/>before them<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of them”</note> judgment, and they will judge you with their judgments. <verse-number id="Eze 23:25">25</verse-number>And I will direct my zeal against you, and they will deal with you in anger; your nose and your ears they will remove, and <idiom-start/>those who are left<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “and remainder your”</note> they will fall by the sword, and they will take your sons and your daughters, and <idiom-start/>your remnant<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and remainder your”</note> will be consumed by fire. <verse-number id="Eze 23:26">26</verse-number>And they will strip you <supplied>of</supplied> your clothes, and they will take <idiom-start/>your splendid jewelry<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the jewelry of splendor your”; or “your beautiful jewelry”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 23:27">27</verse-number>And I will put an end to your obscene conduct <supplied>coming</supplied> from you and your fornication from the land of Egypt, and you will not lift your eyes to them; and you will not remember Egypt again.’ <verse-number id="Eze 23:28">28</verse-number>For thus says the Lord Yahweh: ‘Look! I <supplied>am</supplied> giving you into the hand of those you hated, into the hand of those from whom<note>Literally “them”</note> you turned away. <verse-number id="Eze 23:29">29</verse-number>And they will deal with you in hatred, and they will take all of your acquisitions, and they will leave you naked and <supplied>in</supplied> bareness; and the nakedness of your fornication and your obscene conduct and your whorings will be exposed. <verse-number id="Eze 23:30">30</verse-number>These <supplied>things</supplied> <supplied>are</supplied> accomplished<note>Or “done”</note> against<note>Hebrew “in”</note> you since you prostituted yourself after the nations, <supplied>and</supplied> on account of that, you defiled yourself by their idols. <verse-number id="Eze 23:31">31</verse-number>You went in the <supplied>same</supplied> way of your sister, and I will give her cup into your hand.” ’ </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 23:32">32</verse-number>Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “You will drink the deep and wide<note>Or place “drink deep and wide the cup”</note> cup of your sister; you will be as laughter and as scorn; <idiom-start/>the cup holds so much<idiom-end/>!<note>Literally “a large among to hold”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 23:33">33</verse-number>You will be filled with drunkenness and sorrow, for a cup of horror and desolation <supplied>is</supplied> the cup of your sister, Samaria. <verse-number id="Eze 23:34">34</verse-number>And you will drink it, and you will drain <supplied>it</supplied>, and its potsherds you will gnaw, and you will tear out your breasts, for <idiom-start/>I myself<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I, I”</note> spoke,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh. <verse-number id="Eze 23:35">35</verse-number>Therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Because you have forgotten me, and you threw me behind your back, now in turn<note>Or “also”</note> you bear your obscene conduct and your whorings.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 23:36">36</verse-number>And Yahweh said to me, “Son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> will you judge Oholah and Oholibah and declare their abominable deeds to<note>Or “for”</note> them? <verse-number id="Eze 23:37">37</verse-number>For they committed adultery, and blood <supplied>is</supplied> on their hands, and they committed adultery with their idols, and even their children that they had borne for me—they sacrificed them as food! <verse-number id="Eze 23:38">38</verse-number>Also they did this to me: they defiled my sanctuary on that day, and they profaned my Sabbaths, <verse-number id="Eze 23:39">39</verse-number>and when they slaughtered their children for their idols, they came to my sanctuary on that day to profane it. And look, <idiom-start/>this is what they did in my house<idiom-end/>!<note>Literally “thus they did in the midst of house my”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 23:40">40</verse-number><idiom-start/>What is worse<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “and also for/indeed”</note> they sent for men <idiom-start/>who come<idiom-end/><note>Literally “coming”</note> from a distant place, <supplied>to</supplied> whom a messenger <supplied>was</supplied> sent to them, and look! They came! <supplied>Men</supplied> for whom you bathed and painted your eyes, and you adorned yourself <supplied>with</supplied> an ornament. <verse-number id="Eze 23:41">41</verse-number>And you sat on a magnificent couch and a table prepared <idiom-start/>before her<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to the face of her”</note> and my incense and my olive oil you put on her.<note>Or “it”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 23:42">42</verse-number>And a sound of a carefree crowd <supplied>was</supplied> with it,<note>Or “her”</note> and in addition to <supplied>these</supplied> men, <idiom-start/>a crowd of drunken men<note>A problematic verse; reading according to the reading tradition (<i>Qere</i>)</note> was brought in<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from an abundance of men being brought in drunken”</note> from <supplied>the</supplied> desert,<note>Or “wilderness”</note> and they put bracelets on their arms and a crown of splendor on their heads. <verse-number id="Eze 23:43">43</verse-number>And I said to<note>Or “about”</note> the one worn out <supplied>with</supplied> adulteries, ‘Now they will prostitute <supplied>her</supplied> <supplied>concerning</supplied> her fornication, even her.’<note>Or “that <supplied>she</supplied> did”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 23:44">44</verse-number>And <supplied>so</supplied> they went to her like going to a female<note>Or “a woman”</note> prostitute; and thus they went to Oholah and to Oholibah, the women of obscene conduct. <verse-number id="Eze 23:45">45</verse-number>But righteous men, they will judge them <supplied>with</supplied> <supplied>the</supplied> judgment of committing adultery, and <supplied>with</supplied> <supplied>the</supplied> judgment of shedding blood; for they were committing adultery, and blood <supplied>was</supplied> on their hands.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 23:46">46</verse-number>For thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Bring up against them an assembly, and make them as a thing of horror and as plunder. <verse-number id="Eze 23:47">47</verse-number>And an assembly must stone them <supplied>with</supplied> stones,<note>Hebrew “stone”</note> and they must cut them down. With their swords they shall kill their sons and their daughters, and with fire they shall burn their houses. <verse-number id="Eze 23:48">48</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>I will cause obscene conduct to cease from the land<idiom-end/>,<note>Or “I will put an end to obscene conduct from the land”</note> and all of the women will be warned, and they will not do according to your wickedness. <verse-number id="Eze 23:49">49</verse-number>And they will repay your obscene conduct upon you, and the guilt of your idols you will bear, and you will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> the Lord Yahweh. </p>
		</chapter>