<chapter id="Eze 24">
			<pericope>The Boiling Pot and the Death of Ezekiel’s Wife</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 24:1">1</verse-number>And the word of Yahweh <idiom-start/>came<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was”</note> to me in the ninth year, in the tenth month, on the tenth <supplied>day</supplied> of the month, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 24:2">2</verse-number>“Son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> write for yourself the name of the day, <idiom-start/>this very day<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “exactly the day the this”</note> The king of Babylon laid siege to Jerusalem on exactly this day! <verse-number id="Eze 24:3">3</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>deliver a proverb<idiom-end/><note>Literally “quote a proverb”; “proverb a proverb”</note> to <idiom-start/>the rebellious house<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the house of rebellion”</note> and you must say to them, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Place the pot! Place <supplied>it</supplied> and also pour water into it. <verse-number id="Eze 24:4">4</verse-number>Gather its pieces to it, every good piece, thigh and shoulder, fill it <supplied>with</supplied> choice bones; <verse-number id="Eze 24:5">5</verse-number>take the choicest of the flock, and also pile the bones<note>Or possibly “logs”; the difference is one letter in Hebrew</note> under it; <idiom-start/>boil it vigorously<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “boil its boiling”</note> indeed,<note>Or “also”</note> its bones boiled in the midst of it.” ’ ” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 24:6">6</verse-number>Therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Woe <supplied>to</supplied> the city of bloodguilt! A pot that <supplied>has</supplied> its rust in it; <idiom-start/>its rust did not go out from it<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “rust her not went forth from her”</note> Bring it out <idiom-start/>piece by piece<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “according to its pieces”</note> <idiom-start/>one is as good as another<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “no lot has fallen on it”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 24:7">7</verse-number>For her blood was in the midst of her; <idiom-start/>she put it on a bare rock<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “on barrenness of <supplied>a</supplied> rock she put it”</note> she <supplied>did</supplied> not pour it on the ground to cover it <supplied>with</supplied> dust.<note>Or “earth” or “dirt”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 24:8">8</verse-number>To stir up rage, to avenge myself <supplied>through</supplied> vengeance, I placed its blood on <supplied>the</supplied> barrenness of a rock, <idiom-start/>so that it may not be covered<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “so <supplied>as</supplied> not to be covered”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 24:9">9</verse-number>Therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Woe <supplied>to</supplied> the city of bloodguilt! I, even I, will make the pile of wood great! <verse-number id="Eze 24:10">10</verse-number>Pile up the logs; kindle the fire; finish <supplied>cooking</supplied> the meat, and mix <supplied>in</supplied> the spices, and let the bones be burned.<note>Or “charred”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 24:11">11</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>make it stand<idiom-end/><note>Literally “cause it to stand”</note> empty upon its burning coals so that it may become hot, and its copper may become molten and be melted in the midst of it,<note>Literally “her”</note> <supplied>so that</supplied> its uncleanness and its rust be consumed. <verse-number id="Eze 24:12">12</verse-number><supplied>Through</supplied> effort she has caused weariness; <idiom-start/>its thick rust<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the abundance of its rust”</note> went not <supplied>out of</supplied> it. Its rust! Into <supplied>the</supplied> fire <supplied>with</supplied> its rust! <verse-number id="Eze 24:13">13</verse-number>In your uncleanness <supplied>is</supplied> obscene conduct, because I cleansed you, but you were not clean from your uncleanness; you will not be clean again until <idiom-start/>I fully vent my rage<idiom-end/><note>Literally “until causing rest I to my rage”</note> on you. <verse-number id="Eze 24:14">14</verse-number>I, Yahweh, I have spoken. <supplied>It is</supplied> coming, and I did <supplied>it</supplied>; I will not disregard, and I will not take pity, and I will not reconsider. According to your ways and according to your deeds they will judge you!”<note>Or “I will judge”</note> <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 24:15">15</verse-number>And the word of Yahweh <idiom-start/>came<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was”</note> to me, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 24:16">16</verse-number>“Son of man,<note>Literally “to say”</note> look! I <supplied>am</supplied> taking from you what is pleasing to your eyes with a plague,<note>Or “blow”</note> but you shall not mourn, and you shall not weep, and your tears shall not run down. <verse-number id="Eze 24:17">17</verse-number>Sigh in silence <supplied>for the</supplied> dead; you shall not make a mourning ceremony. Bind your turban on you, and you must put your sandals on your feet. You must not cover your <supplied>upper</supplied> lip,<note>Or “your mustache” (NASB)</note> and the bread of <idiom-start/>mourners<idiom-end/><note>Literally “men”</note> you shall not eat.” <verse-number id="Eze 24:18">18</verse-number>And I spoke to the people in the morning, and my wife died in the evening, and I did in the morning <idiom-start/>just as<idiom-end/><note>Literally “as that”</note> I was commanded. <verse-number id="Eze 24:19">19</verse-number>And the people said to me, “Will you not make known to us what these <supplied>things</supplied> that you are doing <supplied>mean</supplied> for us?” <verse-number id="Eze 24:20">20</verse-number>And I said to them that the word of Yahweh <idiom-start/>came<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was”</note> to me, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 24:21">21</verse-number>“Say to the house of Israel, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Look! I <supplied>will be</supplied> profaning my sanctuary, the pride of your strength <supplied>and</supplied> the delight of your eyes and the object of your own<note>Or “souls’,” or “selves’ ”</note> affection; and your sons and your daughters whom you left behind will fall by the sword, <verse-number id="Eze 24:22">22</verse-number>and you shall do <idiom-start/>just as<idiom-end/><note>Literally “as that”</note> I did: You shall not cover your <supplied>upper</supplied> lip,<note>Or “mustache”</note> and you shall not eat <supplied>the</supplied> bread of <idiom-start/>mourners<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “men”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 24:23">23</verse-number>And your turban <supplied>must be</supplied> on your heads, and your sandals <supplied>must be</supplied> on your feet. You shall not mourn, and you shall not weep, but you shall waste away because of your iniquities, and you shall groan <idiom-start/>to one another<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “a man to his brother”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 24:24">24</verse-number>And Ezekiel will be to you as a sign; <idiom-start/>everything that he did<idiom-end/><note>Literally “like all that he did”</note> you shall do; and when it comes you will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> the Lord Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 24:25">25</verse-number>“And you, son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> <supplied>will it</supplied> not <supplied>be that</supplied> on the day <idiom-start/>when I take from them<idiom-end/><note>Literally “on the day of to take me from them”</note> their stronghold, the joy of their glory, the delight of their eyes, and the longing of their inner self,<note>Or “soul”</note> their sons and daughters— <verse-number id="Eze 24:26">26</verse-number>on that day a survivor will come to you <idiom-start/>with the news<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “with a message for ears”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 24:27">27</verse-number>On that day your mouth shall be opened <idiom-start/>at the arrival of the fugitive<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “with the fugitive”; or “to the one who has escaped” (NRSV; cf. NASB)</note> and you shall speak, and you shall not be silent <supplied>any</supplied> longer, and you shall be to them as a sign, and they will know that I am Yahweh.” </p>
		</chapter>