<chapter id="Eze 25">
			<pericope>Judgment upon Various Gentile Nations</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 25:1">1</verse-number>And the word of Yahweh <idiom-start/>came<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was”</note> to me, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 25:2">2</verse-number>“Son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> set your face toward the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons of Ammon”</note> and prophesy against them, <verse-number id="Eze 25:3">3</verse-number>and you must say to the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons of Ammon”</note> ‘Hear the word of the Lord Yahweh! Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Because of your saying, ‘Ah!’ to my sanctuary when it was profaned, and to the land of Israel when it was<note>Or “became”</note> desolate, and to the house of Judah when they went into the exile, <verse-number id="Eze 25:4">4</verse-number>therefore look! I <supplied>am</supplied> giving you to the people<note>Or “children”</note> of the East as a possession, and they will set up their encampments in you, and they will make in you their dwelling places; <idiom-start/>they themselves<idiom-end/><note>Literally “they, they”</note> will eat your fruit and <idiom-start/>they themselves<idiom-end/><note>Literally “they, they”</note> will drink your milk. <verse-number id="Eze 25:5">5</verse-number>And I will make Rabbah as a pasture of camels and the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons of Ammon”</note> as a haunt of flocks, and they will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh.” ’ ” <verse-number id="Eze 25:6">6</verse-number>For thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Because of clapping your hand and stamping with your foot, and <supplied>because</supplied> you rejoiced in<note>Or “to”</note> yourself with all of your malice over the land of Israel, <verse-number id="Eze 25:7">7</verse-number>therefore look! I stretched out my hand against you, and I will give you as plunder<note>According to the reading tradition (<i>Qere</i>)</note> to the nations, and I will cut you off from the peoples, and I will destroy you from the countries, and I will wipe you out, and you will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 25:8">8</verse-number>Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Because of Moab and Seir saying, ‘The house of Judah <supplied>is</supplied> like all of the nations,’ <verse-number id="Eze 25:9">9</verse-number>therefore, look! I <supplied>am</supplied> opening the side of<note>Or “the flank”</note> Moab from the cities on its frontier, <supplied>the</supplied> glory of <supplied>the</supplied> land: Beth Jeshimoth, Baal Meon, and Kiriathaim. <verse-number id="Eze 25:10">10</verse-number>I will give it to the people<note>Or “children”</note> of the East in addition to the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons of Ammon”</note> as a possession, so that the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons of Ammon”</note> will not be remembered among the nations. <verse-number id="Eze 25:11">11</verse-number>And on Moab I will execute punishments, and they will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 25:12">12</verse-number>Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Because of the doings of Edom in avenging himself <supplied>with</supplied> vengeance for<note>Or “toward”</note> the house of Judah, and <supplied>so</supplied> they became very guilty and<note>Or “since”</note> they avenged themselves on them,” <verse-number id="Eze 25:13">13</verse-number>therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh: “so<note>Literally “and”</note> I will stretch out my hand against Edom and I will cut off from it <supplied>both</supplied> human and animal, and I will make it a ruin from Teman and Dedan; they will fall by the sword. <verse-number id="Eze 25:14">14</verse-number>And I will exact my vengeance on Edom by the hand of my people Israel, and they will do in Edom according to my anger and according to my rage, and they will know my vengeance,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 25:15">15</verse-number>Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Because of the <idiom-start/>acting<idiom-end/><note>Literally “doing”</note> of <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines in vengeance, so that they avenged themselves relentlessly with malice in themselves for destruction <idiom-start/>with everlasting hostility<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “<supplied>with</supplied> hostility of ongoing ages/eternity”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 25:16">16</verse-number>therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh: ‘Look! I <supplied>am</supplied> stretching out my hand against <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines, and I will cut off the Kerethites, and I will destroy the remainder of <idiom-start/>the seacoast<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the coast of the sea”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 25:17">17</verse-number>And I will execute on them great vengeance with punishments of rage, and they will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh when I exact my vengeance on them!” </p>
		</chapter>