<chapter id="Eze 26">
			<pericope>Ezekiel Prophesies Against Tyre</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 26:1">1</verse-number>And it was in the <idiom-start/>eleventh<idiom-end/><note>Literally “one ten”</note> year, on the first <supplied>day</supplied> of the month, the word of Yahweh <idiom-start/>came<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was”</note> to me, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 26:2">2</verse-number>“Son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> because<note>Hebrew “because that”</note> Tyre said concerning Jerusalem, ‘Ah! The gates of the peoples are broken; it has swung <supplied>open</supplied> to me; I shall be filled, <supplied>for</supplied> it lies in ruins!’ <verse-number id="Eze 26:3">3</verse-number>Therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh: ‘Look! I <supplied>am</supplied> against you, Tyre, and I will bring up against you many nations like the stirring up of the sea <idiom-start/>stirring up its waves<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “<supplied>with respect to</supplied> its waves”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 26:4">4</verse-number>And I will destroy the walls of Tyre, and they will demolish its towers, and I will scrape away its earthen dirt from it, and I will make it into <idiom-start/>a bare rock<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to barrenness of rock”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 26:5">5</verse-number>It will become a place for spreading out dragnets in the midst of the sea; for I have spoken,’ <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh. ‘And it will become as plunder for the nations, <verse-number id="Eze 26:6">6</verse-number>and its daughters who <supplied>are</supplied> in the field with the sword, they will be killed; and they will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh.’ ” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 26:7">7</verse-number>For thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Look! I <supplied>am</supplied> bringing to Tyre Nebuchadnezzar, the king of Babylon, from <supplied>the</supplied> north, <supplied>the</supplied> king of kings, with horse and with chariot and with horsemen and <supplied>his</supplied> assembly and many people. <verse-number id="Eze 26:8">8</verse-number>Your daughters he will kill in the field with the sword, and he will place<note>Hebrew “give”</note> against you siege works, and he will build against you a siege ramp, and he will raise against you a shield, <verse-number id="Eze 26:9">9</verse-number>and the thrust of his battering ram he will direct against your walls, and your towers he will break down with his weapons. <verse-number id="Eze 26:10">10</verse-number>From the abundance of his horses he will cover you <supplied>with</supplied> their fine dust; at <supplied>the</supplied> sound of horseman and wheel and chariot your walls will shake, at his coming into your gates like the entrance of a city <supplied>that is</supplied> being broken through. <verse-number id="Eze 26:11">11</verse-number>With the hooves of his horses he will trample all of your streets. He will kill your people with the sword, and <idiom-start/>your strong stone pillars<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the stone pillars of strength your”</note> will tumble down to the earth. <verse-number id="Eze 26:12">12</verse-number>And they will plunder your wealth, and they will loot your merchandise, and they will break down your walls, and the houses of your delight they will break down, and your stones and your timbers and your earthen dirt they will cast into the midst of <supplied>the</supplied> water. <verse-number id="Eze 26:13">13</verse-number>And, I will put an end to the noise of your songs, and the sound of your lyres will not be heard any longer. <verse-number id="Eze 26:14">14</verse-number>And I will make you into <idiom-start/>a bare rock<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to barrenness of rock”</note> a place for <supplied>the</supplied> spreading out of dragnets. You will not be built again, for I, Yahweh, I have spoken,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 26:15">15</verse-number>Thus says the Lord Yahweh to Tyre, “Will not the coastlands shake from the sound of your downfall, at <supplied>the</supplied> groaning of the wounded, <idiom-start/>at people being killed<idiom-end/><note>Literally “at being killed a killing”</note> in the midst of you? <verse-number id="Eze 26:16">16</verse-number>And all the princes of the sea will go down from their thrones, and they will remove their robes, and their <idiom-start/>beautiful garments<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the garments of beautiful finished cloth”</note> <supplied>of</supplied> finished cloth they will take off. With terror they will be clothed, and on the ground they will sit, and they will tremble <idiom-start/>continually<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “for moments”</note> and they will be appalled over you. <verse-number id="Eze 26:17">17</verse-number>And they will raise a lament over you, and they will say to you, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>‘How you have been lost <supplied>who was</supplied> inhabited from<note>Or “on”</note> <supplied>the</supplied> seas; </li1>
				<li2>the city that was praised, that was strong. </li2>
				<li1>It <supplied>is</supplied> <supplied>located</supplied> on the sea, </li1>
				<li2>and its inhabitants imposed their terror <idiom-start/>on all of its inhabitants<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to all of its inhabitants”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Eze 26:18">18</verse-number>Now the coastlands will tremble </li1>
				<li2><supplied>at</supplied> the day of your downfall, </li2>
				<li1>and the islands that <supplied>are</supplied> in the sea </li1>
				<li2>will be horrified because of your departure.’ ” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 26:19">19</verse-number>For thus says the Lord Yahweh: “When I make you a desolate city, like the cities that are not inhabited, when bringing up over you the deep, the <idiom-start/>great surging waters<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the waters the many”</note> will cover you. <verse-number id="Eze 26:20">20</verse-number>And I will bring you down with <supplied>those who are</supplied> going down to the grave,<note>Or “pit”</note> <idiom-start/>an ancient people<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “a people of eternity/endless ages”</note> and I will cause you to dwell in the world<note>Or “land”</note> of <supplied>the</supplied> depths, in the ruins from of old with <supplied>those who are</supplied> going down to <supplied>the</supplied> grave,<note>Or “pit”</note> so that you will not be inhabited and <idiom-start/>have a place<idiom-end/><note>Hebrew “and I will give beauty in <supplied>the</supplied> land of <supplied>the</supplied> living”</note> in <supplied>the</supplied> land of <supplied>the</supplied> living. <verse-number id="Eze 26:21">21</verse-number>Sudden terrors I will bring <supplied>on</supplied> you, and you shall no <supplied>longer exist</supplied>; and you will be sought, and you will not be found again <idiom-start/>forever<idiom-end/>,”<note>Literally “to eternity/endless ages”</note> <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh. </p>
		</chapter>