<chapter id="Eze 29">
			<pericope>Yahweh’s Judgment upon Egypt</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 29:1">1</verse-number>In the tenth year, in the tenth <supplied>month</supplied>, on the <idiom-start/>twelfth<idiom-end/><note>Literally “two ten”</note> <supplied>day</supplied> of the month, the word of Yahweh <idiom-start/>came<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was”</note> to me, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 29:2">2</verse-number>“Son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> set your face against Pharaoh, the king of Egypt, and prophesy against him and against Egypt, all of it. <verse-number id="Eze 29:3">3</verse-number>Speak, and you must say, ‘thus says the Lord Yahweh: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Look! I am against you, </li1>
				<li2>Pharaoh, king of Egypt, </li2>
				<li1>the great sea monster, </li1>
				<li2>the <supplied>one</supplied> lying down </li2>
				<li1>in the midst of his Nile streams, </li1>
				<li2>who says to me, “<supplied>It is</supplied> my Nile, and I made <supplied>it</supplied> <supplied>for</supplied> myself.”<note>Hebrew “me”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Eze 29:4">4</verse-number>And so I will put hooks in your jawbones, </li1>
				<li2>and I will make the fish of your Nile streams stick to your scales, </li2>
				<li1>and I will bring you up from the midst of your Nile streams, </li1>
				<li2>and all of the fish of your Nile streams <supplied>which</supplied> cling to your scales. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Eze 29:5">5</verse-number>And I will fling you <supplied>to</supplied> the desert, </li1>
				<li2>you and all the fish of your Nile streams. </li2>
				<li1>On the surface of the field you will fall; </li1>
				<li2>you will not be gathered, </li2>
				<li2>and you will not be assembled. </li2>
				<li1>To the animals<note>Hebrew “animal”</note> of the field </li1>
				<li2>and to the birds<note>Hebrew “bird”</note> of the heavens </li2>
				<li2>I will give you as food. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Eze 29:6">6</verse-number>And all of the inhabitants of Egypt will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh, </li1>
				<li2>because of their<note>LXX, Syriac, and Vulgate: “you”</note> being a staff of reed for the house of Israel. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Eze 29:7">7</verse-number>When they took hold of you with the hand, you snapped, </li1>
				<li2>and you split their every shoulder. </li2>
				<li1>And when they leaned on you, you broke, </li1>
				<li2>and you caused all of their loins to wobble.” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 29:8">8</verse-number>Therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Look! I <supplied>am</supplied> bringing on you <supplied>a</supplied> sword, and I will cut off from you human and animal. <verse-number id="Eze 29:9">9</verse-number>And the land of Egypt will become<note>Hebrew “be”</note> <supplied>a</supplied> desolation and ruins, and they will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh because he<note>That is, Pharaoh</note> said, ‘The Nile <supplied>is</supplied> <idiom-start/>mine<idiom-end/>!<note>Literally “to me”</note> And I, I made <supplied>it</supplied>!’ <verse-number id="Eze 29:10">10</verse-number>Therefore look! I <supplied>am</supplied> against you and against your Nile streams, and I will make the land of Egypt into ruins, <supplied>a</supplied> pile of rubble, <supplied>a</supplied> desolation from Migdol <supplied>to</supplied> Syene and up to the boundary of Cush. <verse-number id="Eze 29:11">11</verse-number>A foot of a human will not pass over it, and a foot of an animal will not pass over it, and so it will not be inhabited <supplied>for</supplied> forty years.<note>Hebrew “year”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 29:12">12</verse-number>And I will make the land of Egypt a desolation in the midst of desolated countries, and its cities <supplied>to be</supplied> in the midst of ruined cities. They will be <supplied>a</supplied> desolation <supplied>for</supplied> forty years, and I will scatter Egypt among the nations, and I will disperse them among the countries.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 29:13">13</verse-number>For thus says the Lord Yahweh: “At the end of forty years I will gather Egypt from the peoples <supplied>among</supplied> whom they were scattered. <verse-number id="Eze 29:14">14</verse-number>And I will restore the fortunes of Egypt, and I will bring them back <supplied>to</supplied> the land of Pathros, to the land of their origin, and they will be a lowly kingdom there. <verse-number id="Eze 29:15">15</verse-number>Of <supplied>all</supplied> the kingdoms it will be <supplied>the most</supplied> lowly, and it will not exalt itself again over the nations, and I will make them small <supplied>so as</supplied> not to rule over the nations. <verse-number id="Eze 29:16">16</verse-number>And it will not be again for the house of Israel an object of trust, bringing to remembrance <supplied>their</supplied> guilt <idiom-start/>when they turned back to them<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “at their turning”</note> and they will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> the Lord Yahweh.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 29:17">17</verse-number><idiom-start/>And then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and it happened”</note> in <idiom-start/>the twenty-seventh year<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “twenty and seven year”</note> in the first <supplied>month</supplied>, on the first <supplied>day</supplied> of the month, the word of Yahweh <idiom-start/>came<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was”</note> to me, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 29:18">18</verse-number>“Son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon, he made his army labor hard against Tyre. Every head was rubbed bare, and every shoulder <supplied>was</supplied> rubbed raw, but<note>Or “and”</note> a wage was not <supplied>paid</supplied> for him and for his army from Tyre for the labor that he did against it.” <verse-number id="Eze 29:19">19</verse-number>Therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Look! I <supplied>am</supplied> giving to Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon the land of Egypt, and he will carry its wealth <supplied>away</supplied>, and he will plunder its plunder, and he will loot its loot, and it will be <supplied>a</supplied> wage for his army. <verse-number id="Eze 29:20">20</verse-number><supplied>As</supplied> his wages that he worked for, I will give to him the land of Egypt, because they worked for me,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 29:21">21</verse-number>“On that day I will cause <idiom-start/>power<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a horn”</note> to grow <supplied>up</supplied> for the house of Israel, and for you I will give an opening of <supplied>your</supplied> mouth in the midst of them, and they will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh.” </p>
		</chapter>