<chapter id="Eze 30">
			<pericope>A Lament over the Nation and Land of Egypt</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 30:1">1</verse-number>And the word of Yahweh <idiom-start/>came<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was”</note> to me, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 30:2">2</verse-number>“Son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> prophesy, and you must say, ‘thus says the Lord Yahweh: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Wail, alas! For the day! </li1>
				<li2><verse-number id="Eze 30:3">3</verse-number>For a day <supplied>is</supplied> near; </li2>
				<li2>indeed, a day <supplied>is</supplied> near for Yahweh. </li2>
				<li1>A day of cloud, </li1>
				<li2>a time of <supplied>the</supplied> nations it will be. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Eze 30:4">4</verse-number>And a sword will come in Egypt, </li1>
				<li2>and anguish will be in Cush, </li2>
				<li1>at the falling of <supplied>the</supplied> slain in Egypt. </li1>
				<li1>And they will take its wealth, </li1>
				<li2>and its foundation will be demolished. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 30:5">5</verse-number>Cush and Put and Lud and all of Arabia and Kub and the people<note>Or “children”</note> of the land of the treaty<note>Or “covenant”</note> with them—by the sword they will fall.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 30:6">6</verse-number>Thus says Yahweh: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“And the supporters of Egypt will fall, </li1>
				<li2>and the majesty of its strength will go down </li2>
				<li1>from Migdol <supplied>to</supplied> Syene; </li1>
				<li2>by the sword they will fall in it,” </li2>
				<li1><idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Eze 30:7">7</verse-number>“And they will be desolate in the midst of desolate countries, </li1>
				<li2>and its cities will be in the midst of ruined cities. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Eze 30:8">8</verse-number>And they will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh </li1>
				<li2>when I put my fire in Egypt, </li2>
				<li2>and all of its helpers are broken. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 30:9">9</verse-number>On that day messengers will go down from <idiom-start/>before me<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of me”</note> in the ships to terrify unsuspecting Cush, and anguish will be in them on the day of Egypt; for look, <supplied>it is</supplied> coming!” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 30:10">10</verse-number>Thus says the Lord Yahweh: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“And I will put an end to the crowds<note>Or “hordes”</note> of Egypt </li1>
				<li2>by the hand of Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Eze 30:11">11</verse-number>He and his people with him, <supplied>the most</supplied> ruthless of nations, </li1>
				<li2><supplied>will</supplied> be brought to destroy the land. </li2>
				<li1>And they will draw their swords against Egypt, </li1>
				<li2>and they will fill the land <supplied>with</supplied> <supplied>the</supplied> slain, </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Eze 30:12">12</verse-number>and I will make the Nile streams dry land, </li1>
				<li2>and I will sell the land into <supplied>the</supplied> hand of bad <supplied>people</supplied>, </li2>
				<li1>and I will lay waste <supplied>the</supplied> land and its fullness </li1>
				<li2>by <supplied>the</supplied> hand of strangers. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p>I, Yahweh, I have spoken.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 30:13">13</verse-number>Thus says the Lord Yahweh: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“And I will destroy <supplied>the</supplied> idols, </li1>
				<li2>and I will put an end to <supplied>the</supplied> worthless idols from Memphis. </li2>
				<li1>And there will <idiom-start/>no longer be<idiom-end/><note>Literally “not be any longer”</note> a prince from the land of Egypt, </li1>
				<li2>and I will put fear in the land of Egypt. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Eze 30:14">14</verse-number>And I will lay waste Pathros, </li1>
				<li2>and I will set fire in Zoan, </li2>
				<li2>and I will execute judgments in No.<note>That is, Thebes</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Eze 30:15">15</verse-number>I will pour out my rage over Sin, </li1>
				<li2>the stronghold of Egypt, </li2>
				<li2>and I will cut off the crowd<note>Or “horde”</note> of No.<note>That is, Thebes</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Eze 30:16">16</verse-number>And I will set fire in Egypt, </li1>
				<li2>certainly Sin will writhe, </li2>
				<li1>and No<note>That is, Thebes</note> will be breached, </li1>
				<li2>and Memphis <supplied>will</supplied> face enemies <idiom-start/>daily<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “of by day”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Eze 30:17">17</verse-number>The young men of On and Pi Beseth will fall by the sword, </li1>
				<li2>and they will go into captivity. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Eze 30:18">18</verse-number>And at Tahpanhes the day will become dark </li1>
				<li2>when I break the yoke of Egypt, </li2>
				<li1>and in it the majesty of its strength </li1>
				<li2>will come to an end. </li2>
				<li1>A cloud will cover it, </li1>
				<li2>and its daughters will go into captivity. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Eze 30:19">19</verse-number>And I will execute judgments in Egypt, </li1>
				<li2>and they will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh.” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 30:20">20</verse-number><idiom-start/>And then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and it was”</note> <idiom-start/>in the eleventh<idiom-end/><note>Literally “on one ten”</note> year, in the first <supplied>month</supplied>, on the seventh <supplied>day</supplied> of the month, the word of Yahweh <idiom-start/>came<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was”</note> to me, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 30:21">21</verse-number>“Son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> the arm of Pharaoh, the king of Egypt, I have broken. And look, it has not been bound up for giving of a remedy, or for <supplied>the</supplied> placing of a splint to bind it <supplied>up</supplied> to make it strong to take hold of the sword.” <verse-number id="Eze 30:22">22</verse-number>Therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Look! I <supplied>am</supplied> against Pharaoh, the king of Egypt, and I will break his strong arm and the broken <supplied>arm</supplied>, and I will let the sword fall from his hand. <verse-number id="Eze 30:23">23</verse-number>And I will scatter Egypt among the nations, and I will disperse them among the countries. <verse-number id="Eze 30:24">24</verse-number>And I will strengthen the arm of the king of Babylon, and I will give my sword into his hand, and I will break the arms of Pharaoh, and he will groan <supplied>with the</supplied> groaning of <supplied>the</supplied> mortally wounded <idiom-start/>before him<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the face of him”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 30:25">25</verse-number>And I will strengthen the arm of the king of Babylon, and the arms of Pharaoh will fall. And they will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh when I give my sword into the hand of the king of Babylon, and he will stretch it out to the land of Egypt. <verse-number id="Eze 30:26">26</verse-number>And I will scatter Egypt among the nations, and I will disperse them into the countries, and they will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh.” </p>
		</chapter>