<chapter id="Eze 31">
			<pericope>Pharaoh Is Warned Through Assyria’s Destruction</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 31:1">1</verse-number><idiom-start/>And then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and it happened/it was”</note> <idiom-start/>in the eleventh<idiom-end/><note>Literally “on one ten”</note> year, in the third <supplied>month</supplied>, on the first <supplied>day</supplied> of the month, the word of Yahweh <idiom-start/>came<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was”</note> to me, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 31:2">2</verse-number>“Son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> say to Pharaoh, the king of Egypt, and to his crowd,<note>Or “hordes”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>‘To whom are you like in your greatness? </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Eze 31:3">3</verse-number>Look! Assyria <supplied>was</supplied> a cedar in Lebanon, </li1>
				<li2><supplied>with</supplied> beautiful branches<note>Hebrew “branch”</note> and a forest giving shade, </li2>
				<li1>and <idiom-start/>very high<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “high of height”</note> </li1>
				<li2>and its treetop <supplied>was</supplied> between <supplied>the</supplied> clouds. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Eze 31:4">4</verse-number>Waters made it great, </li1>
				<li2>the deep made it grow high; </li2>
				<li1>its rivers <supplied>were</supplied> going all around <idiom-start/>its planting area<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “base of its tree”; NRSV, “in the place where it was planted”</note> </li1>
				<li2>and its channels it sent <supplied>out</supplied> </li2>
				<li2>to all of the trees of the field. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Eze 31:5">5</verse-number>Therefore it became tall, </li1>
				<li2><supplied>with</supplied> its height more than all of the trees of the field, </li2>
				<li1>and its branches became numerous, </li1>
				<li2>and its branches became long </li2>
				<li2><idiom-start/>from its sending its shoots from abundant water<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “from water much at sending <supplied>shoots</supplied> its”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Eze 31:6">6</verse-number>In its branches all the birds<note>Hebrew “bird”</note> of the heaven<note>Or “sky”</note> made their nest, </li1>
				<li2>and under its branches all the animals<note>Hebrew “animal”</note> of the field gave birth, </li2>
				<li2>and in its shadow all <supplied>the</supplied> many nations lived. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Eze 31:7">7</verse-number>And it was beautiful in its greatness, </li1>
				<li2>in the length of its branches, </li2>
				<li2>for its root <supplied>was</supplied> toward much water. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Eze 31:8">8</verse-number>Cedars in the garden of God </li1>
				<li2>could not <supplied>be</supplied> equal to it; </li2>
				<li1>fir trees<note>Or possibly, juniper</note> could not resemble its branches, </li1>
				<li2>and plane trees were not <supplied>even</supplied> like its branches; </li2>
				<li1>any tree <supplied>even</supplied> in the garden of God </li1>
				<li2>could not resemble it in its beauty. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Eze 31:9">9</verse-number>I made it beautiful with the abundance of its branches, </li1>
				<li2>and all of the trees of Eden that <supplied>were</supplied> in the garden of God envied it.’ ” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 31:10">10</verse-number>Therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh: “<idiom-start/>Because<idiom-end/><note>Literally “because that”</note> it was tall in height and it set its treetop between<note>Hebrew “to between”</note> thick clouds, and <idiom-start/>he took pride in his tallness<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “and his heart he raised in his tallness”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 31:11">11</verse-number>then<note>Or “and”</note> I gave it into <supplied>the</supplied> hand of <supplied>the</supplied> leader of nations; he <idiom-start/>dealt thoroughly<idiom-end/><note>Literally “doing he did”</note> with it according to its wickedness. I drove it <supplied>out</supplied>. <verse-number id="Eze 31:12">12</verse-number>And strangers cut it off, <supplied>the most</supplied> ruthless of nations, and they abandoned it. On the mountains and in all <supplied>of the</supplied> valleys its branches fell, and its branches were broken in all the river channels of the land, and all the peoples of the world went out from its shadow, and they abandoned it. <verse-number id="Eze 31:13">13</verse-number>On its fallen trunk all the birds<note>Hebrew “bird”</note> of the heaven<note>Or “sky”</note> <supplied>now</supplied> dwell, and all the animals of the field were on its branches. <verse-number id="Eze 31:14">14</verse-number><supplied>This occurred</supplied> so that all of <supplied>the</supplied> trees <supplied>with abundant</supplied> water will not become tall, and they will not set their treetop between<note>Or “among”</note> <supplied>their</supplied> thick foliage,<note>Or “clouds”</note> and <supplied>so that</supplied><idiom-start/>all of the trees that are abundantly watered<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all of <supplied>the</supplied> drinkers of water”</note> <idiom-start/>will not stand up to them<idiom-end/><note>Literally “will not stand to them”</note> in their tallness, for all of them, they have been given <supplied>over</supplied> to death, to <supplied>the</supplied> world below in the midst of <idiom-start/>mortals<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons of men,” or “children of humankind”</note> to <supplied>the people</supplied> going down to the grave.”<note>Or “pit”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 31:15">15</verse-number>Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “On the day of its going down <supplied>to</supplied> Sheol, I caused mourning; I covered over it <supplied>with</supplied> the deep, and I withheld its rivers, and many waters were restrained, and I brought gloom over it; Lebanon and all of the trees of the field, they <supplied>had</supplied> fainted because of it. <verse-number id="Eze 31:16">16</verse-number>From the sound of its downfall I caused nations to shake when I made it go down to Sheol, with <supplied>the people</supplied> going down to <supplied>the</supplied> grave,<note>Or “the pit”</note> and <supplied>so</supplied> in <supplied>the</supplied> world below all of the trees of Eden, <supplied>the</supplied> choice and the best of Lebanon, <idiom-start/>all the well-watered trees<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all <supplied>of</supplied><supplied>the</supplied> drinkers of water”</note> were comforted! <verse-number id="Eze 31:17">17</verse-number>They also went down with it to Sheol to <idiom-start/>those who died by the sword<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to the slain of <supplied>the</supplied> sword”</note> and its army <supplied>who</supplied> <supplied>had</supplied> lived in its shadow in the midst of nations. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 31:18">18</verse-number><idiom-start/>To whom could you be compared, whether in glory or in majesty<idiom-end/><note>Literally “To who you are like as in glory and in majesty”</note> among the trees of Eden? And yet you will be brought down with the trees of Eden to <supplied>the</supplied> world below; in the midst of <supplied>the</supplied> uncircumcised you will lie with <idiom-start/>those who died by the sword<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the slain of <supplied>the</supplied> sword”</note> That is Pharaoh and <idiom-start/>his entire<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all his hordes/crowd”</note> crowd!”<note>Or “hordes”</note> <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh. </p>
		</chapter>