<chapter id="Eze 32">
			<pericope>A Lament for Pharaoh, King of Egypt</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 32:1">1</verse-number><idiom-start/>And then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and it was/happened”</note> in <idiom-start/>the twelfth<idiom-end/><note>Literally “two of ten”</note> year, in the <idiom-start/>twelfth<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in two ten month”</note> month, on the first <supplied>day</supplied> of the month, the word of Yahweh <idiom-start/>came<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was”</note> to me, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 32:2">2</verse-number>“Son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> raise a lament over Pharaoh, the king of Egypt, and you must say to him, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>‘<supplied>With</supplied> a fierce, strong lion among nations you compared yourself, </li1>
				<li2>and you <supplied>are</supplied> like the sea monster in the seas, </li2>
				<li2>and you thrash about in your rivers, </li2>
				<li2>and you make water turbid with your feet, </li2>
				<li2>and you make your rivers muddy. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 32:3">3</verse-number>Thus says the Lord Yahweh: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>Now I will spread my net over you </li1>
				<li2>in <supplied>the</supplied> assembly of many peoples, </li2>
				<li2>and I will bring you up in my dragnet. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Eze 32:4">4</verse-number>And I will throw you on the ground; </li1>
				<li2>on the surface of the open field I will hurl you, </li2>
				<li1>and I will cause every bird of the heaven to dwell on you, </li1>
				<li2>and I will satisfy the animals<note>Hebrew “animal”</note> of all of the world from you. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Eze 32:5">5</verse-number>And I will put your flesh on the mountains, </li1>
				<li2>and I will fill the valleys <supplied>with</supplied> your carcass. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Eze 32:6">6</verse-number>And I will water <supplied>the</supplied> land <supplied>with</supplied> your discharge from your blood </li1>
				<li2>on the mountains, </li2>
				<li2>and valleys will be filled from<note>Or “with”</note> you. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Eze 32:7">7</verse-number>And I will cover <supplied>you</supplied> at<note>Or “by”</note> extinguishing your heavens, </li1>
				<li2>and I will make dark their stars, </li2>
				<li1>and I will cover <supplied>the</supplied> sun with the cloud, </li1>
				<li2>and <supplied>the</supplied> moon will not give its light. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Eze 32:8">8</verse-number>All<note>Or “every”</note> sources of light in the heavens, </li1>
				<li2>I will make them dark over you, </li2>
				<li2>and I will put<note>Or “give”</note> darkness on your land,’ ” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh. </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Eze 32:9">9</verse-number>“And I will disturb <supplied>the</supplied> hearts<note>Hebrew “heart”</note> of many peoples </li1>
				<li2>at my bringing <supplied>about</supplied> your captivity among the nations, </li2>
				<li2>to countries that you do not know. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Eze 32:10">10</verse-number>And I will cause many peoples to be awestruck over you, </li1>
				<li2>and their kings will shudder over you <supplied>in</supplied> horror, </li2>
				<li1>at<note>Or “when”</note> my brandishing my sword before their faces, </li1>
				<li2>and they will tremble <idiom-start/>continually<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “for moments/seconds”</note> </li2>
				<li1>each <supplied>person</supplied> for his life, </li1>
				<li2>on the day of your downfall.” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 32:11">11</verse-number>For thus says the Lord Yahweh: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“The sword of the king of Babylon, </li1>
				<li2>it will come to you. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Eze 32:12">12</verse-number>By the swords of warriors I will cause to fall your hordes </li1>
				<li2><supplied>by</supplied> <supplied>the most</supplied> ruthless of <supplied>the</supplied> nations, all of them, </li2>
				<li1>and they will devastate the majesty of Egypt, </li1>
				<li2>and all of its hordes will be destroyed. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Eze 32:13">13</verse-number>And I will destroy all her domestic livestock </li1>
				<li2><idiom-start/>beside<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from on”</note> many waters. </li2>
				<li1><supplied>The</supplied> feet of humans<note>Hebrew “human”</note> will not make them turbid again, </li1>
				<li2>and <supplied>the</supplied> hooves of domestic livestock will not make them turbid. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Eze 32:14">14</verse-number>Then I will make their waters settle, </li1>
				<li2>and their rivers as the olive oil I will let flow,” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh. </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Eze 32:15">15</verse-number>“Then I make the land of Egypt <supplied>a</supplied> desolation, </li1>
				<li2>so that the land will be stripped from its fullness </li2>
				<li1>when I strike all of <supplied>those</supplied> dwelling in it, </li1>
				<li2>and they will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 32:16">16</verse-number><idiom-start/>This is<idiom-end/><note>Literally “she <supplied>is</supplied>”</note> a lament, and they will chant it as a lament; the daughters <supplied>of</supplied> the nations will chant it as a lament over Egypt, and over all of its hordes they will chant it as a lament,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 32:17">17</verse-number><idiom-start/>And then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and it happened/was”</note> in the <idiom-start/>twelfth<idiom-end/><note>Literally “two of ten”</note> year, <idiom-start/>on the fifteenth<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the five ten of”</note> <supplied>day</supplied> of the month, the word of Yahweh <idiom-start/>came<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was”</note> to me, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 32:18">18</verse-number>“Son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> mourn over the hordes of Egypt, and make her go down, <supplied>and</supplied> with her <supplied>the</supplied> daughters of mighty nations, <idiom-start/>down to the deep underworld<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to <supplied>the</supplied> world/earth deeps/depth”</note> with <supplied>the people</supplied> going down to <supplied>the</supplied> grave.<note>Or “pit” or “netherworld”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 32:19">19</verse-number><idiom-start/>You are more lovely than whom<idiom-end/>?<note>Literally “from whom are you lovely”</note> Go down and be laid in rest with <supplied>the</supplied> uncircumcised. <verse-number id="Eze 32:20">20</verse-number>In the midst of <supplied>the</supplied> people slain by <supplied>the</supplied> sword it<note>Or “she”; that is, Egypt</note> is given they will fall <supplied>to</supplied> a sword; they carried her<note>Or “it”</note> off and all of her<note>Or “its”</note> hordes. <verse-number id="Eze 32:21">21</verse-number><supplied>The</supplied> chiefs of <supplied>the</supplied> warriors will speak to him from the middle of Sheol; with his helpers they have gone down; the uncircumcised lie <supplied>still</supplied>, <idiom-start/>those slain by the sword<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “<supplied>the</supplied> slain of <supplied>the</supplied> sword”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 32:22">22</verse-number>Assyria <supplied>is</supplied> there and all of its assembly; all around it <supplied>are</supplied> its graves, all of them killed, those fallen by the sword, <verse-number id="Eze 32:23">23</verse-number>who<note>That is, Assyria</note> will be given its graves in <supplied>the</supplied> remote areas of <supplied>the</supplied> pit, and its assembly will be all around its grave, all of them killed, fallen by the sword, <supplied>those</supplied> who spread terror in <supplied>the</supplied> land of <supplied>the</supplied> living. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 32:24">24</verse-number>Elam <supplied>is</supplied> there and all of its hordes, all around its grave, all of them dead who fell by the sword, <supplied>those</supplied> who went down uncircumcised to <supplied>the</supplied> depths of <supplied>the</supplied> underworld,<note>Literally “land/earth/world”</note> <supplied>those</supplied> who spread their terror to <supplied>the</supplied> land of <supplied>the</supplied> living, and <supplied>now</supplied> they bear their disgrace with <supplied>the people</supplied> going down <supplied>to the</supplied> grave.<note>Or “pit” or “sheol”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 32:25">25</verse-number>In the midst of <supplied>the</supplied> slain they made a bed for her with all of her hordes all around its graves, all of them uncircumcised, slain by <supplied>the</supplied> sword, for their terror was spread in <supplied>the</supplied> land of <supplied>the</supplied> living, and they <supplied>now</supplied> bear their disgrace with <supplied>the people</supplied> going down to <supplied>the</supplied> grave;<note>Or “pit”</note> in the midst of <supplied>the</supplied> slain it was placed. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 32:26">26</verse-number>Meshech <supplied>and</supplied> Tubal <supplied>are</supplied> there and all of its hordes, all around him its graves, all of them uncircumcised <supplied>and</supplied> killed by <supplied>the</supplied> sword, for they gave their terror in <supplied>the</supplied> land of <supplied>the</supplied> living. <verse-number id="Eze 32:27">27</verse-number>And they do not lie with warriors fallen from long ago, who went down <supplied>to</supplied> Sheol with their weapons of war,<note>Literally “with the weapons of war their”</note> and they placed their sword under their heads, and their shields<note>Reading “their shields” for “their guilt”</note> were on their bones, for <supplied>the</supplied> terror of <supplied>the</supplied> warriors <supplied>was</supplied> in <supplied>the</supplied> land of the living. <verse-number id="Eze 32:28">28</verse-number>And you<note>Evidently refers to Egypt</note> <supplied>too</supplied> in the midst of uncircumcised <supplied>people</supplied> will be broken, and you will lie with <supplied>those</supplied> slain by <supplied>the</supplied> sword. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 32:29">29</verse-number>There <supplied>is</supplied> Edom, its kings and all of its leaders who are laid <supplied>along</supplied> with their might with <supplied>those</supplied> killed by <supplied>the</supplied> sword; they will lie with <supplied>the</supplied> uncircumcised and with <supplied>the people</supplied> going down to the grave.<note>Or “pit”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 32:30">30</verse-number>There are <supplied>also</supplied> the princes of <supplied>the</supplied> north, all of them, all of <supplied>the</supplied> Sidonians who have gone down, being ashamed <supplied>to lie</supplied> with <supplied>the</supplied> slain because<note>Or “in spite of” (cf. NJPS, NIV)</note> of their terror <supplied>that they caused</supplied> from their might, and they lie uncircumcised with <supplied>those killed</supplied> by <supplied>the</supplied> sword, and they bear their disgrace <supplied>along with</supplied> <supplied>the people</supplied> going down to <supplied>the</supplied> grave.<note>Or “pit”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 32:31">31</verse-number>Pharaoh will see them, and he will be comforted over all of his hordes killed by <supplied>the</supplied> sword, Pharaoh and all of his army,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh. <verse-number id="Eze 32:32">32</verse-number>“For<note>Or “although”</note> he spread<note>Hebrew “I gave”</note> my terror in <supplied>the</supplied> land of <supplied>the</supplied> living, and <supplied>so</supplied> he will be laid down in the midst of the uncircumcised with those killed by <supplied>the</supplied> sword: Pharaoh and all of his hordes,”<idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh. </p>
		</chapter>