<chapter id="Eze 34">
			<pericope>Prophecy Concerning Israel’s Shepherds and Sheep</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 34:1">1</verse-number>And the word of Yahweh <idiom-start/>came<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was”</note> to me, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>, <verse-number id="Eze 34:2">2</verse-number>“Son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> prophesy against the shepherds of Israel, prophesy, and you must say to them, to the shepherds, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Woe <supplied>to</supplied> the shepherds of Israel who were feeding themselves! Must not the shepherds feed the flock? <verse-number id="Eze 34:3">3</verse-number>The fat you eat, and you clothe <supplied>yourself</supplied> <supplied>with</supplied> the wool; the well-nourished <supplied>animals</supplied> you slaughter, <supplied>but</supplied> you do not feed the flock. <verse-number id="Eze 34:4">4</verse-number>The weak you <supplied>have</supplied> not strengthened, and the sick you <supplied>have</supplied> not healed, and <idiom-start/>with respect to<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for”</note> the hurt<note>Or “wounded”</note> you have not bound <supplied>them up</supplied>, and you <supplied>have</supplied> not brought back the scattered, and you <supplied>have</supplied> not sought the lost, but <supplied>rather</supplied> you ruled over them with force<note>Or “violence”</note> and with ruthlessness. <verse-number id="Eze 34:5">5</verse-number>And they were scattered <idiom-start/>without<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from not”</note> a shepherd, and they were<note>Or “became”</note> as food for all the animals<note>Hebrew “animal”</note> of the field <supplied>when</supplied> they were scattered. <verse-number id="Eze 34:6">6</verse-number>My flock went astray upon all of the mountains and on every high hill, and <supplied>so</supplied> upon all the surface of the world<note>Or “earth”</note> my flock were scattered, and <idiom-start/>there was no one seeking them<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “there was not <supplied>someone</supplied> seeking <supplied>them</supplied>”</note> and <idiom-start/>there was no one searching for them<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “there was not <supplied>someone</supplied> searching for <supplied>them</supplied>”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 34:7">7</verse-number>Therefore, hear, <supplied>O</supplied> shepherds, the word of Yahweh: <verse-number id="Eze 34:8">8</verse-number>“<idiom-start/>As I live<idiom-end/>,”<note>Literally “live I”</note> <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh, “<idiom-start/>Surely<idiom-end/><note>Literally “if not”</note> because my flock have become as plunder, and my flock became as food to<note>Or “for”</note> all the animals<note>Hebrew “animal”</note> of the field, since there was not a shepherd, <supplied>since</supplied> my shepherds <supplied>have</supplied> not sought my flock, but the shepherds fed themselves, and they fed not my flock,’ ” <verse-number id="Eze 34:9">9</verse-number>therefore, O shepherds, hear the word of Yahweh, <verse-number id="Eze 34:10">10</verse-number>‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Look! I <supplied>am</supplied> against the shepherds, and I will seek my flock from their hand, and I will put an end to them from shepherding flocks, and the shepherds will <idiom-start/>no longer<idiom-end/><note>Literally “not <supplied>any</supplied> longer”</note> feed themselves, and I will deliver my flocks from their mouth, so that they will not be as food for them.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 34:11">11</verse-number>“ ‘For thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Look! I, even I, will seek my flock, and I will look after them, <verse-number id="Eze 34:12">12</verse-number><supplied>just</supplied> like <supplied>the</supplied> caring of a shepherd <supplied>for</supplied> his herd on<note>Or “in”</note> the day when he is in the midst of his scattered flock. Thus I will look after my flock, and I will deliver them from all the places <idiom-start/>to which they were scattered<idiom-end/><note>Literally “which they were scattered there”</note> on <supplied>the</supplied> day <idiom-start/>of storm and stress<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “on <supplied>the</supplied> day of cloud and deep gloom”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 34:13">13</verse-number>And I will bring them out from the peoples, and I will gather them from the countries, and I will bring them to their soil, and I will feed them on the mountains of Israel, in the valleys, and in all of the settlements of the land. <verse-number id="Eze 34:14">14</verse-number>I will feed them in good pasture, and their pasture will be on the mountains of the heights of Israel; there they will lie down in good pasture, and <supplied>on</supplied> lush pasture they will feed on the mountains of Israel. <verse-number id="Eze 34:15">15</verse-number><idiom-start/>I myself<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I, I”</note> will feed my flock and <idiom-start/>I myself<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I, I”</note> will allow them to lie down,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh. <verse-number id="Eze 34:16">16</verse-number>“I will seek the lost, and I will bring back the scattered, and I will bind <supplied>up</supplied> the one hurt, and I will strengthen the sick; and the fat and the strong I will destroy. I will feed her with justice.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 34:17">17</verse-number>“ ‘And you, my flock, thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Look! I <supplied>am</supplied> judging between <idiom-start/>one sheep and another<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “small sheep and small sheep”</note> between the rams and between the he-goats. <verse-number id="Eze 34:18">18</verse-number><idiom-start/>Is it not enough for you<idiom-end/><note>Literally “is it <supplied>too</supplied> little from you”</note> <supplied>that</supplied> you feed on the good pasture? And <supplied>still</supplied> you must trample the remainder of your pasture with your feet, and <idiom-start/>clear water<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and settling of water”</note> you drink, and the <idiom-start/>leftover water<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<supplied>water</supplied> being left”</note> you must make muddy with your feet. <verse-number id="Eze 34:19">19</verse-number>And my flock must graze the <supplied>pasture</supplied> treaded upon by<note>Hebrew “of”</note> your feet, and must drink the mud puddle <supplied>stirred up</supplied> by<note>Hebrew “of”</note> your feet.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 34:20">20</verse-number>“ ‘Therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh to them: “Look! I, even I will judge between fat sheep and between lean sheep, <verse-number id="Eze 34:21">21</verse-number>because with <supplied>your</supplied> flank and with <supplied>your</supplied> shoulder you shoved, and with your horns you pushed all of the sick <supplied>animals</supplied> <idiom-start/>until<idiom-end/><note>Literally “until that”</note> you scattered it<note>Or “them”</note> to the outside. <verse-number id="Eze 34:22">22</verse-number>And <supplied>so</supplied> I will save my flock, and <idiom-start/>they will no longer be<idiom-end/><note>Literally “not they will be longer for plunder”</note> for plunder, and I will judge between <idiom-start/>one sheep and another<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sheep and sheep”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 34:23">23</verse-number>And I will set up over them one shepherd, and he will feed them; <supplied>that is</supplied>, my servant David. He will feed them, and he will be for them as<note>Or “like”</note> a shepherd. <verse-number id="Eze 34:24">24</verse-number>And I, Yahweh, I will be for them <idiom-start/>as God<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to a God”</note> and my servant David <supplied>will be</supplied> a leader in the midst of them. I, Yahweh, I have spoken. <verse-number id="Eze 34:25">25</verse-number>And I will make them a covenant of peace, and I will put an end to wild animals<note>Hebrew “animal”</note> from the land, and they will dwell in the desert <idiom-start/>safely<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “with confidence/trust”</note> and they will sleep in the forest. <verse-number id="Eze 34:26">26</verse-number>And I will make them and <supplied>the area</supplied> all around my hill a blessing, and I will let the rain go down <idiom-start/>at its appointed time<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “in time his”</note> they will be rains of blessing. <verse-number id="Eze 34:27">27</verse-number>And the tree<note>Or “trees”</note> of the field will give its fruit, and the land will give its produce, and they will be on their land <idiom-start/>safely<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “with/in conficence”</note> and they will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh when I break their yoke, and I will deliver them from the hand of the ones enslaving them. <verse-number id="Eze 34:28">28</verse-number>And they will not be <supplied>any</supplied> longer plunder to the nations, and the animals of the land will not eat them, and they will dwell <idiom-start/>in safety<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “with confidence”</note> and <supplied>there will</supplied> not <supplied>be anyone</supplied> frightening <supplied>them</supplied>. <verse-number id="Eze 34:29">29</verse-number>And I will raise for them a garden plot<note>Or “planting”</note> of renown, and they will <idiom-start/>no longer<idiom-end/><note>Literally “not <supplied>any</supplied> longer”</note> be victims of famine in the land, and they will not bear any more the insult of the nations. <verse-number id="Eze 34:30">30</verse-number>And they will know that I, Yahweh their God, <supplied>am</supplied> with them and they <supplied>are</supplied> my people, the house of Israel,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh, <verse-number id="Eze 34:31">31</verse-number>“and you <supplied>are</supplied> my flock, the flock of my pasture. You <supplied>are</supplied> <idiom-start/>my people<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “humanity, Mankind, human, mankind”</note> I <supplied>am</supplied> your God,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh.’ ” </p>
		</chapter>