<chapter id="Eze 35">
			<pericope>Prophecy Directed at Edom</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 35:1">1</verse-number>And the word of Yahweh <idiom-start/>came<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was”</note> to me, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 35:2">2</verse-number>“Son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> set your face against the mountain of Seir and prophesy against it, <verse-number id="Eze 35:3">3</verse-number>and you must say to it, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Look! I am against you, mountain of Seir, and I will stretch out my hand against you, and I will make you <supplied>a</supplied> desolation and <supplied>a</supplied> wasteland. <verse-number id="Eze 35:4">4</verse-number>Your cities I will make ruins, and you will be <supplied>a</supplied> desolation, and <supplied>then</supplied> you will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh, <verse-number id="Eze 35:5">5</verse-number>because there <supplied>has been</supplied> to you <idiom-start/>an ancient hostility<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “enmity of eternity”</note> and you handed over the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> to <supplied>the</supplied> power of <supplied>the</supplied> sword at the time of their disaster, at the time of <idiom-start/>their final punishment<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “<supplied>the</supplied> time of punishment of end”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 35:6">6</verse-number>Therefore <idiom-start/>as I live<idiom-end/>,”<note>Literally “live I”</note> <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh, “Certainly to blood <supplied>guilt</supplied> I will prepare you and blood<note>Or “blood vengeance”</note> will pursue; <idiom-start/>since<idiom-end/><note>Literally “if not”</note> <idiom-start/>you did not hate blood<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “not blood you hated”</note> it will pursue you. <verse-number id="Eze 35:7">7</verse-number>And I will make the mountain of Seir into <supplied>a</supplied> desolation and ruin, and I will cut off from it <supplied>both</supplied> <supplied>he who is</supplied> crossing over and <supplied>he who is</supplied> returning. <verse-number id="Eze 35:8">8</verse-number>And I will fill its mountains <supplied>with</supplied> its slain; your hills and your valleys and all of your watercourses, the slain by <supplied>the</supplied> sword will fall in them. <verse-number id="Eze 35:9">9</verse-number><idiom-start/>An everlasting desolation<idiom-end/><note>Literally “of eternity/endless ages”</note> I will make you, and your cities will not return, and you will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh. <verse-number id="Eze 35:10">10</verse-number><supplied>I do this</supplied> because of your saying,<note>Or “thinking”</note> ‘The two nations and the two lands, they will be <idiom-start/>mine<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to me”</note> and we will take possession of it,’ and <supplied>yet</supplied> Yahweh was there. <verse-number id="Eze 35:11">11</verse-number>Therefore, <idiom-start/>as I live<idiom-end/>,”<note>Literally “live I”</note> <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh, “so I will deal <supplied>with you</supplied> according to your anger and according to your jealousy that you did,<note>Or “showed” or “acted on”</note> because of your hatred against them, and I will make myself known among them when I judge you. <verse-number id="Eze 35:12">12</verse-number>And you will know that I, Yahweh, I have heard all of your contemptible words that you said<note>Or “spoke”</note> against the mountains of Israel, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> ‘They will be desolate; they are given to us as food.’ <verse-number id="Eze 35:13">13</verse-number>And you magnified yourself against me with your <idiom-start/>insolent speech<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “with your mouth”</note> and you spoke voluminously against me <supplied>with</supplied> your words—I heard! <verse-number id="Eze 35:14">14</verse-number>Thus the Lord Yahweh says, ‘<idiom-start/>As the whole world rejoices<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “as/like <supplied>the</supplied> rejoicing of all of the world”</note> I will make you <supplied>a</supplied> desolation. <verse-number id="Eze 35:15">15</verse-number><idiom-start/>Like your rejoicing over the inheritance of the house of Israel<idiom-end/><note>Literally “as/like rejoicing your for the inheritance of the house of Israel”</note> <idiom-start/>because<idiom-end/><note>Literally “because that”</note> it was desolate, I will do to you; you will be <supplied>a</supplied> desolation, mountain of Seir and all of Edom, indeed all of it; and they will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh.’ ” ’ </p>
		</chapter>