<chapter id="Eze 36">
			<pericope>Prophecy to the Mountains of Israel and of Israel’s Restoration</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 36:1">1</verse-number>“And you, son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> prophesy to the mountains of Israel; and <supplied>so</supplied> you must say, ‘Mountains of Israel, hear the word of Yahweh; <verse-number id="Eze 36:2">2</verse-number>thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Because the enemy said concerning you, ‘Ah, and<note>Or “now”</note> <supplied>the</supplied> ancient high places will be to us as a possession!’ ” ’ <verse-number id="Eze 36:3">3</verse-number>Therefore prophesy, and you must say, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “<idiom-start/>Because indeed<idiom-end/><note>Literally “with because”</note> <idiom-start/>when you were desolate<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “<supplied>you</supplied> being desolate”</note> then they crushed you from all around, so that you became a possession to the remainder<note>Or “the rest of”</note> of the nations, and you became <idiom-start/>a byword and object of slander for the people<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “on lips of <supplied>the</supplied> tongue and slander of <supplied>the</supplied> people”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 36:4">4</verse-number>Therefore, mountains of Israel, hear the word of the Lord Yahweh; thus says the Lord Yahweh to the mountains and to the hills, to the river channels and to the valleys and to the ruins that <supplied>are</supplied> desolate and to the cities that <supplied>are</supplied> abandoned <supplied>and</supplied> that have become as plunder and as scorn for the remainder<note>Or “the rest of”</note> of the nations that <supplied>are</supplied> from all around. <verse-number id="Eze 36:5">5</verse-number>Therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh: “<idiom-start/>Certainly<idiom-end/><note>Literally “if not”</note> in the fire of my passion I spoke against the rest of the nations and against all<note>Literally “against Edom all of it”</note> Edom, who made my land as <supplied>a</supplied> possession, because of<note>Or “in order to plunder its pasture<supplied>land</supplied>”</note> its pastureland for plunder, for themselves in all of <supplied>the</supplied> joy of their whole heart <supplied>and</supplied> in <supplied>their</supplied> inner disdain.”<note>Or “malice/disrespect”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 36:6">6</verse-number>Therefore prophesy against the land of Israel, and you must say to the mountains and to the hills, to the river channels and to the valleys, thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Look! I spoke in my passion and in my anger <supplied>the</supplied> insult of <supplied>the</supplied> peoples you have endured.” <verse-number id="Eze 36:7">7</verse-number>Therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh: “<idiom-start/>I swear<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I, raise my hand”</note> <idiom-start/>certainly<idiom-end/><note>Literally “if not”</note> <supplied>that</supplied> the nations <idiom-start/>that are all around you<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “that <supplied>are</supplied> to you from all around”</note> they indeed will endure their disgrace. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 36:8">8</verse-number>“ ‘ “But you, mountains of Israel, your branch you will shoot, and your fruit you will carry<note>Or “bear”</note> for my people Israel, for they <supplied>are</supplied> soon to come. <verse-number id="Eze 36:9">9</verse-number>For look! I <supplied>am</supplied> for you, and I will turn you, and you will be tilled, and you will be planted. <verse-number id="Eze 36:10">10</verse-number>And I will cause <idiom-start/>your population<idiom-end/><note>Literally “humans/humankind”</note> to increase for you, all of the house of Israel, all of it, and the towns will be inhabited, and the ruins will be built. <verse-number id="Eze 36:11">11</verse-number>And I will cause <idiom-start/>your population<idiom-end/><note>Literally “humans/humankind”</note> to increase for you, and domestic animals, <supplied>even</supplied> they will be numerous, and they will be fruitful, and I will cause you to be inhabited like your <idiom-start/>ancient times<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “past days/times/ancient times”</note> and I will do good <supplied>things</supplied> more than <supplied>in</supplied> your former times, and you will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh. <verse-number id="Eze 36:12">12</verse-number>And I will send over you my people Israel, and they will take possession of you, and you will be for them as an inheritance, and <idiom-start/>you will no longer bereave them of their children<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “not you will again longer to bring bereavement for them”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 36:13">13</verse-number>“ ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh, because <supplied>they are</supplied> saying to you, “You <supplied>are</supplied> <supplied>an</supplied> eater of humans,<note>Or “peoples”</note> and you are <idiom-start/>one who makes childless<idiom-end/><note>Literally “maker of childless”</note> your people.”<note>That is, Israel and Judah; Cf. <cite title="BibleLEB2: Eze 37:15–22">Ezek 37:15–22</cite></note> <verse-number id="Eze 36:14">14</verse-number>Therefore humans<note>Or “peoples”</note> you will not eat <supplied>any</supplied> longer, and your nation you will not make childless<note>According to the reading tradition (<i>Qere</i>)</note> <supplied>any</supplied> longer,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh. <verse-number id="Eze 36:15">15</verse-number>“And I will not let you hear <supplied>any</supplied> longer the insult of the nations, and <supplied>the</supplied> disgrace of <supplied>the</supplied> peoples you will not bear <supplied>any</supplied> longer; you <supplied>yourself</supplied> will not cause your nation to stumble,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh.’ ” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 36:16">16</verse-number>And the word of Yahweh <idiom-start/>came<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was”</note> to me, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 36:17">17</verse-number>“Son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> the house of Israel, <supplied>they</supplied> were dwelling on their soil, and they defiled it with their way and with their deeds; like the uncleanness of menstruation was their way <idiom-start/>before me<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to the face of me”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 36:18">18</verse-number>And I poured out my rage on them for the blood that they poured on the land and for their idols <supplied>with which</supplied> they defiled it. <verse-number id="Eze 36:19">19</verse-number>And I scattered them among the nations, and I dispersed <supplied>them</supplied> in the countries according to their way, and according to their deeds I judged them. <verse-number id="Eze 36:20">20</verse-number>And they came<note>Or “went”</note> into the nations <idiom-start/>to which they went<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “who/which they went there”</note> and they profaned <idiom-start/>my holy name<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the name of my holiness”</note> when they said to them, ‘These <supplied>are</supplied> the people of Yahweh, and from his land they went out.’ <verse-number id="Eze 36:21">21</verse-number>And I was concerned for <idiom-start/>my holy name<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the name of my holiness”</note> which, the house <supplied>of</supplied> Israel defiled among the nations <idiom-start/>to which they went<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “which they went there”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 36:22">22</verse-number>“Therefore thus say to the house of Israel, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “<idiom-start/>Not for your sake<idiom-end/> <note>Literally “not for the sake of/on behalf of you”</note> <supplied>am</supplied> I about to act, house of Israel, <idiom-start/>but<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for it”</note> <idiom-start/>for my holy name<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “for the name of holiness my”</note> which you defiled among the nations <idiom-start/>to which you went<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “which you went there”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 36:23">23</verse-number>And I will consecrate my great name, which <supplied>was</supplied> profaned among the nations <supplied>and</supplied> which you have profaned in the midst of them, and the nations will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh!” ’ <supplied>a</supplied> declaration of the Lord Yahweh, <idiom-start/>when I show myself holy<idiom-end/><note>Literally “at/in showing/to show self holy my”</note> <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to their eyes”</note> their eyes. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 36:24">24</verse-number>“ ‘And I will take you from the nations, and I will gather you from all of the lands, and I will bring you to your land. <verse-number id="Eze 36:25">25</verse-number>And I will sprinkle on you pure water, and you will be clean from all of your uncleanness, and I will cleanse you from all of your idols. <verse-number id="Eze 36:26">26</verse-number>And I will give a new heart to you, and a new spirit I will give<note>Or “put/place”</note> into your inner parts, and I will remove the<note>Or “your”</note> heart of stone from your flesh, and I will give to you a heart of flesh. <verse-number id="Eze 36:27">27</verse-number>And I will give<note>Or “place/put”</note> my spirit into your inner parts, and I will make <supplied>it</supplied> <supplied>so</supplied> that you will go<note>Or “walk”</note> in my rules, and my regulations you will remember, and you will do <supplied>them</supplied>. <verse-number id="Eze 36:28">28</verse-number>And you will dwell in the land that I gave to your ancestors,<note>Or “fathers”</note> and you will be to me <supplied>as</supplied> a people, and I will be to you as<note>Hebrew “to”</note> God. <verse-number id="Eze 36:29">29</verse-number>And I will save you from all of your uncleanness, and I will call to the grain, and I will cause it to increase, and I will not bring famine upon you. <verse-number id="Eze 36:30">30</verse-number>And I will cause the fruit of the tree and the crop of the field to increase, so that you will not suffer again <supplied>the</supplied> disgrace of famine among the nations. <verse-number id="Eze 36:31">31</verse-number>And you will remember your evil ways and your deeds that <supplied>were</supplied> not good, and you will loathe <idiom-start/>yourself<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for face your”</note> over<note>Or “because of”</note> your iniquities and over your detestable things. <verse-number id="Eze 36:32">32</verse-number><supplied>But</supplied> not for your sake <supplied>am</supplied> I acting,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh. “Let it be known to you, be ashamed, and be put to shame because of your ways, house of Israel. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 36:33">33</verse-number>“Thus says the Lord Yahweh: ‘On the day when I cleanse you from all of your iniquities, I will cause the cities to be inhabited, and the ruins will be rebuilt. <verse-number id="Eze 36:34">34</verse-number>And the land that was desolate will be cultivated in <idiom-start/>the very place that<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the place that/which/where”</note> it was desolate before <supplied>the</supplied> eyes of all of <supplied>the persons</supplied> crossing over. <verse-number id="Eze 36:35">35</verse-number>And they will say, “<idiom-start/>This desolate land<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the land this the being desolate”</note> has become like the garden of Eden, and the wasted and desolate and destroyed cities, <supplied>now</supplied> being refortified, are inhabited.” <verse-number id="Eze 36:36">36</verse-number>And the nations who are left all around, you will know that I, Yahweh, I built <idiom-start/>that which was destroyed<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “the destroyed”</note> I planted the desolate <supplied>land</supplied>; I, Yahweh, I have spoken, and I will act.’ </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 36:37">37</verse-number>“Thus says the Lord Yahweh: ‘Again this <supplied>time</supplied> I will let <idiom-start/>myself be inquired of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I will be/let me be searched”</note> by the house of Israel, to do <supplied>something</supplied> for them; I will cause them to increase <idiom-start/>their population like a flock<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “them as the flock humankind”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 36:38">38</verse-number>Like <supplied>the</supplied> flock of <supplied>the</supplied> sanctuary, like the flock of Jerusalem at its festival, so the desolate cities will be filled with flocks<note>Hebrew “flock”</note> of people; and they will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh.’ ” </p>
		</chapter>