<chapter id="Eze 37">
			<pericope>A Valley of Dried Bones; A Renewed Nation of Israel</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 37:1">1</verse-number>The hand of Yahweh was upon me, and he brought me by the Spirit of Yahweh, and he <idiom-start/>let me rest<idiom-end/><note>Or “placed me”; literally “set me”</note> in the midst of the valley, and it <supplied>was</supplied> full of bones. <verse-number id="Eze 37:2">2</verse-number>And he led me <idiom-start/>all around<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all around, all around”</note> over them, and look, very many on the surface of the valley, and look, very dry. <verse-number id="Eze 37:3">3</verse-number>And he said to me, “Son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> can these bones live?” And I said, “Lord Yahweh, you know.” <verse-number id="Eze 37:4">4</verse-number>And he said to me, “Prophesy to these bones, and you must say to them, <supplied>to</supplied> the dry bones, ‘Hear the word of Yahweh! <verse-number id="Eze 37:5">5</verse-number>Thus says the Lord Yahweh to these bones: “Look! I <supplied>am</supplied> bringing into you breath, and you will live! <verse-number id="Eze 37:6">6</verse-number>And I will lay on you sinews, and I will let flesh come upon you, and I will cover you over <supplied>with</supplied> skin, and I will put breath into you, and you will live, and you will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh.” ’ ” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 37:7">7</verse-number>And I prophesied <idiom-start/>just as<idiom-end/><note>Literally “as that”</note> I had been commanded, and <supplied>there</supplied> was a sound at my prophesying, and look! A rattling, and they came together—<supplied>the</supplied> bones! Bone to its bone! <verse-number id="Eze 37:8">8</verse-number>And I looked, and indeed, sinews <supplied>were</supplied> on them, and flesh went up,<note>Or “appeared”</note> and skin covered over<note>Or “on”</note> them <idiom-start/>upward<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from to above”</note> but breath <supplied>was</supplied> not in them. <verse-number id="Eze 37:9">9</verse-number>And he said to me, “Prophesy to the breath; prophesy, son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> and you must say to the breath, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh <idiom-start/>from the four winds<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from four winds”</note> “Come, O spirit and breath, on these dead ones, so that they may live!” ’ ” <verse-number id="Eze 37:10">10</verse-number>And I prophesied <idiom-start/>as<idiom-end/><note>Literally “like what”</note> he commanded me, and the breath came into them, and they became alive, and they stood on their feet, a very, very large group. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 37:11">11</verse-number>And he said to me, “Son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> these bones <supplied>are</supplied> all of the house of Israel; look! <supplied>they are</supplied> saying, ‘Our bones are dried up, and our hope is destroyed; <idiom-start/>we are cut off as far as we are concerned<idiom-end/>.’<note>Literally “we are cut in two for us”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 37:12">12</verse-number>Therefore prophesy, and you must say to them, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Look! I <supplied>am</supplied> opening your graves, and I will bring you up from your graves, my people, and I will bring you to the land of Israel! <verse-number id="Eze 37:13">13</verse-number>And you will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh when I open your graves when I bring you up from your graves, my people! <verse-number id="Eze 37:14">14</verse-number>And I will put my breath into you so that you may live, and I will cause you to rest on your soil, and you will know that I, Yahweh, I have spoken, and I will act!” ’ <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> Yahweh.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 37:15">15</verse-number>And the word of Yahweh <idiom-start/>came<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was”</note> to me, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 37:16">16</verse-number>“And you, son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> take for yourself <idiom-start/>a piece of wood<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “<supplied>a piece of</supplied> wood one”</note> and write on it, ‘For Judah and for the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> his associates,’ and take another <supplied>piece of</supplied> wood, and write on it, ‘For Joseph, <supplied>the piece of</supplied> wood of<note>Or “for”</note> Ephraim and all of the house of Israel his associates.’ <verse-number id="Eze 37:17">17</verse-number>And join them one to <supplied>the</supplied> other with respect to you <supplied>as</supplied> one <supplied>piece of</supplied> wood, so that they may become one in your hand. <verse-number id="Eze 37:18">18</verse-number><idiom-start/>When<idiom-end/><note>Literally “as that”</note> <idiom-start/>your people<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the children of your people”</note> say to you, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> ‘Will you not inform us <supplied>as to</supplied> what these <supplied>actions</supplied> mean for you?’ <verse-number id="Eze 37:19">19</verse-number><supplied>Then</supplied> speak to them, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Look! I <supplied>am</supplied> taking <supplied>the piece of</supplied> wood for Joseph that <supplied>is</supplied> in the hand of Ephraim and the tribes of Israel its associates, and I will put them on it, <supplied>the piece of</supplied> wood of Judah, and I will make them into one <supplied>piece of</supplied> wood, so that they be one in my hand.’ ” <verse-number id="Eze 37:20">20</verse-number>And the <supplied>pieces of</supplied> wood <supplied>on</supplied> which you wrote will be in your hand before their eyes. <verse-number id="Eze 37:21">21</verse-number>And speak to them, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Look! I <supplied>am</supplied> taking the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> from among <idiom-start/>the nations to which they went<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “which they went there”</note> and I will gather them from <idiom-start/>everywhere<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “all around”</note> and I will bring them to their <supplied>own</supplied> soil. <verse-number id="Eze 37:22">22</verse-number>And I will make them into one nation in the land on the mountains of Israel, and <idiom-start/>they will all have one king as their king<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “and king one he will be for all of them to king”</note> and they<note>According to the reading tradition (<i>Qere</i>)</note> will not again be two nations and will not again divide into two kingdoms again. <verse-number id="Eze 37:23">23</verse-number>And they will not defile themselves again with their idols and with vile idols and with all of their transgressions, and I will save them from all of their apostasy <idiom-start/>by which they sinned<idiom-end/>,<note>Or “which they sinned by them”</note> and I will cleanse them and they will be for me as a people and I, I will be for them as God. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 37:24">24</verse-number>“ ‘ “And my servant David <supplied>will be</supplied> king over them, and one shepherd will be for all of them, and in my regulations they will go, and my statutes they will observe, and they will do them. <verse-number id="Eze 37:25">25</verse-number>And they will dwell on the land that I gave to my servant, to Jacob, <idiom-start/>in which your ancestors dwelled<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “which they dwelt in it your fathers”</note> and they will dwell on it, they and their children and the children of their children <idiom-start/>forever<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “until eternity” or “until unlimited time”</note> and my servant David <supplied>will be</supplied> a leader for them <idiom-start/>forever<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to eternity” or “to endless ages”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 37:26">26</verse-number>And I will make with them a covenant of peace; <idiom-start/>an everlasting covenant<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a covenant of eternity”</note> it will be with them. And I will establish them, and I will cause them to increase, and I will put my sanctuary in the midst of them <idiom-start/>forever<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to eternity” or “to unlimited ages”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 37:27">27</verse-number>And my tabernacle will be with them, and I will be for them as God, and they will be to me as a nation. <verse-number id="Eze 37:28">28</verse-number>And the nations will know that I, Yahweh, <supplied>am</supplied> consecrating Israel when my sanctuary <supplied>is</supplied> in the midst of them <idiom-start/>forever<idiom-end/>.” ’ ”<note>Literally “to eternity” or “to unlimited ages”</note> </p>
		</chapter>