<chapter id="Eze 38">
			<pericope>God’s Message to Gog</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 38:1">1</verse-number>And the word of Yahweh <idiom-start/>came<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was”</note> to me, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 38:2">2</verse-number>“Son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> set your face toward Gog of the land of Magog, the head<note>Or “chief”</note> leader of Meshech and Tubal, and prophesy against him. <verse-number id="Eze 38:3">3</verse-number>And you must say, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Look! I <supplied>am</supplied> against you, Gog, the head<note>Or “chief”</note> leader of Meshach and Tubal, <verse-number id="Eze 38:4">4</verse-number>and I will turn you around, and I will place<note>Or “give”</note> hooks in your cheeks, and I will bring you out and all of your horses and horsemen <idiom-start/>fully armed<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “clothed of fullness”</note> all of them, <supplied>a</supplied> great crowd, holding <supplied>a</supplied> shield,<note>Or “buckler”</note> and small shield, <supplied>and</supplied> holding<note>Or “wielding”</note> swords, all of them. <verse-number id="Eze 38:5">5</verse-number>Persia, Cush, and Put <supplied>are</supplied> with them, all of them, with <supplied>a</supplied> small shield and helmet. <verse-number id="Eze 38:6">6</verse-number>Gomer and all of its troops, Beth Togarmah, the remote areas of the north, and with all of its troops and many peoples with them. <verse-number id="Eze 38:7">7</verse-number>Be ready, and prepare <idiom-start/>yourselves<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “for you”</note> you and all of your assembly,<note>Or “battalions” or “hoards”</note> the assembling<note>Or “assemblies”</note> around you, and you must be<note>Or “serve”</note> for them as a guard. <verse-number id="Eze 38:8">8</verse-number>After many days you will be mustered; <idiom-start/>in the last years<idiom-end/><note>Or “final years”; literally “in the last of the years”</note> you will come to a restored land from <supplied>the</supplied> sword, gathered from many peoples on the mountains of Israel which were as <idiom-start/>permanent ruins<idiom-end/><note>Literally “ruins continually/permanently”</note> <supplied>but</supplied> from peoples it was brought out, and they will dwell <idiom-start/>in safety<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “with confidence/assurance/trust”</note> all of them. <verse-number id="Eze 38:9">9</verse-number>And you will advance like a storm; you will come, <supplied>and</supplied> you will be like a cloud <idiom-start/>covering<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to cover”</note> the land, and all of your troops and many nations <supplied>along</supplied> with you.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 38:10">10</verse-number>“ ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “<idiom-start/>And then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and it will be”</note> on that day, things<note>Or “thoughts”</note> will come up on<note>Or “in”</note> your mind, and you will devise evil plans. <verse-number id="Eze 38:11">11</verse-number>And you will say, ‘I will go up against a land of open country; I will come<note>Or “go”</note> <supplied>to</supplied> the <supplied>people</supplied> being at rest <idiom-start/>in safety<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “with confidence”</note> all of them dwelling without a wall<note>Or “walls”</note> and crossbars<note>Hebrew “crossbar”</note> and <idiom-start/>without doors<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “and doors there are not for them”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 38:12">12</verse-number>to<note>Or “for”</note> loot loot,<note>Or “war-booty”; this word is chosen because of the alliteration in Hebrew</note> and to plunder<note>Or “seize”; this word is chosen because of the alliteration in Hebrew</note> plunder, <idiom-start/>to assail<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to bring back your hand against”; NJPS, “to turn your hand against”</note> inhabited ruins and <supplied>a</supplied> people gathered together from <supplied>various</supplied> peoples <supplied>and who are</supplied> acquiring livestock and goods <supplied>and</supplied> dwelling at the center of the world. <verse-number id="Eze 38:13">13</verse-number>Sheba and Dedan and traders of Tarshish and all its strong lions,<note>Or “all of its violent leaders”</note> they <supplied>will</supplied> ask you, ‘To<note>Or “for”</note> loot loot<note>Or “war-booty” this word is chosen because of the alliteration in Hebrew</note> are you coming? To plunder<note>Or “seize”; this word is chosen because of the alliteration in Hebrew</note> plunder <supplied>have</supplied> you summoned your assembly, to take away silver and gold, to take livestock and goods, to loot great amounts<note>Hebrew “amount”</note> of loot?” ’ </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 38:14">14</verse-number>“Therefore prophesy, son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> and you must say to Gog, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Will you not realize<note>LXX reads, “stir up/rouse yourself”</note> on that day when my people Israel are dwelling <idiom-start/>in safety<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “with confidence/trust”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 38:15">15</verse-number>and <supplied>so</supplied> you will come from your place, from <supplied>the</supplied> remote areas of <supplied>the</supplied> north, you and many people with you, <idiom-start/>horsemen<idiom-end/><note>Literally “riders of horsemen”</note> all of them, a great crowd and a vast army, <verse-number id="Eze 38:16">16</verse-number>and you will advance against my people Israel like a cloud <idiom-start/>covering<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to cover”</note> the land; it will be<note>Or “occur”</note> in the last days, and I will bring you against my land, so that the nations know me, <idiom-start/>when I show myself holy through you<idiom-end/> before their eyes, O Gog!” ’ </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 38:17">17</verse-number>“Thus says the Lord Yahweh, ‘<supplied>Are</supplied> you he of whom I spoke in former days by the hand of my servants the prophets of Israel <supplied>who</supplied> were prophesying in those days for years <supplied>that I would</supplied> bring you against them? <verse-number id="Eze 38:18">18</verse-number>And <supplied>so</supplied> then in that day, on the day of the coming of God against the land of Israel,’ <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh, ‘my rage will come up in my anger. <verse-number id="Eze 38:19">19</verse-number>And in my passion, <supplied>in</supplied> the fire of my wrath, I spoke<note>Or “I asserted”</note> <supplied>that</supplied> <idiom-start/>certainly<idiom-end/><note>Literally “if not”</note> on that day <supplied>a</supplied> great earthquake will be on the land of Israel. <verse-number id="Eze 38:20">20</verse-number>And the fish of the sea and the birds<note>Hebrew “bird”</note> of the heaven<note>Or “sky”</note> and the animals<note>Hebrew “animal”</note> of the field and all of the creeping things that creep on the earth and all of the humans<note>Or “every human being”</note> who <supplied>are</supplied> on the surface of the earth will shake <idiom-start/>at my presence<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “from the face of me”</note> and the mountains will be demolished, and the steep mountain sides will fall, and every wall on<note>Or “to”</note> the earth will fall. <verse-number id="Eze 38:21">21</verse-number>And I will call against him<note>Or “summon against him” (cf. NJPS)</note> in all of my mountains a sword,’ <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh, ‘<supplied>And</supplied> <supplied>the</supplied> sword of each <supplied>person</supplied> will be against his brother. <verse-number id="Eze 38:22">22</verse-number>And I will execute justice with<note>Or “with respect to him”</note> him with a plague and with blood and <idiom-start/>torrents of rain<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “rain flooding/pouring down”</note> and hailstones; fire and sulfur I will cause to fall on him and on his troops and on many peoples who <supplied>are</supplied> with him. <verse-number id="Eze 38:23">23</verse-number>And <supplied>so</supplied> I will exalt myself, and I will show myself holy, and I will make myself known before <supplied>the</supplied> eyes of many nations, and they will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh.’ ” </p>
		</chapter>