<chapter id="Eze 39">
			<pericope>God’s Destruction of Gog and His Hordes</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 39:1">1</verse-number>“And you, son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> prophesy against Gog, and you must say, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Look! I <supplied>am</supplied> against you Gog, the head<note>Or “chief”</note> leader of Meshech and Tubal, <verse-number id="Eze 39:2">2</verse-number>and I will turn you around, and I will drag you along, and I will bring you up from <supplied>the</supplied> remote areas of <supplied>the</supplied> north, and I will bring you against the mountains of Israel, <verse-number id="Eze 39:3">3</verse-number>and I will strike your bow from <idiom-start/>your left hand<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the hand of left your”</note> and your arrows from <idiom-start/>your right hand<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the hand of right your”</note> I will cause to fall. <verse-number id="Eze 39:4">4</verse-number>On the mountains of Israel you will fall, you and all of your troops, and <supplied>the</supplied> peoples who <supplied>are</supplied> with you, to birds<note>Hebrew “bird”</note> of prey, birds of every wing,<note>Or “kind”</note> and animals of the field I will give you as food. <verse-number id="Eze 39:5">5</verse-number>On the surface of the field you will fall, for <idiom-start/>I myself<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I, I”</note> have spoken,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh. <verse-number id="Eze 39:6">6</verse-number>“And I will send fire against Magog and among <supplied>the people</supplied> inhabiting the coastlands <idiom-start/>in safety<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “with confidence/trust”</note> and they will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh. <verse-number id="Eze 39:7">7</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>my holy name<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the name of my holiness”</note> I will make known in the midst of my people Israel, and I will not let the name of my holiness be profaned anymore, and the nations will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh, <supplied>the</supplied> holy <supplied>one</supplied> in Israel. <verse-number id="Eze 39:8">8</verse-number>Look! <supplied>it is</supplied> coming, and it will happen,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh. “It is the day <idiom-start/>about which I have spoken<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “which I have spoken <supplied>of</supplied>”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 39:9">9</verse-number>“ʻ“And the inhabitants of the towns<note>Or “cities”</note> of Israel will go out, and they will set ablaze, and they will kindle a fire with a weapon<note>Or “weapons”</note> and a small shield and a shield,<note>Or “shields and bucklers”; cf. NJPS</note> <supplied>with</supplied> a bow and with arrows, and with <idiom-start/>hand clubs<idiom-end/><note>Literally “with club of hand”</note> and with spears,<note>Hebrew “spear”</note> and <supplied>so</supplied> they will light a fire with them, <idiom-start/>a fire lasting seven years<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “a fire of seven years”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 39:10">10</verse-number>And they will not carry trees from the field, and they will not chop wood from the forests, for with the weapons<note>Hebrew “weapon”</note> they will light a fire; and they will plunder <supplied>those</supplied> plundering them, and they will plunder <supplied>those</supplied> plundering them,” ’ <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 39:11">11</verse-number>“ ‘ “<idiom-start/>And then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and it will happen”</note> on that day I will give to Gog <idiom-start/>a grave there<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a place there of a grave”</note> in Israel, The Valley of the Travelers, east of the sea,<note>That is, the Dead Sea</note> and it <idiom-start/>will block<idiom-end/><note>Literally “blocking”</note> the travelers and Gog and all of his hordes<note>Hebrew “horde”</note> they will bury there, and they will call <supplied>it</supplied> the Valley of <idiom-start/>Hamon-Gog<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “Gog’s Multitude”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 39:12">12</verse-number>And the house of Israel will bury them for seven months to cleanse the land. <verse-number id="Eze 39:13">13</verse-number>All of the people of the land will bury them, and it will be an honor for them <supplied>on</supplied> the day when I appear,” ’ <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh. <verse-number id="Eze 39:14">14</verse-number>ʻ“And they will set apart <idiom-start/>men to continually<idiom-end/><note>Literally “men of continuity/men who regularly”</note> go through the land burying the travelers,<note>In a negative sense = “invaders”</note> the ones left over on <supplied>the</supplied> surface of the land to cleanse it; <idiom-start/>for the whole of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from <supplied>the</supplied> end of”</note> seven months they will explore <supplied>it</supplied>. <verse-number id="Eze 39:15">15</verse-number>And the ones going through, they will go through within the land, and if <supplied>anyone</supplied> sees <supplied>the</supplied> bones of <supplied>a</supplied> person, <supplied>then</supplied> he will build beside it a sign <supplied>to remain</supplied> until the buriers have buried him in the Valley of Hamon-Gog.<note>Or “Gog’s multitude”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 39:16">16</verse-number>And furthermore <supplied>the</supplied> name of <supplied>the</supplied> city <supplied>there</supplied> <supplied>is</supplied> Hamonah,<note>That is, “Multitude”</note> and <supplied>thus</supplied> they will cleanse the land.” ’ </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 39:17">17</verse-number>“And you, son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> thus says the Lord Yahweh: ‘Say to <idiom-start/>all kinds of birds and animals of the field<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to bird of every wind and to every animal of the field”</note> “Be gathered, come be gathered <idiom-start/>from everywhere<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all around”</note> to my sacrifice that I <supplied>am</supplied> sacrificing for you, a great sacrifice on the mountains of Israel, and you will eat flesh, and you will drink blood. <verse-number id="Eze 39:18">18</verse-number>Flesh of warriors you will eat, and the blood of leaders of the land you will drink; rams, young rams and goats, bulls, <supplied>and</supplied> the fattened animals of Bashan—all of them! <verse-number id="Eze 39:19">19</verse-number>And you will eat fat <idiom-start/>until you are satiated<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “satiation/gluttony”</note> and you will drink blood <idiom-start/>until you are drunk<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to drunkenness”</note> from my sacrifice that I sacrifice for you, <verse-number id="Eze 39:20">20</verse-number>and you will be satisfied at my table <supplied>with</supplied> horse and horsemen and warriors and every man of war,” ’ <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh. <verse-number id="Eze 39:21">21</verse-number>“And I will display my glory among the nations, and all of the nations will see my judgment that I have executed and my hand that I have laid upon them. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 39:22">22</verse-number>“And the house of Israel will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh their God from that day and beyond, <verse-number id="Eze 39:23">23</verse-number>and the nations will know that because of their guilt the house of Israel went into exile, <idiom-start/>because<idiom-end/><note>Literally “because that”</note> they acted unfaithfully against me, and I hid my face from them, and I gave them into the hand of their foes, and they fell by the sword, all of them. <verse-number id="Eze 39:24">24</verse-number>According to their uncleanness and according to their transgression I dealt with them, and I hid my face from them. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 39:25">25</verse-number>Therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Now I will restore the fortunes of Jacob, and I will have compassion on all of the house of Israel, and I will be jealous<note>Or “zealous”</note> for <idiom-start/>my holy name<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “for the name of holiness my”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 39:26">26</verse-number>And they will forget their disgrace and all of their infidelity that they displayed against me when they dwelt on their soil <idiom-start/>in safety<idiom-end/><note>Literally “with confidence”</note> <idiom-start/>with nobody making them afraid<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “and not <supplied>was somebody</supplied> making afraid”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 39:27">27</verse-number>When I restore them from the nations and I gather them from the countries of their enemies, then I will show myself holy through them before the eyes of many nations. <verse-number id="Eze 39:28">28</verse-number>And they will know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh their God, <supplied>because of</supplied> when I deported them into the nations, and I reassembled them to their soil, and <idiom-start/>I will not let any of them remain there any longer<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “not I will leave over/let remain again/still from them there”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 39:29">29</verse-number>And I will not hide my face again from them when I pour out my Spirit over<note>Or “upon”</note> the house of Israel,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh. </p>
		</chapter>