<chapter id="Eze 40">
			<pericope>A Vision of the New Temple</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 40:1">1</verse-number>In the twenty-fifth year of our exile, at the beginning of the year, on the tenth <supplied>day</supplied> of the month, in the fourteenth year after the city was destroyed, in this day exactly, the hand of Yahweh was on me, and he brought me there <verse-number id="Eze 40:2">2</verse-number>in visions from God. He brought me to the land of Israel and put me on a very high mountain, and on it <supplied>was</supplied> <supplied>something</supplied> like a structure of a city to the south. <verse-number id="Eze 40:3">3</verse-number>And he brought me there, and look, there was a man whose<note>Hebrew “his”</note> appearance <supplied>was</supplied> like <supplied>the</supplied> appearance of bronze, and a cord of linen <supplied>was</supplied> in his hand and a reed for measurement; <supplied>he</supplied> was standing in the gate. <verse-number id="Eze 40:4">4</verse-number>And the man spoke to me, “Son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> look with your eyes and listen with your ears and apply<note>Or “set/put”</note> your heart to all that I <supplied>am</supplied> showing you, for you were brought here in order to show you <supplied>this</supplied>; tell all that you <supplied>are</supplied> seeing to the house of Israel.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Eastern Gate</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 40:5">5</verse-number>And there was a wall on <supplied>the</supplied> outside of the temple <idiom-start/>all the way around it<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “all around, all around”</note> and in the hand of the man the reed<note>Or “rod”</note> for measurement <supplied>was</supplied> six <supplied>long</supplied> cubits, <idiom-start/>according to<idiom-end/><note>Literally “with/in”</note> the cubit<note>That is, about 18 inches</note> and a handbreadth,<note>A handbreadth wasabout 3 inches; the reed/rod was 10.5 feet long</note> and he measured the width of the outer wall <supplied>as</supplied> one reed,<note>That is, 10.5 feet</note> and <supplied>the</supplied> height <supplied>as</supplied> one reed.<note>That is, about 10.5 feet</note> <verse-number id="Eze 40:6">6</verse-number>And <supplied>then</supplied> he went toward<note>Or “to”</note> <supplied>the</supplied> gate whose face <supplied>was</supplied> <idiom-start/>to the east<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to the way toward the east”</note> And he went up by<note>Or “with”</note> its steps, and he measured the threshold of the gate, one reed<note>That is, about 10.5 feet</note> wide. <verse-number id="Eze 40:7">7</verse-number>And the alcove<note>Or “niches” in the temple tower</note> <supplied>was</supplied> one reed<note>That is, about 10.5 feet</note> long and one reed<note>That is, about 10.5 feet</note> wide,<note>That is, 10.5 x 10.5 feet</note> and between the alcoves <supplied>was</supplied> five cubits,<note>That is, about 8.75 feet</note> and the threshold of the gate along the side of the portico of the gate <idiom-start/>on the inside<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from the house”</note> <supplied>was</supplied> one reed.<note>That is, about 10.5 feet</note> <verse-number id="Eze 40:8">8</verse-number>And <supplied>then</supplied> he measured the portico of the gate <idiom-start/>on the inside<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from the house”</note> <supplied>as</supplied> one reed.<note>That is, about 10.5 feet.</note> <verse-number id="Eze 40:9">9</verse-number>And he measured the portico of the gate <supplied>as</supplied> eight cubits,<note>That is, about 14 feet</note> and its pilaster <supplied>was</supplied> two cubits<note>That is, 3.5 feet</note> <supplied>thick</supplied>, and <supplied>he measured</supplied> the portico of the gate <idiom-start/>on the inside<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “from the house”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 40:10">10</verse-number>And the alcoves<note>Hebrew “alcove”</note> of the gate <supplied>toward</supplied> the way<note>Or “direction”</note> <idiom-start/>eastward<idiom-end/><note>Literally “of the east”</note> <supplied>were</supplied> <idiom-start/>three on each side<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “<supplied>was</supplied> three from here and three from here”</note> <idiom-start/>the same measurements applied to all three of them<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “measurement one <supplied>was</supplied> to the three of them”</note> and <idiom-start/>the same measurement applied to the pilaster<idiom-end/><note>Literally “measurement one <supplied>was</supplied> to the pilaster”</note> <idiom-start/>on each side<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “from here and from there”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 40:11">11</verse-number>And he measured the width of the doorway of the gate <supplied>as</supplied> ten cubits<note>That is, 17.5 feet</note> and the length of the gateway<note>Hebrew “gate”</note> <supplied>was</supplied> thirteen cubits.<note>That is, 22.75 feet; or the inside width of the gateway was 22.75 feet</note> <verse-number id="Eze 40:12">12</verse-number>And a wall<note>Or “guard wall”; others prefer “curb” (NLT)</note> <idiom-start/>was before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<supplied>was</supplied> to the face of”</note> the alcoves; <idiom-start/>one cubit<note>That is, about 18 inches</note> on either side<idiom-end/><note>Literally “cubit one and cubit one”; or 21 inches</note> <supplied>was the</supplied> wall from here.<note>Or “from the front”</note> And the alcove <idiom-start/>was six cubits<note>That is, 10.5 feet</note> on each side<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “<supplied>was</supplied> six cubits from here and six cubits from here”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 40:13">13</verse-number>And he measured the gate from the top slab of the alcove to its <supplied>opposite</supplied> top slab <supplied>as</supplied> twenty-five cubits <supplied>in</supplied> width, <idiom-start/>from one entrance to the other one opposite it<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “doorway opposite doorway”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 40:14">14</verse-number>And he made <supplied>the</supplied> pilasters sixty cubits,<note>That is, 105 feet (problematic in this context)</note> and to the pilaster of the courtyard <idiom-start/>all the way around the gate<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the gate all around, all around”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 40:15">15</verse-number><idiom-start/>And from the front of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and at the face of”</note> the gate <supplied>at</supplied> the entrance to <idiom-start/>the front of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the face of”</note> the portico of the inner gate <supplied>was</supplied> fifty cubits.<note>That is, 87.5 feet</note> <verse-number id="Eze 40:16">16</verse-number>And <supplied>there were</supplied> narrow windows for the alcoves and for their pilasters to <supplied>the</supplied> inside of the gate <idiom-start/>all the way around<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all around, all around”</note> <supplied>it</supplied>. And likewise <supplied>with respect</supplied> to the porticos and windows <supplied>were</supplied> <idiom-start/>all the way around<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all around, all around”</note> to the inside, and on a pilaster <supplied>there were</supplied> images <supplied>of</supplied> palm trees.<note>Hebrew “tree”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Outer Courtyard</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 40:17">17</verse-number>And he brought me to the outer courtyard, and there were chambers and a pavement made for the courtyard all around <supplied>it</supplied>, <supplied>and</supplied> thirty chambers <supplied>were facing</supplied> to the pavement. <verse-number id="Eze 40:18">18</verse-number>And the pavement <idiom-start/>flanked<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<supplied>was</supplied> to the side of”</note> the side of the gates <idiom-start/>and all along the gates<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “to along side the length of the gates”</note> this <supplied>describes</supplied> the lower pavement. <verse-number id="Eze 40:19">19</verse-number>And he measured <supplied>the width</supplied> from <idiom-start/>the front of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of”</note> the lower gate to <idiom-start/>the front of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of”</note> the outside of <supplied>the</supplied> inner courtyard <supplied>as</supplied> a hundred cubits<note>That is, 175 feet</note> to the east and to the north. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Measurement of the North Gate</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 40:20">20</verse-number>And <supplied>as for</supplied> the gate that <supplied>had</supplied> its face <idiom-start/>toward the north<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the way of the north”</note> of the outer courtyard, he measured its length and its width. <verse-number id="Eze 40:21">21</verse-number>And its alcoves <supplied>were</supplied> <idiom-start/>three on each side<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “three from here and three from here”</note> and its pilasters and its porticos <idiom-start/>had the same measurement<idiom-end/><note>Literally “it was like the measurement of”</note> <supplied>as</supplied> the first gate: its length <supplied>was</supplied> fifty cubits,<note>That is, 87.5 feet</note> and <supplied>its</supplied> width <supplied>was</supplied> twenty-five <idiom-start/>cubits<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “in/by the cubit”; 43.5 feet</note> <verse-number id="Eze 40:22">22</verse-number>And its windows and its porticos and its palm tree images <supplied>were</supplied> like the measurement of the gate that <supplied>was</supplied> <idiom-start/>facing toward the east<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “its face <supplied>to</supplied> the way of the east”</note> and <idiom-start/>it had<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and with steps”</note> seven steps that go up it, and <supplied>there were</supplied> porticos <idiom-start/>before them<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to the face of them”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 40:23">23</verse-number>And a gate <supplied>led</supplied> to the inner courtyard, opposite the gate to the north and to the east, and he measured from gate to gate <supplied>as</supplied> a hundred cubits.<note>That is, 175 feet</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Gate to the South</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 40:24">24</verse-number>And <supplied>then</supplied> he took me <idiom-start/>toward the south<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to the way of the south”</note> and look, a gate <idiom-start/>toward the south<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to the way of the south”</note> and he measured its pilasters and its porticos; <supplied>they had</supplied> measurements <supplied>just</supplied> <idiom-start/>like the others<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “like the measurements the these”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 40:25">25</verse-number>And <supplied>there were</supplied> for it windows and for its porticos <idiom-start/>all the way around it<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all around, all around”</note> like these windows; fifty cubits<note>That is, 87.5 feet</note> long and twenty-five cubits<note>That is, 43.75 feet</note> wide. <verse-number id="Eze 40:26">26</verse-number>And seven steps <supplied>were</supplied> going up <supplied>to</supplied> it and its porticos <idiom-start/>before them<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to the face of them”</note> And <idiom-start/>it had palm tree images<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and palm tree images <supplied>were</supplied> for it”</note> <idiom-start/>all along<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from here and one from here to”</note> its pilasters. <verse-number id="Eze 40:27">27</verse-number>And <supplied>there was</supplied> <supplied>to</supplied> the way of the south<note>That is, “to the south”</note> a gate for the inner courtyard, and he measured from gate to the gate <supplied>on</supplied> the way of the south, <supplied>a</supplied> hundred cubits.<note>That is, 175 feet</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Gates to the Inner Courtyard</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 40:28">28</verse-number>And he brought me to <supplied>the</supplied> inner courtyard through<note>Or “at”</note> the gate of the south, and he measured the south gate, <supplied>and it had</supplied> measurements like <idiom-start/>the others<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the measurements the these”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 40:29">29</verse-number>And its alcoves and its pilasters and its porticos <supplied>were</supplied> <supplied>just</supplied> like these measurements. And <supplied>it had</supplied> windows for it and for its porticos<note>Hebrew “portico”</note> <idiom-start/>all the way around<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “all around, all around”</note> fifty cubits<note>Hebrew “cubit”</note> along<note>Literally “long”</note> <supplied>its length</supplied>, and twenty-five cubits<note>That is, 43.75 feet</note> <supplied>wide</supplied>. <verse-number id="Eze 40:30">30</verse-number>And <supplied>there were</supplied> porticos <idiom-start/>all the way around<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all around, all around”</note> <supplied>its</supplied> length, twenty-five cubits;<note>That is, 43.75 feet</note> and <supplied>its</supplied> width <supplied>was</supplied> five cubits.<note>That is, 8.75 feet, which differs from 40:9; the LXX and some Greek versions lack this verse altogether</note> <verse-number id="Eze 40:31">31</verse-number>And its porticos <supplied>were</supplied> to the outer courtyard, and palm tree images <supplied>were</supplied> on its pilasters, and eight steps <supplied>were for</supplied> its stairs. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 40:32">32</verse-number>And he brought me to the inner courtyard <supplied>by way of</supplied> the east <supplied>gate</supplied>, and he measured the gate <supplied>as</supplied> <supplied>just</supplied> like <idiom-start/>the other measurements<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the measurements the these”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 40:33">33</verse-number>And its alcoves and its pilasters and its porticos <supplied>were also</supplied> like these measurements, and windows <supplied>were</supplied> for it and for its porticos all around;<note>Literally “all around, all around”</note> <supplied>its</supplied> length <supplied>was</supplied> fifty cubits,<note>That is, 87.5 feet</note> <supplied>and</supplied> <supplied>it was</supplied> twenty-five cubits<note>That is, 43.75 feet</note> wide. <verse-number id="Eze 40:34">34</verse-number>And its porticos <supplied>were</supplied> toward the outer courtyard, and palm tree images <supplied>were</supplied> on its pilasters <idiom-start/>one each side<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from here and from here”</note> and <idiom-start/>eight steps served as it stairs<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “and eight steps its stairs”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 40:35">35</verse-number>And he brought me to the gate of the north, and he measured <supplied>it</supplied>; and he measured <idiom-start/>the same measurements as these others<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “like the measurements the these”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 40:36">36</verse-number>its alcoves, its pilasters and porticos, <idiom-start/>and its windows<idiom-end/><note>Literally “its windows <supplied>were</supplied> for it”</note> <idiom-start/>all the way around<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “all around, all around”</note> and <supplied>a</supplied> length of fifty cubits<note>That is, 87.5 feet</note> and twenty-five cubits wide.<note>That is, 43.75 feet</note> <verse-number id="Eze 40:37">37</verse-number>And its pilasters <idiom-start/>faced the outer courtyard<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “<supplied>were</supplied> to the courtyard the outer”</note> and <idiom-start/>it had palm tree images on its pilasters<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and palm tree images <supplied>were</supplied> for its pilaster”</note> <idiom-start/>on each side<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “from here and from here”</note> and eight steps <supplied>served as</supplied> its stairs. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Rooms for Sacrificial Preparations</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 40:38">38</verse-number>And a chamber with its doorway <supplied>was</supplied> in<note>Or “<supplied>set</supplied> among”</note> the pilasters at the gates,<note>Or “gate”</note> and there they rinsed off<note>Or “washed”</note> the burnt offering. <verse-number id="Eze 40:39">39</verse-number>And in the portico of the gate <idiom-start/>were two tables on each side<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<supplied>were</supplied> two tables from here and two tables from here”</note> to slaughter the burnt offering on them and the sin offering and the guilt offering. <verse-number id="Eze 40:40">40</verse-number>And on the outer side as <supplied>one</supplied> goes up to the doorway of the gate <supplied>to</supplied> the north <supplied>were</supplied> two tables, and on the other side, which <supplied>is</supplied> toward the portico of the gate, <supplied>were</supplied> two tables. <verse-number id="Eze 40:41">41</verse-number><idiom-start/>On each side of the gate were four tables<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “four tables from here and four tables from here”</note> eight tables <supplied>in all</supplied>, <supplied>and</supplied> on them they slaughtered <supplied>sacrifices</supplied>. <verse-number id="Eze 40:42">42</verse-number>And four tables <supplied>were</supplied> for the burnt offering, <supplied>and made of</supplied> dressed stones, one cubit and a half<note>That is, 31.5 inches</note> long and one cubit and a half wide and one cubit<note>That is, 21 inches</note> high <idiom-start/>was their measurements<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “<supplied>was</supplied>to them</note> and they placed the objects<note>Or “instruments/utensils”</note> <supplied>with</supplied> which they slaughtered the burnt offering on them and the sacrifice. <verse-number id="Eze 40:43">43</verse-number>And <supplied>there were</supplied> double-pronged hooks, one handbreadth <supplied>in width</supplied>, put in place in the house<note>Or “inside”</note> all around, and on the tables <supplied>was</supplied> the flesh of the offering. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Rooms for Priests and Other Worship Leaders</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 40:44">44</verse-number>And on the outside of the inner gate, <supplied>there were</supplied> chambers for<note>Hebrew “of”</note> singers in the inner courtyard, which <supplied>was</supplied> to the side of the north gate, and their faces<note>That is, of the chambers</note> <idiom-start/>were to the south<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<supplied>were to</supplied> the way of the south”</note> <supplied>with respect to one</supplied>, <supplied>and</supplied> on the side of the east gate <supplied>one</supplied> facing to the north. <verse-number id="Eze 40:45">45</verse-number>And he said to me, “This chamber <idiom-start/>with its face toward the south<idiom-end/><note>Literally “which its face <supplied>is to</supplied> the way of the south”</note> <supplied>is</supplied> for the priests <supplied>who are</supplied> taking care of the responsibility of the temple. <verse-number id="Eze 40:46">46</verse-number>And the chamber <idiom-start/>with its face to the north<idiom-end/><note>Literally “with its face <supplied>is to</supplied> the way of the north”</note> <supplied>is</supplied> for the priests <supplied>who are</supplied> taking care of the responsibility of the altar. They <supplied>are</supplied> the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Zadok, the <supplied>ones who</supplied> approach <supplied>from among</supplied> the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Levi to Yahweh to serve him.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Inner Courtyard and Temple Measurements</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 40:47">47</verse-number>And he measured the courtyard <supplied>as to its</supplied> length, a hundred cubits,<note>That is, 175 feet</note> and a hundred cubits<note>That is, 175 feet</note> wide, squared, and the altar <idiom-start/>is in front of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “before face of”</note> the temple. <verse-number id="Eze 40:48">48</verse-number>And he brought me to the portico of the temple, and he measured <supplied>the</supplied> pilaster of <supplied>the</supplied> portico, <idiom-start/>five cubits on each side<idiom-end/>,<note>That is, 8.75 feet; literally “five cubits from here and five cubits from here”</note> and the width of the gate <idiom-start/>was three cubits on each side<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “<supplied>was</supplied> three cubit<supplied>s</supplied> from here and three cubits from here”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 40:49">49</verse-number>The length of the portico <supplied>was</supplied> twenty cubits<note>That is, 35 feet</note> and its width eleven cubits,<note>That is, 19.25 feet; LXX reads 12 cubits or 21 feet</note> and with ten steps they went up to it, and the <idiom-start/>pilasters had pillars<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “and pillars <supplied>were</supplied> to the pilasters”</note> <idiom-start/>one on each side<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “one from here and one from here”</note> </p>
		</chapter>