<chapter id="Eze 41">
			<pericope>Sanctuary and Temple</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 41:1">1</verse-number>And he brought me to the temple <supplied>sanctuary</supplied>,<note>Or “main room” (of the temple of Jerusalem); “great hall” (JPS); “outer sanctuary” (NIV); word can refer to surrounding courts and halls; HALOT 245.</note> and he measured the pilasters, <idiom-start/>six cubits<note>That is, 10.5 feet</note> wide on each side<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “six cubits wide from here and six cubits wide from here”</note> <supplied>this was</supplied> the width of the tent.<note>Or “of the jambs”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 41:2">2</verse-number>And the width of the doorway <supplied>was</supplied> ten cubits,<note>That is, 17.5 feet</note> and the sidewall of the doorway <idiom-start/>was five cubits on each side<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “<supplied>was</supplied> five cubits from here and five cubits from here”; five cubits = 8.75 feet</note> and he measured its<note>That is, the outer sanctuary</note> length <supplied>as</supplied> forty cubits,<note>That is, 70 feet</note> and <supplied>its</supplied> width <supplied>was</supplied> twenty cubits.<note>That is, 35 feet</note> <verse-number id="Eze 41:3">3</verse-number>And he went into <supplied>the</supplied> inner <supplied>room</supplied>, and he measured the pilaster of the doorway <supplied>as</supplied> two cubits<note>That is, 3.5 feet</note> and the doorway <supplied>as</supplied> six cubits<note>That is, 10.5 feet</note> and the width of the doorway seven cubits.<note>That is, 12.25 feet</note> <verse-number id="Eze 41:4">4</verse-number>And he measured its length <supplied>as</supplied> twenty cubits<note>That is, 35 feet</note> and <supplied>its</supplied> width <supplied>as</supplied> twenty cubits to <supplied>the</supplied> front of the temple, and he said to me, “This <supplied>is</supplied> <idiom-start/>the most holy place<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the holy of the holies”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 41:5">5</verse-number>And he measured the wall of the temple <supplied>as</supplied> six cubits,<note>That is, 10.5 feet</note> and the width of the side room <supplied>as</supplied> four cubits<note>That is, 7 feet</note> <idiom-start/>all along the outside wall for the temple all around the wall<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “all around, all around for the temple all around”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 41:6">6</verse-number>And the side rooms <supplied>were</supplied> <idiom-start/>side by side<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<supplied>were</supplied> side room to side room”</note> <supplied>in</supplied> three <supplied>stories</supplied> and <supplied>a total of</supplied> thirty <idiom-start/>rooms<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “times”</note> and <supplied>there were</supplied> offsets<note>Meaning of word is uncertain</note> in the wall, which <supplied>was</supplied> for the temple for the side rooms, <idiom-start/>all the way around<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all around, all around”</note> to be supports, and <supplied>so</supplied> they were not supports <supplied>extending</supplied> into the wall of the temple. <verse-number id="Eze 41:7">7</verse-number>And <supplied>each level</supplied> widened, and it went around<note>Or “was surrounded”</note> <idiom-start/>upward<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to above, to above”</note> to the side rooms for the structure that surrounds<note>Or “goes around”</note> the temple <idiom-start/>upward<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to above, to above”</note> <idiom-start/>all the way around<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “all around, all around”</note> therefore <supplied>the</supplied> width <supplied>increased</supplied> to the temple <idiom-start/>upward<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to above”</note> and thus the lower <supplied>level</supplied> goes up to the upper <supplied>level</supplied> by <supplied>means of</supplied> the middle story. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 41:8">8</verse-number>And I saw for the temple a platform <idiom-start/>all the way around<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all around, all around”</note> the foundations of the side rooms; <supplied>it was</supplied> the length of a full reed, six cubits long.<note>That is, 10.5 feet</note> <verse-number id="Eze 41:9">9</verse-number>The width of the <supplied>outside</supplied> wall, which <supplied>was</supplied> for the side room to the outside, <supplied>was</supplied> five cubits,<note>That is, 8.75 feet</note> and <supplied>a space</supplied> that was set between <supplied>the</supplied> side rooms, which <supplied>was</supplied> for the temple <verse-number id="Eze 41:10">10</verse-number>and between the chambers <supplied>was the</supplied> width of twenty cubits<note>That is, 35 feet</note> all around the temple, <idiom-start/>all the way around<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all around, all around”</note> <supplied>it</supplied>. <verse-number id="Eze 41:11">11</verse-number>And the doorway of the side room <idiom-start/>faced<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was to”</note> the open area; one doorway <idiom-start/>faced<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was to”</note> <idiom-start/>the north<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the way of the north”</note> and one doorway <supplied>was</supplied> to the south, and the width of the place of the open area <supplied>was</supplied> five cubits<note>That is, 8.75 feet</note> all around.<note>Literally “all around, all around”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 41:12">12</verse-number>And the building that <idiom-start/>faced<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<supplied>was</supplied> to the front of”</note> the courtyard <idiom-start/>was toward the west<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “<supplied>was</supplied><supplied>to</supplied> the side of the way of the sea/west”</note> <supplied>and</supplied> its width <supplied>was</supplied> seventy cubits,<note>That is, 122.5 feet</note> and the wall of the building <supplied>was</supplied> five cubits<note>That is, 8.25 feet</note> wide <idiom-start/>all the way around<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “all around, all around”</note> and its length <supplied>was</supplied> ninety cubits.<note>That is, 157.5 feet</note> <verse-number id="Eze 41:13">13</verse-number>And he measured the temple, <supplied>and</supplied> its length <supplied>was</supplied> <supplied>a</supplied> hundred cubits,<note>That is, 175 feet</note> and the courtyard and the building and its walls, <supplied>their</supplied> length <supplied>was</supplied> <supplied>a</supplied> hundred cubits.<note>That is, 175 feet</note> <verse-number id="Eze 41:14">14</verse-number>And the width of the front of the temple and the courtyard to the east <supplied>was</supplied> <supplied>a</supplied> hundred cubits.<note>That is, 175 feet</note> <verse-number id="Eze 41:15">15</verse-number>And he measured the length of the building <idiom-start/>facing the courtyard<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the front of the courtyard”</note> <idiom-start/>at the rear<idiom-end/><note>Literally “which <supplied>was</supplied> on behind her/it”</note> and its galleries, <idiom-start/>a hundred cubits<note>That is, 175 feet</note> on each side<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from here and from here”</note> and <supplied>also</supplied> the temple, the court, and the porticos of the courtyard, <verse-number id="Eze 41:16">16</verse-number>the thresholds and the framed windows and the galleries around the three of them. Before the threshold <supplied>was</supplied> a covering of wood all around,<note>Literally “all around, all around”</note> and <supplied>from</supplied> the ground up to the windows, and <supplied>all around</supplied> the windows, <supplied>they were</supplied> covered. <verse-number id="Eze 41:17">17</verse-number><idiom-start/>Above<idiom-end/><note>Literally “On from on”</note> the doorway and up to the inner temple<note>Or “sanctuary”</note> and on the outside, and on all of the wall <idiom-start/>all the way around<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all around, all around”</note> in the inner and in the outer <supplied>areas</supplied> <supplied>were</supplied> <idiom-start/>patterns<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “measurements”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 41:18">18</verse-number>and <supplied>it was</supplied> made of cherubim and palm tree images; a palm tree image between cherub and cherub, and <idiom-start/>the cherub had two faces<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “two faces <supplied>were</supplied> for the cherub”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 41:19">19</verse-number>And <supplied>the</supplied> face of a human <idiom-start/>was toward<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was to”</note> the palm tree image <idiom-start/>on the one side<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from here”</note> and <supplied>the</supplied> face of a fierce strong lion <idiom-start/>faced<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<supplied>was</supplied> to”</note> the palm tree image <idiom-start/>on the other side<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “from here”</note> <idiom-start/>this work was executed<idiom-end/><note>Literally “being made”</note> for the entire temple <idiom-start/>all the way around<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “all around, all around”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 41:20">20</verse-number>From the ground up to <idiom-start/>above<idiom-end/><note>Literally “up to form on”</note> the doorway,<note>Or “entrance”</note> the cherubim and the palm tree images <supplied>were</supplied> made,<note>Or “being made”</note> and <supplied>also</supplied> the <supplied>outer</supplied> wall of the temple. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 41:21">21</verse-number><supplied>As far as</supplied> the temple <supplied>is concerned</supplied> <supplied>its</supplied> doorframe <supplied>was</supplied> squared, and <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the front of”</note> the sanctuary <supplied>was</supplied> the appearance as <supplied>it were</supplied> the appearance of <verse-number id="Eze 41:22">22</verse-number><idiom-start/>a wooden altar<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the altar <supplied>made of</supplied> wood”</note> <supplied>that</supplied> <supplied>was</supplied> three cubits<note>That is, 5.25 feet</note> high, and its length <supplied>was</supplied> two cubits,<note>That is, 3.5 feet</note> and its corners<note>Hebrew “corner”</note> for it and its length and its walls <supplied>were of</supplied> wood. And he spoke to me, “This <supplied>is</supplied> the table that <supplied>is</supplied> <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of”</note> Yahweh.” <verse-number id="Eze 41:23">23</verse-number>And the two doors <supplied>were</supplied> for the temple and for the sanctuary. <verse-number id="Eze 41:24">24</verse-number>And two leaves<note>That is, two swinging leaves for each door</note> of a door <supplied>were</supplied> for <supplied>each of</supplied> the doors, two hinged leaves of a door: two <supplied>were</supplied> for the first door, and two leaves of a door <supplied>were</supplied> for the other door. <verse-number id="Eze 41:25">25</verse-number>And cherubim <supplied>were</supplied> made<note>Or “carved”</note> on them, that is, on the doors of the temple and palm tree images like <idiom-start/>the ones prepared for the walls<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “like which <supplied>they</supplied> were made for the walls”</note> and <supplied>an</supplied> overhang <supplied>of</supplied> wood <supplied>was</supplied> on the surface of the porticos on the outside. <verse-number id="Eze 41:26">26</verse-number>And narrow windows and palm tree images <idiom-start/>were on either side<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “<supplied>were</supplied> from here and from here”</note> <supplied>and</supplied> on the side walls of the portico, and the side rooms of the temple and their<note>Literally “the”</note> overhang. </p>
		</chapter>