<chapter id="Eze 42">
			<pericope>Description of Rooms for the Priests</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 42:1">1</verse-number>And he brought me out to the outer courtyard <idiom-start/>to the north<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “<supplied>to</supplied> the way of the north”</note> and he brought me to the chamber which <supplied>was</supplied> opposite the courtyard and which <supplied>is</supplied> opposite the building to the north. <verse-number id="Eze 42:2">2</verse-number><supplied>As</supplied> to<note>Or “along the face of”</note> <supplied>the</supplied> face of <supplied>the</supplied> length <supplied>of the building</supplied> <supplied>with</supplied> the doorway to the north, <supplied>it</supplied> <supplied>was</supplied> a hundred cubits,<note>That is, 175 feet</note> and its<note>Or “the”</note> width <supplied>was</supplied> fifty cubits.<note>That is, 87.5 feet</note> <verse-number id="Eze 42:3">3</verse-number>Opposite the twenty <supplied>cubits</supplied> <idiom-start/>of the inner courtyard<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “which <supplied>were</supplied> to the courtyard the inner”</note> and opposite <supplied>the</supplied> pavement that <supplied>was</supplied> to the outer courtyard <supplied>was</supplied> a gallery <idiom-start/>facing<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to<supplied>ward</supplied> in the face/front of”</note> a gallery in the three <supplied>stories</supplied>. <verse-number id="Eze 42:4">4</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>in front of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of”</note> the chambers <supplied>was</supplied> a passageway ten cubits<note>That is, 17.5 feet</note> <supplied>in</supplied> width toward the inside, a walkway of one cubit,<note>One cubit of 18–21 inches is problematic; LXX and Syriac read 100 cubits (175 feet) running the length of the building</note> and their doorways <supplied>were</supplied> to the north. <verse-number id="Eze 42:5">5</verse-number>And the upper chambers narrowed, for <supplied>the</supplied> galleries took away <supplied>space</supplied> from them more than <supplied>they took</supplied> from the lower <supplied>levels</supplied> and more than <supplied>they took</supplied> from the middle <supplied>level</supplied> <supplied>in the</supplied> building. <verse-number id="Eze 42:6">6</verse-number>For they<note>Or “there”</note> <supplied>were</supplied> three stories and <idiom-start/>they had no pillars<idiom-end/><note>Literally “there were not for them pillars”</note> like<note>Or “as”</note> the pillars of<note>Or “for”</note> the courtyards; therefore they were smaller than the lower <supplied>stories</supplied> and than the middle <supplied>stories</supplied> from the ground <supplied>up</supplied>. <verse-number id="Eze 42:7">7</verse-number>And <supplied>there was</supplied> a wall that was to the outside <idiom-start/>alongside<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the outside to corresponding”</note> the chambers <supplied>on</supplied> the walkway to<note>Or “of”</note> the outer courtyard<note>That is, “to the north”</note> <idiom-start/>in front of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to in face of”</note> the chambers; its length <supplied>was</supplied> fifty<note>That is, 87.5 feet</note> cubits.<note>Hebrew “cubit”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 42:8">8</verse-number>For<note>Or “while”</note> the length of the chambers which <supplied>were</supplied> to the outer courtyard <supplied>was</supplied> fifty<note>Hebrew “cubit”</note> cubits,<note>That is, 87.5 feet</note> and look!<note>Or “yet!”</note> <supplied>The chambers</supplied> on the front of the temple <supplied>were</supplied> a hundred<note>Hebrew “cubit”</note> cubits.<note>That is, 175 feet</note> <verse-number id="Eze 42:9">9</verse-number>And from under these chambers <supplied>was</supplied> the entrance<note>Reading the Ketiv</note> from the east for them <idiom-start/>when one enters<idiom-end/><note>Literally “at/in his/its coming”</note> from the outer courtyard. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 42:10">10</verse-number>All along the width of the wall of the courtyard <idiom-start/>eastward<idiom-end/><note>Literally “on the way of the east”</note> in front of the courtyard to the front of the building <supplied>were</supplied> chambers. <verse-number id="Eze 42:11">11</verse-number>And a walkway <supplied>was</supplied> <idiom-start/>before them<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was to the face of them”</note> like the appearance of the chambers which <supplied>were on</supplied> <idiom-start/>the north<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “<supplied>were on</supplied> the way of the north”</note> <supplied>just</supplied> like <supplied>them in</supplied> their length, <supplied>and</supplied> so <supplied>was</supplied> their width and all their exits, and <supplied>they were built</supplied> like their arrangements and like their doorways, <verse-number id="Eze 42:12">12</verse-number>and like the doorways of the chambers which <supplied>were on</supplied> the way of the south <supplied>was</supplied> <supplied>a</supplied> doorway at the head of the way<note>Dropping one “way”</note> <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/> the stone wall, projecting<note>Or “protecting wall”</note> <supplied>on</supplied><note>Or “toward”</note> the way of the east at their coming.<note>That is, when people entered the complex</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 42:13">13</verse-number>And he said to me, “The chambers of the north <supplied>and</supplied> the chambers of the south which <supplied>are</supplied> <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the front of”</note> the courtyard, they <idiom-start/>are the holy chambers<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<supplied>are</supplied> the chambers of the holiness”</note> in which the priests, who <supplied>are</supplied> near to Yahweh, will eat the <idiom-start/>most holy objects<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “holy objects of the holy objects”</note> There they shall put the <idiom-start/>most holy objects<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “holy objects of the holy objects”</note> and the grain offering and the sin offering and the guilt offering, for the place <supplied>is</supplied> holy. <verse-number id="Eze 42:14">14</verse-number><idiom-start/>When the priests enter<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “at coming their”</note> then they shall not go out from the sanctuary to the outer courtyard; and there they must put<note>Or “deposit/leave/remove”</note> their garments in which they serve because they <supplied>are</supplied> holy. They must put on other garments and <supplied>then</supplied> they may approach <supplied>the area</supplied> that <supplied>is</supplied> for the people. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 42:15">15</verse-number>And he completed the measurements of the inner temple, and he brought me <supplied>to</supplied> the walkway of the gate <idiom-start/>that faces toward the east<idiom-end/><note>Literally “which its face <supplied>is to</supplied> the way of the east”</note> and he measured it <idiom-start/>all the way around<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “all around, all around”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 42:16">16</verse-number>He measured the east side with the reed<note>Or “rod”</note> for<note>Literally “of measuring”</note> measuring, five hundred cubits,<note>Hebrew has “reeds” here (= 5,250 feet), which is not correct; 500 cubits = 875 feet.</note> with <supplied>respect to</supplied> reeds with the reed for measurement, <supplied>he measured it</supplied> all around. <verse-number id="Eze 42:17">17</verse-number>He measured the north side <supplied>as</supplied> five hundred <supplied>cubits</supplied>, <supplied>with respect to</supplied> reeds with the reed for measurement all around. <verse-number id="Eze 42:18">18</verse-number><supplied>Then</supplied> he measured the south side <supplied>as</supplied> five hundred <supplied>cubits</supplied>, <supplied>with respect to</supplied> reeds with the reed for measurement. <verse-number id="Eze 42:19">19</verse-number>He went around the west side<note>Or “side toward/to the sea”</note> <supplied>and</supplied> he measured five hundred <supplied>cubits</supplied>, <supplied>with respect to</supplied> reeds with the reed for measurement. <verse-number id="Eze 42:20">20</verse-number><idiom-start/>Toward the four sides<idiom-end/><note>Literally “toward the four winds”</note> he measured it; <supplied>there</supplied> <supplied>was</supplied> a wall for it <idiom-start/>all the way around<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “all around, all around”</note> <supplied>Its</supplied> length <supplied>was</supplied> five hundred <supplied>cubits</supplied><note>That is, 875 feet</note> and <supplied>its</supplied> width <supplied>was</supplied> five hundred <supplied>cubits</supplied>, in order to make <supplied>a</supplied> separation between what is holy and what is common. </p>
		</chapter>