<chapter id="Eze 43">
			<pericope>Return of the Lord’s Glory and Description of Sacrifices and Worship</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 43:1">1</verse-number>And he brought me to the gate which <supplied>was</supplied> <idiom-start/>facing east<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “which <supplied>was</supplied> facing <supplied>to</supplied> the way of the east”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 43:2">2</verse-number>And, look! The glory of the God of Israel, it came from the way of the east, and its sound <supplied>was</supplied> like <supplied>the</supplied> sound of many waters<note>Hebrew “water”</note> and the land radiated due to his glory! <verse-number id="Eze 43:3">3</verse-number>And<note>Or “and as”; as is not needed in translation</note> the appearance of the vision which I saw <supplied>was</supplied> as<note>Or “like”</note> the vision which I saw at his<note>Or “my coming”</note> coming to destroy the city, and <supplied>these</supplied> visions <supplied>were</supplied> <supplied>also</supplied> as<note>Or “like”</note> the vision which I saw by the <idiom-start/>Kebar River<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “river of Kebar”</note> and I fell on my face. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 43:4">4</verse-number>And <supplied>then</supplied> the glory of Yahweh came to the temple <idiom-start/>by the way of the gate facing east<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “<supplied>by</supplied> the way of <supplied>the</supplied> gate which its face <supplied>was to</supplied> the way of the east”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 43:5">5</verse-number>And <supplied>the</supplied> Spirit lifted me and it brought me to the inner courtyard and, look! The glory of Yahweh filled the temple! <verse-number id="Eze 43:6">6</verse-number>And I heard <supplied>someone</supplied> speaking to me from the house,<note>Or “from inside”</note> and a man was standing beside me. <verse-number id="Eze 43:7">7</verse-number>And he said to me, “Son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> <supplied>this is</supplied> the place of my throne and the place for the soles of my feet <idiom-start/>where I will dwell<idiom-end/><note>Literally “which I will dwell there”</note> in the midst of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> to eternity, and they, the house of Israel, they and their kings, will not again defile <idiom-start/>my holy name<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the name of my holiness”</note> with their fornication and with their offerings for the dead<note>Or “corpses”</note> of their kings <supplied>on</supplied> their high places. <verse-number id="Eze 43:8">8</verse-number><idiom-start/>When they placed their threshold<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in/at their placing their threshold”</note> with<note>Or “beside/next to”</note> my threshold, their doorframe beside my doorframe and the<note>Or “their”</note> wall <supplied>was</supplied> between me and between them, then they defiled <idiom-start/>my holy name<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the name of my holiness”</note> with their detestable things that they did, and <supplied>so</supplied> I consumed them in my anger. <verse-number id="Eze 43:9">9</verse-number>Now let them send their fornication far away and the offerings for the dead<note>Or “corpses”</note> of their kings <supplied>away</supplied> from me, and I will dwell in the midst of them <idiom-start/>forever<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to eternity”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 43:10">10</verse-number>You, son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> describe <supplied>to</supplied> the house of Israel the temple and let them be ashamed of their iniquities and let them measure the pattern. <verse-number id="Eze 43:11">11</verse-number>And if they are ashamed of all that they did, <supplied>then</supplied> the plan of the temple and its arrangement and its exits and its entrances and all of its plans<note>Or “its entire pattern”</note> and all of its statutes. And all of its plans<note>Or “purposes”</note> and all of its laws<note>According to the reading tradition (<i>Qere</i>); cf. BHS</note> make known <supplied>to</supplied> them and write <supplied>them</supplied> before their eyes, so that they may remember all of its plans and all of its statutes, so that they do them! <verse-number id="Eze 43:12">12</verse-number>This <supplied>is</supplied> the law<note>Literally “torah” or “instruction”</note> of the temple: On the top of the mountain, all of its territory, <idiom-start/>all the way around it<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “all around, all around”</note> <idiom-start/>will be most holy<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “<supplied>will be</supplied> a holiness of holinesses”</note> Look, this <supplied>is</supplied> the law of the temple. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 43:13">13</verse-number>And these <supplied>are</supplied> the measurements of the altar in the cubits<note>Or “in long cubits”</note> (a cubit <supplied>is</supplied> a cubit and a handbreadth):<note>That is, about 18 inches (regular cubit) + 3 inches = 21 inches (long cubit)</note> now its gutter<note>Or “trench” (NJPS)</note> <idiom-start/>is a cubit<note>That is, 21 inches</note> in depth by a cubit<note>That is, 21 inches</note> in width<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the cubit and cubit <supplied>its</supplied> width”</note> and its rim along its edge all around is one span,<note>That is, 9 inches</note> and this <supplied>is</supplied> <supplied>also</supplied> the height of the altar. <verse-number id="Eze 43:14">14</verse-number>And from the gutter<note>Or “trench”</note> at the ground up to the lower ledge <supplied>is</supplied> two cubits,<note>That is, 3 feet 6 inches</note> and <supplied>its</supplied> width <supplied>is</supplied> one cubit,<note>That is, 21 inches</note> and from the small ledge up to the large ledge <supplied>is</supplied> four cubits,<note>That is, 7 feet</note> and <supplied>its</supplied> width <supplied>is</supplied> one cubit. <verse-number id="Eze 43:15">15</verse-number>And the altar hearth <supplied>was</supplied> four cubits,<note>That is, 7 feet</note> and from the altar hearth and <idiom-start/>upwards<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and to above”</note> <supplied>were</supplied> the four horns <supplied>of the altar</supplied>. <verse-number id="Eze 43:16">16</verse-number>And the altar hearth <supplied>was</supplied> <idiom-start/>twelve<idiom-end/><note>Literally “two ten”</note> <supplied>cubits</supplied> <supplied>in</supplied> length and <idiom-start/>twelve<idiom-end/><note>Literally “two ten”</note> <supplied>cubits</supplied> <supplied>in</supplied> width<note>That is, 21 feet square</note>; <supplied>it was</supplied> <idiom-start/>squared on its four sides<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “squared to the four of its sides”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 43:17">17</verse-number>And the ledge <supplied>was</supplied> <idiom-start/>fourteen<idiom-end/><note>Literally “four ten”</note> <supplied>cubits</supplied> in length with <idiom-start/>fourteen<idiom-end/><note>Literally “four ten”</note> <supplied>cubits</supplied> <supplied>its</supplied> width<note>That is, 24.5 feet on all four sides, a square</note> to <supplied>all</supplied> four of its sides, and a rim <supplied>was</supplied> all around it of one-half cubit.<note>That is, 10.5 inches</note> And the gutter<note>Or “trench”</note> for it <supplied>was</supplied> a cubit<note>That is, 21 inches</note> all around, and its steps <supplied>were</supplied> facing east.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 43:18">18</verse-number>And he said to me, “Son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> thus says the Lord Yahweh: ‘These <supplied>are</supplied> the statutes of the altar on the day <idiom-start/>when it is made<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to be made it”</note> to sacrifice a burnt offering on it and to sprinkle blood on it. <verse-number id="Eze 43:19">19</verse-number>And you must give to the Levitical priests who <supplied>are</supplied> from the offspring of Zadok, the <supplied>ones</supplied> <supplied>coming</supplied> near me,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh, “to serve me, a bull, <idiom-start/>a calf<idiom-end/><note>Literally “son of cattle,” or “son of <supplied>the</supplied> herd”</note> as <supplied>a</supplied> sin offering. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 43:20">20</verse-number>You must take some of its blood and put <supplied>it</supplied> on <idiom-start/>the four horns of the altar<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “on its four horns”</note> and the four corners of the ledge, and on the rim all around; thus you must purify it and make atonement for it. <verse-number id="Eze 43:21">21</verse-number>And you must take the bull, the sin offering, and you must burn it in the designated place of the temple outside of the holy place. <verse-number id="Eze 43:22">22</verse-number>And on the second day you must offer a he-goat without defect as <supplied>a</supplied> sin offering, and they must purify the altar <idiom-start/>like<idiom-end/><note>Literally “as that”</note> they purified with the bull. <verse-number id="Eze 43:23">23</verse-number><idiom-start/>When you are finished<idiom-end/><note>Literally “at your finishing”</note> from purifying, you must offer a bull, <idiom-start/>a calf<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “son of cattle,” or “son of <supplied>the</supplied> herd”</note> without defect, and a ram from the flock without defect. <verse-number id="Eze 43:24">24</verse-number>And you must bring them near <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of”</note> Yahweh, and the priests must throw salt on them, and they must offer them <supplied>as</supplied> a burnt offering to Yahweh. <verse-number id="Eze 43:25">25</verse-number><supplied>For</supplied> seven days you must provide a goat of sin offering for the day and a bull, <idiom-start/>a calf<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “son of cattle,” or “son of <supplied>the</supplied> herd”</note> and a ram from the flock without defect; you must provide <supplied>them</supplied>. <verse-number id="Eze 43:26">26</verse-number>Seven days they must purify the altar and they must cleanse it and <supplied>so</supplied> <idiom-start/>they will consecrate it<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “they must fill its hand”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 43:27">27</verse-number>And they will finish the days, <idiom-start/>and then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and it will happen”</note> on the eighth day and beyond <supplied>that</supplied> the priests will offer on the altar your burnt offerings and your fellowship offerings, and <supplied>then</supplied> I will be pleased with you,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh. </p>
		</chapter>