<chapter id="Eze 44">
			<pericope>The Prince, the Levites, and the Priests Described</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 44:1">1</verse-number>And he brought me back <supplied>by</supplied> the way of the outer gate of the sanctuary that <supplied>is</supplied> facing east, and it was shut. <verse-number id="Eze 44:2">2</verse-number>And Yahweh said to me, “This gate will be shut. It shall not be opened, and <idiom-start/>no one<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and a man not”</note> will go through it, for Yahweh, the God of Israel, has entered it, and it will be shut. <verse-number id="Eze 44:3">3</verse-number>The prince, he may sit in it to eat food <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of”</note> Yahweh; he will come from the way<note>Or “direction”</note> of the portico of the gate and by means of its way he will <supplied>also</supplied> go out.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 44:4">4</verse-number>Then he brought me <supplied>by</supplied> the way of the gate of the north to the front of the temple,<note>Or “house”</note> and I looked,<note>Or “saw”</note> and look! The glory of Yahweh filled the temple<note>Or “house”</note> of Yahweh, and I fell on my face. <verse-number id="Eze 44:5">5</verse-number>And Yahweh said, “Son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> set your heart<note>Or “pay close attention” or “listen closely”</note> and look with your eyes and with your ears hear <idiom-start/>everything<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all of which/what”</note> I <supplied>am</supplied> saying <supplied>to</supplied> you concerning all the statutes of the temple<note>Or “house”</note> of Yahweh and concerning all its laws,<note>According to the reading tradition (<i>Qere</i>); cf. BHS</note> and you must listen <supplied>with</supplied> your heart concerning the entrance of the temple<note>Or “house”</note> with all of <supplied>the</supplied> exits of the sanctuary. <verse-number id="Eze 44:6">6</verse-number>And you must say to <supplied>the</supplied> rebellious, to the house of Israel, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Enough for you, house of Israel, of<note>Or “from”</note> all of your detestable things! <verse-number id="Eze 44:7">7</verse-number>At<note>Or “in”</note> your bringing <idiom-start/>foreigners<idiom-end/><note>Literally “children/people of a foreign land”</note> <supplied>who are</supplied> uncircumcised of heart and uncircumcised of flesh to be in my sanctuary to profane it, my temple,<note>Or “house”</note> <idiom-start/>as you offered my food, fat, and blood<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “in/at your offering my food and fat and blood”</note> so<note>Or “and”</note> you broke my covenant by all of your detestable things. <verse-number id="Eze 44:8">8</verse-number>And you did not observe the responsibility of my sanctuary, but<note>Or “and”</note> you appointed <supplied>them</supplied><note>That is, foreigners</note> as the keepers of my responsibility in my sanctuary for you.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 44:9">9</verse-number>Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Every <idiom-start/>foreigner<idiom-end/><note>Literally “child of a foreign land”</note> uncircumcised of heart and uncircumcised of flesh shall not come into my sanctuary—<supplied>not</supplied> any of <supplied>the</supplied> <idiom-start/>foreigners<idiom-end/><note>Literally “child of a foreign land”</note> who <supplied>are</supplied> in the midst of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 44:10">10</verse-number><idiom-start/>But<idiom-end/><note>Literally “For if”</note> the Levites who removed themselves from me <idiom-start/>at the going astray of Israel<idiom-end/>,<note>Or “when Israel went astray”</note> who went astray from me <supplied>and went</supplied> after their idols, as a result they will bear their guilt. <verse-number id="Eze 44:11">11</verse-number>Then they will be<note>Or “may be”</note> in my sanctuary, <supplied>those</supplied> serving <supplied>in</supplied> my sanctuary, <supplied>as</supplied> sentries<note>Or “guards”</note> at the gates of the temple<note>Or “house”</note> and <supplied>as</supplied> <supplied>those</supplied> serving the temple;<note>Or “house”</note> they will slaughter the burnt offering and the sacrifice for the people, and they will stand <idiom-start/>before them<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of them”</note> to serve them, <verse-number id="Eze 44:12">12</verse-number><idiom-start/>because<idiom-end/><note>Literally “because that”</note> they used to serve them <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of”</note> their idols and they were for the house of Israel <supplied>like</supplied> a stumbling block of iniquity. Therefore <idiom-start/>I swore<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I raised my hand”</note> concerning them,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh, “<supplied>that</supplied> they will bear their iniquity. <verse-number id="Eze 44:13">13</verse-number>And they shall not approach me to serve as <supplied>a</supplied> priest for me and to come near to all of<note>Or “any of”</note> my holy objects, <idiom-start/>to the most holy objects<idiom-end/>, <note>Literally “to the holy objects of the holy objects”</note> and they will bear their disgrace and <supplied>the results of</supplied> their detestable things they have done. <verse-number id="Eze 44:14">14</verse-number>And I will appoint them <supplied>as</supplied> the keepers of the responsibility of<note>Or “toward”</note> the temple, for all of its work<note>Or “tasks”</note> and <idiom-start/>everything<idiom-end/> <note>Literally “all”</note>which will be done in it. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 44:15">15</verse-number>But the Levitical priests, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Zadok, who cared for the responsibility of my sanctuary <idiom-start/>when the Israelites went astray<idiom-end/><note>Literally “at going astray the children of Israel”</note> from me, they will approach me to serve me, and they will stand <idiom-start/>before me<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of me”</note> to offer to me fat and blood,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh. <verse-number id="Eze 44:16">16</verse-number>“They shall come to my sanctuary, and they shall approach my table to serve me, and they will observe my requirement. <verse-number id="Eze 44:17">17</verse-number><idiom-start/>And then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and it will happen”</note> <idiom-start/>when they come<idiom-end/><note>Literally “at their coming”</note> to the gates of the inner courtyards, they shall put on their<note>Hebrew “the”</note> inner linen garments and not wear wool <supplied>garments</supplied> <idiom-start/>when they serve<idiom-end/><note>Literally “at their serving”</note> in the gates of the inner courtyard and <idiom-start/>inside<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and toward”</note> the temple. <verse-number id="Eze 44:18">18</verse-number>Linen turbans shall be on their head and linen undergarments shall be on their waists; they shall not gird themselves with <supplied>material causing</supplied> perspiration. <verse-number id="Eze 44:19">19</verse-number>When they go out to the outer courtyard to the people, they must take off their garment in which they <supplied>were</supplied> serving, and they must place them <idiom-start/>in the holy chambers<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “in the chambers of the holiness”</note> and they must put on other <supplied>garments</supplied>, so that they will not make the people holy with their garments. <verse-number id="Eze 44:20">20</verse-number>And their head they shall not shave, or long hair they shall not let grow; short they shall clip their heads. <verse-number id="Eze 44:21">21</verse-number>And no priest shall drink wine when they come into the inner courtyard. <verse-number id="Eze 44:22">22</verse-number>And a widow or divorced <supplied>woman</supplied> they shall not take for themselves as wives, <idiom-start/>but only<idiom-end/><note>Literally “but if”</note> a virgin from the offspring of the house of Israel, or the widow who is a widow for a priest they may take. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 44:23">23</verse-number>And they will teach my people <supplied>the difference</supplied> between what is holy and what is unholy, and <supplied>the difference</supplied> between unclean and clean they must show them. <verse-number id="Eze 44:24">24</verse-number>And at a legal dispute they themselves shall stand to judge; employing<note>Or “with”</note> my judgments they shall judge it, and <supplied>with respect to</supplied> my laws and my statutes. All my festivals they shall keep and my Sabbaths they shall consecrate. <verse-number id="Eze 44:25">25</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>near a dead person<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and to a dead person of a man”</note> he<note>That is, the priest</note> shall not come to be defiled, <idiom-start/>but only<idiom-end/><note>Literally “but if”</note> for a father and for a mother and for a son and for a daughter, for a brother and for a sister <idiom-start/>who was not married<idiom-end/><note>Literally “who not she was for a man”</note> may they defile themselves. <verse-number id="Eze 44:26">26</verse-number>And, after his<note>That is, the priest</note> cleansing, they shall count for him seven days, <verse-number id="Eze 44:27">27</verse-number>and <supplied>then</supplied> on the day of his coming into the sanctuary to the inner courtyard to serve in the sanctuary, he shall offer his sin offering,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 44:28">28</verse-number>And <supplied>thus</supplied> it will be to them as <supplied>regards</supplied> inheritance, <supplied>that</supplied> I <supplied>am</supplied> their inheritance, and <supplied>so</supplied> you shall not give to them property in Israel; I <supplied>am</supplied> their property. <verse-number id="Eze 44:29">29</verse-number>The grain offering and the sin offering and the guilt offering, they themselves may eat them, and <supplied>also</supplied> all <supplied>the</supplied> consecrated possessions<note>Hebrew “possession”</note> in Israel will be theirs. <verse-number id="Eze 44:30">30</verse-number>And <supplied>also</supplied> what is first of all of <supplied>the</supplied> firstfruits of everything, and of all of <supplied>the</supplied> contribution of everything from all of your contributions, to the priest <idiom-start/>it belongs<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “it shall be”</note> and what is first of your dough you shall give to the priest, so that a blessing may rest on your house. <verse-number id="Eze 44:31">31</verse-number>Any dead body or mangled carcass from the birds<note>Hebrew “bird”</note> or from the animals,<note>Hebrew “animal”</note> the priests shall not eat.” </p>
		</chapter>