<chapter id="Eze 45">
			<pericope>Instructions about Divisions of the Renewed Land</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 45:1">1</verse-number>And when you allocate the land as an inheritance, you shall provide a contribution for Yahweh <supplied>as</supplied> a holy portion from the land, <supplied>its</supplied> length <supplied>being</supplied> twenty-five thousand <supplied>cubits</supplied><note>Or 8.33 miles</note> and <supplied>its</supplied> width ten thousand <supplied>cubits</supplied>;<note>Hebrew 3.5 miles; LXX reads 6.67 miles in width, or 20,000 cubits (cf. 45:3, 5; 48:9)</note> it <supplied>is</supplied> holy in all its territory, all around. <verse-number id="Eze 45:2">2</verse-number>And <supplied>there</supplied> shall be from this <supplied>area</supplied> five hundred <supplied>cubits</supplied><note>That is, “875 feet by 875 feet”</note> by five hundred <supplied>cubits</supplied>, squared all around, for the sanctuary; and fifty cubits<note>Hebrew “cubit”</note>﻿<note>That is, “87.5 feet”</note> <supplied>of</supplied> open space <supplied>shall be</supplied> for it all around <supplied>it</supplied>. <verse-number id="Eze 45:3">3</verse-number>And from this measured area you shall measure a length of twenty-five<note>According to the reading tradition (<i>Qere</i>)</note> thousand <supplied>cubits</supplied><note>That is, 8.33 miles; cf. 45:5</note> and a width of ten thousand <supplied>cubits</supplied>,<note>That is, 3.5 miles; cf. 45:5</note> and in it will be the sanctuary, <idiom-start/>the most holy place<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the holiness of holinesses”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 45:4">4</verse-number>It<note>Or “this area”</note> <supplied>is</supplied> a holy portion from the land; it will be for the priests, the servants of the sanctuary <idiom-start/>who approach<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the ones who approach”</note> to serve Yahweh, and it will be for them a place for houses and a holy place for the sanctuary. <verse-number id="Eze 45:5">5</verse-number>And <supplied>an area</supplied> twenty-five thousand <supplied>cubits</supplied> <supplied>in</supplied> length and ten thousand <supplied>cubits</supplied> <supplied>in</supplied> width will be for the Levites, the servants of the temple. <supplied>It will serve</supplied> <supplied>as</supplied> property for them <idiom-start/>as cities to dwell in<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “twenty chambers”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 45:6">6</verse-number>And <supplied>as</supplied> property of the city, you must set apart alongside the contribution of the sanctuary <supplied>a portion</supplied> five thousand <supplied>cubits</supplied><note>That is, 1.67 miles</note> in width and twenty-five thousand <supplied>cubits</supplied><note>That is, 8.33 miles</note> in length, <supplied>and</supplied> it shall be for the entire house of Israel. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 45:7">7</verse-number>And <supplied>a portion will be</supplied> for<note>Hebrew “to”</note> the prince <idiom-start/>on both sides<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from this and from this”</note> of <idiom-start/>the holy district<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the contribution of the holiness”</note> and <supplied>both sides</supplied> of the property of the city, <supplied>and</supplied> <idiom-start/>alongside<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the front of”</note> the property of the city <idiom-start/>on the west<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from/on the side of <supplied>the</supplied> sea”</note> and <supplied>alongside the property</supplied> <idiom-start/>on the east<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “from/on the side of east”</note> And <supplied>also</supplied> <supplied>its</supplied> length<note>Or “portion”</note> <idiom-start/>corresponds to one of the tribal portions to the west<idiom-end/><note>Literally “corresponding <supplied>to</supplied> one of the portions from <supplied>the</supplied> boundary of <supplied>the</supplied> sea”</note> <supplied>running</supplied> <idiom-start/>to the eastern border<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to <supplied>the</supplied> boundary of <supplied>the</supplied> east”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 45:8">8</verse-number><supplied>This</supplied> shall be to him <idiom-start/>with respect to the land<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the land”</note> as property in Israel; <supplied>and so</supplied> my princes shall not again oppress my people, but they shall give the land to the house of Israel according to their tribes.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 45:9">9</verse-number>Thus says the Lord Yahweh, “Enough <supplied>of this</supplied> for you, the princes of Israel; put away violence and destruction and do justice and righteousness; revoke your <supplied>acts of</supplied> dispossession from upon<note>Or “against”</note> my people!” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh. <verse-number id="Eze 45:10">10</verse-number><supplied>There</supplied> shall be for you <idiom-start/>an honest set of scales<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a set of scales of justice/honesty”</note> and <idiom-start/>an honest ephah<idiom-end/><note>Literally “an ephah of honesty”</note> and <idiom-start/>an honest bath<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “a bath of honesty”; a bath is a liquid measure</note> <verse-number id="Eze 45:11">11</verse-number>The ephah and the bath shall be one unit of measurement;<note>Or “shall be the same size”</note> the tenth part of the homer <supplied>is</supplied> the bath, and the tenth of the homer <supplied>is</supplied> the ephah; <supplied>so</supplied> the homer shall be its<note>Or “the”</note> unit of measurement. <verse-number id="Eze 45:12">12</verse-number>And the shekel <supplied>shall weigh</supplied> twenty gerahs, twenty shekels<note>Hebrew “shekel”</note> and five and twenty shekels<note>Hebrew “shekel”</note> <supplied>and</supplied> ten and five shekels,<note>Hebrew “shekel”</note> <supplied>that</supplied> shall make the mina for you.<note>Meaning of Hebrew uncertain</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 45:13">13</verse-number>This <supplied>is</supplied> the contribution <supplied>offering</supplied> which you shall present: a sixth of the ephah from a<note>Or “each”; literally “the”</note> homer of wheat, and a<note>Literally “the”</note> sixth of the ephah from a<note>Literally “the”</note> homer of barley. <verse-number id="Eze 45:14">14</verse-number>And the quota of the olive oil, the bath <supplied>of</supplied> the olive oil, <supplied>is</supplied> the tenth part of a bath from a kor, <supplied>which</supplied> <supplied>is</supplied> ten baths, <supplied>or</supplied> a homer—for ten baths <supplied>are equal to</supplied> a homer. <verse-number id="Eze 45:15">15</verse-number>And one<note>Or “a”</note> sheep from the flock from <supplied>among</supplied> two hundred from the pastures of Israel <supplied>will be taken</supplied> as <supplied>a</supplied> grain offering and as <supplied>a</supplied> burnt offering <supplied>and</supplied> <supplied>as</supplied> <supplied>a</supplied> fellowship offering to make atonement for them,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh. <verse-number id="Eze 45:16">16</verse-number>“All of the people of the land shall join <supplied>in</supplied><note>Or “participate/ take part in”</note> to this contribution with<note>Or possibly “for/to”</note> the prince in Israel. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 45:17">17</verse-number>“But on the prince shall be <supplied>the responsibility for</supplied> the burnt offerings, and the grain offering, and the libation at the feasts, and at the New Moon festivals, and at<note>Or “on”</note> the Sabbaths at all of the assemblies of the house of Israel; he shall provide the sin offering, and the grain offering, and the burnt offering, and the fellowship offering to make atonement for the house of Israel. <verse-number id="Eze 45:18">18</verse-number>Thus says the Lord Yahweh: ‘On the first <supplied>month</supplied> on the first <supplied>day</supplied> of the month, you shall take a bull, <idiom-start/>a calf<idiom-end/><note>Literally “son of cattle,” or “son of <supplied>the</supplied> herd”</note> without defect, and you shall purify the sanctuary. <verse-number id="Eze 45:19">19</verse-number>And the priest shall take from the blood of the sin offering, and he shall put <supplied>it</supplied> on the doorframe of the temple<note>Or “house”</note> and on the four corners of the ledge of the altar and on the doorframe of the gate of the inner courtyard. <verse-number id="Eze 45:20">20</verse-number>And so you shall do on the seventh <supplied>day</supplied> in the month for anyone doing wrong inadvertently or due to ignorance, and <supplied>so</supplied> you must make atonement for the temple.<note>Or “house”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 45:21">21</verse-number>In the first <supplied>month</supplied>, on the <idiom-start/>fourteenth<idiom-end/><note>Literally “four ten”</note> day of the month, you shall have the Passover, <supplied>a</supplied> feast <supplied>lasting for</supplied> <idiom-start/>seven days<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “a week of days”</note> <supplied>when</supplied> you shall eat unleavened breads. <verse-number id="Eze 45:22">22</verse-number>And the prince shall provide on that day for himself<note>Hebrew “him”</note> and for all of the people of the land a bull <supplied>as</supplied> <supplied>a</supplied> sin offering. <verse-number id="Eze 45:23">23</verse-number>And <supplied>during</supplied> the seven days of the religious feast he shall provide <supplied>as</supplied> a burnt offering to Yahweh seven bulls and seven rams without defect for each of the seven days, and <supplied>as</supplied> a sin offering a he-goat for each day. <verse-number id="Eze 45:24">24</verse-number>And <supplied>as a</supplied> grain offering, an ephah for<note>Hebrew “to”</note> the bull and an ephah for<note>Hebrew “to”</note> the ram he must provide, and a hin of olive oil for <idiom-start/>each<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the”</note> ephah. <verse-number id="Eze 45:25">25</verse-number>In the seventh <supplied>month</supplied>, on the <idiom-start/>fifteenth<idiom-end/><note>Literally “five ten”</note> day of the month, during the feast, he shall provide just as <supplied>he has for</supplied> these seven days, as <supplied>he did for</supplied> the sin offering, <supplied>as he did for</supplied> the burnt offering, and <supplied>as he did</supplied> for the grain offering, and <supplied>as he did</supplied> for the olive oil.’ ” </p>
		</chapter>