<chapter id="Eze 46">
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 46">46</verse-number><verse-number id="Eze 46:1">1</verse-number> Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “The gate of the inner courtyard facing east must be shut <supplied>on</supplied><note>Or “during”</note> the six of the days for work, but on the day of the Sabbath it must be opened and on the day of the new moon it must be opened. <verse-number id="Eze 46:2">2</verse-number>And the prince shall come <supplied>by</supplied> way of the portico of the gate from <supplied>the</supplied> outside, and he shall stand at the doorframe of the gate and the priests shall prepare his burnt offering and his fellowship offerings, and he shall bow down at the threshold of the gate. Then he shall go out, but the gate shall not be closed until the evening. <verse-number id="Eze 46:3">3</verse-number>And the people of the land will bow down <supplied>at</supplied> the doorway of that gate on the Sabbaths and on the new moons <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of”</note> Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 46:4">4</verse-number>And the burnt offering which the prince will offer to Yahweh on the Sabbath day <supplied>must be</supplied> six male lambs without defect and a ram without defect. <verse-number id="Eze 46:5">5</verse-number>And <supplied>the</supplied> grain offering <supplied>he will give</supplied> <supplied>shall be</supplied> an ephah <idiom-start/>for each ram<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to the ram”</note> and for the male lambs <supplied>the</supplied> grain offering <supplied>shall be</supplied> <idiom-start/>as much as he wants to give<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the gift of his hand”</note> and a hin of olive oil <idiom-start/>for each ephah<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to the ephah”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 46:6">6</verse-number>And on the day of the new moon <supplied>he will offer</supplied> a bull, <idiom-start/>a calf<idiom-end/><note>Literally “son of cattle,” or “son of <supplied>the</supplied> herd”</note> without defect and six male lambs and a ram; they must be without defect. <verse-number id="Eze 46:7">7</verse-number>And an ephah for each bull and an ephah for the ram he must provide <supplied>as</supplied> a grain offering, and <supplied>also</supplied> for the male lambs <idiom-start/>as much as he can afford<idiom-end/><note>Literally “as that it stretches out his hand”</note> and a hin <supplied>of</supplied> olive oil for each ephah. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 46:8">8</verse-number>And when the prince comes, on<note>Or “by”</note> the way of the portico of the gate he shall come and by this<note>Or “his”</note> way he shall go out. <verse-number id="Eze 46:9">9</verse-number>And when the people of the land come <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of”</note> Yahweh at the festivals, <supplied>the</supplied> one coming <supplied>by</supplied> way of <supplied>the</supplied> gate of <supplied>the</supplied> north to bow down<note>Or “to worship”</note> must go out <supplied>by</supplied> <supplied>the</supplied> way of <supplied>the</supplied> gate of <supplied>the</supplied> south, and the <supplied>one</supplied> coming <supplied>by</supplied> way of <supplied>the</supplied> gate of <supplied>the</supplied> south must go out <supplied>by the</supplied> way of <supplied>the</supplied> gate of <supplied>the</supplied> north, <supplied>so</supplied> he must not return <supplied>by</supplied> the way of the gate <supplied>by</supplied> which he came,<note>Hebrew “came by it”</note> but before it he<note>According to the reading tradition (<i>Qere</i>)</note> shall go out opposite it. <verse-number id="Eze 46:10">10</verse-number>And the prince <supplied>will be</supplied> in the midst of them; he will come in when they come in, and when they go out he will go out. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 46:11">11</verse-number>And at the festivals and at the appointed times, the grain offering will be an ephah with a bull and an ephah with the ram and with the male lambs, <idiom-start/>as much as he wants to give<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the gift of his hand”</note> and a hin of olive oil <idiom-start/>for each ephah<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to the ephah”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 46:12">12</verse-number>And when the prince makes a freewill offering, a burnt offering, or a fellowship offering <supplied>as</supplied> a freewill offering to Yahweh, the gate facing east will be open for him. And he must offer his burnt offering and his fellowship offering <idiom-start/>just as<idiom-end/><note>Literally “as that”</note> he does on the day of the Sabbath, and <supplied>then</supplied> he must go out and the gate will shut <idiom-start/>after he goes out<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “after his going out”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 46:13">13</verse-number>And a male lamb, <idiom-start/>a yearling<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a son of his year”</note> without defect, he must provide as a burnt offering <idiom-start/>daily<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for the day”</note> for Yahweh; <idiom-start/>every morning<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the morning in the morning”</note> he must provide it. <verse-number id="Eze 46:14">14</verse-number>And <supplied>a</supplied> grain offering he must provide in addition to it <idiom-start/>every morning<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “in the morning in the morning”</note> a<note>Hebrew “the”</note> sixth of an<note>Hebrew “the”</note> ephah and a third of a hin of olive oil to moisten the finely milled flour <supplied>as</supplied> a grain offering to Yahweh <idiom-start/>as a perpetual statute<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “regulations of everlasting continually”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 46:15">15</verse-number><supplied>So</supplied> they must provide the male lamb and the grain offering and the olive oil <idiom-start/>every morning<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the morning in the morning”</note> <idiom-start/>as a regular burnt offering<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “as burnt offering of regularity/continuity”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 46:16">16</verse-number>Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “If the prince gives a gift to any <supplied>one</supplied> from <supplied>among</supplied> his sons, it <supplied>is</supplied> his inheritance <supplied>and</supplied> it will belong<note>Hebrew “be”</note> to his sons; it is their possession as an inheritance. <verse-number id="Eze 46:17">17</verse-number>And if he give a gift from his inheritance to one from <supplied>among</supplied> his servants, then it will belong<note>Hebrew “be”</note> to him until the year of release,<note>That is, the Year of Jubilee</note> and <supplied>then</supplied> it will return to the prince. His inheritance <supplied>with respect to</supplied> his sons will be only for them. <verse-number id="Eze 46:18">18</verse-number>But the prince shall not take from the inheritance of the people to rob<note>Or “oppress”</note> them, <supplied>separating them</supplied> from their property; from his <supplied>own</supplied> property he shall bestow an inheritance on his sons, so that my people will not be driven away, any one, from his property.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 46:19">19</verse-number>Then he brought me through the entrance which <supplied>was</supplied> on the side of the gate <idiom-start/>to the holy chambers<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the chamber of the holiness”</note> to the priests; <supplied>the chambers</supplied> were facing northwards and, look, there <supplied>was</supplied> a place at the extreme end westwards. <verse-number id="Eze 46:20">20</verse-number>And he said to me, “This <supplied>is</supplied> the place where the priests will boil the guilt offering and the sin offering, <supplied>and</supplied> where they shall bake the grain offering <supplied>in order</supplied> not to bring <supplied>them</supplied> out to the outer courtyard to make the people holy. <verse-number id="Eze 46:21">21</verse-number>And he brought me to the outer courtyard and led me past the four corners of the courtyard; and look, <idiom-start/>there was a courtyard in each corner of the courtyard<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “a courtyard in the corner of the courtyard, a courtyard in the corner of the courtyard”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 46:22">22</verse-number>In the four corners of the courtyard <supplied>were</supplied> small<note>Hebrew uncertain</note> courtyards forty <supplied>cubits</supplied> <supplied>in</supplied> length and thirty <supplied>cubits</supplied> <supplied>in</supplied> width, <supplied>each with</supplied> <idiom-start/>the same measurements<idiom-end/><note>Literally “measurement one”</note> for the four of them with corners.<note>Or “<supplied>being</supplied> cornered”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 46:23">23</verse-number>And a row <supplied>was</supplied> all around inside<note>Hebrew “in”</note> them, and cooking-places <supplied>were</supplied> made under the rows of stones<note>Possibly some kind of stone ledge</note> all around. <verse-number id="Eze 46:24">24</verse-number>And he said to me, “These <supplied>are</supplied> the houses for<note>Hebrew “of”</note> cooking, where <supplied>the ones</supplied> serving the temple shall cook the sacrifices of the people.” </p>
		</chapter>