<chapter id="Eze 47">
			<pericope>River of the Temple, Division of the Land and Its Boundaries</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 47:1">1</verse-number>And he brought me back to the doorway of the temple and, look! There was water coming out from under the threshold of the temple eastward, because the face of the temple <supplied>was</supplied> eastwards; and the water was coming down from under the south side of the temple, from south of the altar. <verse-number id="Eze 47:2">2</verse-number>And he brought me out <supplied>by the way</supplied> of <supplied>the</supplied> north gate and he led me around <supplied>by the</supplied> <idiom-start/>way leading to the outside of the outer gate<idiom-end/><note>Literally “way of <supplied>the</supplied> outside to the gate of the outside”</note> <supplied>by</supplied> way of the <supplied>gate</supplied> facing east, and look, there was water trickling from the south side. <verse-number id="Eze 47:3">3</verse-number>As the man went eastward a measuring line <supplied>was</supplied> in his hand, and he measured a thousand <idiom-start/>cubits<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “in the cubit”; about 1,750 feet</note> And he led me through <supplied>on</supplied> into the water; <supplied>it was</supplied> <idiom-start/>ankle deep<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “water of ankles”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 47:4">4</verse-number>And he measured a thousand <supplied>cubits</supplied>,<note>About 1,750 feet</note> and he brought me over into the waters <supplied>and</supplied> <supplied>it was</supplied> <idiom-start/>knee deep<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “water of knees”</note> And he measured a thousand <supplied>cubits</supplied>,<note>About 1,750 feet</note> and he brought me over <supplied>into</supplied> the waters <supplied>and</supplied> <supplied>it was</supplied> <idiom-start/>waist deep<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “water of waist”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 47:5">5</verse-number>And he measured a thousand <supplied>cubits</supplied>,<note>About 1,750 feet</note> <supplied>and</supplied> <supplied>it became</supplied> a stream that I was not able to cross, because the water rose, <idiom-start/>waters a person could swim in<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “water of swimming”</note> <supplied>and became</supplied> a stream that could not be crossed. <verse-number id="Eze 47:6">6</verse-number>And he asked me, “Son of man,<note>Or “mortal,” or “son of humankind”</note> did you see <supplied>this</supplied>?” And he made me go, and he brought me back <supplied>along</supplied> the bank of the stream. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 47:7">7</verse-number><idiom-start/>When I returned<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “At my returning”</note> then look! On the bank of the river <supplied>were</supplied> many trees <idiom-start/>on both sides<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “from this and from this”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 47:8">8</verse-number>And he said to me, “These waters <supplied>are</supplied> going out to the eastern region, and they go down to the <idiom-start/>Jordan Valley<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “Arabah”</note> and they come <supplied>to</supplied> the sea<note>Clearly refers to the Dead Sea</note> <supplied>and flow</supplied> into the sea <supplied>where</supplied> <idiom-start/>they issue out<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “being brought out/are issued out”</note> and the waters <supplied>in the sea</supplied> will be healed.<note>Or “made fresh”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 47:9">9</verse-number>And then every living creature <supplied>with</supplied> which it teems,<note>Or “swarms”</note> <idiom-start/>to every place the waters come<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to all of which they come there the water”</note> it will live; <supplied>and</supplied> very many fish will live because these waters came there, and <supplied>so</supplied> the <supplied>water</supplied> will be healed<note>Or “fresh”</note> and everything <supplied>will be</supplied> alive <idiom-start/>everywhere that<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all that”</note> <idiom-start/>the stream will come<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “that <supplied>it</supplied> will come there the stream”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 47:10">10</verse-number>And then fishers<note>Or “fishermen”</note> from En Gedi and <supplied>on</supplied> up to En Eglaim will stand beside it, a sea-girt drying yard for nets; their fish for the dragnets will be <idiom-start/>of every kind<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to the”</note> like the fish of the great sea,<note>That is, the Mediterranean</note> <supplied>and</supplied> very many. <verse-number id="Eze 47:11">11</verse-number>But its marshes and its swamps will not be cured, for they were given for salt. <verse-number id="Eze 47:12">12</verse-number>And along the stream will go up on its banks <idiom-start/>from both sides<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from this and from this”</note> every tree <idiom-start/>producing food<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “of food”</note> its leaf will not wither and it will not cease <supplied>producing</supplied> its fruit. <idiom-start/>Every month<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for its months”</note> it will bear early fruit, for its waters <supplied>are</supplied> going out from the sanctuary, and its fruit will be as food, and its leaf for healing.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 47:13">13</verse-number>Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “This <supplied>is</supplied> the boundary <supplied>by</supplied> which you shall distribute the land for <idiom-start/>the twelve<idiom-end/><note>Literally “two ten”</note> tribes of Israel: Two shares <supplied>shall be for</supplied> Joseph. <verse-number id="Eze 47:14">14</verse-number>And you must take possession of it, each <supplied>one</supplied> <supplied>a share</supplied> like his brother, <supplied>of this land</supplied> which <idiom-start/>I swore<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I raised my hand”</note> to give it to your fathers, and <supplied>so</supplied> this land shall fall to you as an inheritance. <verse-number id="Eze 47:15">15</verse-number>And<note>Or “Bow”</note> this <supplied>is</supplied> the boundary of the land: <idiom-start/>On the north side<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to the side of <supplied>the</supplied> north”</note> from the great sea <supplied>by</supplied> the way of Hethlon <idiom-start/>until you come to Zedad<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to the arriving at Zedad”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 47:16">16</verse-number>Hamath<note>Or “Lebo-Hamath to Zeded” (cf. NRSV, NJPS)</note> <supplied>to</supplied> Berothath <supplied>to</supplied> Sibraim, which <supplied>is</supplied><note>Or “are”</note> between the boundary of Damascus and the boundary of Hamath, <supplied>on to</supplied> Hazer Hatticon, which <supplied>is</supplied> on the boundary of Hauran. <verse-number id="Eze 47:17">17</verse-number>And <supplied>so</supplied> <supplied>the</supplied> boundary will be from the sea<note>That is, the Mediterranean</note> to Hazar Enan <supplied>at</supplied> the boundary of Damascus northwards and the boundary of Hamath <supplied>to the north</supplied>, and this <supplied>is the boundary on the</supplied> side of <supplied>the</supplied> north. <verse-number id="Eze 47:18">18</verse-number><idiom-start/>And the eastern boundary<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and <supplied>the</supplied> side of <supplied>the</supplied> east”</note> <supplied>will be</supplied> between Hauran and Damascus, and from between Gilead and the land of Israel <supplied>along</supplied> the Jordan <supplied>River</supplied> from<note>Or “to”</note> <supplied>the</supplied> boundary on the eastern sea to Tamar. And<note>Or “Now”</note> <idiom-start/>this is the border on the east<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “and this <supplied>is the</supplied> side of <supplied>the</supplied> east”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 47:19">19</verse-number><idiom-start/>And on the south side the border<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and the side of the south <supplied>to</supplied> south”</note> <supplied>will run</supplied> from Tamar up to the waters <supplied>of</supplied> Meribot Kadesh <supplied>and along</supplied> the wadi<note>That is, the Wadi of Egypt</note> to the Great Sea.<note>That is, the Mediterranean</note> And this <supplied>is</supplied> <idiom-start/>the boundary to the south<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “and this <supplied>is</supplied> the side of south <supplied>to</supplied> the south”</note> <verse-number id="Eze 47:20">20</verse-number><idiom-start/>And on the west side<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and the side of the west”</note> the Great Sea<note>That is, the Mediterranean</note> <supplied>shall be</supplied> the boundary up to opposite Lebo-Hamath. <idiom-start/>This is the western boundary<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “this <supplied>is the</supplied> side of <supplied>the</supplied> west”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Eze 47:21">21</verse-number>You shall divide this land for yourselves according to the tribes of Israel. <verse-number id="Eze 47:22">22</verse-number>And then you shall allocate it as an inheritance for yourselves and for the aliens dwelling as aliens in the midst of you who have children in the midst of you, and <supplied>so</supplied> they shall be to you <supplied>just</supplied> like full citizens among the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> With you they shall be allotted with an inheritance in the midst of the tribes of Israel. <verse-number id="Eze 47:23">23</verse-number>And then in the tribe <supplied>in</supplied> which an alien who is with you dwells, there you shall give his inheritance,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh. </p>
		</chapter>