<chapter id="Je 1">
			<pericope>Yahweh Appoints Jeremiah as a Prophet to the Nations</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 1:1">1</verse-number>The words of Jeremiah, the son of Hilkiah, among the priests who <supplied>were</supplied> in Anathoth, in the land of Benjamin, <verse-number id="Je 1:2">2</verse-number><supplied>to</supplied> whom the word of Yahweh came in the days of Josiah the son of Amon, the king of Judah, in the thirteenth year of his reign. <verse-number id="Je 1:3">3</verse-number>It came also in the days of Jehoiakim, the son of Josiah, the king of Judah, until the end of the eleventh year of Zedekiah, the son of Josiah, the king of Judah, until the exile of Jerusalem in the fifth month. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 1:4">4</verse-number>And the word of Yahweh came to me, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 1:5">5</verse-number>“Before I formed you in the womb I knew you, </li1>
				<li1>and before you came out from <supplied>the</supplied> womb I consecrated you; </li1>
				<li1>I appointed you <supplied>as</supplied> a prophet to the nations.” </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 1:6">6</verse-number>Then I said, “Ah, Lord Yahweh! Look, I do not know <supplied>how</supplied> to speak, for I <supplied>am</supplied> a youth.”<note>Or “boy”</note> <verse-number id="Je 1:7">7</verse-number>But Yahweh said to me, “You must not say, ‘I <supplied>am</supplied> a youth,’<note>Or “boy”</note> for to <idiom-start/>whomever<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all of whom”</note> I send you, you will go, and <idiom-start/>whatever<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all of that”</note> I command you, you will speak. <verse-number id="Je 1:8">8</verse-number><idiom-start/>Do not be afraid of them<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “you must not be afraid from the faces of them”</note> for I <supplied>am</supplied> with you to deliver you,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> Yahweh. <verse-number id="Je 1:9">9</verse-number>Then Yahweh stretched out his hand and he touched my mouth, and Yahweh said to me, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Look, I have put my words in your mouth. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 1:10">10</verse-number>See, I appoint you this day over the nations </li1>
				<li1>and over the kingdoms, </li1>
				<li1>to pluck up and to pull down, </li1>
				<li1>and to destroy and to tear down, </li1>
				<li1>to build and to plant.” </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Yahweh Confirms Jeremiah’s Call</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 1:11">11</verse-number>And the word of Yahweh came to me, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> “What <supplied>are</supplied> you seeing, Jeremiah?” And I said, “I <supplied>am</supplied> seeing a branch of an almond tree.” <verse-number id="Je 1:12">12</verse-number>Then Yahweh said to me, “You did well to see, for I <supplied>am</supplied> watching over my word to perform it.” <verse-number id="Je 1:13">13</verse-number>And the word of Yahweh came to me a second <supplied>time</supplied>, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> “What <supplied>are</supplied> you seeing?” And I said, “I <supplied>am</supplied> seeing a <idiom-start/>boiling<idiom-end/><note>Literally “blown upon”</note> pot, and its face <supplied>is</supplied> from <supplied>the</supplied> face of <supplied>the</supplied> north.” <verse-number id="Je 1:14">14</verse-number>Then Yahweh said to me, “From <supplied>the</supplied> north disaster will be unleashed<note>Or “opened”</note> on all the inhabitants of the land. <verse-number id="Je 1:15">15</verse-number>For, look, I <supplied>am</supplied> calling to all <supplied>the</supplied> clans<note>Or “families”</note> of <supplied>the</supplied> kingdoms of <supplied>the</supplied> north,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh, “and they will come and set each one his throne <supplied>at</supplied> the entrance of the gates of Jerusalem, and against all its surrounding walls, and against all the cities of Judah. <verse-number id="Je 1:16">16</verse-number>And I will pass<note>Or “pronounce”</note> my judgments on them because of all their wickedness <supplied>in</supplied> that they have forsaken me, and they made sacrifices to other gods, and they bowed in worship to the works of their hands. <verse-number id="Je 1:17">17</verse-number>But you, you must gird your loins, and stand, and speak to them all that I command you. <idiom-start/>Do not be afraid of them<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “You must not be filled with terror from the faces of them”</note> or I will shatter you <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the faces of”</note> them. <verse-number id="Je 1:18">18</verse-number>Now look, I have made you <idiom-start/>today<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the day”</note> as a fortified city and as an iron pillar and a bronze wall<note>Hebrew “walls”</note> against all the land, against the kings of Judah, against its princes, against its priests, and against the people of the land. <verse-number id="Je 1:19">19</verse-number>And they will fight against you but they will not prevail against you, for I <supplied>am</supplied> with you,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh, “to deliver you.” </p>
		</chapter>