<chapter id="Je 9">
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 9">9</verse-number><verse-number id="Je 9:1">1</verse-number> <note><cite title="BibleLEB2: Je 9:1–26">Jeremiah 9:1–26 </cite>in the English Bible is 8:23–9:25 in the Hebrew Bible</note> <idiom-start/>Oh that my head were waters<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “Who he gives my head waters”</note> </li1>
				<li2>and my eyes a fountain of tears, </li2>
				<li1>so that I might weep day and night, </li1>
				<li2><supplied>for</supplied> the slain of the daughter of my people. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 9:2">2</verse-number><idiom-start/>Oh that I had<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Who he gives me”</note> in the desert a place of overnight lodging for travelers, </li1>
				<li2>that I may leave my people and go from them, </li2>
				<li1>for all of them <supplied>are</supplied> adulterers, </li1>
				<li2>a band of traitors. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 9:3">3</verse-number>And they bend their tongue <supplied>like</supplied> their bow, </li1>
				<li2><supplied>for</supplied> falsehood and not truth is superior in the land, </li2>
				<li1>for they go forth<note>Or “proceed”</note> from evil to evil, </li1>
				<li2>and they do not know me,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A Nation Characterized by Deceit</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 9:4">4</verse-number>“Let everyone be on your guard against his neighbor, </li1>
				<li2>and you must not trust in any brother, </li2>
				<li1>for everyone surely betrays, </li1>
				<li2>and every neighbor goes about <supplied>with</supplied> slander. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 9:5">5</verse-number>And everyone deceives his neighbor, </li1>
				<li2>and they do not speak <supplied>the</supplied> truth, </li2>
				<li1>they have taught their tongues<note>Hebrew “tongue”</note> to speak lies,<note>Hebrew “lie”</note> </li1>
				<li2>they are tired <supplied>from</supplied> going astray. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 9:6">6</verse-number>Your dwelling <supplied>is</supplied> in the midst of deceit, </li1>
				<li2>upon<note>Or “through”</note> deceit they refuse to know me,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 9:7">7</verse-number>Therefore, thus says Yahweh of hosts: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Look, I <supplied>am</supplied> about to refine them, </li1>
				<li2>and I will test them, </li2>
				<li1>for what else can I do, </li1>
				<li2>because of the <idiom-start/>presence<idiom-end/><note>Literally “faces”</note> of the daughter of my people? </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 9:8">8</verse-number>Their tongue <supplied>is</supplied> a murderous arrow, </li1>
				<li2>it speaks deceit. </li2>
				<li1>With his mouth he speaks peace with his neighbor, </li1>
				<li2>but in his inner parts he sets up his ambush. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 9:9">9</verse-number>Because of these <supplied>things</supplied> shall I not punish them?” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh, </li1>
				<li1>“On a nation that <supplied>is</supplied> like this shall I not take revenge? </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 9:10">10</verse-number>For the mountains I lift up weeping and wailing, </li1>
				<li2>and for <supplied>the</supplied> pastures of <supplied>the</supplied> desert a lament, </li2>
				<li1>because they are laid waste so that no man passes through. </li1>
				<li2>And <supplied>the</supplied> sounds<note>Hebrew “sound”</note> of cattle are not heard, </li2>
				<li1>from <supplied>the</supplied> birds<note>Hebrew “bird”</note> of heaven to <supplied>the</supplied> animals<note>Hebrew “animal”</note> </li1>
				<li2>they have fled, they are gone. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 9:11">11</verse-number>And I will make Jerusalem as heaps <supplied>of ruins</supplied>, a lair of jackals, </li1>
				<li2>and the towns of Judah I will make a desolation, <idiom-start/>without inhabitants<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “from no inhabitant”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 9:12">12</verse-number>Who <supplied>is</supplied> the wise man that can understand this? </li1>
				<li2>And to whom has the mouth of Yahweh spoken, so that he may declare it? </li2>
				<li1>Why is the land destroyed? </li1>
				<li2>It is laid waste like the desert<note>Or “wilderness”</note> so that no one passes through.” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Nation is Judged by Yahweh</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 9:13">13</verse-number>And Yahweh said, “Because of their forsaking my law that I set <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of”</note> them, and they have not obeyed my voice, and have not walked in it, <verse-number id="Je 9:14">14</verse-number>but they went after the stubbornness of their heart, and after the Baals, which their ancestors<note>Or “fathers”</note> taught them.” <verse-number id="Je 9:15">15</verse-number>Therefore thus says Yahweh of hosts, the God of Israel, “Look, I <supplied>am</supplied> feeding this people wormwood, and providing drink for them, water of poison, <verse-number id="Je 9:16">16</verse-number>and I will scatter them among the nations that they have not known, they and their ancestors,<note>Or “fathers”</note> and I will send the sword after them until I bring them to an end.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 9:17">17</verse-number>Thus says Yahweh of hosts: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Consider closely, and call for the wailing women, so that they come, </li1>
				<li2>and for the skillful women, so that they come. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 9:18">18</verse-number>And let them hasten, </li1>
				<li2>and let them lift up wailing over us, </li2>
				<li1>so that our eyes may melt <supplied>with</supplied> tears, </li1>
				<li2>and our eyelids may flow <supplied>with</supplied> water. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 9:19">19</verse-number>For a sound of wailing is heard from Zion, </li1>
				<li2>‘How we are devastated! </li2>
				<li1>We are very ashamed because we have left the land, </li1>
				<li2>because they have overthrown our dwelling places.’ </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 9:20">20</verse-number>For hear, <supplied>O</supplied> women, the word of Yahweh, </li1>
				<li2>and let your ear receive the word of his mouth, </li2>
				<li1>and teach your daughters a lamentation, </li1>
				<li2>and each woman her neighbor a lament. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 9:21">21</verse-number>For death has come into our windows, </li1>
				<li2>it has entered into our fortresses, </li2>
				<li1>to cut off <supplied>the</supplied> children<note>Hebrew “child”</note> from <supplied>the</supplied> streets,<note>Hebrew “street”</note> </li1>
				<li2><supplied>the</supplied> young men from <supplied>the</supplied> public squares. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 9:22">22</verse-number>Speak, ‘thus <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“The dead body of the human will fall </li1>
				<li2>like dung upon the surface of the field, </li2>
				<li1>and like cut grain behind the reaper, </li1>
				<li2>and there is no <supplied>one who</supplied> gathers.” ’ ” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Things in Which Yahweh Delights</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 9:23">23</verse-number>Thus says Yahweh, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“<supplied>The</supplied> wise man must not boast in his wisdom, </li1>
				<li2>and the warrior must not boast in his might, </li2>
				<li1><supplied>the</supplied> wealthy man must not boast in his wealth. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 9:24">24</verse-number><idiom-start/>But only<idiom-end/><note>Literally “But it”</note> in this must the one who boasts boast, </li1>
				<li2><supplied>that</supplied> he has insight, </li2>
				<li1>and <supplied>that</supplied> he knows me, </li1>
				<li2>that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh, </li2>
				<li1>showing loyal love, justice, and righteousness on the earth, </li1>
				<li2>for in these <supplied>things</supplied> I delight,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Way of the Nations</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 9:25">25</verse-number>“Look, days <supplied>are</supplied> coming,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh, “and I will call into account all those who are circumcised in <supplied>the</supplied> foreskin: <verse-number id="Je 9:26">26</verse-number>Egypt, Judah, and Edom, and the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Ammon”</note> and Moab, and all those who are trimmed to <supplied>the</supplied> side, those who live in the desert,<note>Or “wilderness”</note> for all the nations <supplied>are</supplied> uncircumcised, and all the house of Israel <supplied>are</supplied> uncircumcised of heart.” </p>
		</chapter>