<chapter id="Je 11">
			<pericope>The Broken Covenant</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 11:1">1</verse-number>The word that came to Jeremiah from Yahweh, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Je 11:2">2</verse-number>“Hear the words of this covenant, and speak to the <idiom-start/>people<idiom-end/><note>Literally “man”</note> of Judah and to the inhabitants of Jerusalem, <verse-number id="Je 11:3">3</verse-number>and say to them, ‘Thus says Yahweh, the God of Israel: “The man is cursed who does not obey the words of this covenant, <verse-number id="Je 11:4">4</verse-number>which I commanded your ancestors<note>Or “fathers”</note> in the day of my bringing them from the land of Egypt, from the furnace of iron, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> ‘Listen to my voice and do according to all that I command you, <idiom-start/>so will you be my people, and I will be your God<idiom-end/>.’<note>Literally “and you shall be to me as people and I will be to you as God”</note> <verse-number id="Je 11:5">5</verse-number>in order to keep the oath that I swore to your ancestors,<note>Or “fathers”</note> to give them a land flowing with milk and honey, as <supplied>it is</supplied> this day.” ’ ” Then I answered and said, “<idiom-start/>Let it be so<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “Amen”</note> O Yahweh.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 11:6">6</verse-number>And Yahweh said to me, “Proclaim all these words in the cities of Judah and in the streets of Jerusalem, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> ‘Hear the words of this covenant and do them, <verse-number id="Je 11:7">7</verse-number>for I solemnly admonished your ancestors<note>Or “fathers”</note> in the day of my leading them out from the land of Egypt and up to this day, <idiom-start/>admonishing persistently<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “do early and admonishing”</note> <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> “Obey my voice.” <verse-number id="Je 11:8">8</verse-number>But they did not obey and they did not incline their ear. Instead each one walked in the stubbornness of his<note>Hebrew “their”</note> evil heart. Therefore, I brought on them all the words of this covenant which I commanded <supplied>them</supplied><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to do, and they did not <supplied>do it</supplied>.’ ”<note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 11:9">9</verse-number>And Yahweh said to me, “A conspiracy is found among the <idiom-start/>people<idiom-end/><note>Literally “man”</note> of Judah and among the inhabitants of Jerusalem. <verse-number id="Je 11:10">10</verse-number>They have turned back to the iniquities of their former ancestors,<note>Or “fathers”</note> who refused to obey my words, and they have gone after other gods, to serve them. The house of Israel and the house of Judah have broken my covenant that I <idiom-start/>made<idiom-end/><note>Literally “cut”</note> with their ancestors.”<note>Or “fathers”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 11:11">11</verse-number><idiom-start/>Therefore<idiom-end/><note>Literally “To thus”</note> thus says Yahweh, “I <supplied>am</supplied> about to bring on them disaster from which they will not be able to escape. Though they cry out to me, yet I will not listen to them. <verse-number id="Je 11:12">12</verse-number>Then the cities of Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem will go and cry out to the gods <supplied>to</supplied> whom they <supplied>are</supplied> making smoke offerings, but they will certainly not save them in the time of their trouble. <verse-number id="Je 11:13">13</verse-number>For the number of your towns are your gods, <supplied>O</supplied> Judah, and the number of the streets of Jerusalem <supplied>are the</supplied> altars you have set up to the shameful things, to make smoke offerings to Baal. <verse-number id="Je 11:14">14</verse-number>Therefore you must not pray for this people, and you must not lift up for them a cry of entreaty, or a prayer, for I <supplied>will</supplied> not listen in the time of their calling to me, in the time of their trouble. </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 11:15">15</verse-number><idiom-start/>What rights has my beloved in my house<idiom-end/><note>Literally “What for my beloved in my house”</note> </li1>
				<li2><supplied>when</supplied> she has done many wicked things?<note>Hebrew “wicked thing”</note> </li2>
				<li1>Can the flesh of holiness pass over you? </li1>
				<li2>For <idiom-start/>you engage in your wickedness<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “your wickedness”</note> then you exult. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 11:16">16</verse-number>Yahweh called your name, ‘A leafy olive tree, <idiom-start/>beautiful with fine fruit<idiom-end/>.’<note>Literally “beautiful of fruit of appearance”</note> </li1>
				<li1>With the sound of a great storm he will set fire to it, </li1>
				<li2>and its branches will be good for nothing. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 11:17">17</verse-number>And Yahweh of hosts, the <supplied>one who</supplied> planted you, </li1>
				<li2>has spoken evil against you, </li2>
				<li1>because of the evil of the house of Israel and the house of Judah, </li1>
				<li2>that they have done to themselves, </li2>
				<li1>to provoke me to anger by making smoke offerings to Baal.” </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A Warning for the People of Anathoth</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 11:18">18</verse-number>Moreover, Yahweh let <supplied>it be</supplied> made known to me, and I knew. </li1>
				<li2>Then you showed me their deeds. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 11:19">19</verse-number>And I <supplied>was</supplied> like a gentle ram-lamb that is brought to slaughter, </li1>
				<li2>and I did not know that they planned plans against me, <supplied>saying</supplied>, </li2>
				<li1>“Let us destroy the tree with its fruit, </li1>
				<li2>and let us cut him off from <supplied>the</supplied> land of <supplied>the</supplied> living, </li2>
				<li2>so that his name will no longer be remembered.” </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 11:20">20</verse-number>But <supplied>O</supplied> Yahweh of hosts, who judges <supplied>in</supplied> righteousness, </li1>
				<li2>who tests <supplied>the</supplied> <idiom-start/>inmost being<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “kidney”</note> and <supplied>the</supplied> <idiom-start/>mind<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “heart”</note> </li2>
				<li1>let me see your retribution upon them, </li1>
				<li2>for to you I have revealed my legal case. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 11:21">21</verse-number><idiom-start/>Therefore<idiom-end/><note>Literally “To thus”</note> thus says Yahweh concerning the people<note>Or “men”</note> of Anathoth who seek your life, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> “You shall not prophesy in the name of Yahweh <idiom-start/>or<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and not”</note> you will die by our hand.” <verse-number id="Je 11:22">22</verse-number><idiom-start/>Therefore<idiom-end/><note>Literally “To thus”</note> thus says Yahweh of hosts: “Look, I <supplied>am about to</supplied> punish them. The young men will die by the sword. Their sons and their daughters will die by the famine. <verse-number id="Je 11:23">23</verse-number>And a remnant will not be <supplied>left</supplied> for them, for I will bring disaster to the people<note>Or “men”</note> of Anathoth, the year of their punishment.” </p>
		</chapter>