<chapter id="Je 12">
			<pericope>Jeremiah’s Complaint</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 12:1">1</verse-number>You <supplied>will be</supplied> in the right, <supplied>O</supplied> Yahweh, when I complain to you. </li1>
				<li2>Even so, let me speak <supplied>my</supplied> claims with you. </li2>
				<li1>Why does <supplied>the</supplied> way of <supplied>the</supplied> wicked succeed? </li1>
				<li2>All those who deal treacherously with treachery are at ease. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 12:2">2</verse-number>Not only do you plant them, they take root. </li1>
				<li2>They grow, but also they produce fruit. </li2>
				<li1>You <supplied>are</supplied> near in their mouths, </li1>
				<li2>but far from their <idiom-start/>inmost beings<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “kidneys”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 12:3">3</verse-number>But you, <supplied>O</supplied> Yahweh, you know me, </li1>
				<li2>you see me, and you test <supplied>that</supplied> my heart <supplied>is</supplied> with you. </li2>
				<li1>Tear them apart like sheep for <supplied>the</supplied> slaughtering, </li1>
				<li2>and set them apart for <supplied>the</supplied> day of slaughter. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 12:4">4</verse-number><idiom-start/>How long<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Until when”</note> will the land mourn, and the vegetation of every field dry up, </li1>
				<li2>because of the wickedness of those who live in it? </li2>
				<li1><supplied>The</supplied> animals and <supplied>the</supplied> birds<note>Hebrew “bird”</note> are swept away, </li1>
				<li2>because they have said, “He does not see our future.” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Lord’s Reply</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 12:5">5</verse-number>“If you run with foot soldiers and they have made you weary, </li1>
				<li2>then how will you compete with horses? </li2>
				<li1>If you have fallen in <idiom-start/>a peaceful land<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “a land of peace”</note> </li1>
				<li2>then how will you do in the thickets of the Jordan? </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 12:6">6</verse-number>For even your relatives, and the house of your father, </li1>
				<li2>even they have dealt treacherously with you, </li2>
				<li1>even they call <idiom-start/>loudly<idiom-end/><note>Literally “full”</note> after you. </li1>
				<li2>You must not trust in them, though they speak kindly to you. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 12:7">7</verse-number>I have forsaken my house, I have abandoned my inheritance. </li1>
				<li2>I have given the beloved one of my <idiom-start/>heart<idiom-end/><note>Literally “soul”</note> into the hand of her enemies. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 12:8">8</verse-number>My inheritance has become to me like a lion in the forest. </li1>
				<li2>She has lifted up against me her voice; <idiom-start/>therefore<idiom-end/><note>Literally “unto thus”</note> I hate her. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 12:9">9</verse-number>The lair of <supplied>the</supplied> hyena <supplied>is</supplied> my inheritance to me, </li1>
				<li2>the birds of prey<note>Hebrew “bird of prey”</note> <supplied>are</supplied> all around her. </li2>
				<li1>Go, gather all of the animals<note>Hebrew “animal”</note> of the field, </li1>
				<li2>bring <supplied>them</supplied> <idiom-start/>to come and devour<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to food”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 12:10">10</verse-number>Many shepherds have destroyed my vineyard, </li1>
				<li2>they have trampled down my plot of land. </li2>
				<li1>They have made <idiom-start/>my pleasant field<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the plot of land of my desire”</note> </li1>
				<li2>like the desert<note>Or “wilderness”</note> of desolation. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 12:11">11</verse-number>They have made it a desolation. </li1>
				<li2>Desolate, it mourns to me. </li2>
				<li1>All the land is made desolate, </li1>
				<li2>but there is no person taking <supplied>it</supplied> to heart. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 12:12">12</verse-number>Upon all <supplied>the</supplied> barren heights in the desert<note>Or “wilderness”</note> destroyers have come, </li1>
				<li2>for <supplied>the</supplied> sword of Yahweh devours, </li2>
				<li1>from <supplied>one</supplied> end of <supplied>the</supplied> land to the <supplied>other</supplied> end of the land, </li1>
				<li2>there is no peace for all flesh. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 12:13">13</verse-number>They have sown wheat and they have reaped thorns. </li1>
				<li2>They are exhausted, they do not profit. </li2>
				<li1>And they will be ashamed of your produce, </li1>
				<li2>because of <idiom-start/>the burning anger<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the blaze of the nose”</note> of Yahweh.” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 12:14">14</verse-number>Thus says Yahweh concerning all of the evil neighbors who touch the inheritance that I gave as an inheritance <supplied>to</supplied> my people Israel: “Look, I <supplied>am</supplied> about to drive them out from their land, and the house of Judah I will drive out from among them. <verse-number id="Je 12:15">15</verse-number><idiom-start/>And then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And it will happen”</note> after my driving them out, I will once again have compassion on them, and I will bring them back, each one to his inheritance, and each one to his land. <verse-number id="Je 12:16">16</verse-number><idiom-start/>And then<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “And it will happen”</note> if they diligently learn the ways of my people, to swear by my name, ‘<idiom-start/>as Yahweh lives<idiom-end/>,’<note>Literally “the life of Yahweh”</note> even as they taught my people to swear by Baal, then they will live in the midst of my people. <verse-number id="Je 12:17">17</verse-number>But if they do not listen, then <idiom-start/>I will completely uproot and destroy that nation<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “I will drive out the nation that driving out and destroying”</note> <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> Yahweh. </p>
		</chapter>