<chapter id="Je 13">
			<pericope>The Linen Loincloth</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 13:1">1</verse-number>Thus Yahweh said to me: “Go and buy for yourself a loincloth of linen and put it on your loins, but you must not <idiom-start/>place<idiom-end/><note>Literally “bring”</note> it in water.” <verse-number id="Je 13:2">2</verse-number>So I bought the loincloth according to the word of Yahweh and I put <supplied>it</supplied><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> on my loins. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 13:3">3</verse-number>Now the word of Yahweh came to me a second <supplied>time</supplied>, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Je 13:4">4</verse-number>“Take the loincloth that you bought, that <supplied>is</supplied> on your loins, and stand up, go <supplied>to the</supplied> Euphrates and hide it there in the cleft of the rock.” <verse-number id="Je 13:5">5</verse-number>So I went and hid it by <supplied>the</supplied> Euphrates just as Yahweh had commanded me. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 13:6">6</verse-number><idiom-start/>And then<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “And it happened”</note> <idiom-start/>after a long time<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from the end of many days”</note> then Yahweh said to me, “Stand up, go <supplied>to the</supplied> Euphrates and take from there the loincloth that I commanded you to hide there.” <verse-number id="Je 13:7">7</verse-number>Then I went <supplied>to the</supplied> Euphrates and I dug, and I took the loincloth from the place where I had hidden it, and look, the loincloth was ruined; it was not good for anything. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 13:8">8</verse-number><idiom-start/>And then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And it happened”</note> the word of Yahweh came to me, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Je 13:9">9</verse-number>“Thus says Yahweh: ‘So I will ruin the pride of Judah and the great pride of Jerusalem. <verse-number id="Je 13:10">10</verse-number>This evil people, who refuse to listen to my words, who go<note>Or “walk”</note> in the stubbornness of their hearts,<note>Hebrew “heart”</note> and have gone after other gods, to serve them, and to bow in worship to them, let them be like this loincloth which is not good for anything. <verse-number id="Je 13:11">11</verse-number>For as the loincloth clings to <supplied>the</supplied> loins of a person, so I caused to cling to me all the house of Israel and all the house of Judah,’ <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh, ‘to be for me a people, and a name, and a praise, and a glory, but they would not listen.’ </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 13:12">12</verse-number>“Therefore, you shall say to them this word, ‘Thus says Yahweh, the God of Israel: “Every jar must be filled with wine.” ’ And they will say to you, ‘Do we not certainly know that every jar should be filled with wine?’ <verse-number id="Je 13:13">13</verse-number>Then you shall say to them, ‘Thus says Yahweh: “Look, I <supplied>am</supplied> about to fill all the inhabitants of this land, and the kings who sit on David’s throne, and the priests, and the prophets, and all the inhabitants of Jerusalem <supplied>with</supplied> drunkenness. <verse-number id="Je 13:14">14</verse-number>And I will smash them, each one against his brother, and the fathers and the sons together,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh. “I will not have compassion, and I will not take pity, and I will not show compassion from destroying them.” ’ ” </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 13:15">15</verse-number>Listen, and pay attention, </li1>
				<li2>you must not be haughty, for Yahweh has spoken. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 13:16">16</verse-number>Give glory to Yahweh your God <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “at not yet”</note> he brings darkness, </li1>
				<li2>and <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “at not yet”</note> your feet stumble on the mountains at twilight. </li2>
				<li1>And you will hope for light, but he makes it as gloom, </li1>
				<li2>he makes <supplied>it</supplied><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> as thick darkness. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 13:17">17</verse-number>But if you will not listen to it, </li1>
				<li2>my inner self<note>Or “soul”</note> will weep in secret places, </li2>
				<li2>because of <idiom-start/>the presence of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the face of”</note> <supplied>your</supplied> pride. </li2>
				<li1>And my eyes<note>Hebrew “eye”</note> will weep bitterly, </li1>
				<li2>and they will melt <supplied>in</supplied> tears, </li2>
				<li2>because the flock of Yahweh has been taken captive. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A Message for the King and the Queen Mother</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 13:18">18</verse-number>“Say to the king and to the queen mother, ‘<idiom-start/>Take a lower seat<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “Bring low sit”</note> </li1>
				<li2>for <idiom-start/>your beautiful crown<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the crown of your beauty”</note> has come down from your head.’<note>Or “at the head of you”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 13:19">19</verse-number>The towns of the Negev are shut up, </li1>
				<li2>and there is no <supplied>one who</supplied> opens <supplied>them</supplied>.<note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> </li2>
				<li1>All of Judah is deported; </li1>
				<li2>it is deported <supplied>in</supplied> completeness. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 13:20">20</verse-number>Lift up your eyes </li1>
				<li2>and see those coming from <supplied>the</supplied> north. </li2>
				<li1>Where <supplied>is</supplied> the flock that was given to you, </li1>
				<li2><idiom-start/>your magnificent flock<idiom-end/>?<note>Literally “the flock of your splendor”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 13:21">21</verse-number>What will you say when he sets over you— </li1>
				<li2>and you have taught them—allies as head over you? </li2>
				<li1>Will not labor pains take hold of you, </li1>
				<li2>like a woman giving birth? </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 13:22">22</verse-number>And if you say in your heart, </li1>
				<li2>‘Why have these <supplied>things</supplied> happened to me?’ </li2>
				<li1>Because of the greatness of your iniquity your skirts are uncovered; </li1>
				<li2>your heels have endured violence. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 13:23">23</verse-number>Can a Cushite change his skin, </li1>
				<li2>or a leopard his spots? </li2>
				<li1><supplied>Then</supplied> you also will be able to do good, </li1>
				<li2><supplied>who</supplied> are accustomed to doing evil. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 13:24">24</verse-number>And I will scatter them </li1>
				<li2>like stubble scattered by <supplied>the</supplied> wind of <supplied>the</supplied> desert.<note>Or “wilderness”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 13:25">25</verse-number>This <supplied>is</supplied> your lot, </li1>
				<li2>the portion of your measure from me,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh, </li2>
				<li1>“because you have forgotten me, </li1>
				<li2>and you have trusted in the lie. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 13:26">26</verse-number>So in turn I will bare your skirts over your face, </li1>
				<li2>and your shame will become visible. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 13:27">27</verse-number>Your adulteries, and your neighings, </li1>
				<li2>the shameful behavior of your fornications </li2>
				<li1>on <supplied>the</supplied> hills in the countryside, </li1>
				<li2>I have seen your abominations. </li2>
				<li1>Woe to you, <supplied>O</supplied> Jerusalem! </li1>
				<li2><idiom-start/>How long will you continue to be unclean<idiom-end/>?<note>Literally “Not you are clean after how long still”</note>” </li2>
			</ul>
		</chapter>