<chapter id="Je 14">
			<pericope>The Severe Drought</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 14:1">1</verse-number><supplied>That</supplied> which came <supplied>as</supplied> the word of Yahweh to Jeremiah concerning the matter<note>Hebrew “matters”</note> of the severe drought. </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 14:2">2</verse-number>“Judah mourns, and her gates languish, </li1>
				<li2>they are in mourning on the ground, </li2>
				<li2>and the cry of lament of Jerusalem goes up. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 14:3">3</verse-number>And their nobles send their servants for water. </li1>
				<li2>They come to <supplied>the</supplied> pits, they find no water. </li2>
				<li1>They return <supplied>with</supplied> their vessels <idiom-start/>empty<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “without success”</note> </li1>
				<li2>They are ashamed, and they are confounded, </li2>
				<li2>and they cover their heads.<note>Hebrew “head”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 14:4">4</verse-number>Because of the ground, <supplied>which</supplied> is cracked </li1>
				<li2>because there was no rain on the ground. </li2>
				<li1><supplied>The</supplied> farmers are ashamed, </li1>
				<li2>they cover their heads.<note>Hebrew “head”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 14:5">5</verse-number>For even <supplied>the</supplied> doe in the field gives birth and forsakes <supplied>her young</supplied>,<note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> </li1>
				<li2>because there is no green growth. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 14:6">6</verse-number>And wild asses stand on <supplied>the</supplied> barren heights, </li1>
				<li2>they gasp <supplied>for</supplied> breath like the jackals. </li2>
				<li1>Their eyes fail </li1>
				<li2>because there is no vegetation.” </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 14:7">7</verse-number>Although our iniquities testify against us, <supplied>O</supplied> Yahweh, </li1>
				<li2>act for the sake of your name. </li2>
				<li1>Yes, our apostasies are many; </li1>
				<li2>we have sinned against you. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 14:8">8</verse-number><supplied>You are</supplied> the hope of Israel, </li1>
				<li2>its savior in time of distress. </li2>
				<li1>Why should you be like an alien in the land, </li1>
				<li2>or like a traveler who spreads out <supplied>his tent</supplied> <note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to spend the night? </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 14:9">9</verse-number>Why should you be like a confused man, </li1>
				<li2>like a warrior <supplied>who</supplied> is not able to help? </li2>
				<li1>Yet you <supplied>are</supplied> in our midst, <supplied>O</supplied> Yahweh, </li1>
				<li2>and your name is called upon us. </li2>
				<li1>You must not leave us! </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 14:10">10</verse-number>Thus says Yahweh concerning this people: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“They have loved so much to wander, </li1>
				<li2>they have not spared their feet. </li2>
				<li1>Therefore Yahweh is not favorable to them, </li1>
				<li2>now he will remember their iniquity and punish their sins.” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Lying Prophets</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 14:11">11</verse-number>So Yahweh said to me, “You must not pray for this people, for <supplied>their</supplied> happiness.<note>Or “good”</note> <verse-number id="Je 14:12">12</verse-number>Although they fast, I <supplied>am</supplied> not listening to their cry of entreaty. And although they present burnt offering and grain offering, I <supplied>am</supplied> not favorable to them. But by the sword, and by the famine, and by the plague, I <supplied>am</supplied> about to destroy them.” <verse-number id="Je 14:13">13</verse-number>Then I said, “Ah, Lord Yahweh, look, the prophets <supplied>are</supplied> saying to them, ‘You will not see <supplied>the</supplied> sword, and famine will not be yours, but reliable peace I will give to you in this place.’ ” <verse-number id="Je 14:14">14</verse-number>And Yahweh said to me, “The prophets <supplied>are</supplied> prophesying lies<note>Hebrew “lie”</note> in my name. I have not sent them, and I have not commanded them, and I have not spoken to them. They are prophesying to you a lying vision, and a divination, worthless, and the deceitfulness of their <idiom-start/>minds<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “heart”</note> <verse-number id="Je 14:15">15</verse-number><idiom-start/>Therefore<idiom-end/><note>Literally “To thus”</note> thus says Yahweh concerning the prophets who prophecy in my name though I have not sent them, yet they <supplied>are</supplied> saying, “Sword and famine will not be in this land.” “By the sword and by the famine those prophets will perish. <verse-number id="Je 14:16">16</verse-number>And the people <supplied>to</supplied> whom they <supplied>are</supplied> prophesying will be cast out into the streets of Jerusalem <idiom-start/>because of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from the face of”</note> the famine and the sword. And there will be no <supplied>one who</supplied> buries them, their wives, or their sons, or their daughters. And I will pour out on them their wickedness. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Nation Hopes in Yahweh</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 14:17">17</verse-number>“And you shall say to them this word, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>‘Let my eyes melt <supplied>with</supplied> tears night and day, </li1>
				<li2>and let them not cease, </li2>
				<li1>for <supplied>with</supplied> a great wound the virgin daughter of my people is broken, </li1>
				<li2><supplied>with</supplied> a very incurable wound. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 14:18">18</verse-number>If I go out <supplied>into</supplied> the field, </li1>
				<li2>then look, those slain by <supplied>the</supplied> sword. </li2>
				<li1>And if I enter the city, </li1>
				<li2>then look, the sickness of <supplied>the</supplied> famine. </li2>
				<li1>For both prophet and priest wander around through the land, </li1>
				<li2><idiom-start/>they do not know what is going on<idiom-end/>.’ ”<note>Literally “and not they know”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 14:19">19</verse-number>Have you completely rejected Judah? </li1>
				<li2>Or has your soul<note>Or “inner self”</note> loathed Zion? </li2>
				<li1>Why have you struck us </li1>
				<li2>so that there is no healing for us? </li2>
				<li1>We hope for peace, but there is no good, </li1>
				<li2>and for a time of healing, but look, there is terror. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 14:20">20</verse-number>We know, <supplied>O</supplied> Yahweh, our wickedness, </li1>
				<li2>the iniquity of our ancestors,<note>Or “fathers”</note> </li2>
				<li2>for we have sinned against you. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 14:21">21</verse-number>You must not spurn <supplied>us</supplied><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> for the sake of your name, </li1>
				<li2>you must not dishonor <idiom-start/>your glorious throne<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the throne of your glory”</note> </li2>
				<li1>Remember <supplied>us</supplied>!<note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> </li1>
				<li2>You must not break your covenant with us. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 14:22">22</verse-number>Are there <supplied>any</supplied> among the idols of the nation <supplied>who</supplied> cause rain to pour? </li1>
				<li2>Or can the heavens give showers? </li2>
				<li1><supplied>Is</supplied> it not you, <supplied>O</supplied> Yahweh our God? </li1>
				<li2>Therefore, we hope in you, for you do all these <supplied>things</supplied>. </li2>
			</ul>
		</chapter>