<chapter id="Je 16">
			<pericope>Jeremiah is Commanded Not to Marry</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 16:1">1</verse-number>And the word of Yahweh came to me, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Je 16:2">2</verse-number>“You shall not take for yourself a wife, there shall not be for you sons and daughters in this place.” <verse-number id="Je 16:3">3</verse-number>For thus says Yahweh concerning the sons and concerning the daughters born in this place, and concerning their mothers who gave birth to them, and concerning their fathers who fathered them in this land: <verse-number id="Je 16:4">4</verse-number>“They will die by diseases, they will not be mourned, and they will not be buried. They will be as dung on the face of the earth. And they will perish by the sword and they will perish by the famine. And their dead bodies<note>Hebrew “dead body”</note> will become food for the birds<note>Hebrew “bird”</note> of the air, and for the wild animals<note>Hebrew “wild animal”</note> of the earth.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 16:5">5</verse-number>For thus says Yahweh, “You must not enter <supplied>the</supplied> house of <supplied>the</supplied> funeral meal, and you must not go to lament, and you must not show sympathy for them, for I have taken away my peace from this people,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh, “the loyal love and the compassion. <verse-number id="Je 16:6">6</verse-number>Both the great and small will die in this land. They will not be buried, and they will not mourn for them, and no one will cut himself with a blade, and no one will shave himself for them. <verse-number id="Je 16:7">7</verse-number>And they will not break bread for <supplied>the</supplied> mourning ceremony for them, to comfort him because of <supplied>the</supplied> dead. And they will not give drink to them, <supplied>the</supplied> cup of desolation, for their fathers,<note>Hebrew “father”</note> or for their mothers.<note>Hebrew “mother”</note> <verse-number id="Je 16:8">8</verse-number>And you shall not enter <supplied>the</supplied> house of <supplied>the</supplied> banquet, to sit with them, to eat and drink.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 16:9">9</verse-number>For thus says Yahweh of hosts, the God of Israel, “Look, I <supplied>am</supplied> about to cause to disappear from this place, before your eyes and in your days, <supplied>the</supplied> voice of jubilation, and <supplied>the</supplied> voice of joy, and <supplied>the</supplied> voice of <supplied>the</supplied> bridegroom, and <supplied>the</supplied> voice of <supplied>the</supplied> bride. <verse-number id="Je 16:10">10</verse-number><idiom-start/>And then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And it will happen”</note> when you tell this people all these words and they ask you, ‘<idiom-start/>Why<idiom-end/><note>Literally “On what”</note> has Yahweh pronounced against us all this great evil, and what <supplied>is</supplied> our iniquity, and what <supplied>is</supplied> our sin that we have sinned against Yahweh our God?’ <verse-number id="Je 16:11">11</verse-number>Then you shall say to them, ‘<idiom-start/>Because<idiom-end/><note>Literally “On that”</note> your ancestors<note>Or “fathers”</note> have forsaken me,’ <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh, ‘and they have gone after other gods, and they have served them, and they have bowed down in worship to them, and they have forsaken me, and they have not kept my laws. <verse-number id="Je 16:12">12</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>you have behaved badly<idiom-end/><note>Literally “you have done evil to do”</note> more than your ancestors,<note>Or “fathers”</note> and look, you <supplied>are</supplied> going each one after the stubbornness of his evil heart, without listening to me. <verse-number id="Je 16:13">13</verse-number>So I will throw you from this land to the land that you have not known, you or your ancestors,<note>Or “fathers”</note> and there you will serve other gods day and night, for I will not show you favor. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Nation’s Return to the Land</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 16:14">14</verse-number><idiom-start/>Therefore<idiom-end/><note>Literally “To thus”</note> look, days <supplied>are</supplied> coming,’ <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh, ‘and it will no longer be said, “<idiom-start/>As Yahweh lives<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “The life of Yahweh”</note> who led up the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> from the land of Egypt,” <verse-number id="Je 16:15">15</verse-number><idiom-start/>but only<idiom-end/><note>Literally “but if”</note> “<idiom-start/>As Yahweh lives<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “The life of Yahweh”</note> who led up the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> from <supplied>the</supplied> land of <supplied>the</supplied> north, and from all the lands where he had driven them,” for I will bring them back to their ground that I gave to their ancestors.<note>Or “fathers”</note> <verse-number id="Je 16:16">16</verse-number>Look, I <supplied>am</supplied> sending for many fishermen,’ <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh, ‘and they will fish them out, and <idiom-start/>afterward<idiom-end/><note>Literally “after thus”</note> I will send for many hunters, and they will hunt them from every mountain, and from every hill, and from the clefts of the cliffs. <verse-number id="Je 16:17">17</verse-number>For my eyes <supplied>are</supplied> on all their ways, they are not hidden <idiom-start/>from before me<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from to the face of me”</note> and their iniquity is not concealed from before my eyes. <verse-number id="Je 16:18">18</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>I will first doubly repay<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I will reward first second”</note> their iniquity and their sin because of their profaning my land with the dead bodies<note>Hebrew “dead body”</note> of their abhorrences, and <supplied>with</supplied> their abominations they have filled up my inheritance.’ ” </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 16:19">19</verse-number><supplied>O</supplied> Yahweh, my strength, and my stronghold, </li1>
				<li2>and my refuge in <supplied>the</supplied> day of distress, </li2>
				<li1>to you <supplied>the</supplied> nations will come from the ends of <supplied>the</supplied> earth, </li1>
				<li2>and they will say, “Our ancestors<note>Or “fathers”</note> have inherited only lies,<note>Hebrew “lie”</note> </li2>
				<li2>vanity, and there is no profit in them. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 16:20">20</verse-number>Can a human make for himself gods? </li1>
				<li2>Yet they <supplied>are</supplied> not gods!” </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 16:21">21</verse-number>“<idiom-start/>Therefore<idiom-end/><note>Literally “To thus”</note> look, I <supplied>am</supplied> about to let them know, </li1>
				<li2>this time I am going to let them know </li2>
				<li1>my <idiom-start/>power<idiom-end/><note>Literally “hand”</note> and my might, </li1>
				<li2>and they will know that my name <supplied>is</supplied> Yahweh.” </li2>
			</ul>
		</chapter>