<chapter id="Je 17">
			<pericope>The Sin of Judah</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 17:1">1</verse-number>“The sin of Judah <supplied>is</supplied> written with an iron stylus, </li1>
				<li2>with a point of diamond <supplied>it is</supplied> engraved </li2>
				<li1>on the tablet of their heart, </li1>
				<li2>and on the horns of their altars. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 17:2">2</verse-number>As the remembering of their children, </li1>
				<li2><supplied>so is the remembering of</supplied> their altars </li2>
				<li1>and their poles of Asherah worship </li1>
				<li2>beside <supplied>the</supplied> leafy trees<note>Hebrew “tree”</note> on <supplied>the</supplied> high hills. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 17:3">3</verse-number><supplied>O</supplied> my mountain in the open country, </li1>
				<li2>I will give your wealth, all your treasures, for spoil, </li2>
				<li1>your high places, because of <supplied>your</supplied> sin, </li1>
				<li2>throughout all your territories. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 17:4">4</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>you will let go your hand from your inheritance<idiom-end/><note>Literally “you shall loose and in you from your inheritance”</note> </li1>
				<li2>that I gave to you, </li2>
				<li1>and I will make you serve your enemies </li1>
				<li2>in the land that you do not know, </li2>
				<li1>for you kindled a fire in my anger, </li1>
				<li2>until eternity it will be kindled.” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The One Who Trusts in Humankind Contrasted With the One Who Trusts in Yahweh</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 17:5">5</verse-number>Thus says Yahweh, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Cursed <supplied>is</supplied> the person who trusts in humankind </li1>
				<li2>and makes flesh his <idiom-start/>strength<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “arm”</note> </li2>
				<li2>and turns aside his heart from Yahweh. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 17:6">6</verse-number>And he will be like a juniper in the wilderness,<note>Or “Arabah”</note> </li1>
				<li2>and he will not see when good comes, </li2>
				<li1>and he will dwell <supplied>in the</supplied> parched places in the desert,<note>Or “wilderness”</note> </li1>
				<li2><supplied>in</supplied> a land of salt flats,<note>Hebrew “salt flat”</note> where no one lives. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 17:7">7</verse-number>Blessed be the person who trusts in Yahweh, </li1>
				<li2>and Yahweh is his trust. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 17:8">8</verse-number>For he will be like a tree planted by water, </li1>
				<li2>and to <supplied>the</supplied> stream it sends its roots, </li2>
				<li1>and it will not fear when heat comes, </li1>
				<li2>and its leaves<note>Hebrew “leaf”</note> will be luxuriant, </li2>
				<li1>and in <supplied>the</supplied> year of drought it will not be anxious, </li1>
				<li2>and it will not cease from the bearing of fruit. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 17:9">9</verse-number>The heart <supplied>is</supplied> deceitful more than anything else, </li1>
				<li2>and it <supplied>is</supplied> disastrous. Who can understand it? </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 17:10">10</verse-number>I, Yahweh, examine <supplied>the</supplied> <idiom-start/>mind<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “heart”</note> </li1>
				<li2><supplied>I</supplied> test <supplied>the</supplied> <idiom-start/>heart<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “kidneys”</note> </li2>
				<li1>and give to each one according to his way, </li1>
				<li2>according to the fruit of his deeds. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 17:11">11</verse-number><supplied>Like</supplied> a partridge that hatches eggs it did not lay </li1>
				<li2><supplied>is</supplied> one who amasses wealth without justice. </li2>
				<li1>In the middle of his days it will leave him, </li1>
				<li2>and at his end he will <supplied>prove to</supplied> be a fool.” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Fountain of Living Water</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 17:12">12</verse-number>A lofty throne of glory from the beginning </li1>
				<li2><supplied>is</supplied> the place of our sanctuary. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 17:13">13</verse-number><supplied>O</supplied> Yahweh, the hope of Israel, </li1>
				<li2>all <supplied>those who</supplied> forsake you will be put to shame, </li2>
				<li1>and <supplied>those who</supplied> turn aside from you in the earth will be recorded, </li1>
				<li2>for they have forsaken the fountain of living water, Yahweh. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 17:14">14</verse-number>Heal me, <supplied>O</supplied> Yahweh, and I will be healed, </li1>
				<li2>save me, and I will be saved, </li2>
				<li2>for you <supplied>are</supplied> my praise. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 17:15">15</verse-number>Look, they <supplied>are</supplied> saying to me, </li1>
				<li2>“Where <supplied>is</supplied> the word of Yahweh? </li2>
				<li2>Please let it come.” </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 17:16">16</verse-number>But I, I have not run away from being a shepherd <idiom-start/>who follows you<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “after you”</note> </li1>
				<li2>and I have not desired the disastrous day. </li2>
				<li1>You, you know the pronouncement of my lips, </li1>
				<li2>it was before your face. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 17:17">17</verse-number>You must not become to me a terror, </li1>
				<li2>you <supplied>are</supplied> my refuge in <supplied>the</supplied> day of disaster. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 17:18">18</verse-number>Let my persecutors be put to shame, </li1>
				<li2><idiom-start/>but as for me<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “I”</note> <supplied>do</supplied> not let me be put to shame. </li2>
				<li1>Let them be dismayed, </li1>
				<li2><idiom-start/>but as for me<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “I”</note> <supplied>do</supplied> not let me be dismayed. </li2>
				<li1>Bring on them the day of disaster, </li1>
				<li2>and <supplied>with</supplied> double destruction, destroy them. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Sabbath Day</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 17:19">19</verse-number>Thus said Yahweh to me, “Go, and you must stand in the <idiom-start/>People’s Gate<idiom-end/><note>Literally “gate of the sons/children of the people”</note> through which the kings of Judah enter, and through which they go out, and in all the gates of Jerusalem. <verse-number id="Je 17:20">20</verse-number>And you must say to them, ‘Hear the word of Yahweh, kings of Judah, and all Judah, and all the inhabitants of Jerusalem who enter through these gates. <verse-number id="Je 17:21">21</verse-number>Thus says Yahweh, “Be on your guard for the sake of yourselves, that you must not carry a burden on the day of the Sabbath, and you must <supplied>not</supplied> bring <supplied>it</supplied><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> through the gates of Jerusalem. <verse-number id="Je 17:22">22</verse-number>And you must not carry a burden from your houses on the day of the Sabbath, and you must not do any work. But you must declare holy the day of Sabbath, just as I commanded your ancestors.<note>Or “fathers”</note> <verse-number id="Je 17:23">23</verse-number>Yet they did not listen, and they did not incline their ear, and they hardened their neck <supplied>so as</supplied> to not hear, nor to receive discipline. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 17:24">24</verse-number>“And it will happen, if you carefully listen to me,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh, “to bring no burden through the gates of this city on the day of the Sabbath, but to declare holy the day of Sabbath, not to do on it any work, <verse-number id="Je 17:25">25</verse-number>then kings and officials who sit on the throne of David will enter through the gates of this city riding in chariots<note>Hebrew “chariot”</note> and on horses, they, and their officials, the people of Judah, and the inhabitants of Jerusalem, and this city will be inhabited <idiom-start/>forever<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to eternity”</note> <verse-number id="Je 17:26">26</verse-number>And they will come from the towns of Judah, and from all around Jerusalem, and from the land of Benjamin, and from the Shephelah, and from the hill country, and from the Negev, bringing burnt offerings,<note>Hebrew “burnt offering”</note> and sacrifices,<note>Hebrew “sacrifice”</note> and grain offerings,<note>Hebrew “grain offering”</note> and frankincense, and bringing thank offerings<note>Hebrew “thank offering”</note> <supplied>to</supplied> the house of Yahweh. <verse-number id="Je 17:27">27</verse-number>But if you do not listen to me, to declare holy the day of the Sabbath, and to not carry a burden and enter through the gates of Jerusalem on the day of the Sabbath, then I will kindle a fire in its gates, and it will devour the palaces of Jerusalem, and it will not be quenched.” ’ ” </p>
		</chapter>