<chapter id="Je 18">
			<pericope>The Potter and the Clay</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 18:1">1</verse-number>The word that came to Jeremiah from Yahweh, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Je 18:2">2</verse-number>“Stand up and go down <supplied>to</supplied> the house of the potter, and there I will let you hear my words.” <verse-number id="Je 18:3">3</verse-number>So I went down <supplied>to</supplied> the house of the potter and look, there he was doing work at the potter’s wheels. <verse-number id="Je 18:4">4</verse-number>And the vessel that he <supplied>was</supplied> making with the clay was spoiled in the hand of the potter, so <idiom-start/>he made again<idiom-end/><note>Literally “he turned back and he made it”</note> another vessel, as it was right in the eyes of the potter to make. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 18:5">5</verse-number>And the word of Yahweh came to me, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Je 18:6">6</verse-number>“Like this potter, am I not able to do to you, O house of Israel?” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh. “Look, like the clay in the hand of the potter, so <supplied>are</supplied> you in my hand, O house of Israel. <verse-number id="Je 18:7">7</verse-number>One moment I speak concerning a nation or concerning a kingdom, to uproot, and to tear down, and to destroy <supplied>it</supplied>.<note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <verse-number id="Je 18:8">8</verse-number>But <supplied>if</supplied> that nation turns back from its evil that I have threatened against it, then I will relent concerning the disaster that I planned to do to it. <verse-number id="Je 18:9">9</verse-number>And the <supplied>next</supplied> moment I speak concerning a nation or concerning a kingdom, to build, and to plant <supplied>it</supplied>.<note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <verse-number id="Je 18:10">10</verse-number>But <supplied>if</supplied> it does evil in my sight, to not listen to my voice, then I will relent concerning the good that I said I would do <supplied>to</supplied> it. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 18:11">11</verse-number>“So now then, say, please, to the <idiom-start/>people<idiom-end/><note>Literally “man”</note> of Judah and to the inhabitants of Jerusalem, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> ‘Thus says Yahweh, “Look, I <supplied>am</supplied> preparing evil against you, and <supplied>I am</supplied> planning a plan against you. Please turn back, each one from his evil way, and walk rightly <supplied>in</supplied> your ways and your deeds.” ’ <verse-number id="Je 18:12">12</verse-number>But they will say, ‘<supplied>It is</supplied> hopeless, for we will go after our <supplied>own</supplied> plans, and each one of us will act <supplied>according to</supplied> the stubbornness of his evil heart.’ </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 18:13">13</verse-number>“Therefore thus says Yahweh, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>‘Please ask among the nations, “Who has heard <idiom-start/>the like of this<idiom-end/>?”<note>Literally “like these”</note> </li1>
				<li2>The virgin of Israel has done something very horrible. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 18:14">14</verse-number>Does the snow of Lebanon leave from <supplied>the</supplied> crags<note>Hebrew “crag”</note> of Sirion? </li1>
				<li2>Or are <supplied>the</supplied> cold waters flowing from distant mountains dried up? </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 18:15">15</verse-number>But my people have forgotten me. </li1>
				<li2>They make smoke offerings to the idols,<note>Hebrew “idol”</note> </li2>
				<li1>and they caused them to stumble in their ways, <supplied>the</supplied> ancient ways, </li1>
				<li2>to go <supplied>into</supplied> <idiom-start/>bypaths<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “paths of way”</note> not <supplied>one that</supplied> is built up. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 18:16">16</verse-number>To make their land a horror, </li1>
				<li2><supplied>an object of</supplied> whistling for eternity. </li2>
				<li1>All <supplied>who</supplied> pass by it will be appalled, </li1>
				<li2>and he will shake his head. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 18:17">17</verse-number>Like the wind from the east </li1>
				<li2>I will scatter them <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of”</note> <supplied>the</supplied> enemy. </li2>
				<li1>I will show them <supplied>my</supplied> back and not <supplied>my</supplied> face </li1>
				<li2>in the day of their disaster.’ ” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jeremiah’s Imprecatory Prayer</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 18:18">18</verse-number>Then they said, “Come and let us plan plans against Jeremiah, for instruction will not be lost from <supplied>the</supplied> priest, nor advice from <supplied>the</supplied> wise man, nor <supplied>the</supplied> word from <supplied>the</supplied> prophet. Come and <idiom-start/>let us bring charges against him<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “let us strike him with the tongue”</note> and let us not listen attentively to any of his words.” </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 18:19">19</verse-number>Listen attentively to me, <supplied>O</supplied> Yahweh, </li1>
				<li2>and listen to <supplied>the</supplied> voice of my opponents. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 18:20">20</verse-number>Should good be repaid in place of evil? </li1>
				<li2>Yet they have dug a pit for me. </li2>
				<li1>Remember my standing <idiom-start/>before you<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of you”</note> to speak good for them, </li1>
				<li2>to avert your wrath from them. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 18:21">21</verse-number><idiom-start/>Therefore<idiom-end/><note>Literally “To thus”</note> give their children to the famine, </li1>
				<li2>and hand them over to <supplied>the</supplied> <idiom-start/>power<idiom-end/><note>Literally “hand”</note> of <supplied>the</supplied> sword, </li2>
				<li1>and let their wives be bereaved and widows, </li1>
				<li2>and let their men be killed by death, </li2>
				<li1>their young men struck dead </li1>
				<li2><supplied>by the</supplied> sword in the battle. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 18:22">22</verse-number>Let a cry for help be heard from their houses </li1>
				<li2>when you suddenly bring upon them <supplied>the</supplied> raiding band, </li2>
				<li1>for they have dug a pit to catch me, </li1>
				<li2>and they have fixed secretly a trap for my feet. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 18:23">23</verse-number>But you, <supplied>O</supplied> Yahweh, you know </li1>
				<li2><idiom-start/>all their plans of assassination against me<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “all of their plan against me to the death”</note> </li2>
				<li1>You must not make atonement for their iniquity, </li1>
				<li2>and you must not cause their sin to be blotted out from <idiom-start/>before you<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to the face of you”</note> </li2>
				<li1>But let them be overthrown <idiom-start/>before you<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to the face of you”</note> </li1>
				<li2>Deal with them in the time of your anger. </li2>
			</ul>
		</chapter>