<chapter id="Je 20">
			<pericope>A Message for Pashhur</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 20:1">1</verse-number>Now Pashhur, the son of Immer, the priest <supplied>who was</supplied> officer in charge in the temple of Yahweh, heard Jeremiah prophesying these things. <verse-number id="Je 20:2">2</verse-number>Then Pashhur struck Jeremiah the prophet and put him in the stocks that <supplied>were</supplied> in the upper Gate of Benjamin, which <supplied>was</supplied> by the temple of Yahweh. <verse-number id="Je 20:3">3</verse-number><idiom-start/>And then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And it was”</note> on the next day, when Pashhur brought Jeremiah out from the stocks, Jeremiah said to him, “Yahweh will not call your name Pashhur, <idiom-start/>but<idiom-end/><note>Literally “but if”</note> Terror From All Around. <verse-number id="Je 20:4">4</verse-number>For thus says Yahweh, ‘Look, I <supplied>am</supplied> making you a terror to yourself and to all your friends, and they will fall by the sword of their enemies, and your eyes <supplied>will be</supplied> seeing <supplied>it</supplied>.<note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> And all Judah I will give into the hand of the king of Babylon, and he will deport them <supplied>to</supplied> Babylon, and he will strike them with the sword. <verse-number id="Je 20:5">5</verse-number>And I will give all the wealth of this city, and all its acquisitions, and all its precious items, and all of the treasures of the kings of Judah I will give into the hand of their enemies, and they will plunder them, and they will seize them, and they will bring them <supplied>to</supplied> Babylon. <verse-number id="Je 20:6">6</verse-number>And you, Pashhur, and all <supplied>those who</supplied> live <supplied>in</supplied> your house will go into captivity, and you will go <supplied>to</supplied> Babylon, and there you will die, and there you will be buried, you, and all your friends to whom you have prophesied <idiom-start/>falsely<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “in the lie”</note>’ ” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jeremiah’s Lament</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 20:7">7</verse-number>You have persuaded me, <supplied>O</supplied> Yahweh, and I was persuaded. </li1>
				<li2>You have overpowered me, and you have prevailed. </li2>
				<li1>I have become a laughingstock all day <supplied>long</supplied>. </li1>
				<li2><idiom-start/>Everyone<idiom-end/><note>Literally “All of him”</note> <supplied>is</supplied> mocking me. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 20:8">8</verse-number>For <idiom-start/>as often as<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from enough”</note> I speak, </li1>
				<li2>I must cry out violence and destruction. </li2>
				<li1>I must shout, for the word of Yahweh has become for me </li1>
				<li2>a disgrace and derision all day <supplied>long</supplied>. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 20:9">9</verse-number>But <supplied>if</supplied> I say, “I will not mention him </li1>
				<li2>and I will no longer speak in his name,” </li2>
				<li1>then it becomes in my heart like a fire burning, </li1>
				<li2>locked up in my bones, </li2>
				<li1>and I struggle to contain <supplied>it</supplied>,<note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> </li1>
				<li2>and I am not able. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 20:10">10</verse-number>For I hear the rumor of many, </li1>
				<li2>“Terror <supplied>is</supplied> from all around, denounce <supplied>him</supplied>,<note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> </li2>
				<li2>yes, let us denounce him!” </li2>
				<li1><idiom-start/>All my close friends<idiom-end/><note>Literally “All the human being of my peace”</note> <supplied>are</supplied> watchers of my stumbling, </li1>
				<li2><supplied>saying</supplied>, “perhaps he can be persuaded, </li2>
				<li1>and we can prevail over him, </li1>
				<li2>and we can take our revenge on him.” </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 20:11">11</verse-number>But Yahweh <supplied>is</supplied> with me like a powerful warrior. </li1>
				<li2><idiom-start/>Therefore<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Unto thus”</note> my persecutors will stumble and will not prevail. </li2>
				<li1>They will be very ashamed, for they will not achieve success. </li1>
				<li2><supplied>Their</supplied> <idiom-start/>everlasting insult<idiom-end/><note>Literally “insult of eternity”</note> will not be forgotten. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 20:12">12</verse-number>Yet, <supplied>O</supplied> Yahweh of hosts, who tests <supplied>the</supplied> righteous, </li1>
				<li2>who sees <supplied>the</supplied> <idiom-start/>heart<idiom-end/><note>Literally “kidneys”</note> and <supplied>the</supplied> <idiom-start/>mind<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “heart”</note> </li2>
				<li1>let me see your retribution upon them, </li1>
				<li2>for to you I have revealed my legal case. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 20:13">13</verse-number>Sing to Yahweh, praise Yahweh, </li1>
				<li2>for he has delivered <supplied>the</supplied> life of <supplied>the</supplied> poor from <supplied>the</supplied> hand of evildoers. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 20:14">14</verse-number>Cursed be <supplied>the</supplied> day <supplied>on</supplied> which I was born, </li1>
				<li2>let not the day <supplied>on</supplied> which my mother gave birth to me be blessed. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 20:15">15</verse-number>Cursed be the man who brought the news <supplied>to</supplied> my father, </li1>
				<li2><idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> “A child is born to you, a son!” </li2>
				<li2>and he made him very glad. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 20:16">16</verse-number>And let that man be like the cities </li1>
				<li2>that Yahweh demolished without regret, </li2>
				<li1>and let him hear a cry for help in the morning, </li1>
				<li2>and an alarm at the time of noon. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 20:17">17</verse-number>Because he did not kill me in <supplied>the</supplied> womb, </li1>
				<li2>so that my mother would have been for me my grave, </li2>
				<li2>and <supplied>her</supplied> womb <supplied>would be</supplied> pregnant forever. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 20:18">18</verse-number><idiom-start/>Why<idiom-end/><note>Literally “To what this”</note> did I come out from <supplied>the</supplied> womb, </li1>
				<li2>to see toil, and sorrow, and <supplied>to</supplied> <idiom-start/>end my days in shame<idiom-end/>?<note>Literally “my days will come to an end in shame”</note> </li2>
			</ul>
		</chapter>