<chapter id="Je 22">
			<p><verse-number id="Je 22">22</verse-number><verse-number id="Je 22:1">1</verse-number> Thus says Yahweh: “Go down <supplied>to</supplied> the house of the king of Judah and you must speak this word there. <verse-number id="Je 22:2">2</verse-number>And you must say, ‘Hear the word of Yahweh, O king of Judah, who sits on the throne of David, you, and your servants, and your people who enter through these gates. <verse-number id="Je 22:3">3</verse-number>Thus says Yahweh, “Act <supplied>with</supplied> justice and righteousness, and deliver <supplied>the</supplied> one who has been seized from the hand of <supplied>the</supplied> oppressor. And you must not oppress <supplied>the</supplied> immigrant, <supplied>the</supplied> orphan, and <supplied>the</supplied> widow. And you must not shed innocent blood in this place. <verse-number id="Je 22:4">4</verse-number>And if you indeed obey this word, then kings who sit for David on his throne will enter through the gates of this house, riding in chariots<note>Hebrew “chariot”</note> and on horses, he, and his servants, and his people. <verse-number id="Je 22:5">5</verse-number>But if you do not obey these words, I swear by myself,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh, “that this house will become a site of ruins.” ’ ” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 22:6">6</verse-number>For thus says Yahweh concerning the house of the king of Judah, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“You <supplied>are like</supplied> Gilead to me, </li1>
				<li2><supplied>like</supplied> the head of the Lebanon. </li2>
				<li1><idiom-start/>Surely<idiom-end/><note>Literally “If not”</note> I will make you a desert,<note>Or “wilderness”</note> </li1>
				<li2><supplied>like</supplied> cities <supplied>that</supplied> are not inhabited. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 22:7">7</verse-number>And I will consecrate against you destroyers, </li1>
				<li2>everyone with his weapons, </li2>
				<li1>and they will cut down <idiom-start/>your choicest cedars<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the choicest thing of your cedars”</note> </li1>
				<li2>and cast <supplied>them</supplied><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> on the fire. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 22:8">8</verse-number>And many nations will pass by this city and they will say each one to his neighbor, ‘<idiom-start/>Why<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Over what”</note> has Yahweh done in this manner to this great city?’ <verse-number id="Je 22:9">9</verse-number>Then they will answer, ‘Because they abandoned the covenant of Yahweh their God, and bowed down in worship to other gods, and served them.’ ” </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 22:10">10</verse-number>You must not weep for <supplied>the</supplied> dead person, </li1>
				<li2>and you must not show sympathy for him. </li2>
				<li1>Weep bitterly for the one who goes away, </li1>
				<li2>for he will not return, or see the land of his birth again. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 22:11">11</verse-number>For thus says Yahweh concerning Shallum, the son of Josiah, the king of Judah, who reigned as king in place of Josiah his father, who went out from this place: “He will not return here again. <verse-number id="Je 22:12">12</verse-number>But in <supplied>the</supplied> place where they have deported him, there he will die, and he will not see this land again. </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 22:13">13</verse-number>Woe <supplied>to the one who</supplied> builds his house without righteousness, </li1>
				<li2>and his upper rooms without justice. </li2>
				<li1>His fellow countryman, he works for nothing, </li1>
				<li2>and he does not give to him his wages.<note>Hebrew “wage”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 22:14">14</verse-number>Who says ‘I will build for myself </li1>
				<li2>a spacious house with large upper rooms,’ </li2>
				<li1>and he cuts windows for it, </li1>
				<li2>and <supplied>it is</supplied><note>Here the subject is supplied from context in the English translation</note> paneled with cedar, </li2>
				<li2>and he paints <supplied>it</supplied><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> with vermilion. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 22:15">15</verse-number>Do you reign as king because you <supplied>are</supplied> competing in cedar? </li1>
				<li2>Did not your father eat and drink, </li2>
				<li1>and he did justice and righteousness, </li1>
				<li2>then it was well with him? </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 22:16">16</verse-number>He judged <supplied>the</supplied> legal cause of <supplied>the</supplied> needy and <supplied>the</supplied> poor, </li1>
				<li2><supplied>and</supplied> then it was well. </li2>
				<li2><idiom-start/>Is that not what it means to know me<idiom-end/>?<note>Literally “Not that the knowledge me”</note>” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 22:17">17</verse-number>“But there is nothing <supplied>in</supplied> your eyes and your heart </li1>
				<li2><idiom-start/>except<idiom-end/><note>Literally “but if”</note> your unlawful gain, </li2>
				<li1>and on shedding the blood of the innocent, </li1>
				<li2>and on committing oppression and extortion.” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 22:18">18</verse-number><idiom-start/>Therefore<idiom-end/><note>Literally “To thus”</note> thus says Yahweh concerning Jehoiakim, the son of Josiah, the king of Judah: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“They will not lament for him, </li1>
				<li2>‘Alas, my brother,’ or ‘Alas, sister.’ </li2>
				<li1>They will not lament for him, </li1>
				<li2>‘Alas, lord,’ or ‘alas, his majesty.’ </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 22:19">19</verse-number>He will be buried <supplied>with</supplied> the burial of a donkey. </li1>
				<li2><supplied>He will be</supplied><note>Here the subject is supplied from context in the English translation</note> dragged away and thrown <idiom-start/>outside<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from beyond”</note> the gates of Jerusalem. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 22:20">20</verse-number>Go up <supplied>to</supplied> Lebanon and cry out, </li1>
				<li2>and in Bashan lift up your voice, </li2>
				<li1>and cry out from Abarim, </li1>
				<li2>for all your lovers are shattered. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 22:21">21</verse-number>I spoke to you <idiom-start/>in the times you were secure<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “in your security”</note> </li1>
				<li2><supplied>and</supplied> you said, ‘I will not listen!’ </li2>
				<li1>This <supplied>was</supplied> your way from your youth, </li1>
				<li2>for you have not obeyed my voice. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 22:22">22</verse-number>All your shepherds will shepherd <supplied>the</supplied> wind, </li1>
				<li2>and your lovers will go into captivity. </li2>
				<li1>Yes, then you will be ashamed and humiliated </li1>
				<li2>because of all your wickedness. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 22:23">23</verse-number>Inhabitants<note>Hebrew “Inhabitant”</note> of Lebanon, </li1>
				<li2>nestled among the cedars, </li2>
				<li1>how you will groan when labor pains come to you, </li1>
				<li2>fear and pain as the <supplied>woman who</supplied> gives birth. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 22:24">24</verse-number>“As I live,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh, “surely if Coniah, the son of Jehoiakim, the king of Judah, were <supplied>the</supplied> seal on my right hand, surely from there I would wrench you off. <verse-number id="Je 22:25">25</verse-number>And I would give you into the hand of those who seek your life, and into the hand of those from whom you <supplied>are</supplied> frightened by their presence, and into the hand of Nebuchadnezzar, the king of Babylon, and into the hand of the Chaldeans. <verse-number id="Je 22:26">26</verse-number>And I will throw you and your mother who gave birth to you to another country where you were not born, and there you will die. <verse-number id="Je 22:27">27</verse-number>As for the land to which they are <idiom-start/>longing<idiom-end/><note>Literally “lifting their inner self”</note> to return, they will not return. </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 22:28">28</verse-number><supplied>Is</supplied> this man Coniah a despised, shattered vessel? </li1>
				<li2>Or a vessel <supplied>in which</supplied> there is no delight? </li2>
				<li1>Why are he and his offspring thrown far, </li1>
				<li2>and cast away to the land that they do not know?” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 22:29">29</verse-number><supplied>O</supplied> land, land, land, hear the word of Yahweh. <verse-number id="Je 22:30">30</verse-number>Thus says Yahweh: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Record this man <supplied>as</supplied> childless, </li1>
				<li2>a man <supplied>who</supplied> will not succeed in his days, </li2>
				<li1>for no man from his offspring will succeed <supplied>him</supplied>,<note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> </li1>
				<li2>sitting on the throne of David and ruling again in Judah.” </li2>
			</ul>
		</chapter>