<chapter id="Je 23">
			<pericope>Woe to the Evil Shepherds</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 23:1">1</verse-number>“Woe <supplied>to the</supplied> shepherds who destroy and scatter the flock of my pasture,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh. <verse-number id="Je 23:2">2</verse-number><idiom-start/>Therefore<idiom-end/><note>Literally “To thus”</note> thus says Yahweh, the God of Israel concerning the shepherds who shepherd my people, “You yourselves have scattered my flock, and you have driven them away, and you do not attend to them. Look, I <supplied>will</supplied> punish you <supplied>for</supplied> the evil of your deeds,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh. <verse-number id="Je 23:3">3</verse-number>“Then I myself will gather together the remnant of my flock from all the lands where I have driven them, and I will bring them back to their grazing place, and they will be fruitful, and they will become numerous. <verse-number id="Je 23:4">4</verse-number>And I will raise up over them shepherds, and they will shepherd them, and they will no longer fear, and they will not be dismayed, and they will not be missing,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Righteous Branch</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 23:5">5</verse-number>“Look, days <supplied>are</supplied> coming,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh, </li1>
				<li2>“when I will raise up for David a righteous branch, </li2>
				<li1>and he will reign <supplied>as</supplied> king, and he will achieve success, </li1>
				<li2>and he will do justice and righteousness in the land. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 23:6">6</verse-number>In his days Judah will be saved, </li1>
				<li2>and Israel will dwell <idiom-start/>in safety<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “with confidence”</note> </li2>
				<li1>and this <supplied>is</supplied> his name <supplied>by</supplied> which he will be called: </li1>
				<li2>‘Yahweh <supplied>is</supplied> our righteousness.’ </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 23:7">7</verse-number>“<idiom-start/>Therefore<idiom-end/><note>Literally “To thus”</note> look, days <supplied>are</supplied> coming,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh, “when they will no longer say, ‘<idiom-start/>As Yahweh lives<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the life of Yahweh”</note> who led up the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> from the land of Egypt,’ <verse-number id="Je 23:8">8</verse-number>but ‘<idiom-start/>As Yahweh lives<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the life of Yahweh”</note> who led up, and who brought the offspring of the house of Israel from <supplied>the</supplied> land <supplied>of the</supplied> north and from all the lands where he had driven them.’ Then they will live in their land.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Unfaithful Prophets</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 23:9">9</verse-number>Concerning the prophets: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>My heart is broken in my midst. </li1>
				<li2>All my bones tremble. </li2>
				<li1>I have become like a drunken man, </li1>
				<li2>even like a man over whom wine has passed, </li2>
				<li1>because of Yahweh, </li1>
				<li2>and because of <idiom-start/>his holy words<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “words of his holiness”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 23:10">10</verse-number>For the land is full <supplied>of</supplied> adulterers; </li1>
				<li2>for the land mourns because of a curse. </li2>
				<li1><supplied>The</supplied> pastures of <supplied>the</supplied> desert<note>Or “wilderness”</note> are dry, </li1>
				<li2>and their evil has been their way of running, </li2>
				<li2>and their power <supplied>is</supplied> not right. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 23:11">11</verse-number>“For both prophet as well as priest are godless, </li1>
				<li2>even in my temple I have found their wickedness,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 23:12">12</verse-number>“<idiom-start/>Therefore<idiom-end/><note>Literally “To thus”</note> their way will be to them like the slippery places, </li1>
				<li2>they will be pushed in the darkness, </li2>
				<li1>and they will fall into it, </li1>
				<li2>for I will bring disaster on them <supplied>in</supplied> the year of their punishment,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 23:13">13</verse-number>“Now in the prophets of Samaria I saw a disgusting thing. </li1>
				<li2>They prophesied by Baal and they caused my people Israel to err. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 23:14">14</verse-number>And in the prophets of Jerusalem I have seen something horrible. </li1>
				<li2>They commit adultery, and they walk in lies,<note>Hebrew “the lie”</note> </li2>
				<li1>and they make strong <supplied>the</supplied> hands of evildoers, </li1>
				<li2><supplied>so</supplied> that they have not turned back each from his wickedness. </li2>
				<li1>All of them have become to me like Sodom, </li1>
				<li2>and its inhabitants like Gomorrah.” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 23:15">15</verse-number><idiom-start/>Therefore<idiom-end/><note>Literally “To thus”</note> thus says Yahweh concerning the prophets, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Look, I <supplied>am</supplied> going to let them eat wormwood </li1>
				<li2>and I will give them water of poison to drink, </li2>
				<li1>for from the prophets of Jerusalem </li1>
				<li2>went out ungodliness to all the land.” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 23:16">16</verse-number>Thus says Yahweh of hosts, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“You must not listen to the words of the prophets who prophesy to you. </li1>
				<li2>They <supplied>are</supplied> deluding you <supplied>with</supplied> visions of their <idiom-start/>mind<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “heart”</note> </li2>
				<li2>They do not speak from the mouth of Yahweh. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 23:17">17</verse-number><supplied>They are</supplied><note>Here the subject and verb are supplied from context in the English translation</note> continually saying to those who disregard the word of Yahweh, </li1>
				<li2>‘Peace it will be to you,’ </li2>
				<li1>and <supplied>to</supplied> <idiom-start/>each one<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all”</note> who walks in the stubbornness of his heart they say, </li1>
				<li2>‘Calamity will not come upon you.’ </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 23:18">18</verse-number>For who has stood in the council of Yahweh, </li1>
				<li2>that he has seen and heard his word? </li2>
				<li1>Who has listened attentively <supplied>to</supplied> his word </li1>
				<li2>and heard <supplied>it</supplied>?<note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 23:19">19</verse-number>Look, the storm of Yahweh has gone forth <supplied>in</supplied> wrath, </li1>
				<li2>even a whirling tempest. </li2>
				<li1>It will whirl upon <supplied>the</supplied> head of <supplied>the</supplied> wicked. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 23:20">20</verse-number>The <idiom-start/>anger<idiom-end/><note>Literally “nose”</note> of Yahweh will not turn back </li1>
				<li2>until his doing and until his keeping the plans of his <idiom-start/>mind<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “heart”</note> </li2>
				<li1><idiom-start/>In latter days<idiom-end/><note>Literally “In the last of the days”</note> you will look closely at it <supplied>with</supplied> understanding. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 23:21">21</verse-number>I have not sent the prophets, yet they ran. </li1>
				<li2>I have not spoken to them, yet they prophesied. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 23:22">22</verse-number>But if they had stood in my council, </li1>
				<li2>then they would have proclaimed my words <supplied>to</supplied> my people, </li2>
				<li1>and they would have caused them to turn from their evil way, </li1>
				<li2>and from the evil of their deeds. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 23:23">23</verse-number><supplied>Am</supplied> I a God from near,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh, </li1>
				<li2>“and not a God from far? </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 23:24">24</verse-number>Or can a person hide himself in secret places </li1>
				<li2>and I cannot see him?” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh. </li2>
				<li1>“<supplied>Do</supplied> I not fill up the heaven and the earth?” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh. </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 23:25">25</verse-number>“I have heard what the prophets who prophesy lies<note>Hebrew “lie”</note> have said in my name, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> ‘I have dreamed! I have dreamed!’ <verse-number id="Je 23:26">26</verse-number><idiom-start/>How long<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Until when”</note> <supplied>will</supplied> this be in the hearts<note>Hebrew “heart”</note> of the prophets who prophesy lies,<note>Hebrew “the lie”</note> even the prophets of the deceitfulness of their hearts,<note>Hebrew “heart”</note> <verse-number id="Je 23:27">27</verse-number>who plan to make my people forget my name by their dreams that they tell each one to his neighbor, just as their ancestors<note>Or “fathers”</note> forgot my name through Baal? <verse-number id="Je 23:28">28</verse-number>The prophet who <supplied>has</supplied> with him a dream, let him tell <supplied>the</supplied> dream. But <supplied>the prophet</supplied><note>Here the subject is supplied from context in the English translation</note> who <supplied>has</supplied> my word with him, let him speak my word faithfully. <idiom-start/>What is straw compared to wheat<idiom-end/>?”<note>Literally “What to the straw in comparison with the wheat”</note> <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh. <verse-number id="Je 23:29">29</verse-number>“<supplied>Is</supplied> not my word like fire?” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh, “and like a blacksmith’s hammer <supplied>that</supplied> breaks a rock into pieces? </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 23:30">30</verse-number>“<idiom-start/>Therefore<idiom-end/><note>Literally “To thus”</note> look, I <supplied>am</supplied> against the prophets,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh, “who steal my words each one from his neighbor. <verse-number id="Je 23:31">31</verse-number>Look, I <supplied>am</supplied> against the prophets,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh, “who take their tongues<note>Hebrew “tongue”</note> and declare as prophets, ‘<supplied>Yahweh</supplied> <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/>.’<note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> <verse-number id="Je 23:32">32</verse-number>Look, I <supplied>am</supplied> against those who prophesy dreams of lies,”<note>Hebrew “lie”</note> <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh, “and tell them, and they caused my people to err through their lies, and in their recklessness, when I myself have not sent them nor commanded them, so they profit not this people at all,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 23:33">33</verse-number>“Now when this people, or a prophet, or a priest, ask you, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> ‘What <supplied>is</supplied> the burden<note>Or “oracle”</note> of Yahweh?’ then you shall say to them, ‘<idiom-start/>You are the burden<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “What burden”</note> and I will forsake you,’ ” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh. <verse-number id="Je 23:34">34</verse-number>“And the prophet, and the priest, and the people who say, ‘The burden<note>Or “oracle”</note> of Yahweh,’ I will punish that man and his house. <verse-number id="Je 23:35">35</verse-number>Thus you shall say, each one to his neighbor and each one to his brother: ‘What has Yahweh answered?’ or, ‘What has Yahweh spoken?’ <verse-number id="Je 23:36">36</verse-number>But you shall not mention the burden<note>Or “oracle”</note> of Yahweh, for the burden<note>Or “oracle”</note> is to each one his word, and so you twist the words of <supplied>the</supplied> living God, Yahweh of hosts, our God. <verse-number id="Je 23:37">37</verse-number>Thus you shall say to that prophet, ‘What has Yahweh answered you?’ or, ‘What has Yahweh spoken?’ <verse-number id="Je 23:38">38</verse-number>But if you say, ‘The burden<note>Or “oracle”</note> of Yahweh,’ <idiom-start/>therefore<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to thus”</note> thus says Yahweh, ‘because of your saying these words,<note>Hebrew “word”</note> “The burden<note>Or “oracle”</note> of Yahweh,” then I will send to you, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> “You shall not say, ‘The burden<note>Or “oracle”</note> of Yahweh.’ ” ’ <verse-number id="Je 23:39">39</verse-number><idiom-start/>Therefore<idiom-end/><note>Literally “To thus”</note> look, here I am, and I will surely lift you up and forsake you and the city that I gave to you and to your ancestors<note>Or “fathers”</note> from <idiom-start/>my presence<idiom-end/><note>Literally “my face”</note>, <verse-number id="Je 23:40">40</verse-number>and I will bring upon you <idiom-start/>an everlasting disgrace<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a disgrace of eternity”</note> and <idiom-start/>an everlasting shame<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a shame of eternity”</note> that will not be forgotten.” </p>
		</chapter>