<chapter id="Je 24">
			<pericope>Two Baskets of Figs</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 24:1">1</verse-number>Yahweh showed me, and look, there were two baskets of figs placed <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of”</note> the temple of Yahweh—after Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon had deported Jeconiah the son of Jehoiakim, the king of Judah, with the officials of Judah, and the craftsmen, and the smiths,<note>Hebrew “smith”</note> from Jerusalem and had brought them <supplied>to</supplied> Babylon. <verse-number id="Je 24:2">2</verse-number>The one basket <supplied>had</supplied> very good figs, like <idiom-start/>early figs<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the figs of the early ripened fruit”</note> and the other basket <supplied>had</supplied> very bad figs that could not be eaten because of <supplied>their</supplied> bad quality. <verse-number id="Je 24:3">3</verse-number>And Yahweh asked me, “What <supplied>are</supplied> you seeing, Jeremiah?” And I said, “Figs—the good figs, very good, and the bad <supplied>figs</supplied>, very bad, that cannot be eaten because of <supplied>their</supplied> bad quality.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 24:4">4</verse-number>Then the word of Yahweh came to me, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Je 24:5">5</verse-number>“Thus says Yahweh, the God of Israel, ‘Like these good figs, so I will regard as good the exiles<note>Hebrew “exile”</note> of Judah whom I have sent away from this place <supplied>to the</supplied> land of <supplied>the</supplied> Chaldeans. <verse-number id="Je 24:6">6</verse-number>For I will set my eyes<note>Hebrew “eye”</note> on them for good, and I will bring them back to this land. And I will build them and not annihilate <supplied>them</supplied>, and I will plant them and not uproot <supplied>them</supplied>. <verse-number id="Je 24:7">7</verse-number>And I will give to them a heart to know me, that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh, and <idiom-start/>they will be my people<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “they shall be for me as a people”</note> and <idiom-start/>I will be their God<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “I will be for them as God”</note> for they will return to me with the whole of their heart. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 24:8">8</verse-number>But like the bad figs that cannot be eaten because of <supplied>their</supplied> bad quality—for thus says Yahweh—so I will treat Zedekiah the king of Judah, and his officials, and the remnant of Jerusalem who remain in this land, and those who live in the land of Egypt. <verse-number id="Je 24:9">9</verse-number>And I will make them as a terror, an evil to all the kingdoms of the earth, as a disgrace and a proverb, as a taunt and a curse, in all the places where I will drive them. <verse-number id="Je 24:10">10</verse-number>And I will send among them the sword, the famine, and the plague, until they perish from the land that I gave to them and their ancestors.’ ”<note>Or “fathers”</note> </p>
		</chapter>