<chapter id="Je 25">
			<pericope>Seventy Years of Servitude</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 25:1">1</verse-number>The word that came to Jeremiah concerning all the people of Judah in the fourth year of Jehoiakim the son of Josiah, the king of Judah, that <supplied>was</supplied> the first year of Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon, <verse-number id="Je 25:2">2</verse-number>which Jeremiah the prophet spoke to all the people of Judah and to all the inhabitants of Jerusalem, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Je 25:3">3</verse-number>“From <supplied>the</supplied> thirteenth year of Josiah, the son of Amon, the king of Judah, even up to this day, these twenty-three years<note>Hebrew “year”</note> the word of Yahweh has come to me, and <idiom-start/>I have spoken to you over and over again<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “I have spoken to you doing early and speaking”</note> but you have not listened. <verse-number id="Je 25:4">4</verse-number>And <supplied>though</supplied> Yahweh has sent all his servants the prophets to you <idiom-start/>over and over again<idiom-end/><note>Literally “do early and sending”</note> you have not listened, and you have not inclined your ear to hear, <verse-number id="Je 25:5">5</verse-number><idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> ‘Turn back please, each one from his evil way, and from the evil of your deeds, and live on the land that Yahweh has given to you and to your ancestors<note>Or “fathers”</note> from a long time back and until forever, <verse-number id="Je 25:6">6</verse-number>and you must not go after other gods to serve them, and to bow in worship to them, and you must not provoke me to anger with the work of your hands, then I will not do something bad to you.’ <verse-number id="Je 25:7">7</verse-number>‘Yet you have not listened to me,’ <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh, ‘so that you<note>Hebrew “they”</note> have provoked me to anger with the work of your hands for your own harm.’ </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 25:8">8</verse-number><idiom-start/>Therefore<idiom-end/><note>Literally “To thus”</note> thus says Yahweh of hosts, ‘Because you have not obeyed my words, <verse-number id="Je 25:9">9</verse-number>look, I <supplied>am</supplied> going to send and take all <supplied>the</supplied> clans<note>Or “families”</note> of <supplied>the</supplied> north,’ <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh, ‘and <supplied>I will send</supplied><note>Here the subject and verb are supplied from context in the English translation</note> to Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon, my servant, and I will bring them against this land, and against its inhabitants, and against all these nations all around, and I will destroy them, and I will make them a horror, and <supplied>an object of</supplied> hissing, and <idiom-start/>everlasting ruins<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sites of ruins of eternity”</note> <verse-number id="Je 25:10">10</verse-number>And I will exterminate from them the sound of jubilation, and the sound of joy, <supplied>the</supplied> voice of <supplied>the</supplied> bridegroom, and <supplied>the</supplied> voice of <supplied>the</supplied> bride, <supplied>the</supplied> sound of <supplied>the</supplied> millstones, and <supplied>the</supplied> light of <supplied>the</supplied> lamp. <verse-number id="Je 25:11">11</verse-number>And all this land will become a site of ruins, a desolation, and these nations will serve the king of Babylon seventy years.<note>Hebrew “year”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Cup of Wrath</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 25:12">12</verse-number><idiom-start/>And then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And it will happen”</note> when <supplied>the</supplied> seventy years<note>Hebrew “year”</note> <supplied>are</supplied> fulfilled, I will punish the king of Babylon and that nation,’ <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh, ‘for their iniquity, and <supplied>the</supplied> land of <supplied>the</supplied> Chaldeans, and I will make it <idiom-start/>an everlasting waste<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “a waste of eternity”</note> <verse-number id="Je 25:13">13</verse-number>And I will bring upon that land all my words that I have spoken against it, everything that is written in this scroll which Jeremiah prophesied against all the nations. <verse-number id="Je 25:14">14</verse-number>For many nations and great kings will let them work, even them, and I will repay them according to their deeds, and according to the work of their hands.’ ” <verse-number id="Je 25:15">15</verse-number>For thus said Yahweh, the God of Israel, to me, “Take this cup of the wine <supplied>of</supplied> wrath from my hand, and you must give it <supplied>to</supplied> all the nations to whom I <supplied>am</supplied> sending you to drink. <verse-number id="Je 25:16">16</verse-number>And they will drink, and they will stagger, and they will act like madmen because of the <idiom-start/>presence<idiom-end/><note>Literally “face”</note> of the sword that I <supplied>am</supplied> sending among them.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 25:17">17</verse-number>So I took the cup from the hand of Yahweh and I gave <supplied>it</supplied><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <supplied>to</supplied> all the nations to whom Yahweh sent me to drink: <verse-number id="Je 25:18">18</verse-number>Jerusalem and the towns of Judah, and its kings, <supplied>and</supplied> its officials, to make them a site of ruins, a horror, an <supplied>object of</supplied> hissing, and a curse, as <supplied>it is</supplied> this day; <verse-number id="Je 25:19">19</verse-number>Pharaoh, the king of Egypt, and his servants, and his officials, and all his people; <verse-number id="Je 25:20">20</verse-number>and all the other<note>Or “foreign”</note> people; and all the kings of the land of Uz; and all the kings of the land of <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines—<note>Hebrew “Philistine”</note>Ashkelon, and Gaza, and Ekron, and the remnant of Ashdod; <verse-number id="Je 25:21">21</verse-number>Edom, and Moab, and the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “sons of Ammon”</note> <verse-number id="Je 25:22">22</verse-number>and all the kings of Tyre, and all the kings of Sidon, and the kings of the coastland that <supplied>is</supplied> across the sea; <verse-number id="Je 25:23">23</verse-number>and Dedan, and Tema, and Buz, and all those who are trimmed to <supplied>the</supplied> side; <verse-number id="Je 25:24">24</verse-number>and all the kings of Arabia, and all the kings of the other<note>Or “foreign”</note> people who dwell in the desert;<note>Or “wilderness”</note> <verse-number id="Je 25:25">25</verse-number>and all the kings of Zimri, and all the kings of Elam, and all the kings of Media; <verse-number id="Je 25:26">26</verse-number>and all the kings of the north, near and far, each one to his brother, and all the kingdoms of the world that <supplied>are</supplied> on the face of the earth; and the king of Sheshach, he will drink after them. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 25:27">27</verse-number>“And you shall say to them, ‘Thus says Yahweh of hosts, the God of Israel, “Drink and become drunk, and vomit, and fall, and you must not rise because of the <idiom-start/>presence<idiom-end/><note>Literally “face”</note> of the sword that I <supplied>am</supplied> sending among you.” ’ <verse-number id="Je 25:28">28</verse-number>And it will happen, if they refuse to take the cup from your hand to drink, then you shall say to them, ‘Thus says Yahweh of hosts, “You must certainly drink! <verse-number id="Je 25:29">29</verse-number>For look, on the city that is called <idiom-start/>by<idiom-end/><note>Literally “on it”</note> my name I <supplied>am</supplied> beginning to inflict harm, and you indeed, will you go unpunished? You will not go unpunished, for I <supplied>am</supplied> summoning a sword against all the inhabitants of the earth,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh of hosts.’ </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 25:30">30</verse-number>And you yourself shall prophesy against them all these words, and you shall say to them: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>‘Yahweh will roar from <supplied>on</supplied> high, </li1>
				<li2>and from <idiom-start/>his holy dwelling place<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the dwelling place of his holiness”</note> he will give his voice. </li2>
				<li1>He will roar mightily against his settlement, </li1>
				<li2>a jubilant shout like those who tread <supplied>grapes</supplied>, </li2>
				<li1>he will answer against all the inhabitants of the earth. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 25:31">31</verse-number><supplied>The</supplied> rage of battle will resound to the end of the earth, </li1>
				<li2>for <supplied>there is</supplied> a lawsuit of Yahweh against the nations. </li2>
				<li1>He <supplied>is</supplied> entering into judgment with all wicked flesh, </li1>
				<li2>he will give them to the sword,’ <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh.” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 25:32">32</verse-number>Thus says Yahweh of hosts, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Look, disaster <supplied>is</supplied> going out from nation to nation, </li1>
				<li2>and a great tempest is stirred up from the farthest parts of <supplied>the</supplied> earth. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 25:33">33</verse-number>And the slain <supplied>ones</supplied> of Yahweh will be on that day </li1>
				<li2>from <supplied>one</supplied> end of the earth to the <supplied>other</supplied> end of the earth, </li2>
				<li1>and they will not be mourned, </li1>
				<li2>and they will not be gathered, </li2>
				<li1>and they will not be buried. </li1>
				<li2>They will become like dung on the <idiom-start/>surface<idiom-end/><note>Literally “face”</note> of the ground. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 25:34">34</verse-number>Wail, you shepherds, and cry out. </li1>
				<li2>And roll about in mourning <supplied>in the dust</supplied>, O leaders<note>Or “nobles”</note> of the flock. </li2>
				<li1>For your days of slaughter and your dispersions have arrived, </li1>
				<li2>and you will fall like a vessel of desire. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 25:35">35</verse-number>And flight will perish from the shepherds, </li1>
				<li2>and escape from the leaders<note>Or “nobles”</note> of the flock. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 25:36">36</verse-number>A sound, the cry of distress of the shepherds </li1>
				<li2>and the wailing of the leaders<note>Or “nobles”</note> of the flock, </li2>
				<li2>for Yahweh <supplied>is</supplied> despoiling their pasture. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 25:37">37</verse-number>And the <idiom-start/>peaceful settlements<idiom-end/><note>Literally “settlements of the peace”</note> are devastated </li1>
				<li2>because of <idiom-start/>the burning anger of Yahweh<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the blaze of the nose of Yahweh”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Je 25:38">38</verse-number>He has left his den like a lion, </li1>
				<li2>for their land has become a horror, </li2>
				<li1>because of the anger of the oppressors, </li1>
				<li2>and because of <idiom-start/>his burning anger<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “the blaze of his nose”</note> </li2>
			</ul>
		</chapter>