<chapter id="Je 28">
			<pericope>Hananiah, the False Prophet</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 28:1">1</verse-number>And it was in that <supplied>same</supplied> year, at the beginning of the reign of Zedekiah, the king of Judah, in the fourth year, in the fifth month, that Hananiah, the son of Azzur, the prophet who <supplied>was</supplied> from Gibeon, said to me in the house of Yahweh before the eyes of the priests and all the people, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Je 28:2">2</verse-number>“Thus says Yahweh of hosts, the God of Israel, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> ‘I have broken the yoke of the king of Babylon. <verse-number id="Je 28:3">3</verse-number><idiom-start/>Within two years<idiom-end/><note>Literally “In still two years days”</note> I <supplied>will</supplied> bring back to this place all the vessels of the house of Yahweh which Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon took away from this place and brought <supplied>to</supplied> Babylon. <verse-number id="Je 28:4">4</verse-number>And Jeconiah the son of Jehoiakim, the king of Judah, and all the exiles<note>Hebrew “exile”</note> from Judah who went <supplied>to</supplied> Babylon, I <supplied>will</supplied> bring back to this place,’ <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh, ‘For I will break the yoke of the king of Babylon.’ ” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 28:5">5</verse-number>Then Jeremiah the prophet said to Hananiah the prophet before the eyes of the priests and before the eyes of all the people who were standing in the house of Yahweh, <verse-number id="Je 28:6">6</verse-number>and Jeremiah the prophet said, “Amen! May Yahweh do so; may Yahweh fulfill your words that you have prophesied, to bring back the vessels of the house of Yahweh and all the exiles<note>Hebrew “exile”</note> from Babylon to this place. <verse-number id="Je 28:7">7</verse-number>Nevertheless listen please <supplied>to</supplied> this word that I <supplied>am</supplied> speaking in your <idiom-start/>hearing<idiom-end/><note>Literally “ears”</note> and in the <idiom-start/>hearing<idiom-end/><note>Literally “ears”</note> of all the people, <verse-number id="Je 28:8">8</verse-number>The prophets who were <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of”</note> me and <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of”</note> you from ancient <supplied>times</supplied> prophesied against many countries and against great kingdoms of war, and of disaster, and of plague. <verse-number id="Je 28:9">9</verse-number>The prophet who prophesies peace, at the coming of the word of the prophet, will become known <supplied>as</supplied> the prophet that Yahweh has <idiom-start/>truly<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in truth”</note> sent.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 28:10">10</verse-number>Then Hananiah the prophet took the yoke from the neck of Jeremiah the prophet and broke it. <verse-number id="Je 28:11">11</verse-number>Then Hananiah said before the eyes of all the people, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> “Thus says Yahweh, ‘This is how I will break the yoke of Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon, <idiom-start/>within two years<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “in still two years days”</note> from the neck of all the nations.’ ” And Jeremiah the prophet went on his way. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 28:12">12</verse-number>And the word of Yahweh came to Jeremiah after Hananiah the prophet broke the yoke from the neck of Jeremiah the prophet, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Je 28:13">13</verse-number>“Go, and you must say to Hananiah, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> ‘Thus says Yahweh, “You have broken yoke bars of wood, but you have made in place of them yoke bars of iron.” <verse-number id="Je 28:14">14</verse-number>For thus says Yahweh of hosts, the God of Israel, “I have put a yoke of iron on the neck of all these nations, to serve Nebuchadnezzar, the king of Babylon, and they will serve him, and I have even given the animals<note>Hebrew “animal”</note> of the open field to him.” ’ ” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 28:15">15</verse-number>Then Jeremiah the prophet said to Hananiah the prophet, “Please listen, Hananiah, Yahweh has not sent you, and you have made this people trust in a lie. <verse-number id="Je 28:16">16</verse-number><idiom-start/>Therefore<idiom-end/><note>Literally “To thus”</note> thus says Yahweh, ‘Look, I <supplied>am</supplied> going to send you from the face of the earth. This year you <supplied>will</supplied> die because you have spoken rebellion against Yahweh.’ ” <verse-number id="Je 28:17">17</verse-number>And Hananiah the prophet died in that <supplied>same</supplied> year in the seventh month. </p>
		</chapter>