<chapter id="Je 29">
			<pericope>Jeremiah’s Letter to the Exiles in Babylon</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 29:1">1</verse-number>And these <supplied>are</supplied> the words of the letter that Jeremiah the prophet sent from Jerusalem to the remainder of the exiles,<note>Hebrew “exile”</note> and to the priests, and to the prophets, and to all the people whom Nebuchadnezzar had deported from Jerusalem <supplied>to</supplied> Babylon, <verse-number id="Je 29:2">2</verse-number>after the going out of Jeconiah the king, and the queen mother, and the court officials, the leaders of Judah and Jerusalem, and the artisans,<note>Hebrew “artisan”</note> and the smiths<note>Hebrew “smith”</note> from Jerusalem, <verse-number id="Je 29:3">3</verse-number>by the hand of Elasah, the son of Shaphan, and Gemariah, the son of Hilkiah, whom Zedekiah, the king of Judah, sent to Nebuchadnezzar, the king of Babylon, <supplied>to</supplied> Babylon, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Je 29:4">4</verse-number>“Thus says Yahweh of hosts, the God of Israel, to all the exiles<note>Hebrew “exile”</note> whom I have deported from Jerusalem <supplied>to</supplied> Babylon, <verse-number id="Je 29:5">5</verse-number>‘Build houses and live <supplied>in them</supplied>,<note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and plant gardens and eat their fruit. <verse-number id="Je 29:6">6</verse-number>Take wives and father sons and daughters, and take for your sons wives, and give your daughters to men that they may bear sons and daughters, and multiply there, and you must not be few. <verse-number id="Je 29:7">7</verse-number>And seek the prosperity of the city where I have deported you, and pray on behalf of it to Yahweh, for in its prosperity you will have prosperity.’ </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 29:8">8</verse-number>For thus says Yahweh of hosts, the God of Israel, ‘Do not let your prophets who <supplied>are</supplied> in your midst, and your diviners, deceive you, and you must not listen to your dreams that you <supplied>are</supplied> causing <supplied>them</supplied> to dream. <verse-number id="Je 29:9">9</verse-number>For they <supplied>are</supplied> prophesying <idiom-start/>falsely<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in a lie”</note> to you in my name; I have not sent them,’ <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh. <verse-number id="Je 29:10">10</verse-number>For thus says Yahweh, ‘<idiom-start/>As soon as the time has passed<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “When to the mouth of being full”</note> seventy years<note>Hebrew “year”</note> for Babylon, I will attend to you, and I will fulfill my good word to you, to bring you back to this place. <verse-number id="Je 29:11">11</verse-number>For I know the plans that I <supplied>am</supplied> planning concerning you,’ <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh, ‘plans for prosperity and not for harm, to give to you a future and a hope. <verse-number id="Je 29:12">12</verse-number>Then <supplied>when</supplied> you call me, and you come and pray to me, then I will listen to you. <verse-number id="Je 29:13">13</verse-number>When you search for me, then you will find <supplied>me</supplied>, if you seek me with all your heart. <verse-number id="Je 29:14">14</verse-number>And I will let myself be found by you,’ <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh, ‘and I will restore your fortunes,<note>Hebrew “fortune”</note> and I will gather you from all the nations and from all the places to which I have driven you,’ <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh, ‘and I will bring you back to the place from which I deported you.’ </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 29:15">15</verse-number>Because you have said, ‘Yahweh has raised up prophets for us <supplied>in</supplied> Babylon’— <verse-number id="Je 29:16">16</verse-number>for thus says Yahweh concerning the king who sits on the throne of David and concerning all the people who live in this city, your fellow kinsmen who did not go with you into the exile— <verse-number id="Je 29:17">17</verse-number>thus says Yahweh of hosts, ‘Look, I <supplied>am</supplied> going to send among them the sword, the famine, and the plague, and I will make them like rotten figs that cannot be eaten because of <supplied>their</supplied> bad quality. <verse-number id="Je 29:18">18</verse-number>And I will pursue them with the sword, with the famine, and with the plague, and I will make them a terror to all the kingdoms of the earth, a curse, and a horror, and <supplied>an object of</supplied> hissing, and a disgrace among all the nations to which I have driven them, <verse-number id="Je 29:19">19</verse-number>because they did not listen to my words,’ <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh, ‘when I sent to them my servants the prophets, <idiom-start/>sending over and over again<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “doing early and sending”</note> and they would not listen,’ <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 29:20">20</verse-number>And you, hear the word of Yahweh, all <supplied>you</supplied> exiles<note>Hebrew “exile”</note> whom I sent away from Jerusalem <supplied>to</supplied> Babylon. <verse-number id="Je 29:21">21</verse-number>Thus says Yahweh of hosts, the God of Israel, concerning Ahab, the son of Kolaiah, and concerning Zedekiah, the son of Maaseiah, who are prophesying to you in my name a lie, ‘Look, I <supplied>am</supplied> going to give them into the hand of Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon, and he will strike them before your eyes. <verse-number id="Je 29:22">22</verse-number>And a curse will be taken <supplied>up</supplied> because of them by all the exiles<note>Hebrew “exile”</note> of Judah who <supplied>are</supplied> in Babylon, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> “May Yahweh make you like Zedekiah and like Ahab, whom the king of Babylon roasted in the fire,” <verse-number id="Je 29:23">23</verse-number>because they have done a disgraceful thing in Israel, and they have committed adultery with the wives of their neighbors, and they have spoken words<note>Hebrew “word”</note> in my name, lies<note>Hebrew “lie”</note> that I have not commanded them, and I <supplied>am</supplied> he who knows, and <supplied>I am</supplied> a witness,’ <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Shemaiah’s Letter to Zephaniah the Priest</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 29:24">24</verse-number>And to Shemaiah the Nehelamite you shall say, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Je 29:25">25</verse-number>“Thus says Yahweh of hosts, the God of Israel, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> ‘Because you yourself sent <supplied>a</supplied> letter<note>Hebrew “letters”</note> in your name to all the people who <supplied>are</supplied> in Jerusalem, and to Zephaniah, the son of Maaseiah, the priest, and to all the priests, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Je 29:26">26</verse-number>“Yahweh made you priest instead of Jehoiada the priest, so that there are overseers <supplied>in</supplied> the house of Yahweh over any mad man <supplied>who</supplied> exhibits the behavior of a prophet, and you must put him into the stocks and into the neck iron, <verse-number id="Je 29:27">27</verse-number>and so then why have you not rebuked Jeremiah the Anathothite who exhibits the behavior of a prophet for you? <verse-number id="Je 29:28">28</verse-number><idiom-start/>Because<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Seeing that unto thus”</note> he has sent to us <supplied>in</supplied> Babylon, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> ‘It <supplied>will be</supplied> a long time, build houses and live <supplied>in them</supplied>,<note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and plant gardens and eat their fruit.’ ” ’ ” <verse-number id="Je 29:29">29</verse-number>And Zephaniah the priest read this letter in the <idiom-start/>hearing<idiom-end/><note>Literally “ears”</note> of Jeremiah the prophet. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jeremiah’s Response to Shemaiah’s Letter</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 29:30">30</verse-number>And the word of Yahweh came to Jeremiah, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Je 29:31">31</verse-number>“Send to all the exiles,<note>Hebrew “exile”</note> <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> ‘Thus says Yahweh concerning Shemaiah the Nehelamite: “Because Shemaiah prophesied to you, though I have not sent him, and he has made you trust in a lie,” <verse-number id="Je 29:32">32</verse-number><idiom-start/>therefore<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to thus”</note> thus says Yahweh, “Look, I <supplied>am</supplied> going to punish Shemaiah the Nehelamite and his offspring. There will not be for him a man who lives in the midst of this people, and he will not see the good that I <supplied>am</supplied> going to do to my people,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh, “For he has spoken rebellion against Yahweh.” ’ ” </p>
		</chapter>