<chapter id="Je 33">
			<pericope>The Fortunes of Judah and Israel Will Be Restored</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 33:1">1</verse-number>And the word of Yahweh came to Jeremiah <supplied>a</supplied> second <supplied>time</supplied> while he <supplied>was</supplied> still held back in the courtyard of the guard, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Je 33:2">2</verse-number>“Thus says Yahweh who made <supplied>the earth</supplied>,<note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> Yahweh who formed it to establish it, Yahweh <supplied>is</supplied> his name: <verse-number id="Je 33:3">3</verse-number>‘Call to me, and I will answer you, and I will tell you great <supplied>things</supplied> and inaccessible <supplied>things that</supplied> you have not known.’ <verse-number id="Je 33:4">4</verse-number>For thus says Yahweh, the God of Israel, concerning the houses of this city and concerning the houses of the kings of Judah, that were torn down <supplied>to make a defense</supplied> against the siege ramps and against the sword: <verse-number id="Je 33:5">5</verse-number>‘<supplied>They are</supplied> coming to fight against the Chaldeans, and to fill them with the corpses of the people whom I will strike in my anger and in my wrath, for whom I have hidden my face from this city because of all their wickedness. <verse-number id="Je 33:6">6</verse-number>Look, I <supplied>am</supplied> going to bring healing and health to it, and I will heal them, and I will reveal to them abundance of peace and reliability. <verse-number id="Je 33:7">7</verse-number>And I will restore the fortunes<note>Hebrew “fortune”</note> of Judah and the fortunes<note>Hebrew “fortune”</note> of Israel, and I will rebuild them as in the beginning. <verse-number id="Je 33:8">8</verse-number>And I will cleanse them from all their guilt that they sinned against me, and I will forgive all their iniquities that they sinned against me, and that they rebelled against me. <verse-number id="Je 33:9">9</verse-number>And it will be to me a name of jubilation, a praise, and a glory before all the nations of the earth, who will hear all the good that I <supplied>will</supplied> do <supplied>for</supplied> them, and they will fear,<note>Or “tremble”</note> and they will tremble because of all the good, and because of all the prosperity that I <supplied>will</supplied> provide for it.’ </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 33:10">10</verse-number>“Thus says Yahweh: ‘Again will be heard in this place, <supplied>of</supplied> which you <supplied>are</supplied> saying, “It <supplied>is</supplied> a waste, <idiom-start/>without<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from there is not”</note> people and <idiom-start/>without<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from there is not”</note> animals,”<note>Hebrew “animal”</note> in the towns of Judah and in the streets of Jerusalem that are desolate, <idiom-start/>without<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from there is not”</note> people and <idiom-start/>without<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from there is not”</note> inhabitants<note>Hebrew “inhabitant”</note> and <idiom-start/>without<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from there is not”</note> animals,<note>Hebrew “animal”</note> <verse-number id="Je 33:11">11</verse-number><supplied>the</supplied> voice of jubilation, and <supplied>the</supplied> voice of joy, <supplied>the</supplied> voice of <supplied>the</supplied> bridegroom, and <supplied>the</supplied> voice of <supplied>the</supplied> bride, <supplied>the</supplied> voices<note>Hebrew “voice”</note> of <supplied>those who</supplied> say, “Praise Yahweh of hosts, for Yahweh <supplied>is</supplied> good, for his loyal love <supplied>is</supplied> <idiom-start/>forever<idiom-end/>,”<note>Literally “to eternity”</note> <supplied>the voices of those who</supplied> bring thank offerings<note>Hebrew “thank offering”</note> <supplied>to</supplied> the house of Yahweh, for I will restore the fortunes<note>Hebrew “fortune”</note> of the land as in the beginning,’ says Yahweh. <verse-number id="Je 33:12">12</verse-number>Thus says Yahweh of hosts: ‘Again there will be in this waste place, <idiom-start/>without<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from there is not”</note> people and animals,<note>Hebrew “animal”</note> and in all its towns, pasture for shepherds allowing <supplied>their</supplied> flock to lie down. <verse-number id="Je 33:13">13</verse-number>In the towns of the hill country, in the towns of the Shephelah, and in the towns of the Negev, and in the land of Benjamin, and in the surroundings <supplied>of</supplied> Jerusalem, and in the towns of Judah, flocks will again pass under <supplied>the</supplied> hands of <supplied>the</supplied> counter,’ says Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 33:14">14</verse-number>‘Look, days <supplied>are</supplied> coming,’ <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh, ‘and I will fulfill the good promise<note>Or “word”</note> that I promised to the house of Israel and to the house of Judah. <verse-number id="Je 33:15">15</verse-number>In those days and in that time I will make a branch of righteousness sprout for David, and he will execute justice and righteousness in the land. <verse-number id="Je 33:16">16</verse-number>In those days Judah will be saved, and Jerusalem will dwell <idiom-start/>safely<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “with confidence”</note> and this <supplied>is</supplied> what they shall call it: “Yahweh <supplied>is</supplied> our righteousness.” ’ <verse-number id="Je 33:17">17</verse-number>For thus says Yahweh: ‘A man who sits on the throne of the house of Israel will not be cut off for David. <verse-number id="Je 33:18">18</verse-number>And for the priests, a man from the Levites <supplied>who</supplied> offers burnt offerings<note>Hebrew “burnt offering”</note> and <supplied>who</supplied> burns grain offerings<note>Hebrew “grain offering”</note> and <supplied>who</supplied> brings sacrifices<note>Hebrew “sacrifice”</note> will not be cut off <idiom-start/>before me<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of me”</note> <idiom-start/>forever<idiom-end/>.’ ”<note>Literally “all the days”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 33:19">19</verse-number>And the word of Yahweh came to Jeremiah, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Je 33:20">20</verse-number>“Thus says Yahweh: ‘If you could break my covenant <supplied>with</supplied> the day, and my covenant <supplied>with</supplied> the night, so that day and night <supplied>would</supplied> not come at their time, <verse-number id="Je 33:21">21</verse-number>then my covenant could be broken with David my servant, from <idiom-start/>having<idiom-end/><note>Literally “being for him”</note> a son who could rule on his throne, and with the Levites, the priests, my ministers. <verse-number id="Je 33:22">22</verse-number>As the host of heaven cannot be counted, and the sand of the sea cannot be measured, so I will make numerous the offspring of David my servant and the Levites <supplied>who</supplied> minister <supplied>to</supplied> me.’ ” <verse-number id="Je 33:23">23</verse-number>And the word of Yahweh came to Jeremiah, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Je 33:24">24</verse-number>“Have you not seen how these people speak, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> ‘The two clans<note>Or “families”</note> whom Yahweh chose, he has also rejected them’? Thus they spurn my people from being a nation <idiom-start/>before them<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of them”</note> <supplied>any</supplied> longer. <verse-number id="Je 33:25">25</verse-number>Thus says Yahweh: ‘If my covenant <supplied>with</supplied> day and <supplied>with</supplied> night, <supplied>the</supplied> regulations of heaven and earth, I had not established, <verse-number id="Je 33:26">26</verse-number>then the offspring of Jacob and David my servant I would reject, from choosing rulers from his offspring over the offspring of Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob; for I will restore their fortunes<note>Hebrew “fortune”</note> and I will have compassion on them.’ ” </p>
		</chapter>