<chapter id="Je 37">
			<pericope>The Babylonians Withdraw to Meet a Threat from Egypt</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 37:1">1</verse-number>And king Zedekiah, the son of Josiah, whom Nebuchadnezzar, the king of Babylon, had made king, reigned as king in the land of Judah in place of Coniah, the son of Jehoiakim. <verse-number id="Je 37:2">2</verse-number>But he and his servants and the people of the land did not listen to the words of Yahweh that he spoke by the hand of Jeremiah the prophet. <verse-number id="Je 37:3">3</verse-number>And king Zedekiah sent Jehucal the son of Shelemiah, and Zephaniah the son of Maaseiah, the priest, to Jeremiah the prophet, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> “Please pray for us to Yahweh our God.” <verse-number id="Je 37:4">4</verse-number>Now Jeremiah <supplied>was</supplied> coming and going out in the midst of the people and they had not put him <supplied>in</supplied> the house of imprisonment. <verse-number id="Je 37:5">5</verse-number>And the army of Pharaoh had come out from Egypt, and the Chaldeans, who were laying siege to Jerusalem, heard their report and they withdrew from Jerusalem. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 37:6">6</verse-number>And the word of Yahweh came to Jeremiah the prophet, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Je 37:7">7</verse-number>“Thus says Yahweh, the God of Israel, ‘This is what you shall say to the king of Judah, who sent you to me to inquire <supplied>of</supplied> me, “Look, the army of Pharaoh, which set out to help you, <supplied>is</supplied> going to return to his land Egypt. <verse-number id="Je 37:8">8</verse-number>And the Chaldeans will return, and they will fight against this city, and they will capture it, and they will burn it with fire.” ’ <verse-number id="Je 37:9">9</verse-number>Thus says Yahweh: ‘You must not deceive yourselves, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> “Surely the Chaldeans will go from us,” for they will not go. <verse-number id="Je 37:10">10</verse-number>For <supplied>even</supplied> if you struck the whole army of <supplied>the</supplied> Chaldeans who are fighting against you, and <supplied>only</supplied> men pierced through remained among them, each one in his tent, they would rise up and they would burn this city with fire.’ ” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jeremiah is Arrested and Put in Prison</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 37:11">11</verse-number><idiom-start/>And then<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “And it will happen”</note> at the withdrawing of the army of the Chaldeans from Jerusalem <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from the face of”</note> the army of Pharaoh, <verse-number id="Je 37:12">12</verse-number>Jeremiah set out from Jerusalem to go <supplied>to</supplied> the land of Benjamin to receive a portion from there in the midst of the people. <verse-number id="Je 37:13">13</verse-number><idiom-start/>And when<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And it was”</note> he <supplied>was</supplied> at the Gate of Benjamin, there <supplied>was</supplied> <idiom-start/>a sentry on duty<idiom-end/><note>Literally “an owner of supervision”</note> whose name <supplied>was</supplied> Irijah, the son of Shelemiah, the son of Hananiah, and he seized Jeremiah the prophet, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> “You <supplied>are</supplied> deserting to the Chaldeans!” <verse-number id="Je 37:14">14</verse-number>And Jeremiah said, “<supplied>That is</supplied> a lie! I <supplied>am</supplied> not deserting to the Chaldeans.” But he would not listen to him. So Irijah seized Jeremiah and brought him to the officials. <verse-number id="Je 37:15">15</verse-number>And the officials were angry at Jeremiah and they struck him. And they put him <supplied>in</supplied> <idiom-start/>prison<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the house of the fetters”</note> <supplied>in</supplied> the house of Jonathan the secretary, for they had converted it to the <idiom-start/>prison<idiom-end/><note>Literally “house of the imprisonment”</note>. <verse-number id="Je 37:16">16</verse-number>So Jeremiah came to the <idiom-start/>dungeon<idiom-end/><note>Literally “house of the cistern”</note>, even to the vaulted cells, and Jeremiah stayed there many days. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 37:17">17</verse-number>Then King Zedekiah sent and fetched him. And the king questioned him in secrecy in his house, and he said, “Is there a word from Yahweh?” And Jeremiah said, “There is.” And he said, “You will be given into the hand of the king of Babylon.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 37:18">18</verse-number>Then Jeremiah said to King Zedekiah, “What did I do wrong to you, or to your servants, or to this people, that you have put me in <idiom-start/>prison<idiom-end/>?<note>Literally “the house of the imprisonment”</note> <verse-number id="Je 37:19">19</verse-number>And where <supplied>are</supplied> your prophets who prophesied to you, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> ‘The king of Babylon will not come against you and against this land’? <verse-number id="Je 37:20">20</verse-number>Now then, my lord the king, please let my plea fall <idiom-start/>before you<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to the face of you”</note> You must not send me back <supplied>to</supplied> the house of Jonathan the secretary, so that I will not die there.” <verse-number id="Je 37:21">21</verse-number>So King Zedekiah commanded, and they handed Jeremiah over in the courtyard of the guard, and they gave to him a round loaf of bread from the street of the bakers <idiom-start/>every day<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for the day”</note> until the finishing of all the bread from the city. And Jeremiah stayed in the courtyard of the guard. </p>
		</chapter>