<chapter id="Je 39">
			<pericope>The Fall of Jerusalem</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 39:1">1</verse-number>In the ninth year of Zedekiah, the king of Judah, in the tenth month, Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon and all his army came against Jerusalem and laid siege to it. <verse-number id="Je 39:2">2</verse-number>In the eleventh year of Zedekiah, in the fourth month, on <supplied>the</supplied> ninth <supplied>day</supplied> of the month, the city was taken by assault. <verse-number id="Je 39:3">3</verse-number>And all the officials of the king of Babylon came and sat in the Middle Gate: Nergal-sharezer, Samgar-nebo, Sarsechim <supplied>the</supplied> chief officer, Nergal-sharezer <supplied>the</supplied> high official, with all the rest of the officials of the king of Babylon. <verse-number id="Je 39:4">4</verse-number><idiom-start/>And then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And it was”</note> <idiom-start/>when<idiom-end/><note>Literally “as that”</note> Zedekiah the king of Judah saw them, and all <idiom-start/>the soldiers<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the men of the war”</note> <supplied>with him</supplied>, they fled and went out <supplied>at</supplied> night from the city <supplied>by</supplied> the way of the garden of the king through <supplied>the</supplied> gate between the walls. And they went out toward the Jordan Valley. <verse-number id="Je 39:5">5</verse-number>But the army of <supplied>the</supplied> Chaldeans pursued after them and overtook Zedekiah in the plains of Jericho. And they took him and brought him up to Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon <supplied>at</supplied> Riblah in the land of Hamath. And he pronounced <idiom-start/>sentence<idiom-end/><note>Literally “judgments”</note> on him. <verse-number id="Je 39:6">6</verse-number>And the king of Babylon slaughtered the sons of Zedekiah at Riblah before his eyes. The king of Babylon also slaughtered all the nobles of Judah. <verse-number id="Je 39:7">7</verse-number>Then he blinded the eyes of Zedekiah and tied him up with bronze fetters to bring him <supplied>to</supplied> Babylon. <verse-number id="Je 39:8">8</verse-number>And the Chaldeans burned the palace<note>Or “house”</note> of the king and the houses<note>Hebrew “house”</note> of the people with fire and broke down the walls of Jerusalem. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 39:9">9</verse-number>Then the rest of the people who were left in the city, and those deserting who had deserted to him, and the rest of the people who remained, Nebuzaradan, <supplied>the</supplied> captain of <supplied>the</supplied> guard,<note>Hebrew “guards”</note> deported <supplied>to</supplied> Babylon. <verse-number id="Je 39:10">10</verse-number>And some of the poor people, <idiom-start/>who had nothing<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “who there was not for them something”</note> Nebuzaradan, <supplied>the</supplied> captain of <supplied>the</supplied> guard,<note>Hebrew “guards”</note> left in the land of Judah. And he gave them vineyards and fields on that day. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 39:11">11</verse-number>And Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon commanded concerning Jeremiah <idiom-start/>through<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the hand of”</note> Nebuzaradan, <supplied>the</supplied> captain of <supplied>the</supplied> guard,<note>Hebrew “guards”</note> <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Je 39:12">12</verse-number>“Take him and set your eyes on him. And you must not do something bad to him, <idiom-start/>but only<idiom-end/><note>Literally “but if”</note> that which he speaks to you, so do with him.” <verse-number id="Je 39:13">13</verse-number>So Nebuzaradan, <supplied>the</supplied> captain of <supplied>the</supplied> guard,<note>Hebrew “guards”</note> sent <supplied>word</supplied>, <idiom-start/>along with<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and”</note> Nebushazban <supplied>the</supplied> chief officer, and Nergal-sharezer <supplied>the</supplied> high official, and all the chief officers of the king of Babylon. <verse-number id="Je 39:14">14</verse-number>And they sent and took Jeremiah from the courtyard of the guard and gave him to Gedaliah the son of Ahikam, the son of Shaphan, to take him to the house, so he stayed in the midst of the people. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Ebed-melech is Rewarded for His Faith</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 39:15">15</verse-number>And the word of Yahweh came to Jeremiah at his confinement in the courtyard of the guard, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> <verse-number id="Je 39:16">16</verse-number>“Go and say to Ebed-melech the Cushite, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> ‘Thus says Yahweh of hosts, the God of Israel: “Look, I <supplied>am</supplied> about to bring my words to pass against this city for evil and not for good. And they will be <idiom-start/>before you<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of you”</note> on that day. <verse-number id="Je 39:17">17</verse-number>But I will rescue you on that day,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh, “and you will not be given into the hand of the men <idiom-start/>of whom you are frightened<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “who you <supplied>are</supplied> frightened from the face of them”</note> <verse-number id="Je 39:18">18</verse-number>For surely I will save you, and you will not fall by the sword. But your life will be for you as booty because you have trusted in me,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a declaration of”</note> Yahweh.’ ” </p>
		</chapter>