<chapter id="Je 43">
			<p><verse-number id="Je 43">43</verse-number><verse-number id="Je 43:1">1</verse-number> <idiom-start/>And then<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “And it was”</note> when Jeremiah had finished speaking to all the people all the words of Yahweh their God, for which Yahweh their God had sent him to them with all these words, <verse-number id="Je 43:2">2</verse-number>Azariah the son of Hoshaiah, and Johanan the son of Kareah, and all the insolent men spoke,<note>The Hebrew verb is singular</note> saying to Jeremiah, “You <supplied>are</supplied> telling a lie! Yahweh our God did not send you, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to say”</note> ‘You must not go <supplied>to</supplied> Egypt to dwell as aliens there.’ <verse-number id="Je 43:3">3</verse-number>But Baruch the son of Neriah <supplied>is</supplied> inciting you against us in order to give us into the hand of the Chaldeans, to kill us and to deport us <supplied>to</supplied> Babylon.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 43:4">4</verse-number>So Johanan the son of Kareah and all the commanders of the armies, and all the people did not listen<note>The Hebrew verb is singular</note> to the voice of Yahweh to stay in the land of Judah. <verse-number id="Je 43:5">5</verse-number>But Johanan the son of Kareah and all the commanders of the armies took<note>The Hebrew verb is singular</note> all the remnant of Judah who had returned from all the nations <supplied>to</supplied> which they had been scattered to dwell as aliens in the land of Judah— <verse-number id="Je 43:6">6</verse-number>the men, and the women, and the little children, and the daughters of the king, and <idiom-start/>everyone<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all of the person”</note> whom Nebuzaradan <supplied>the</supplied> captain of <supplied>the</supplied> <idiom-start/>guard<idiom-end/><note>Hebrew “guards”</note> had left with Gedaliah the son of Ahikam, the son of Shaphan, and Jeremiah the prophet, and Baruch the son of Neriah— <verse-number id="Je 43:7">7</verse-number>and they came <supplied>into</supplied> the land of Egypt, for they did not listen to the voice of Yahweh. And they came up to Tahpanhes. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Throne of Nebuchadnezzar Will be Set Up at Tahpanhes</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 43:8">8</verse-number>And the word of Yahweh came to Jeremiah in Tahpanhes, <idiom-start/>saying<idiom-end/>, <verse-number id="Je 43:9">9</verse-number>“Take in your hands<note>Hebrew “hand”</note> large stones and bury them in the mortar in the clay floor that <supplied>is</supplied> at the entrance of the palace<note>Or “house”</note> of Pharaoh in Tahpanhes before the eyes of <supplied>the</supplied> people<note>Or “men”</note> of <supplied>the</supplied> Judeans, <verse-number id="Je 43:10">10</verse-number>and say to them, ‘Thus says Yahweh of hosts, the God of Israel: “Look, I <supplied>am</supplied> going to send and take Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon, my servant, and I will set his throne above these stones that I have hidden. And he will spread out his canopy over them. <verse-number id="Je 43:11">11</verse-number>And he will come and ravage the land of Egypt, <supplied>and deliver those</supplied> who <supplied>are appointed</supplied> for the plague, to the plague, and <supplied>those</supplied> who <supplied>are appointed</supplied> for the captivity, to the captivity, and <supplied>those</supplied> who <supplied>are appointed</supplied> for the sword, to the sword. <verse-number id="Je 43:12">12</verse-number>Then he will kindle a fire in the <idiom-start/>temples<idiom-end/><note>Literally “houses”</note> of the gods of Egypt, and he will burn them and take them captive. And he will wrap up the land of Egypt just as the shepherd wraps up his cloak. And he will go forth from there in peace. <verse-number id="Je 43:13">13</verse-number>And he will break the stone pillars of Heliopolis, which <supplied>is</supplied> in the land of Egypt. And he will burn the <idiom-start/>temples<idiom-end/><note>Literally “houses”</note> of the gods of Egypt with fire.” ’ ” </p>
		</chapter>