<chapter id="Je 52">
			<pericope>The Fall of Jerusalem</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 52:1">1</verse-number>Zedekiah <supplied>was</supplied> <idiom-start/>twenty-one years old<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a son of twenty-one year”</note> at his beginning to reign, and he reigned eleven years<note>Hebrew “year”</note> in Jerusalem. And the name of his mother <supplied>was</supplied> Hamutal, the daughter of Jeremiah of Libnah. <verse-number id="Je 52:2">2</verse-number>And he did evil in the eyes of Yahweh like all that Jehoiakim had done. <verse-number id="Je 52:3">3</verse-number>For because of the <idiom-start/>anger<idiom-end/><note>Literally “nose”</note> of Yahweh this happened in Jerusalem and Judah until his casting them from his <idiom-start/>presence<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “face”</note> And Zedekiah rebelled against the king of Babylon. <verse-number id="Je 52:4">4</verse-number><idiom-start/>And then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And it was”</note> in the ninth year of his reign, in the tenth month, on the tenth <supplied>day</supplied> of the month, Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon came against Jerusalem, he and all his army. And they laid siege to it, and built siege works<note>Literally “siege work”</note> against it all around. <verse-number id="Je 52:5">5</verse-number>So the city came <idiom-start/>under siege<idiom-end/><note>Literally “into the siege”</note> until <supplied>the</supplied> eleventh year of King Zedekiah. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 52:6">6</verse-number>In the fourth month, on <supplied>the</supplied> ninth <supplied>day</supplied> of the month, the famine in the city became severe and there was no food for the people of the land. <verse-number id="Je 52:7">7</verse-number>Then the city was breached, and all <idiom-start/>the soldiers<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the men of the battle”</note> fled and went out from the city <supplied>by</supplied> night <supplied>by the</supplied> way of <supplied>the</supplied> gate between the two walls that <supplied>are</supplied> at the garden of the king, though <supplied>the</supplied> Chaldeans <supplied>were</supplied> all around the city. And they went <supplied>in</supplied> the direction of the Jordan Valley.<note>Or “Arabah”</note> <verse-number id="Je 52:8">8</verse-number>But the army of <supplied>the</supplied> Chaldeans pursued after the king and they overtook Zedekiah in the plains of Jericho, and all his army was scattered from him. <verse-number id="Je 52:9">9</verse-number>Then they captured the king and brought him up to the king of Babylon <supplied>at</supplied> Riblah in the land of Hamath, and <idiom-start/>he passed sentence on him<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “he spoke to him judgments”</note> <verse-number id="Je 52:10">10</verse-number>And the king of Babylon slaughtered the sons of Zedekiah before his eyes, and he also slaughtered all the officials of Judah at Riblah. <verse-number id="Je 52:11">11</verse-number>Then he made blind the eyes of Zedekiah, and they tied him up with bronze fetters, and the king of Babylon brought him <supplied>to</supplied> Babylon. And he put him in <idiom-start/>prison<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the house of the watch”</note> until the day of his death. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 52:12">12</verse-number>Now in the fifth month, on the tenth <supplied>day</supplied> of the month, which <supplied>was the</supplied> nineteenth year of King Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon, Nebuzaradan <supplied>the</supplied> captain of <supplied>the</supplied> guard,<note>Hebrew “guards”</note> who stood <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of”</note> the king of Babylon, entered into Jerusalem. <verse-number id="Je 52:13">13</verse-number>And he burned the <idiom-start/>temple<idiom-end/><note>Literally “house”</note> of Yahweh, and the palace<note>Or “house”</note> of the king, and all the houses of Jerusalem, even every great house he burned with fire. <verse-number id="Je 52:14">14</verse-number>And all the army of <supplied>the</supplied> Chaldeans who <supplied>were</supplied> with <supplied>the</supplied> captain of <supplied>the</supplied> guard<note>Hebrew “guards”</note> broke down all the walls of Jerusalem all around. <verse-number id="Je 52:15">15</verse-number>And Nebuzaradan <supplied>the</supplied> captain of <supplied>the</supplied> guard<note>Hebrew “guards”</note> deported <supplied>some</supplied> of the poor of the people, and the rest of the people who were left in the city, and the deserters who deserted to the king of Babylon, along with the rest of the craftsmen. <verse-number id="Je 52:16">16</verse-number>But Nebuzaradan <supplied>the</supplied> captain of <supplied>the</supplied> guard<note>Hebrew “guards”</note> left <supplied>some</supplied> of the poor of the land <supplied>to serve</supplied> as vinedressers and farmers. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 52:17">17</verse-number>And <supplied>the</supplied> Chaldeans broke the pillars of bronze that <supplied>were</supplied> in the <idiom-start/>temple<idiom-end/><note>Literally “house”</note> of Yahweh, and the kettle stands and the sea of bronze that <supplied>were</supplied> in the <idiom-start/>temple<idiom-end/><note>Literally “house”</note> of Yahweh, and they carried all their bronze <supplied>to</supplied> Babylon. <verse-number id="Je 52:18">18</verse-number>And they took with them the pots, and the shovels, and the snuffers, and the sprinkling bowls, and the pans, and all the vessels of bronze which <supplied>were used in temple</supplied> service. <verse-number id="Je 52:19">19</verse-number>And <supplied>the</supplied> captain of <supplied>the</supplied> guard<note>Hebrew “guards”</note> <supplied>took</supplied> the bowls, and the firepans, and the sprinkling bowls, and the pots, and the lampstands, and the pans, and the libation bowls, <idiom-start/>those made of solid gold<idiom-end/><note>Literally “which gold gold”</note> and <idiom-start/>those made of solid silver<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “which silver silver”</note> <verse-number id="Je 52:20">20</verse-number>The two pillars, the one sea, and the twelve bronze oxen that <supplied>were</supplied> under the kettle stands which King Solomon had made for the <idiom-start/>temple<idiom-end/><note>Literally “house”</note> of Yahweh—there was not a weight for the bronze of all these vessels! <verse-number id="Je 52:21">21</verse-number>Now the pillars, <supplied>the</supplied> height of one pillar <supplied>was</supplied> eighteen cubits,<note>Hebrew “cubit”</note> and a thread of twelve cubits<note>Hebrew “cubit”</note> surrounded it, and its thickness <supplied>was</supplied> four fingers, hollowed out. <verse-number id="Je 52:22">22</verse-number>And a capital upon it <supplied>was</supplied> bronze and the height of the one capital <supplied>was</supplied> five cubits, and latticework and pomegranates <supplied>were</supplied> on the capital on all sides, all <supplied>of</supplied> bronze. And like these <supplied>was</supplied> the second pillar with pomegranates. <verse-number id="Je 52:23">23</verse-number>And there were ninety-six pomegranates <idiom-start/>on the sides<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “breath”</note> all the pomegranates on the latticework on all sides <supplied>were</supplied> a hundred. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 52:24">24</verse-number>Then <supplied>the</supplied> captain of <supplied>the</supplied> guard<note>Hebrew “guards”</note> took Seraiah <idiom-start/>the chief priest<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the priest of the head”</note> and Zephaniah <idiom-start/>the second priest<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the priest of the second”</note> and three keepers of the threshold. <verse-number id="Je 52:25">25</verse-number>And from the city he took one high official who was chief officer over <idiom-start/>the soldiers<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the men of the battle”</note> and seven men of <idiom-start/>the king’s advisors<idiom-end/><note>Literally “those who see the face of the king”</note> who were found in the city, and the secretary of the commander of the army who levied for military service the people of the land, and sixty men<note>Hebrew “man”</note> of the people of the land who were found in the midst of the city. <verse-number id="Je 52:26">26</verse-number>Then Nebuzaradan <supplied>the</supplied> captain of <supplied>the</supplied> guard<note>Hebrew “guards”</note> took them and brought them to the king of Babylon <supplied>at</supplied> Riblah. <verse-number id="Je 52:27">27</verse-number>And the king of Babylon struck them down and killed them at Riblah in the land of Hamath. So Judah left from its land. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 52:28">28</verse-number>This <supplied>is the number of</supplied> the people whom Nebuchadnezzar deported: in <supplied>the</supplied> seventh year, three thousand twenty-three Judeans; <verse-number id="Je 52:29">29</verse-number>in <supplied>the</supplied> eighteenth year of Nebuchadnezzar, eight hundred and thirty-two persons<note>Hebrew “person”</note> from Jerusalem; <verse-number id="Je 52:30">30</verse-number>in <supplied>the</supplied> twenty-third year of Nebuchadnezzar, Nebuzaradan, <supplied>the</supplied> captain of <supplied>the</supplied> guard,<note>Hebrew “guards”</note> deported seven hundred and forty-five Judean persons;<note>Hebrew “person”</note> <supplied>there were</supplied> four thousand six hundred persons<note>Hebrew “person”</note> in all. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>An Allowance for Jehoiachin</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Je 52:31">31</verse-number><idiom-start/>And then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and it was”</note> in <supplied>the</supplied> thirty-seventh year of the exile of Jehoiachin, the king of Judah, in <supplied>the</supplied> twelfth month, on <supplied>the</supplied> twenty-fifth <supplied>day</supplied> of the month, Evil-merodach, the king of Babylon, in the <supplied>first</supplied> year of his reign, lifted up the head of Jehoiachin, the king of Judah, and brought him out from <idiom-start/>prison<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the house of the imprisonment”</note> <verse-number id="Je 52:32">32</verse-number>Then he spoke with him kindly and gave his seat above the seats<note>Hebrew “seat”</note> of the kings who <supplied>were</supplied> with him in Babylon. <verse-number id="Je 52:33">33</verse-number>So he changed the garments of his imprisonment and he ate food <idiom-start/>before him<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of him”</note> continually all the days of his life. <verse-number id="Je 52:34">34</verse-number>And his allowance, a continual allowance was given to him by the king of Babylon <idiom-start/>on a daily basis<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a matter of a day in its day”</note> all the days of his life up to the day of his death. </p>
		</chapter>