<chapter id="Jos 1">
			<pericope>Joshua Addresses the Israelites</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 1:1">1</verse-number>After the death of Moses the servant of Yahweh, Yahweh said to Joshua son of Nun, the assistant<note>Or “servant”</note> of Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Jos 1:2">2</verse-number>“My servant Moses <supplied>is</supplied> dead. Get up and cross the Jordan, you and all this people, into the land that I <supplied>am</supplied> giving to them, to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> <verse-number id="Jos 1:3">3</verse-number>Every place that the soles of your feet will tread, I have given it to you, as I promised<note>Or “spoke”</note> to Moses. <verse-number id="Jos 1:4">4</verse-number>From the wilderness <idiom-start/>and the Lebanon<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “this Lebanon”; “Lebanon” in Hebrew means “white mountain”</note> up to the great river, the river Euphrates, all of the land of the Hittites, and up to <idiom-start/>the great sea in the west<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the great sea of the setting sun”</note> will be your territory. <verse-number id="Jos 1:5">5</verse-number>No one will stand before you<note>Or “in your presence”</note> all the days of your life. <supplied>Just</supplied> as I was with Moses, <supplied>so</supplied> will I be with you; I will not fail you, and I will not forsake you. <verse-number id="Jos 1:6">6</verse-number>Be strong and courageous, for you will give the people this land as an inheritance that I swore to their ancestors<note>Or “fathers”</note> to give them. <verse-number id="Jos 1:7">7</verse-number>Only be strong and very courageous <idiom-start/>to observe diligently the whole law<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to keep <supplied>and</supplied> to act according to the whole law”</note> that Moses my servant commanded you. Do not turn aside from it, <supplied>to</supplied> the right or left, so that you may succeed <idiom-start/>wherever you go<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “in all that you go”</note> <verse-number id="Jos 1:8">8</verse-number>The scroll of this law will not depart from your mouth; you will meditate on it day and night so that <idiom-start/>you may observe diligently all that is written<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to keep <supplied>and</supplied> to act according to all that is written”</note> in it. For then you will succeed <supplied>in</supplied> your ways and prosper. <verse-number id="Jos 1:9">9</verse-number>Did I not command you? Be strong and courageous! Do not fear or be dismayed, for Yahweh your God is with you <idiom-start/>wherever you go<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “in all that you go”</note> <verse-number id="Jos 1:10">10</verse-number>Then Joshua commanded the officers of the people, saying, <verse-number id="Jos 1:11">11</verse-number>“Pass through the midst of the camp and command the people: ‘Prepare your provisions;<note>Hebrew “provision”</note> <idiom-start/>in<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for in still”</note> three days you <supplied>are to</supplied> cross the Jordan to go possess the land that Yahweh your God <supplied>is</supplied> giving you to possess.’ ” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 1:12">12</verse-number>To the Reubenites, the Gadites, and the half-tribe of Manasseh Joshua said, <verse-number id="Jos 1:13">13</verse-number>“Remember the word that Moses Yahweh’s servant commanded you, saying, ‘Yahweh your God <supplied>is</supplied> giving rest to you, and he is giving<note>Hebrew “he gave”</note> you this land.’ <verse-number id="Jos 1:14">14</verse-number>Your wives, your little children, and your livestock, they will remain in the land that Moses gave to you beyond the Jordan. <idiom-start/>All of the best fighting men<idiom-end/><note>Literally “All the mighty warriors of the troop”</note> will cross armed in front of your families; they will help you <verse-number id="Jos 1:15">15</verse-number>until Yahweh gives rest to your families as well as to you. They will take possession of the land that Yahweh your God <supplied>is</supplied> giving to them. Then you will return to your own land and take possession of it, <supplied>the land</supplied> that Moses the servant of Yahweh gave you beyond the Jordan <idiom-start/>to the east<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “to the sunrise”</note> <verse-number id="Jos 1:16">16</verse-number>And they answered Joshua, saying, “All that you have commanded us we will do, and wherever you will send us we will go. <verse-number id="Jos 1:17">17</verse-number>Just as we obeyed Moses, so will we obey you. Only may Yahweh your God be with you, as he was with Moses. <verse-number id="Jos 1:18">18</verse-number>Whoever <idiom-start/>rebels against your orders<idiom-end/><note>Literally “defiles against your mouth”</note> and does not obey your words according to what you commanded us will be put to death. Only be strong and courageous.” </p>
		</chapter>