<chapter id="Jos 8">
			<pericope>Ai Is Destroyed</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 8:1">1</verse-number>Then Yahweh said to Joshua, “Do not fear or be dismayed. Take <idiom-start/>all the fighting men<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all the people of war”</note> with you <idiom-start/>and go up immediately to Ai<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “get up and go up to Ai”</note> Look, I am giving into your hand the king of Ai, his city, and his land. <verse-number id="Jos 8:2">2</verse-number>You will do to Ai and its king that which you did to Jericho and its king; you may take only its spoils<note>Hebrew “spoil”</note> and livestock as booty for yourself. Set for yourself an ambush against the city <supplied>from</supplied> behind <supplied>it</supplied>.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 8:3">3</verse-number>So Joshua and <idiom-start/>all the fighting men<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all the people of war”</note> went up immediately to Ai. Joshua chose thirty thousand of the best fighting men and sent them <supplied>by</supplied> night. <verse-number id="Jos 8:4">4</verse-number>And he commanded them, saying, “Look, you are to lay an ambush against the city from behind. Do not go very far from the city and be ready. <verse-number id="Jos 8:5">5</verse-number>Then I and all of the people who <supplied>are</supplied> with me will approach the city. And when they go out to meet us <idiom-start/>as before<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “as that at the first <supplied>occasion</supplied>”</note> we will flee from them.<note>Or “before their presence”</note> <verse-number id="Jos 8:6">6</verse-number>They will come out after us until we draw them away from the city, because they will think, ‘<supplied>They are</supplied> fleeing from us<note>Or “before our presence”</note> <idiom-start/>as before<idiom-end/>.’<note>Literally “as that at the first <supplied>occasion</supplied>”</note> So we will flee from them.<note>Or “before their presence”</note> <verse-number id="Jos 8:7">7</verse-number>Then you will rise up from the ambush and take possession of the city, for Yahweh your God will give it into your hand. <verse-number id="Jos 8:8">8</verse-number>And when you capture the city you will set it on fire as Yahweh commanded. Look, I have commanded you.” <verse-number id="Jos 8:9">9</verse-number>So Joshua sent them out, and they went to the <supplied>place of the</supplied> ambush, and they sat between Bethel and Ai, to the west of Ai; but Joshua spent the night <idiom-start/>with the people<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “in the middle of the people”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 8:10">10</verse-number>Joshua rose early in the morning and mustered the people, and he went up <supplied>with</supplied> the elders of Israel before the people of Ai.<note>Or “before the presence of the people of Ai”</note> <verse-number id="Jos 8:11">11</verse-number><idiom-start/>All the fighting men<idiom-end/><note>Literally “All the people of war”</note> who <supplied>were</supplied> with him <idiom-start/>went up and drew near before the city<idiom-end/><note>Literally “went up, drew near, and came before the city”</note> and camped north of Ai; <supplied>there was</supplied> a valley between him and Ai. <verse-number id="Jos 8:12">12</verse-number>And he took about five thousand men and set them in ambush between Bethel and Ai, to the west of the city. <verse-number id="Jos 8:13">13</verse-number>So they stationed the forces; all the army <supplied>was</supplied> north of the city while <idiom-start/>the rear guard was west<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “while its rear guard <supplied>was</supplied> west of the city”</note> But Joshua went that night to the middle of the valley. <verse-number id="Jos 8:14">14</verse-number>When the king of Ai saw <supplied>this</supplied>, the men of the city hurried and rose early and went out to meet Israel for battle—he<note>That is, the king</note> and all his army—to the meeting place before the Arabah.<note>A dry region that runs south of the Sea of Galilee along the Jordan Valley</note> He did not know that <supplied>there was</supplied> an ambush for him behind the city. <verse-number id="Jos 8:15">15</verse-number>Then Joshua and all Israel acted like they were beaten before them, and they fled <idiom-start/>in the direction of the wilderness<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the way of the wilderness”</note> <verse-number id="Jos 8:16">16</verse-number>All of the people who <supplied>were</supplied> in the city were called to pursue after them. As they pursued after Joshua, they were drawn away from the city. <verse-number id="Jos 8:17">17</verse-number>Not a man remained in Ai or Bethel who had not gone out after Israel; they left the city open and pursued after Israel. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 8:18">18</verse-number>And Yahweh said to Joshua, “Stretch out the sword<note>Or “spear”</note> that is in your hand to Ai, because I will give it into your hand.” And Joshua stretched out the sword that was in his hand to the city. <verse-number id="Jos 8:19">19</verse-number>The moment he stretched out his hand, those in the ambush stood up quickly from their place and ran. And they went <supplied>into</supplied> the city and captured it, quickly setting the city ablaze with fire. <verse-number id="Jos 8:20">20</verse-number>Then the men of Ai looked behind them, and they saw smoke from the city rising to the sky; <idiom-start/>they had no power to flee this way or that<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “it was not in their hands to flee here and here”</note> and the people fleeing the wilderness turned around to the pursuers.<note>Hebrew “pursuer”</note> <verse-number id="Jos 8:21">21</verse-number>And Joshua and all Israel saw that the ambush had captured the city and that the smoke of the city was rising; they returned and struck down the men of Ai. <verse-number id="Jos 8:22">22</verse-number>Then the others from the city came out to meet them, <idiom-start/>and they found themselves surrounded by Israel<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “they were in the middle of Israel”</note> <idiom-start/>some on one side, and others on the other side<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “these from these, and these from this”</note> And they<note>That is, Israel</note> struck them down until no survivor or fugitive <supplied>was</supplied> left. <verse-number id="Jos 8:23">23</verse-number>But they captured the king of Ai alive, and they brought him to Joshua. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 8:24">24</verse-number>When Israel finished slaughtering all the inhabitants of Ai in the open field, in the wilderness where they pursued them, and when all of them had fallen by <idiom-start/>the edge of the sword<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<supplied>the</supplied> mouth of <supplied>the</supplied> sword”</note> until they all had perished, all Israel returned <supplied>to</supplied> Ai and attacked it with <idiom-start/>the edge of the sword<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “<supplied>the</supplied> mouth of <supplied>the</supplied> sword”</note> <verse-number id="Jos 8:25">25</verse-number>All the people that fell on that day, both men and women, <supplied>were</supplied> twelve thousand—all the inhabitants of Ai. <verse-number id="Jos 8:26">26</verse-number>For Joshua did not draw back his hand that was stretched out with the sword until he had utterly destroyed all the inhabitants of Ai. <verse-number id="Jos 8:27">27</verse-number>Only the livestock and the spoil of that city Israel took as booty for themselves, according to the word of Yahweh that Joshua commanded. <verse-number id="Jos 8:28">28</verse-number>So Joshua burned Ai and made it an everlasting heap of rubbish, a desolate place until this day. <verse-number id="Jos 8:29">29</verse-number>The king of Ai he hanged on a tree until the time of evening, and as the sun went down Joshua commanded <supplied>them</supplied>, and they brought down his dead body from the tree. Then they threw it at the entrance of the gate of the city, and they raised over it a great heap of stones <supplied>that remains</supplied> to this day. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Israel Renews the Covenant</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 8:30">30</verse-number>Then Joshua built an altar on Mount Ebal for Yahweh the God of Israel, <verse-number id="Jos 8:31">31</verse-number>as Moses Yahweh’s servant commanded the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> as <supplied>it is</supplied> written in the scroll of the law of Moses: “an altar of unhewn<note>Or “whole”</note> stones <supplied>on</supplied> which no one has <idiom-start/>wielded<idiom-end/><note>Literally “waved over them”</note> an iron implement.”<note>See <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ex 20:25">Exod 20:25</cite></note> And they offered burnt offerings on it and sacrificed fellowship offerings. <verse-number id="Jos 8:32">32</verse-number>And there Joshua wrote on the stones <supplied>a</supplied> copy of the law of Moses, which he<note>That is, Moses</note> had written, in the presence of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> <verse-number id="Jos 8:33">33</verse-number>Then all Israel, <idiom-start/>foreigner as well as native<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “as the alien as the native”</note> with the elders, officials, and judges stood <idiom-start/>on either side<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from this and from this”</note> of the ark before the priests and the Levites, who carried the ark of the covenant of Yahweh. Half of them <supplied>stood</supplied> in front of Mount Gerizim, and the other half in front of Mount Ebal, as Moses Yahweh’s servant had commanded before to bless the people of Israel. <verse-number id="Jos 8:34">34</verse-number>And afterward he read all the words of the law, the blessings<note>Hebrew “blessing”</note> and the curses,<note>Hebrew “curse”</note> according to all that was written in the scroll of the law. <verse-number id="Jos 8:35">35</verse-number>There was not a word from all that Moses commanded that Joshua did not read before the assembly of all Israel, and the women, the little children, and the traveling foreigners<note>Hebrew “foreigner”</note> among them. </p>
		</chapter>