<chapter id="Jos 9">
			<pericope>The Gibeonites Act with Cunning</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 9:1">1</verse-number>Now<note>Or “And it happened”</note> when all the kings who <supplied>were</supplied> beyond the Jordan in the hill country and in the Shephelah,<note>Or “lowlands”; a geographical region on the western edge of the hills of Judea</note> and on all the coast of the great sea toward Lebanon<note>Literally “white mountain”</note>—the Hittites,<note>Hebrew “Hittite”</note> the Amorites,<note>Hebrew “Amorite”</note> the Canaanites,<note>Hebrew “Canaanite”</note> the Perizzites,<note>Hebrew “Perizzite”</note> the Hivites,<note>Hebrew “Hivite”</note> and the Jebusites<note>Hebrew “Jebusite”</note>—heard of <supplied>this</supplied>, <verse-number id="Jos 9:2">2</verse-number>they gathered themselves together to fight with one accord against<note>Hebrew “with”</note> Joshua and Israel. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 9:3">3</verse-number>But the inhabitants of Gibeon heard what Joshua did to Jericho and Ai, <verse-number id="Jos 9:4">4</verse-number>and they acted on their part with cunning: they went and prepared provisions,<note>The Hebrew is difficult here. Some ancient manuscripts read, “they sent out a delegation/an envoy”</note> and took worn-out sacks<note>Or “sackcloths”</note> for their donkeys and old wineskins <supplied>that were</supplied> torn and mended. <verse-number id="Jos 9:5">5</verse-number>The sandals on their feet <supplied>were</supplied> patched and old, their clothes <supplied>were</supplied> old, and their food was dry and crumbled. <verse-number id="Jos 9:6">6</verse-number>And they went to Joshua at the camp <supplied>at</supplied> Gilgal and said to him and to the men of Israel, “We have come from a far land; so then <idiom-start/>make a covenant with us<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “cut for us a covenant”</note> <verse-number id="Jos 9:7">7</verse-number>And the men of Israel said to the Hivites,<note>Hebrew “Hivite”</note> “Perhaps you <supplied>are</supplied> living among us; how can we <idiom-start/>make a covenant<idiom-end/><note>Literally “cut a covenant”</note> with you?” <verse-number id="Jos 9:8">8</verse-number>They said to Joshua, “We <supplied>are</supplied> your servants.” And Joshua said to them, “Who <supplied>are</supplied> you, and from where do you come?” <verse-number id="Jos 9:9">9</verse-number>And they said to him, “Your servants have come from a very far land because of the name of Yahweh your God; we have heard of his reputation, of all that he did in Egypt, <verse-number id="Jos 9:10">10</verse-number>and of all that he did to the two kings of the Amorites who <supplied>were</supplied> beyond the Jordan—to Sihon king of Heshbon and to Og king of Bashan, who <supplied>was</supplied> in Ashtaroth. <verse-number id="Jos 9:11">11</verse-number>So our elders said to us and all the inhabitants of our land, ‘Take in your hand provisions for the journey, and go to meet them, and say to them, “We <supplied>are</supplied> your servants; so then <idiom-start/>make a covenant with us<idiom-end/>.” ’<note>Literally “cut for us a covenant”</note> <verse-number id="Jos 9:12">12</verse-number>This <supplied>is</supplied> our bread; <supplied>it was</supplied> hot <supplied>when</supplied> we took it from our houses as provisions on the day we set out to come to you. But now, look, it is dry and crumbled. <verse-number id="Jos 9:13">13</verse-number>These <supplied>are</supplied> the wineskins that we filled new, but look, they have burst; and these <supplied>are</supplied> our clothes and sandals that have worn out from the very long journey.” <verse-number id="Jos 9:14">14</verse-number>So the leaders<note>Or “men”</note> took from their provisions, but <idiom-start/>they did not ask direction from Yahweh<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the mouth of Yahweh they did not ask”</note> <verse-number id="Jos 9:15">15</verse-number>And Joshua made peace with them, and <idiom-start/>he made a covenant with them<idiom-end/><note>Literally “he cut a covenant with them”</note> to allow them to live happily, and the leaders of the congregation swore <supplied>an oath</supplied> to them. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 9:16">16</verse-number>And it happened that at the end of three days, after they made a covenant with them, they heard that <idiom-start/>they were their neighbors<idiom-end/><note>Literally “they <supplied>were</supplied> near them”</note> and living among them. <verse-number id="Jos 9:17">17</verse-number>And the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> set out and went to their cities on the third day (their cities <supplied>were</supplied> Gibeon, Kephirah, Beeroth, and Kiriath Jearim). <verse-number id="Jos 9:18">18</verse-number>But the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> did not attack them, because the leaders of the congregation had sworn to them by Yahweh the God of Israel. And all the congregation murmured <idiom-start/>against their leaders<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “against the leaders of the congregation”</note> <verse-number id="Jos 9:19">19</verse-number>But all the leaders of the congregation said, “We have sworn to them by Yahweh the God of Israel, and so we cannot touch them. <verse-number id="Jos 9:20">20</verse-number>This we will do to them: <supplied>we will</supplied> let them live so that wrath will not be on us because of the oath we swore to them.” <verse-number id="Jos 9:21">21</verse-number>And the leaders<note>Or “men”</note> said to them, “Let them live.” So they became woodcutters and water carriers for all the congregation, just as the leaders had said to them. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 9:22">22</verse-number>And Joshua summoned them and said, “Why have you deceived us saying, ‘We <supplied>are</supplied> very far from you’ when you <supplied>are</supplied> living among us? <verse-number id="Jos 9:23">23</verse-number>Therefore you <supplied>are</supplied> cursed; some of you will always be slaves as woodcutters and water carriers for the house of my God.” <verse-number id="Jos 9:24">24</verse-number>And they answered Joshua and said, “Because it was told with certainty to your servants that Yahweh your God commanded Moses his servant to give to you all the land and to destroy all the inhabitants of the land before you, so we were very afraid for our lives because of you, and so we did this thing. <verse-number id="Jos 9:25">25</verse-number>So then, look, we <supplied>are</supplied> in your hand; do with us whatever seems good and right in your eyes.” <verse-number id="Jos 9:26">26</verse-number>So he did this to them: he saved them from the hand of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and they did not kill them. <verse-number id="Jos 9:27">27</verse-number>And that day Joshua made them woodcutters and water carriers for the congregation and for the altar of Yahweh, to this day, in the place that he should choose. </p>
		</chapter>