<chapter id="Jos 13">
			<pericope>Land Still Remains to be Conquered</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 13:1">1</verse-number>Now Joshua was old <supplied>and</supplied> <idiom-start/>advanced in years<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “he went in the days”</note> and Yahweh said to him, “You are old <supplied>and</supplied> <idiom-start/>advanced in years<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “you went in the days”</note> and very much of the land remains to be possessed. <verse-number id="Jos 13:2">2</verse-number>This <supplied>is</supplied> the remaining land: all the regions of the Philistines, and all <supplied>of</supplied> the Geshurites,<note>Hebrew “Geshurite”</note> <verse-number id="Jos 13:3">3</verse-number>from the Shihor, which <supplied>is</supplied> <idiom-start/>east of Egypt<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “on the face of Egypt”</note> up to the border of Ekron to <supplied>the</supplied> north, which is reckoned as Canaanite; <supplied>there are</supplied> five Philistine rulers: the Gazites,<note>Hebrew “Gazite”</note> Ashdodites,<note>Hebrew “Ashdodite”</note> Ashkelonites,<note>Hebrew “Ashkelonite”</note> Gittites,<note>Hebrew “Gittite”</note> Ekronites,<note>Hebrew “Ekronite”</note> and the Avvim. <verse-number id="Jos 13:4">4</verse-number>In <supplied>the</supplied> south; all the land of the Canaanites,<note>Hebrew “Canaanite”</note> and Mearah, which <supplied>belongs</supplied> to the Sidonians up to Aphek, to the border of the Amorites,<note>Hebrew “Amorite”</note> <verse-number id="Jos 13:5">5</verse-number>and the land of the Gebalites, and all the Lebanon,<note>Or “white mountain”</note> <idiom-start/>toward the east<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the rise of the sun”</note> from Baal Gad <idiom-start/>at the foot of<idiom-end/><note>Or “below” or “under”</note> Mount Hermon up to Lebo-Hamath; <verse-number id="Jos 13:6">6</verse-number>all the inhabitants of the hill country, from the Lebanon<note>Or “white mountain”</note> up to Misrephoth Maim, and all <supplied>the</supplied> Sidonians. I will drive them out from before the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> only allocate it to Israel as an inheritance just as I have commanded you. <verse-number id="Jos 13:7">7</verse-number>Therefore, divide this land as an inheritance to the nine tribes and the half-tribe of Manasseh.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 13:8">8</verse-number>With it<note>That is, the other half-tribe of Manasseh</note> the Reubenites,<note>Hebrew “Reubenite”</note> and the Gadites<note>Hebrew “Gadite”</note> received their inheritance, which Moses gave them beyond the Jordan to the east, just as Moses Yahweh’s servant gave to them: <verse-number id="Jos 13:9">9</verse-number>from Aroer, which <supplied>is</supplied> on the edge of the wadi<note>A valley that is dry most of the year, but contains a stream during the rainy season</note> of Arnon, and the city which <supplied>is</supplied> in the middle of the wadi, and all the plateau <supplied>from</supplied> Medeba up to Dibon; <verse-number id="Jos 13:10">10</verse-number>and all the cities of Sihon king of the Amorites,<note>Hebrew “Amorite”</note> who reigned in Heshbon up to the border of the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “sons/children of Ammon”</note> <verse-number id="Jos 13:11">11</verse-number>and Gilead, and the border of the Geshurite<note>Hebrew “Geshurite”</note> and the Maacathites,<note>Hebrew “Maacathite”</note> all of <idiom-start/>Mount Hermon<idiom-end/>,<note>Or “the hill country of Hermon”</note> and Bashan up to Salecah; <verse-number id="Jos 13:12">12</verse-number>all the kingdom of Og in Bashan, who reigned in Ashtaroth and Edrei—he was left over from the survivors<note>Hebrew “survivor”</note> of the Rephaim; these Moses had defeated and driven out. <verse-number id="Jos 13:13">13</verse-number>But the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> did not drive out the Geshurites<note>Hebrew “Geshurite”</note> or the Maacathites;<note>Hebrew “Maacathite”</note> Geshur and Maacah live among Israel to this day. <verse-number id="Jos 13:14">14</verse-number>Only the tribe of Levites<note>Hebrew “Levite”</note> Moses did not give an inheritance; the offerings made by fire to Yahweh the God of Israel <supplied>are</supplied> their<note>Hebrew “his”</note> inheritance, just as he promised to them.<note>Hebrew “he said to him”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Reuben’s Inheritance</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 13:15">15</verse-number>Moses gave <supplied>an inheritance</supplied> to the tribe of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Reuben according to their families. <verse-number id="Jos 13:16">16</verse-number>Their territory was from Aroer, which <supplied>was</supplied> on the edge of the wadi<note>A valley that is dry most of the year, but contains a stream during the rainy season</note> of Arnon, and the city that <supplied>is</supplied> in the middle of the valley, and all the plateau by Medeba; <verse-number id="Jos 13:17">17</verse-number>Heshbon and its cities that <supplied>are</supplied> on the plateau; Dibon, Bamoth Baal, Beth Baal Meon, <verse-number id="Jos 13:18">18</verse-number>Jahaz, Kedemoth, Mephaath, <verse-number id="Jos 13:19">19</verse-number>Kiriathaim, Sibmah, and Zereth Shahar on the hill of the valley; <verse-number id="Jos 13:20">20</verse-number>Beth Peor, the slopes of Pisgah, and Beth Jeshimoth; <verse-number id="Jos 13:21">21</verse-number>all of the cities of the plateau, and all the kingdom of Sihon king of the Amorites,<note>Hebrew “Amorite”</note> who reigned in Heshbon and whom Moses defeated with the leaders of Midian, Evi, Rekem, Zur, Hur, and Reba, the princes of Sihon who dwelled in the land. <verse-number id="Jos 13:22">22</verse-number><supplied>In addition</supplied> to their slain, the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> killed with the sword Balaam son of Beor, who practiced divination. <verse-number id="Jos 13:23">23</verse-number>And the border of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Reuben <supplied>was</supplied> the Jordan and <supplied>its</supplied> banks.<note>Hebrew “bank”</note> This <supplied>was</supplied> the inheritance of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Reuben according to their families, the cities, and their villages. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Gad’s Inheritance</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 13:24">24</verse-number>Moses gave <supplied>an inheritance</supplied> to the tribe of Gad, to the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Gad, according to their families. <verse-number id="Jos 13:25">25</verse-number>Their territory was Jazer and all the cities of Gilead, and half the land of the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Ammon”</note> up to Aroer, <idiom-start/>which is east of Rabbah<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “which <supplied>is</supplied> before Rabbah”</note> <verse-number id="Jos 13:26">26</verse-number>and from Heshbon up to Ramah-Mizpeh and Betonim, and from Mahanaim up to the territory to Debir; <verse-number id="Jos 13:27">27</verse-number>in the valley of Beth Haram, Beth Nimrah, Succoth, Zaphon, and the rest of the kingdom of Sihon king of Heshbon, the Jordan and <supplied>its</supplied> banks,<note>Hebrew “bank”</note> up to the <supplied>lower</supplied> end of the Kinnereth Sea<note>That is, the Sea of Galilee</note> beyond the Jordan to the east. <verse-number id="Jos 13:28">28</verse-number>This <supplied>is</supplied> the inheritance of the <idiom-start/>Gadites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Gad”</note> according to their families, the cities, and their villages. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Half-Tribe of Manasseh’s Inheritance</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 13:29">29</verse-number>Moses gave <supplied>an inheritance</supplied> to the half-tribe of Manasseh; it was for the half-tribe of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Manasseh according to their families. <verse-number id="Jos 13:30">30</verse-number>Their territory was from Mahanaim, all Bashan, all the kingdom of Og king of Bashan, and all the settlements<note>Or “tent villages”</note> of Jair, which <supplied>are</supplied> in Bashan, sixty cities, <verse-number id="Jos 13:31">31</verse-number>and half of Gilead, with Ashtaroth, Edrei, and the cities of the kingdom of Og in Bashan; <supplied>these were allotted</supplied> to the children of Makir son of Manasseh, for half of the children of Makir according to their families. <verse-number id="Jos 13:32">32</verse-number>These <supplied>are the territories</supplied> that Moses gave as an inheritance on the desert-plateau of Moab, beyond the Jordan, east of Jericho. <verse-number id="Jos 13:33">33</verse-number>But to the tribe of Levi Moses did not give an inheritance; Yahweh the God of Israel, he <supplied>is</supplied> their inheritance, just as <idiom-start/>he promised them<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “he said to them”</note> </p>
		</chapter>