<chapter id="Jos 14">
			<pericope>The Land Allotted West of the Jordan</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 14:1">1</verse-number>These <supplied>are the territories</supplied> that the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> inherited in the land of Canaan, which Eleazar the priest, Joshua son of Nun, and the heads of the families of the tribes of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> gave as an inheritance to them. <verse-number id="Jos 14:2">2</verse-number>Their inheritance <supplied>was</supplied> by lot, just as Yahweh commanded through the hand of Moses, for the nine tribes and the half-tribe. <verse-number id="Jos 14:3">3</verse-number>For Moses had given <supplied>an</supplied> inheritance of <supplied>the</supplied> two tribes and the half-tribe beyond the Jordan, but to the Levites he gave no inheritance among them. <verse-number id="Jos 14:4">4</verse-number>For the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Joseph were two tribes, Manasseh and Ephraim, and they did not give a plot of ground to the Levites in the land, only cities to live <supplied>in</supplied>, with their pastureland for their flocks and for their goods. <verse-number id="Jos 14:5">5</verse-number>Just as Yahweh commanded Moses, so the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> did; and they allotted the land. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Caleb Receives Hebron</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 14:6">6</verse-number>Then the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Judah came to Joshua at Gilgal; and Caleb son of Jephunneh the Kenizzite said to him, “You know the word that Yahweh said to Moses the man of God at Kadesh Barnea concerning you and me. <verse-number id="Jos 14:7">7</verse-number><idiom-start/>I was forty years old<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I <supplied>was</supplied> a son of forty year<supplied>s</supplied>”</note> when Moses Yahweh’s servant sent me from Kadesh Barnea to spy out the land, and I returned <idiom-start/>with an honest report<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “with a word just as <supplied>was</supplied> with my heart”</note> <verse-number id="Jos 14:8">8</verse-number>My companions who went up with me made the hearts<note>Hebrew “heart”</note> of the people melt, but I remained true to Yahweh my God. <verse-number id="Jos 14:9">9</verse-number>And Moses swore on that day, saying, ‘Surely the land that your foot has trodden on will be an inheritance to you and your sons forever, because you remained true to Yahweh my God.’ <verse-number id="Jos 14:10">10</verse-number>So then, look, Yahweh has kept me alive just as he promised these forty-five years,<note>Hebrew “year”</note> from the time that Yahweh spoke this word to Moses while Israel <idiom-start/>wandered<idiom-end/><note>Literally “went”</note> in the wilderness. Now look, today <idiom-start/>I am eighty-five years old<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “I <supplied>am</supplied> a son of eighty-five year<supplied>s</supplied>”</note> <verse-number id="Jos 14:11">11</verse-number>Today I am still strong, just as on the day that Moses sent me; as my strength <supplied>was</supplied> then, so now also <supplied>is</supplied> my strength for war <idiom-start/>and for daily activities<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “for going out and for coming <supplied>in</supplied>”</note> <verse-number id="Jos 14:12">12</verse-number>So now give me this hill country that Yahweh spoke <supplied>of</supplied> on that day, for you heard on that day that the Anakites <supplied>were</supplied> there, with great and fortified cities. Perhaps Yahweh <supplied>is</supplied> with me, and I will drive them out just as Yahweh promised.”<note>Or “said”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 14:13">13</verse-number>And Joshua blessed him and gave Hebron to Caleb son of Jephunneh as an inheritance. <verse-number id="Jos 14:14">14</verse-number>Thus Hebron became the inheritance of Caleb son of Jephunneh the Kenizzite to this day, because he remained true to Yahweh the God of Israel. <verse-number id="Jos 14:15">15</verse-number>And the name of Hebron formerly <supplied>was</supplied> Kiriath Arba;<note>Or “the city of Arba”</note> <supplied>Arba was</supplied> the greatest person among the Anakites. And the land rested from war. </p>
		</chapter>