<chapter id="Jos 15">
			<pericope>The Allotment of Judah</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 15:1">1</verse-number>The allotment for the tribe of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Judah according to their families reached to the border of Edom, to the wilderness of Zin, <idiom-start/>to the far south<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to the south at the end of south”</note> <verse-number id="Jos 15:2">2</verse-number>Their southern border was from the end of the Salt Sea,<note>That is, the Dead Sea</note> from the bay facing southward; <verse-number id="Jos 15:3">3</verse-number>it continues<note>Hebrew “goes out”</note> to <supplied>the</supplied> south to the ascent of Akrabbim, passes <supplied>along</supplied> to Zin, it goes up south of Kadesh Barnea, passes <supplied>along</supplied> Hezron, goes up to Addar, and makes a turn to Karka; <verse-number id="Jos 15:4">4</verse-number><idiom-start/>it passes on<idiom-end/><note>Literally “it was to”</note> to Azmon, continues<note>Hebrew “goes out”</note> by the wadi of Egypt, and <idiom-start/>it ends<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the goings out of the border were”</note> at the sea. This will be your southern border. <verse-number id="Jos 15:5">5</verse-number><supplied>The</supplied> eastern border <supplied>is</supplied> the Salt Sea<note>That is, the Dead Sea</note> up to the mouth<note>Or “end”</note> of the Jordan. <supplied>The</supplied> border on <supplied>the</supplied> northern side <supplied>runs</supplied> from the bay of the sea at the mouth<note>Or “end”</note> of the Jordan; <verse-number id="Jos 15:6">6</verse-number>the border goes up to Beth-hoglah and passes <supplied>along</supplied> north of Beth Arabah; and the border goes up the stone of Bohan son of Reuben; <verse-number id="Jos 15:7">7</verse-number>and the border goes up to Debir from the valley of Achor, and to the north, turning to Gilgal, which <supplied>is</supplied> opposite the ascent of Adummim, which <supplied>is</supplied> south of the wadi;<note>A valley that is dry most of the year, but contains a stream during the rainy season</note> and the border passes on to the waters of En Shemesh, and it ends at En Rogel. <verse-number id="Jos 15:8">8</verse-number>Then the border goes up <supplied>by</supplied> the Valley of Ben Hinnom<note>Or “valley of the son of Hinnom”</note> to the slope of the Jebusites<note>Hebrew “Jebusite”</note> from <supplied>the</supplied> south (that <supplied>is</supplied>, Jerusalem); and the border goes up to the top of the mountain that <supplied>lies</supplied> opposite the valley of Hinnom to the west, which is at the end of the valley of Rephaim to the north; <verse-number id="Jos 15:9">9</verse-number>then the border turns from the top of the mountain to the spring of the waters of Nephtoah, and continues<note>Hebrew “goes out”</note> from there to the cities of Mount Ephron; the border <supplied>then</supplied> turns <supplied>to</supplied> Baalah (that <supplied>is</supplied>, Kiriath Jearim); <verse-number id="Jos 15:10">10</verse-number>and the border goes around from Baalah to the west, to Mount Seir, and passes on to the slope of Mount Jearim from the north (that <supplied>is</supplied>, Kesalon), and goes down <supplied>to</supplied> Beth Shemesh, and passes <supplied>along by</supplied> Timnah. <verse-number id="Jos 15:11">11</verse-number>The border continues<note>“Hebrew “goes out”</note> to the slope of Ekron to the north, <supplied>then</supplied> bends around to Shikkeron, it passes <supplied>on</supplied> to Mount Baalah and continues <supplied>to</supplied> Jabneel; and <idiom-start/>the border ends<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the goings out of the border were”</note> at the sea. <verse-number id="Jos 15:12">12</verse-number>And <supplied>the</supplied> western border <supplied>is</supplied> to the Great Sea<note>That is, the Mediterranean</note> and its coast. This <supplied>is</supplied> the border surrounding the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Judah according to their families. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 15:13">13</verse-number><idiom-start/>According to the commandment of Yahweh to Joshua<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “according to the mouth of Yahweh to Joshua”</note> he gave to Caleb son of Jephunneh a plot of ground among the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Judah, Kiriath Arba,<note>Or “the city of Arba”</note> which <supplied>is</supplied> Hebron (<supplied>Arba</supplied> was Anak’s father). <verse-number id="Jos 15:14">14</verse-number>Caleb drove out from there three of Anak’s sons, Sheshai, Ahiman, and Talmai, the descendants<note>Or “children”</note> of Anak. <verse-number id="Jos 15:15">15</verse-number>And from there he went up against the inhabitants of Debir (the former name of Debir <supplied>was</supplied> Kiriath Sepher). <verse-number id="Jos 15:16">16</verse-number>And Caleb said, “Whoever attacks Kiriath Sepher and captures it, I will give to him my daughter Acsah as a wife.” <verse-number id="Jos 15:17">17</verse-number>Othniel son of Kenaz, the brother of Caleb, captured it, and he gave to him Acsah his daughter as a wife. <verse-number id="Jos 15:18">18</verse-number>When she came <supplied>to him</supplied> she urged him to ask her father for a field. So she dismounted from the donkey, and Caleb said to her, “<idiom-start/>What do you want<idiom-end/>?”<note>Literally “What <supplied>is</supplied> for you?”</note> <verse-number id="Jos 15:19">19</verse-number>And she said to him, “Give to me a gift;<note>Or “blessing”</note> you have given me the land of the Negev,<note>An arid region south of the Judaean hills</note> and you must give to me a spring of water.” And he gave to her the upper and lower spring.<note><cite title="BibleLEB2: Jos 15:13–19">Joshua 15:13–19 </cite>is almost identical to <cite title="BibleLEB2: Jdg 1:11–15">Judges 1:11–15</cite></note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Cities of Judah</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 15:20">20</verse-number>This <supplied>is</supplied> the inheritance of the tribe of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Judah according to their families: <verse-number id="Jos 15:21">21</verse-number>the cities belonging to the tribe of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Judah to the far south, to <supplied>the</supplied> border of Edom to the south, were Kabzeel, Eder, Jagur, <verse-number id="Jos 15:22">22</verse-number>Kinah, Dimonah, Adadah, <verse-number id="Jos 15:23">23</verse-number>Kedesh, Hazor, Ithnan, <verse-number id="Jos 15:24">24</verse-number>Ziph, Telem, Bealoth, <verse-number id="Jos 15:25">25</verse-number>Hazor Hadattah, Kerioth Hezron (that <supplied>is</supplied>, Hazor), <verse-number id="Jos 15:26">26</verse-number>Amam, Shema, Moladah, <verse-number id="Jos 15:27">27</verse-number>Hazar Gaddah, Heshmon, Beth Pelet, <verse-number id="Jos 15:28">28</verse-number>Hazar Shual, Beersheba, Biziothiah, <verse-number id="Jos 15:29">29</verse-number>Baalah, Iim, Ezem, <verse-number id="Jos 15:30">30</verse-number>Eltolad, Kesil, Hormah, <verse-number id="Jos 15:31">31</verse-number>Ziklag, Madmannah, Sansannah, <verse-number id="Jos 15:32">32</verse-number>Lebaoth, Shilhim, Ain, and Rimmon; <supplied>in</supplied> all, twenty-nine cities and their villages. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 15:33">33</verse-number>In the Shephelah:<note>Or “lowlands”; a geographical region on the western edge of the hills of Judea</note> Eshtaol, Zorah, Ashnah, <verse-number id="Jos 15:34">34</verse-number>Zanoah, En Gannim, Tappuah, Enam, <verse-number id="Jos 15:35">35</verse-number>Jarmuth, Adullam, Socoh, Azekah, <verse-number id="Jos 15:36">36</verse-number>Shaaraim, Adithaim, Gederah, and Gederothaim; fourteen cities and their villages. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 15:37">37</verse-number>Zenan, Hadashah, Migdal Gad, <verse-number id="Jos 15:38">38</verse-number>Dilean, Mizpah, Joktheel, <verse-number id="Jos 15:39">39</verse-number>Lachish, Bozkath, Eglon, <verse-number id="Jos 15:40">40</verse-number>Cabbon, Lahma, Kitlish, <verse-number id="Jos 15:41">41</verse-number>Gederoth, Beth Dagon, Naamah, and Makkedah; sixteen cities and their villages. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 15:42">42</verse-number>Libnah, Ether, Ashan, <verse-number id="Jos 15:43">43</verse-number>Jephthah, Ashnah, Nezib, <verse-number id="Jos 15:44">44</verse-number>Keilah, Aczib, and Mareshah; nine cities and their villages. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 15:45">45</verse-number>Ekron, its towns and villages; <verse-number id="Jos 15:46">46</verse-number>from Ekron to the sea, and all that <idiom-start/>were near<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<supplied>were</supplied> on the hand of”</note> Ashdod and their villages. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 15:47">47</verse-number>Ashdod, its towns and villages; Gaza, its towns and villages, up to the wadi<note>A valley that is dry most of the year, but contains a stream during the rainy season</note> of Egypt and the Great Sea<note>That is, the Mediterranean</note> and its coast.<note>Literally “border”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 15:48">48</verse-number>And in the hill country: Shamir, Jattir, Socoh, <verse-number id="Jos 15:49">49</verse-number>Dannah, Kiriath Sanna (that <supplied>is</supplied>, Debir), <verse-number id="Jos 15:50">50</verse-number>Anab, Eshtemoh, Anim, <verse-number id="Jos 15:51">51</verse-number>Goshen, Holon, and Giloh; eleven cities and their villages. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 15:52">52</verse-number>Arab, Dumah, Eshan, <verse-number id="Jos 15:53">53</verse-number>Janim, Beth-tappuah, Aphekah, <verse-number id="Jos 15:54">54</verse-number>Humtah, Kiriath Arba<note>Or “the city of Arba”</note> (that <supplied>is</supplied>, Hebron), and Zior; nine cities and their villages. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 15:55">55</verse-number>Moan, Carmel, Ziph, Juttah, <verse-number id="Jos 15:56">56</verse-number>Jezreel, Jokdeam, Zanoah, <verse-number id="Jos 15:57">57</verse-number>Kain, Gibeah, and Timnah; ten cities and their villages. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 15:58">58</verse-number>Halhul, Beth Zur, Gedor, <verse-number id="Jos 15:59">59</verse-number>Maarath, Beth Anoth, and Eltekon; six cities and their villages. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 15:60">60</verse-number>Kiriath Baal (that <supplied>is</supplied>, Kiriath Jearim) and Rabbah; two cities and their villages. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 15:61">61</verse-number>In the wilderness: Beth Arabah, Middin, Secacah, <verse-number id="Jos 15:62">62</verse-number>Nibshan, the city of Salt, and En Gedi; six cities and their villages. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 15:63">63</verse-number>But the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Judah were unable to drive out the Jebusites, the inhabitants of Jerusalem, so the Jebusites live with the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Judah in Jerusalem to this day. </p>
		</chapter>