<chapter id="Jos 16">
			<pericope>The Allotment of Ephraim and Manasseh</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 16:1">1</verse-number>The allotment of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Joseph went from <supplied>the</supplied> Jordan by Jericho, at the waters of Jericho to the east, <supplied>into</supplied> the wilderness, going up from Jericho into the hill country <supplied>to</supplied> Bethel; <verse-number id="Jos 16:2">2</verse-number>it continues from Bethel to Luz, and it passes <supplied>along</supplied> to the territory of the Arkites<note>Hebrew “Arkite”</note> at Ataroth. <verse-number id="Jos 16:3">3</verse-number>Then it goes down, to the west, to the territory of the Japhletites,<note>Hebrew “Japhletite”</note> up to the territory of Lower Beth-horon, then to Gezer, and <idiom-start/>it ends<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the goings out of it were”</note> at the sea. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 16:4">4</verse-number>And the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Joseph, Manasseh and Ephraim, received their inheritance. <verse-number id="Jos 16:5">5</verse-number><supplied>This</supplied> was the border of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Ephraim according to their families: the border of their inheritance to the east <supplied>was</supplied> Ataroth Addar, up to Upper Beth-horon. <verse-number id="Jos 16:6">6</verse-number>The border continues to the sea; from Micmethath to <supplied>the</supplied> north, the border turns to the east to Taanath Shiloh, and it passes <supplied>along</supplied> it from the east to Janoah. <verse-number id="Jos 16:7">7</verse-number>Then it goes down from Janoah to Ataroth and to Naarah; it touches Jericho and ends <supplied>at</supplied> the Jordan; <verse-number id="Jos 16:8">8</verse-number>from Tappuah the border goes to the west, <supplied>to</supplied> the wadi<note>A valley that is dry most of the year, but contains a stream during the rainy season</note> of Kanah, and <idiom-start/>it ends<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the goings out of it were”</note> at the sea. This <supplied>is</supplied> the inheritance of the tribe of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Ephraim according to their families, <verse-number id="Jos 16:9">9</verse-number>with the cities that were set apart for the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Ephraim in the midst of the inheritance of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Manasseh, all the cities and their villages. <verse-number id="Jos 16:10">10</verse-number>But they did not drive out the Canananites<note>Hebrew “Canaanite”</note> who were dwelling in Gezer, and so the Canaanites<note>Hebrew “Canaanite”</note> live in the midst of Ephraim to this day, but they became forced laborers. </p>
		</chapter>