<chapter id="Jos 17">
			<pericope>The Allotment of the Other Half-Tribe of Manasseh</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 17:1">1</verse-number>Then the allotment was made for the tribe of Manasseh, because he <supplied>was</supplied> the firstborn of Joseph. To Makir, the firstborn of Manasseh, the father of Gilead, <idiom-start/>were allotted<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and there was to him”</note> Gilead and Bashan, because he was a warrior.<note>Literally “a man of war”</note> <verse-number id="Jos 17:2">2</verse-number><supplied>An allotment</supplied> was <supplied>made</supplied> for the remaining descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Manasseh, according to their families: For the children of Abiezer, Helek, Asriel, Shechem, Hepher, and Shemida—these <supplied>were</supplied> the male descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Manasseh son of Joseph according to their families. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 17:3">3</verse-number>But Zelophehad son of Hepher, son of Gilead, son of Makir, son of Manasseh, had no sons, only daughters. These <supplied>are</supplied> the names of his daughters: Mahlah, Noah, Hoglah, Milcah, and Tirzah. <verse-number id="Jos 17:4">4</verse-number>They came before Eleazar the priest, Joshua son of Nun, and the leaders, saying, “Yahweh commanded Moses to give an inheritance to us among our kinsmen.”<note>Or “among our brothers”</note> Therefore, according to the <idiom-start/>command of Yahweh<idiom-end/><note>Literally “mouth of Yahweh”</note> he gave them an inheritance among the kinsmen<note>Or “brothers”</note> of their father. <verse-number id="Jos 17:5">5</verse-number>Thus ten shares fell to Manasseh, besides the land of Gilead and Bashan, which <supplied>is</supplied> beyond the Jordan, <verse-number id="Jos 17:6">6</verse-number>because the daughters of Manasseh received an inheritance among his sons. And the land of Gilead was <supplied>allotted</supplied> to the remaining descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Manasseh. <verse-number id="Jos 17:7">7</verse-number>The border of Manasseh was from Asher <supplied>to</supplied> Micmethath, which <supplied>is</supplied> opposite Shechem;<note>Or “which faces Shechem”</note> then the border goes to the south, to the inhabitants of En Tappuah. <verse-number id="Jos 17:8">8</verse-number>The land of Tappuah <idiom-start/>belonged to Manasseh<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “was to Manasseh”</note> but Tuppuah on the border of Manasseh <idiom-start/>belonged to the descendants of Ephraim<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “was to the children of Ephraim”</note> <verse-number id="Jos 17:9">9</verse-number>Then the border goes down <supplied>to</supplied> the wadi<note>A valley that is dry most of the year, but contains a stream during the rainy season</note> of Kanah to the south of the wadi. These cities <supplied>belong</supplied> to Ephraim among the cities of Manasseh. The border of Manasseh <supplied>is</supplied> north of the wadi, and <idiom-start/>it ends<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the goings out of it were”</note> at the sea. <verse-number id="Jos 17:10">10</verse-number>The south <supplied>is</supplied> Ephraim’s, and the north <supplied>is</supplied> Manasseh’s; the sea is their<note>Hebrew “its”</note> border; Asher touches <supplied>the</supplied> north and on <supplied>the</supplied> east Issachar. <verse-number id="Jos 17:11">11</verse-number>In Issachar and Asher, Manasseh had Beth-shean and its villages, Ibleam and its villages, the inhabitants of Dor and its villages, the inhabitants of En-dor and its villages, the inhabitants of Taanach and its villages, the inhabitants of Megiddo and its villages; the third is Napheth. <verse-number id="Jos 17:12">12</verse-number>But the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Manasseh were not able to take possession of these towns; the Canaanites<note>Hebrew “Canaanite”</note> were determined to live in this land. <verse-number id="Jos 17:13">13</verse-number>And it happened, when the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> grew strong, they put the Canaanites<note>Hebrew “Canaanite”</note> to forced labor but never drove them out completely. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Tribes of Joseph Object</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 17:14">14</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Joseph spoke with Joshua, saying, “Why have you given us<note>Hebrew “to me”</note> one allotment and one share <supplied>as</supplied> an inheritance? We are many people, which Yahweh has blessed.” <verse-number id="Jos 17:15">15</verse-number>And Joshua said to them, “If you <supplied>are</supplied> many people, go up to the forest and clear <supplied>a place</supplied> there for yourselves in the land of the Perizzites<note>Hebrew “Perizzite”</note> and Rephaim, since the hill country of Ephraim is <supplied>too</supplied> narrow for you.” <verse-number id="Jos 17:16">16</verse-number>And the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Joseph said, “The hill country is not enough for us, and all of the Canaanites<note>Hebrew “Canaanite”</note> living in the land of the valley <supplied>have</supplied> chariots<note>Hebrew “chariot”</note> of iron, those in Beth-shean and its villages, and those in the Jezreel Valley.” <verse-number id="Jos 17:17">17</verse-number>And Joshua said to the house of Joseph, to Ephraim and Manasseh, “You are many people and have great power; you will not have one allotment <supplied>only</supplied>; <verse-number id="Jos 17:18">18</verse-number><supplied>the</supplied> hill country will be yours. Even though it <supplied>is</supplied> a forest, you will clear it, and it will be yours <supplied>to</supplied> its farthest borders. You will drive out the Canaanites,<note>Hebrew “Canaanite”</note> even though they have iron chariots and <supplied>are</supplied> strong.” </p>
		</chapter>