<chapter id="Jos 18">
			<pericope>The Last of the Land Is Divided</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 18:1">1</verse-number>The entire congregation of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> assembled <supplied>at</supplied> Shiloh, and they set up there the tent of meeting, and the land was subdued before them.<note>Or “in their presence”</note> <verse-number id="Jos 18:2">2</verse-number>And seven tribes remained among the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> who had not been apportioned their inheritance. <verse-number id="Jos 18:3">3</verse-number>And Joshua said to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> “<idiom-start/>How long<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Until when”</note> <supplied>will</supplied> you be slack about going to take possession of the land that Yahweh, the God of your ancestors,<note>Or “fathers”</note> has given you? <verse-number id="Jos 18:4">4</verse-number>Provide three men <idiom-start/>from each tribe<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “according to each tribe”</note> and I will send them so that they may begin to go through the land and write <supplied>a description of</supplied> it <idiom-start/>according to their inheritance<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “according to the mouth of their inheritance”</note> and let them come to me. <verse-number id="Jos 18:5">5</verse-number>They will divide it among themselves into seven portions; <idiom-start/>Judah will maintain its border<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Judah will stand on its border”</note> from <supplied>the</supplied> south, and <idiom-start/>the house of Joseph will maintain its border<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the house of Joseph will stand on its border”</note> from <supplied>the</supplied> north. <verse-number id="Jos 18:6">6</verse-number>Describe the land <supplied>in</supplied> seven divisions, and bring <supplied>it</supplied> to me here; I will cast lots for you here before Yahweh our God. <verse-number id="Jos 18:7">7</verse-number>The Levites among you have no portion, for their inheritance <supplied>is</supplied> the priesthood of Yahweh; Gad, Reuben, and the half-tribe of Manasseh received their inheritance beyond the Jordan to the east, which Moses Yahweh’s servant gave to them.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 18:8">8</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>the men went immediately<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the men got up and went”</note> and Joshua commanded the ones going to describe the land, saying, “Go and walk about through the land, write <supplied>a description</supplied>, and return to me, and here I will cast a lot for you before<note>Or “in the presence of”</note> Yahweh at Shiloh.” <verse-number id="Jos 18:9">9</verse-number>And the men went and passed through the land, and they <idiom-start/>described<idiom-end/><note>Literally “wrote it”</note> the cities in seven divisions in a book; and they came to Joshua to the camp <supplied>at</supplied> Shiloh, <verse-number id="Jos 18:10">10</verse-number>and Joshua cast a lot for them at Shiloh before<note>Or “in the presence of”</note> Yahweh, and there he divided the land for the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> <idiom-start/>to each a portion<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “according to their allotment”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Allotment of Benjamin</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 18:11">11</verse-number>And the allotment of the tribe of Benjamin came up according to their families, and the border of their allotment fell<note>Literally “went out”</note> between the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Judah and the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Joseph. <verse-number id="Jos 18:12">12</verse-number>Their northern border began at the Jordan and went up to the slope of Jericho on <supplied>the</supplied> north and continued into the hill country to the west; <idiom-start/>it ends<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the goings out of it were”</note> at the wilderness of Beth Aven. <verse-number id="Jos 18:13">13</verse-number>The border passes <supplied>on</supplied> from there to Luz, to the slope of Luz to the south (that <supplied>is</supplied>, Bethel); then the border goes down to Ataroth Addar to the mountain that is south of Lower Beth-Horon. <verse-number id="Jos 18:14">14</verse-number>Then the border changes direction and turns to the western side southward, from the mountain that <idiom-start/>is opposite<idiom-end/><note>Literally “against the face of”</note> Beth-Horon to the south. <idiom-start/>It ends<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the goings out of it were”</note> at Kiriath Baal (that <supplied>is</supplied>, Kiriath Jearim), a town belonging to the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Judah. This <supplied>is the</supplied> western side. <verse-number id="Jos 18:15">15</verse-number><supplied>The</supplied> southern side <supplied>begins</supplied> on the outskirts of Kiriath Jearim, and the border continues to the west to the spring of the waters of Nephtoah; <verse-number id="Jos 18:16">16</verse-number>the border goes down to the foot<note>Or “to the edge”</note> of the mountain, which <supplied>is</supplied> opposite the Valley of Ben Hinnom,<note>Or “valley of the son of-Hinnom”</note> which <supplied>is</supplied> in the valley of Rephaim to the north; then it does down the valley of Hinnom to the slope of the Jebusites<note>Hebrew “Jebusite”</note> to the south, and then it goes down <supplied>to</supplied> En Rogel. <verse-number id="Jos 18:17">17</verse-number>It changes direction from <supplied>the</supplied> north, and it continues <supplied>to</supplied> En Shemesh; it goes out to Geliloth, which <supplied>is</supplied> opposite the ascent of Adummim, and it goes down <supplied>to</supplied> the stone of Bohan, son of Reuben. <verse-number id="Jos 18:18">18</verse-number>It passes <supplied>on</supplied> to the slope opposite the Arabah<note>A dry region that runs south of the Sea of Galilee along the Jordan Valley</note> to the north, and it goes down to the Arabah.<note>A dry region that runs south of the Sea of Galilee along the Jordan Valley</note> <verse-number id="Jos 18:19">19</verse-number>The border passes <supplied>on</supplied> to the slope of Beth-hoglah to the north and <idiom-start/>ends<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the goings out of it were”</note> at the north bay of the Salt Sea<note>That is, the Dead Sea</note> at the south end of the Jordan. This is the southern border. <verse-number id="Jos 18:20">20</verse-number>The Jordan forms its border on the eastern side. This <supplied>is</supplied> the inheritance of the tribe of Benjamin, its borders that surrounds <supplied>them</supplied>, according to their families. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 18:21">21</verse-number>Now the towns of the tribes of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Benjamin, according to their families, were Jericho, Beth-hoglah, Emek Keziz, <verse-number id="Jos 18:22">22</verse-number>Beth Arabah, Zemaraim, Bethel, <verse-number id="Jos 18:23">23</verse-number>Avvim, Parah, Ophrah, <verse-number id="Jos 18:24">24</verse-number>Kephar Ammoni, Ophni, and Geba; twelve cities and their villages. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 18:25">25</verse-number>Gibeon, Ramah, Beeroth, <verse-number id="Jos 18:26">26</verse-number>Mizpeh, Kephirah, Mozah, <verse-number id="Jos 18:27">27</verse-number>Rekem, Irpeel, Taralah, <verse-number id="Jos 18:28">28</verse-number>Zela, Haeleph, Jebus (that <supplied>is</supplied>, Jerusalem), Gibeah, and Kiriath; fourteen cities and their villages. This <supplied>is</supplied> the inheritance of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Benjamin according to their families. </p>
		</chapter>