<chapter id="Jos 19">
			<pericope>The Allotment of Simeon</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 19:1">1</verse-number>The second allotment <idiom-start/>fell<idiom-end/><note>Literally “went out”</note> for Simeon, for the tribe of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Simeon, according to their families. And their inheritance was in the midst of the inheritance of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Judah. <verse-number id="Jos 19:2">2</verse-number>And they had as their inheritance Beersheba, Sheba, Moladah, <verse-number id="Jos 19:3">3</verse-number>Hazar Shual, Balah, Ezem, <verse-number id="Jos 19:4">4</verse-number>Eltolad, Bethul, Hormah, <verse-number id="Jos 19:5">5</verse-number>Ziklag, Beth Marcaboth, Hazar Susah, <verse-number id="Jos 19:6">6</verse-number>Beth Lebaoth, and Sharuhen; thirteen cities and their villages. <verse-number id="Jos 19:7">7</verse-number>Ain, Rimmon, Ether, and Ashan; four cities and their villages, <verse-number id="Jos 19:8">8</verse-number>and all the villages that <supplied>were</supplied> around these towns up to Baalat-Beor, Ramath of the Negev.<note>An arid region south of the Judaean hills</note> This <supplied>was</supplied> the inheritance of the tribe of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Simeon according to their families. <verse-number id="Jos 19:9">9</verse-number>Part of the portion <supplied>allotted to</supplied> the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Judah <supplied>became</supplied> the inheritance of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Simeon because the portion for the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Judah was <idiom-start/>too large for them<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “large from them”</note> so the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Simeon inherited <supplied>from</supplied> their inheritance. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Allotment of Zebulun</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 19:10">10</verse-number>The third allotment came up for the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Zebulun according to their families. The border of their inheritance went up to Sarid. <verse-number id="Jos 19:11">11</verse-number>Their border goes up to the west, to Maralah; it touches<note>Or “reaches to”</note> Dabbesheth, then the wadi<note>A valley that is dry most of the year, but contains a stream during the rainy season</note> that <supplied>is</supplied> opposite Jokneam. <verse-number id="Jos 19:12">12</verse-number>It turns from Sarid to the east to the sunrise, to the border of Kislot-Tabor; it continues to Daberath and goes up <supplied>to</supplied> Japhia. <verse-number id="Jos 19:13">13</verse-number>From there it passes <supplied>along</supplied> to the east toward the sunrise, to Gath Hepher and to Eth Kazin, and continuing <supplied>to</supplied> Rimmon, it turns <supplied>to</supplied> Neah; <verse-number id="Jos 19:14">14</verse-number>it changes direction from the north of Hannathon, and <idiom-start/>it ends<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the goings out of it were” </note> at the valley of Yiptah-El; <verse-number id="Jos 19:15">15</verse-number>Kattath, Nahalal, Shimron, Idalah, and Bethlehem; twelve cities and their villages. <verse-number id="Jos 19:16">16</verse-number>This <supplied>is</supplied> the inheritance of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Zebulun according to their families, these cities and their villages. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Allotment of Issachar</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 19:17">17</verse-number>The fourth allotment <idiom-start/>fell<idiom-end/><note>Literally “came out”</note> for Issachar, for the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Issachar, according to their families. <verse-number id="Jos 19:18">18</verse-number>Their border went to Jezreel, Chesulloth, Shunem, <verse-number id="Jos 19:19">19</verse-number>Hapharaim, Shion, Anaharath, <verse-number id="Jos 19:20">20</verse-number>Rabbith, Kishion, Ebez, <verse-number id="Jos 19:21">21</verse-number>Remeth, En Gannim, En Haddah, and Beth Pazzez; <verse-number id="Jos 19:22">22</verse-number>and the border touches Tabor, Shahazumah, and Beth Shemesh. <idiom-start/>Its border ends<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the goings out of their border were”</note> at the Jordan; sixteen cities and their villages. <verse-number id="Jos 19:23">23</verse-number>This <supplied>is</supplied> the inheritance of the tribe of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Issachar according to their families, the cities and their villages. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Allotment of Asher</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 19:24">24</verse-number>The fifth allotment <idiom-start/>fell<idiom-end/><note>Literally “came out” </note> for the tribe of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Asher according to their families. <verse-number id="Jos 19:25">25</verse-number>Their border was Helkath, Hali, Beten, Acshaph, <verse-number id="Jos 19:26">26</verse-number>Allamelech, Amad, and Mishal; it touches Carmel to the west, and Shihor-Libnat. <verse-number id="Jos 19:27">27</verse-number>Then it turns <idiom-start/>eastward<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the rising of the sun”</note> to Beth-dagon and touches Zebulun and the valley of Yiptah-El to the north<note>Literally “left hand/side” </note> to Beth Emeck and Neiel; it continues to Cabul from <supplied>the</supplied> north, <verse-number id="Jos 19:28">28</verse-number>and Ebron, Rehob, Hammon, and Kanah up to Great Sidon; <verse-number id="Jos 19:29">29</verse-number>then the border turns <supplied>to</supplied> Ramah, and up to the fortified city of Tyre, <supplied>where</supplied> the border turns <supplied>to</supplied> Hosah; <idiom-start/>it ends<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the goings out of it were”</note> at the sea, from Hebel to Aczib. <verse-number id="Jos 19:30">30</verse-number><supplied>Included were</supplied> Ummah, Aphek, and Rehob; twenty-two cities and their villages. <verse-number id="Jos 19:31">31</verse-number>This <supplied>is</supplied> the inheritance of the tribe of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Asher according to their families, these cities and their villages. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Allotment of Naphtali</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 19:32">32</verse-number>The sixth allotment <idiom-start/>fell<idiom-end/><note>Literally “came out”</note> for the children of Naphtali, for the children of Naphtali according to their families. <verse-number id="Jos 19:33">33</verse-number>Their border was from Heleph, from <supplied>the</supplied> oak in Zaanannim, Adami Nekeb, Jabneel, up to Lakkum; <idiom-start/>it ends<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the goings out of it were”</note> at the Jordan; <verse-number id="Jos 19:34">34</verse-number>then the border turns to the west, to Aznoth Tabor, and continues from there to Hukok, and it touches<note>Or “reaches to”</note> Zebulun on <supplied>the</supplied> south, Asher on <supplied>the</supplied> west, and Judah on <idiom-start/>the east<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the rising of the sun”</note> <supplied>at</supplied> the Jordan. <verse-number id="Jos 19:35">35</verse-number><idiom-start/>The fortified cities<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the cities of fortification”</note> <supplied>are</supplied> Ziddim, Zer, Hammath, Rakkath, Kinnereth, <verse-number id="Jos 19:36">36</verse-number>Adamah, Ramah, Hazor, <verse-number id="Jos 19:37">37</verse-number>Kedesh, Edrei, En Hazor, <verse-number id="Jos 19:38">38</verse-number>Yiron, Migdal El, Horem, Beth-anath, Beth Shemesh; nineteen cities and their villages. <verse-number id="Jos 19:39">39</verse-number>This <supplied>is</supplied> the inheritance of the tribe of the children of Naphtali according to their families, the cities and their villages. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Allotment of Dan</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 19:40">40</verse-number>The seventh lot <idiom-start/>fell<idiom-end/><note>Literally “came out”</note> for the tribe of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Dan according to their families. <verse-number id="Jos 19:41">41</verse-number><supplied>The</supplied> border of their inheritance was Zorah, Eshtaol, Ir Shemesh, <verse-number id="Jos 19:42">42</verse-number>Shaalabbin, Aijalon, Ithlah, <verse-number id="Jos 19:43">43</verse-number>Elon, Timnah, Ekron, <verse-number id="Jos 19:44">44</verse-number>Eltekeh, Gibbethon, Baalath, <verse-number id="Jos 19:45">45</verse-number>Jehud, Bene Berak, Gath Rimmon, <verse-number id="Jos 19:46">46</verse-number>Me Jarkon, Rakkon, with the border opposite Joppa. <verse-number id="Jos 19:47">47</verse-number>The border of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Dan continued <idiom-start/>beyond them<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from them”</note> because the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Dan went up and fought with Lesham, and they captured and struck it with <idiom-start/>the edge of the sword<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “<supplied>the</supplied> mouth of <supplied>the</supplied> sword”</note> and they took possession of it and settled in it; and they called Leshem Dan, after the name of Dan their ancestor.<note>Or “father”</note> <verse-number id="Jos 19:48">48</verse-number>This <supplied>is</supplied> the inheritance of the tribe of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Dan according to their families, these cities and their villages. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Allotment Is Completed</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 19:49">49</verse-number>They finished assigning the land according to its borders, and the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> gave an inheritance <supplied>from</supplied> among them to Joshua son of Nun. <verse-number id="Jos 19:50">50</verse-number><idiom-start/>According to the commandment of Yahweh<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “On the mouth of Yahweh”</note> they gave him the city that he requested, Timnath Serah, in the hill country of Ephraim, and he rebuilt the city and settled<note>Or “dwelt”</note> in it. <verse-number id="Jos 19:51">51</verse-number>These <supplied>are</supplied> the inheritances that Eleazar the priest, Joshua son of Nun, and the heads of the families of the tribes, distributed by allotment <supplied>to</supplied> the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> at Shiloh <idiom-start/>before Yahweh<idiom-end/><note>Or “in the presence of Yahweh”</note> <supplied>at</supplied> the entrance of the tent of meeting. And they finished dividing the land. </p>
		</chapter>