<chapter id="Jos 21">
			<pericope>The Allotment of the Levites</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 21:1">1</verse-number>Then the heads of the families of the Levites came to Eleazar the priest, to Joshua son of Nun, and to the heads of the families of the tribes of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> <verse-number id="Jos 21:2">2</verse-number>And they spoke to them at Shiloh in the land of Canaan, saying, “Yahweh commanded through the hand of Moses to give us cities to live <supplied>in</supplied>, with their pasturelands for our livestock.” <verse-number id="Jos 21:3">3</verse-number>So, <idiom-start/>by command of Yahweh<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “by the mouth of Yahweh”</note> the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> gave the Levites these cities and their pasturelands from their inheritance. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 21:4">4</verse-number>The allotment <idiom-start/>fell<idiom-end/><note>Literally “came out”</note> for the families of the Kohathites.<note>Hebrew “Kohathite”</note> The descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Aaron the priest, who were of the Levites, <idiom-start/>received<idiom-end/><note>Literally “they had”</note> by lot thirteen towns from the tribes of Judah, Simeon, and Benjamin. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 21:5">5</verse-number>The remaining descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Kohath <supplied>received</supplied> by lot ten cities from the families of the tribes of Ephraim, Dan, and the half-tribe of Manasseh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 21:6">6</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Gershon <supplied>received</supplied> by lot thirteen cities from the families of the tribes of Issachar, Asher, and Naphtali and from the half-tribe of Manasseh in Bashan. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 21:7">7</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of the Merarites<note>Hebrew “Merarite”</note> according to their families <supplied>received</supplied> twelve cities from the tribes of Reuben, Gad, and Zebulun. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 21:8">8</verse-number>The <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> gave to the Levites these cities and their pastureland by lot, just as Yahweh commanded through the hand of Moses. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 21:9">9</verse-number>They gave these cities, which are <supplied>here</supplied> mentioned by name, from the tribe of the families of Judah and from the tribe of the families of Simeon; <verse-number id="Jos 21:10">10</verse-number>and they were for the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Aaron, from the families of the Kohathites,<note>Hebrew “Kohathite”</note> from the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Levi, because the first lot was theirs. <verse-number id="Jos 21:11">11</verse-number>And they gave to them Kiriath Arba,<note>Or “the city of Arba”</note> <supplied>Arba being</supplied> the father of Anak (that <supplied>is</supplied>, Hebron), in the hill country of Judah and the pasturelands surrounding it. <verse-number id="Jos 21:12">12</verse-number>But the field of the city and its villages they gave to Caleb son of Jephunneh as his property. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 21:13">13</verse-number>To the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Aaron the priest they gave Hebron, the city of refuge <supplied>for</supplied> the killer, and its pasturelands, Libnah and its pasturelands, <verse-number id="Jos 21:14">14</verse-number>Jattir and its pasturelands, Eshtemoa and its pasturelands, <verse-number id="Jos 21:15">15</verse-number>Holon and its pasturelands, Debir and its pasturelands, <verse-number id="Jos 21:16">16</verse-number>Ain and its pasturelands, Juttah and its pasturelands, and Beth Shemesh and its pasturelands; nine cities from these two tribes. <verse-number id="Jos 21:17">17</verse-number>From the tribe of Benjamin, Gibeon and its pasturelands, Geba and its pasturelands, <verse-number id="Jos 21:18">18</verse-number>Anathoth and its pasturelands, Almon and its pasturelands; four cities. <verse-number id="Jos 21:19">19</verse-number>All the cities of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Aaron the priests, thirteen cities and their pasturelands. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 21:20">20</verse-number>For the families of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Kohath, the remaining Levites of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Kohath, they <supplied>received</supplied> the cities of their lot from the tribe of Ephraim. <verse-number id="Jos 21:21">21</verse-number>They gave them Shechem, the city of refuge <supplied>for</supplied> the killer, and its pasturelands in the hill country of Ephraim, Gezer and its pasturelands, <verse-number id="Jos 21:22">22</verse-number>Kibzaim and its pasturelands, and Beth-horon and its pasturelands; four cities. <verse-number id="Jos 21:23">23</verse-number>From the tribe of Dan, Eltekeh and its pasturelands, Gibbethon and its pasturelands, <verse-number id="Jos 21:24">24</verse-number>Aijalon and its pasturelands, and Gath Rimmon and its pasturelands; four cities. <verse-number id="Jos 21:25">25</verse-number>From the half-tribe of Manasseh, Taanach and its pasturelands and Gath Rimmon with its pasturelands; two cities. <verse-number id="Jos 21:26">26</verse-number>All the cities and their pasturelands for the remaining families of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Kohath <supplied>were</supplied> ten. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 21:27">27</verse-number>To the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Gershon, one of the families of the Levites, from the half-tribe of Manasseh, Golan in Bashan, a city of refuge for the killer, and its pasturelands, and Eshtarah and its pasturelands; two cities. <verse-number id="Jos 21:28">28</verse-number>From the tribe of Issachar, Kishion and its pasturelands, Daberath and its pasturelands, <verse-number id="Jos 21:29">29</verse-number>Jarmuth and its pasturelands, En Gannim and its pasturelands; four cities. <verse-number id="Jos 21:30">30</verse-number>From the tribe of Asher, Mishal and its pasturelands, Abdon and its pasturelands, <verse-number id="Jos 21:31">31</verse-number>Helkath and its pasturelands, Rehob and its pasturelands; four cities. <verse-number id="Jos 21:32">32</verse-number>From the tribe of Naphtali, Kedesh in Galilee, the city of refuge for the killer, and its pasturelands, Hammoth Dor and its pasturelands, and Kartan and its pasturelands; three cities. <verse-number id="Jos 21:33">33</verse-number>All the cities of the Gershonites<note>Hebrew “Gershonite”</note> according to their families <supplied>were</supplied> thirteen cities and their pasturelands. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 21:34">34</verse-number>To the families of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Merarite, the remaining Levites, from the tribe of Zebulun, Jokneam and its pasturelands, Kartah and its pasturelands, <verse-number id="Jos 21:35">35</verse-number>Dimnah and its pasturelands, and Nahalal and its pasturelands; four cities. <verse-number id="Jos 21:36">36</verse-number>From the tribe of Reuben, Bezer and its pasturelands, Jahaz and its pasturelands, <verse-number id="Jos 21:37">37</verse-number>Kedemoth and its pasturelands, and Mephaath and its pasturelands; four cities. <verse-number id="Jos 21:38">38</verse-number>From the tribe of Gad, Ramoth in Gilead, the city of refuge for the killer, and its pasturelands, Mahanaim and its pasturelands, <verse-number id="Jos 21:39">39</verse-number>Heshbon and its pasturelands, and Jazer and its pasturelands; four cities <supplied>in</supplied> all. <verse-number id="Jos 21:40">40</verse-number>All <supplied>these were</supplied> the cities of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Merarite according to their families, the remaining families of the Levites; their allotment was twelve cities. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 21:41">41</verse-number>All the cities of the Levites among the property of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> <supplied>were</supplied> forty-eight cities and their pasturelands. <verse-number id="Jos 21:42">42</verse-number>Each of these cities had pasturelands surrounding them; so <supplied>it was</supplied> for all of these cities. <verse-number id="Jos 21:43">43</verse-number>And Yahweh gave to Israel all the land that he swore to give to their ancestors,<note>Or “fathers”</note> and they took possession of it and <idiom-start/>settled in it<idiom-end/>.<note>Or “dwelled in it”</note> <verse-number id="Jos 21:44">44</verse-number>Yahweh gave them rest on every side, according to all that he had sworn to their ancestors,<note>Or “fathers”</note> and nobody from all their enemies withstood them, for Yahweh had given all their enemies into their hand. <verse-number id="Jos 21:45">45</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>nothing failed from<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Not a thing fell”</note> all the good things<note>Hebrew “thing”</note> that Yahweh promised to the house of Israel; <idiom-start/>everything came to pass<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “everything it came”</note> </p>
		</chapter>