<chapter id="Jos 22">
			<pericope>The Eastern Tribes Return</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 22:1">1</verse-number>Then Joshua summoned the Reubenites, the Gadites, and the half-tribe of Manasseh, <verse-number id="Jos 22:2">2</verse-number>and he said to them, “You have observed all that Moses Yahweh’s servant commanded you, and you have listened<note>Or “you have obeyed”</note> to my voice in all that I have commanded you; <verse-number id="Jos 22:3">3</verse-number>you have not forsaken your kinsmen<note>Or “brothers”</note> these many days, up to this day, and you have observed the obligation of the command of Yahweh your God. <verse-number id="Jos 22:4">4</verse-number>So then, Yahweh your God has given rest to your kinsmen,<note>Or “brothers”</note> just as he promised them; so then, turn and go to your tents to the land of your possession, which Moses Yahweh’s servant gave to you beyond the Jordan. <verse-number id="Jos 22:5">5</verse-number>Only be very careful to observe the commandment and law that Moses Yahweh’s servant commanded you, to love Yahweh your God, to walk in all his ways, to keep his commandments, to hold fast to him, and to serve him with all your heart and with all your soul.”<note>Or “inner self”</note> <verse-number id="Jos 22:6">6</verse-number>And Joshua blessed them and sent them away, and they went to their tents. <verse-number id="Jos 22:7">7</verse-number>And to the half-tribe of Manasseh Moses had given <supplied>a possession</supplied> in Bashan, but to the other half Joshua had given <supplied>a possession</supplied> with their kinsmen<note>Or “brothers”</note> beyond the Jordan to the west; and when Joshua sent them to their tents and blessed them, <verse-number id="Jos 22:8">8</verse-number>he said to them, “Return to your tents with much wealth, and with very much livestock, with silver, gold, copper, iron, and with very much clothing; divide the war-booty of your enemies with your kinsmen.”<note>Or “brothers”</note> <verse-number id="Jos 22:9">9</verse-number>So the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Reuben, Gad, and the half-tribe of Manasseh returned <supplied>home</supplied> and departed with the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> at Shiloh, which <supplied>is</supplied> in the land of Canaan, to go to the land of Gilead to the land of their possession, which they had acquired <idiom-start/>according to the command of Yahweh<idiom-end/><note>Literally “on the mouth of Yahweh”</note> through the hand of Moses. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 22:10">10</verse-number>And they came to the region of the Jordan that <supplied>is</supplied> in the land of Canaan, and the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Reuben, Gad, and the half-tribe of Manasseh built there an altar on the Jordan, <idiom-start/>a large and imposing altar<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “a large altar to appearance”</note> <verse-number id="Jos 22:11">11</verse-number>And the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> heard <supplied>it</supplied> said that the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Reuben, Gad, and the half-tribe of Manasseh had built an altar next to the land of Canaan, in the region of the Jordan, on the side <supplied>belonging to</supplied> the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> <verse-number id="Jos 22:12">12</verse-number>When the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> heard <supplied>of it</supplied>, the whole congregation of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> gathered <supplied>at</supplied> Shiloh to go up against them for battle. <verse-number id="Jos 22:13">13</verse-number>And the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> sent to the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Reuben, Gad, and the half-tribe of Manasseh, to the land of Gilead, Phinehas the priest son of Eleazar, <verse-number id="Jos 22:14">14</verse-number>and ten leaders with him, <idiom-start/>one leader for each<idiom-end/><note>Literally “one leader, one leader”</note> <idiom-start/>family<idiom-end/><note>Literally “of the house of father”</note> from each of the tribes of Israel; and each one <supplied>was</supplied> the head of <idiom-start/>his family<idiom-end/><note>Literally “house of their fathers”</note> among the clans of Israel.<note>Or “thousands of Israel”</note> <verse-number id="Jos 22:15">15</verse-number>They came to the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Reuben, Gad, and the half-tribe of Manasseh, to the land of Gilead, and they spoke with them, saying, <verse-number id="Jos 22:16">16</verse-number>“Thus says all the congregation of Yahweh: ‘What <supplied>is</supplied> this treachery that you have committed against the God of Israel by turning away today from following Yahweh, by building for yourselves an altar to rebel today against Yahweh? <verse-number id="Jos 22:17">17</verse-number><supplied>Is</supplied> not the sin of Peor <idiom-start/>enough for us<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “too little for us”</note> from which we have not cleansed ourselves today, and for which a plague came to the congregation of Yahweh, <verse-number id="Jos 22:18">18</verse-number>that you must turn today from following Yahweh? <supplied>If</supplied> you rebel today against Yahweh, tomorrow he will be angry with all of the congregation of Israel; <verse-number id="Jos 22:19">19</verse-number>if, however, the land of your property <supplied>is</supplied> unclean, cross <supplied>over</supplied> to the land of Yahweh’s property, where Yahweh’s tabernacle resides,<note>Or “stands”</note> and take possession among us. But you must not rebel against Yahweh or against us by building for yourselves an altar other than the altar of Yahweh our God. <verse-number id="Jos 22:20">20</verse-number>Did not Achan son of Zerah commit treachery with devoted things,<note>Or “consecrated possession”</note> and wrath fell on all the congregation of Israel? <idiom-start/>And he alone<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And he <supplied>is</supplied> one man that”</note> did not perish because of his iniquity.’ ” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 22:21">21</verse-number>And the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Reuben, Gad, and the half-tribe of Manasseh spoke with the heads of the clans<note>Or “thousands”</note> of Israel, <verse-number id="Jos 22:22">22</verse-number>“Yahweh, God of gods! Yahweh, God of gods knows. And let Israel itself know, if <supplied>it was</supplied> in rebellion or treachery against Yahweh, do not spare us this day <verse-number id="Jos 22:23">23</verse-number>for building for ourselves an altar to turn away from Yahweh, or if <supplied>it was</supplied> to offer burnt offerings,<note>Hebrew “offering”</note> grain offerings,<note>Hebrew “offering”</note> or fellowship offerings on it, may Yahweh himself take vengeance. <verse-number id="Jos 22:24">24</verse-number>But in fact, we have done this because of anxiety, because of a reason, saying, ‘In the future your children may say to our children, ‘<idiom-start/>What is the relationship between you and Yahweh the God of Israel<idiom-end/>?<note>Literally “What is to you and to Yahweh the God of Israel”</note> <verse-number id="Jos 22:25">25</verse-number>Yahweh has made the Jordan a border between us and you, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Reuben and Gad; you have no portion in Yahweh.’ So your children may put an end to our children worshiping<note>Or “seeing”</note> Yahweh. <verse-number id="Jos 22:26">26</verse-number>So we said, ‘Let us build immediately for ourselves an altar, not for burnt offerings<note>Hebrew “offering”</note> or for sacrifices;<note>Hebrew “sacrifice”</note> <verse-number id="Jos 22:27">27</verse-number>instead, it <supplied>is</supplied> a witness between us and you, and between our generations after us for performing the serving of Yahweh in his presence with our burnt offerings, sacrifices, and fellowship offerings; so that your children may not say in the future to our children, “You have no portion in Yahweh.” ’ <verse-number id="Jos 22:28">28</verse-number>And we thought, if they say to us and to our children in the future, we can say, ‘Look at this replica of the altar of Yahweh, which our ancestors<note>Or “fathers”</note> made, not for burnt offerings<note>Hebrew “offering”</note> or sacrifices;<note>Hebrew “sacrifice”</note> rather, it <supplied>is</supplied> a witness between us and you.’ <verse-number id="Jos 22:29">29</verse-number>Far be it from us to rebel against Yahweh, to turn today from following Yahweh, to build an altar for burnt offerings,<note>Hebrew “offering”</note> grain offerings,<note>Hebrew “offering”</note> or sacrifices,<note>Hebrew “sacrifice”</note> instead of the altar of Yahweh our God that <supplied>is</supplied> before his tabernacle.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 22:30">30</verse-number>Phinehas the priest, the leaders of the congregation, and the heads of the clans<note>Or “thousands”</note> of Israel who <supplied>were</supplied> with him heard the words that the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Reuben, Gad, and Manasseh spoke, and <idiom-start/>they were satisfied<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “it was good in their eyes”</note> <verse-number id="Jos 22:31">31</verse-number>Phinehas the priest, son of Eleazar, said to the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Reuben, Gad, and Manasseh, “Today we know that Yahweh <supplied>is</supplied> among us, because you have not committed this treachery against Yahweh. Therefore you have rescued the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> from the hand of Yahweh.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 22:32">32</verse-number>And Phinehas the priest, son of Eleazar, and the leaders returned from the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Reuben and Gad, from the land of Gilead, to the land of Canaan to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and <idiom-start/>they gave them their report<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “they brought back a word to them”</note> <verse-number id="Jos 22:33">33</verse-number><idiom-start/>The report satisfied the Israelites<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “The report was good in the eyes of the children of Israel”</note> they blessed God, and they did not speak of going up for battle against them to destroy the land in which the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Reuben and Gad were living.<note>Or “dwelling”</note> <verse-number id="Jos 22:34">34</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Reuben and Gad called the altar Witness, “Because,” <supplied>they said</supplied>, “it <supplied>is</supplied> a witness between us that Yahweh <supplied>is</supplied> God.” </p>
		</chapter>