<chapter id="Jos 23">
			<pericope>Joshua’s Farewell Address</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 23:1">1</verse-number>And it happened, after <idiom-start/>a long time<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “many days”</note> after Yahweh had given rest to Israel from all their surrounding enemies, and <supplied>after</supplied> Joshua was old and <idiom-start/>well-advanced in years<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “he went into the days”</note> <verse-number id="Jos 23:2">2</verse-number>Joshua summoned all Israel, their elders, heads, judges, and officials, and he said to them, “I am old and <idiom-start/>well-advanced in years<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “I went into the days”</note> <verse-number id="Jos 23:3">3</verse-number>and you have seen all that Yahweh your God has done to all these nations <idiom-start/>for your sake<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “because of your presence”</note> for Yahweh your God <supplied>is</supplied> fighting for you. <verse-number id="Jos 23:4">4</verse-number>Look! I have allotted to you these remaining nations as an inheritance for your tribes, from the Jordan, <supplied>with</supplied> all the nations that I have cut off, to the Great Sea<note>That is, the Mediterranean</note> <idiom-start/>in the west<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to the setting of the sun”</note> <verse-number id="Jos 23:5">5</verse-number>And Yahweh your God will push them <idiom-start/>back before you<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from your presence”</note> and drive them <idiom-start/>out of your sight<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from your face”</note> and you will possess their land, just as Yahweh your God promised to you. <verse-number id="Jos 23:6">6</verse-number>Be very strong to observe carefully all that is written in the scroll of the law of Moses so as not to turn aside from it, <supplied>to</supplied> the right or left, <verse-number id="Jos 23:7">7</verse-number>so as not to go among these remaining nations with you; <idiom-start/>do not profess<idiom-end/><note>Literally “do not mention”</note> the name of their gods, and do not swear by them, serve them, or <idiom-start/>bow down to them<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “bow yourselves down to them”</note> <verse-number id="Jos 23:8">8</verse-number>But hold fast to Yahweh your God, just as you have done up to this day. <verse-number id="Jos 23:9">9</verse-number>Yahweh has driven out before you great and strong nations; and as for you, <idiom-start/>nobody has withstood<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a man has not stood in your presence”</note> you to this day. <verse-number id="Jos 23:10">10</verse-number>One of your men put to flight a thousand, for Yahweh your God <supplied>is</supplied> fighting for you, just as he promised you. <verse-number id="Jos 23:11">11</verse-number>Take utmost care for <supplied>the sake of</supplied> your life to love Yahweh your God, <verse-number id="Jos 23:12">12</verse-number>for if indeed you turn back and join these remaining nations <idiom-start/>among you<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “with you”</note> and you intermarry with them, <idiom-start/>marrying their women and they yours<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “you go into them and they into you”</note> <verse-number id="Jos 23:13">13</verse-number>know for certain that Yahweh your God <idiom-start/>will not continue to drive out<idiom-end/><note>Literally “will not drive out again”</note> these nations from before you; they will be for you a snare and a trap, a whip on your sides and thorns in your eyes, until you perish from this good land that Yahweh your God has given to you. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jos 23:14">14</verse-number>Look! <idiom-start/>I am about to die<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “I am going today on the way of all the earth”</note> and you know in all your hearts<note>Hebrew “heart”</note> and souls<note>Hebrew “soul”; or “inner self”</note> that not one thing <idiom-start/>failed<idiom-end/><note>Literally “fell”</note> from all the good things that Yahweh your God promised concerning you; everything <idiom-start/>has been fulfilled<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “has come <supplied>out</supplied>”</note> <idiom-start/>not one thing failed<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “not one thing fell from it”</note> <verse-number id="Jos 23:15">15</verse-number>But just as all the good things<note>Hebrew “thing”</note> came to you that Yahweh your God promised, so will Yahweh bring to you all the bad things<note>Hebrew “things”</note> until he has destroyed you from this good land that Yahweh your God has given to you. <verse-number id="Jos 23:16">16</verse-number>If you transgress the covenant of Yahweh your God, which he commanded <supplied>to</supplied> you, and you go and serve other gods and bow down to them, <idiom-start/>Yahweh’s anger will be kindled<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Yahweh’s nose will become hot”</note> against you, and you will perish quickly from the good land that he has given to you.” </p>
		</chapter>