<chapter id="Ro 1">
			<pericope>Greeting</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 1:1">1</verse-number> Paul, a slave of Christ Jesus, called <supplied>to be</supplied> an apostle, set apart for the gospel of God, <verse-number id="Ro 1:2">2</verse-number>which he promised previously through his prophets in the holy scriptures, <verse-number id="Ro 1:3">3</verse-number>concerning his Son, who was born <idiom-start/>a descendant<idiom-end/><note>Literally “of the seed”</note> of David according to the flesh, <verse-number id="Ro 1:4">4</verse-number>who was declared Son of God in power according to <idiom-start/>the Holy Spirit<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the Spirit of holiness”</note> by the resurrection from the dead of Jesus Christ our Lord, <verse-number id="Ro 1:5">5</verse-number>through whom we have received grace and apostleship for the obedience of faith among all the Gentiles<note>Or “nations”; the same Greek word can be translated “nations” or “Gentiles” depending on the context</note> on behalf of his name, <verse-number id="Ro 1:6">6</verse-number>among whom you also are <supplied>the</supplied> called of Jesus Christ. <verse-number id="Ro 1:7">7</verse-number>To all those in Rome who are loved by God, called <supplied>to be</supplied> saints. Grace to you and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Paul Wants to Visit Rome</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 1:8">8</verse-number>First, I give thanks to my God through Jesus Christ for all of you, because your faith is being proclaimed in the whole world. <verse-number id="Ro 1:9">9</verse-number>For God, whom I serve with my spirit in the gospel of his Son, is my witness, how constantly I make mention of you, <verse-number id="Ro 1:10">10</verse-number>always asking in my prayers if somehow now at last I may succeed to come to you in the will of God. <verse-number id="Ro 1:11">11</verse-number>For I desire to see you, in order that I may impart some spiritual gift to you, in order to strengthen you, <verse-number id="Ro 1:12">12</verse-number>that is, to be encouraged together with you through <idiom-start/>our mutual faith<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the in one another faith”</note>, both yours and mine. <verse-number id="Ro 1:13">13</verse-number>Now I do not want you to be ignorant, brothers, that often I intended to come to you, and was prevented until now, in order that I might have some fruit among you also, just as also among the rest of the Gentiles.<note>Or “nations”; the same Greek word can be translated “nations” or “Gentiles” depending on the context</note> <verse-number id="Ro 1:14">14</verse-number>I am under obligation both to Greeks and to barbarians, both to the wise and to the foolish. <verse-number id="Ro 1:15">15</verse-number>Thus <idiom-start/>I am eager<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the according to me eagerness”</note> to proclaim the gospel also to you who <supplied>are</supplied> in Rome. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Gospel’s Power for Salvation</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 1:16">16</verse-number>For I am not ashamed of the gospel, for it is the power of God for salvation to everyone who believes, to the Jew first and also to the Greek. <verse-number id="Ro 1:17">17</verse-number>For the righteousness of God is revealed in it from faith to faith, just as it is written, “But the one who is righteous by faith will live.”<note>Or “But the one who is righteous will live by faith” (differing only in word order)</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>God’s Wrath Revealed Against Sinful Humanity</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 1:18">18</verse-number>For the wrath of God is revealed from heaven against all impiety and unrighteousness of people, who suppress the truth in unrighteousness, <verse-number id="Ro 1:19">19</verse-number>because what can be known about God is evident among<note>Or “in”; or “within”</note> them, for God made <supplied>it</supplied> clear to them. <verse-number id="Ro 1:20">20</verse-number>For from the creation of the world, his invisible <supplied>attributes</supplied>, both his eternal power and deity, are discerned clearly, being understood in the things created, so that they are without excuse. <verse-number id="Ro 1:21">21</verse-number>For <supplied>although they</supplied> knew God, they did not honor <supplied>him</supplied> as God or give thanks, but they became futile in their reasoning, and their senseless hearts were darkened. <verse-number id="Ro 1:22">22</verse-number>Claiming to be wise, they became fools, <verse-number id="Ro 1:23">23</verse-number>and exchanged the glory of the immortal God with the likeness of an image of mortal human beings and birds and quadrupeds and reptiles. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 1:24">24</verse-number>Therefore God gave them over in the desires of their hearts to immorality, <supplied>that</supplied> their bodies would be dishonored among themselves, <verse-number id="Ro 1:25">25</verse-number>who exchanged the truth of God with a lie, and worshiped and served the creation rather than the Creator, who is blessed for eternity. Amen. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>God Hands Sinful Humanity over to Depravity</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 1:26">26</verse-number>Because of this, God gave them over to degrading passions, for their females exchanged the natural relations for those contrary to nature, <verse-number id="Ro 1:27">27</verse-number>and likewise also the males, abandoning the natural relations with the female, were inflamed in their desire toward one another, males with males committing the shameless deed, and receiving in themselves the penalty that was necessary for their error. <verse-number id="Ro 1:28">28</verse-number>And just as they did not see fit <idiom-start/>to recognize God<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to have God in recognition”</note>, God gave them over to a debased mind, to do the things <supplied>that are</supplied> not proper, <verse-number id="Ro 1:29">29</verse-number>being filled with all unrighteousness, wickedness, greediness, malice, full of envy, murder, strife, deceit, malevolence. <supplied>They are</supplied> gossipers, <verse-number id="Ro 1:30">30</verse-number>slanderers, haters of God, insolent, arrogant, boasters, contrivers of evil, disobedient to parents, <verse-number id="Ro 1:31">31</verse-number>senseless, faithless, unfeeling, unmerciful, <verse-number id="Ro 1:32">32</verse-number>who, <supplied>although they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>although</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“know”) which is understood as concessive</note> know the requirements of God, that those who do such things are worthy of death, not only do they do the same <supplied>things</supplied>, but also they approve of those who do <supplied>them</supplied>. </p>
		</chapter>