<chapter id="Ro 2">
			<pericope>The Righteous and Impartial Judgment of God</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 2:1">1</verse-number> Therefore you are without excuse, O man, every one <supplied>of you</supplied> who passes judgment. For in that which you pass judgment on someone else, you condemn yourself, for you who are passing judgment are doing the same <supplied>things</supplied>. <verse-number id="Ro 2:2">2</verse-number>Now we know that the judgment of God is according to truth against those who do such things. <verse-number id="Ro 2:3">3</verse-number>But do you think this, O man who passes judgment on those who do such things, and who does the same <supplied>things</supplied>, that you will escape the judgment of God? <verse-number id="Ro 2:4">4</verse-number>Or do you despise the wealth of his kindness and forbearance and patience, not knowing that the kindness of God leads you to repentance? <verse-number id="Ro 2:5">5</verse-number>But because of your stubbornness and unrepentant heart, you are storing up for yourself wrath in the day of wrath and of the revelation of the righteous judgment of God, <verse-number id="Ro 2:6">6</verse-number>who will reward each one according to his works: <verse-number id="Ro 2:7">7</verse-number>to those who, by perseverance in good work, seek glory and honor and immortality, eternal life, <verse-number id="Ro 2:8">8</verse-number>but to those <supplied>who act</supplied> from selfish ambition and who disobey the truth, but who obey unrighteousness, wrath and anger. <verse-number id="Ro 2:9">9</verse-number><supplied>There will be</supplied> affliction and distress for every <idiom-start/>human being<idiom-end/><note>Literally “soul of man”</note> who does evil, of the Jew first and of the Greek, <verse-number id="Ro 2:10">10</verse-number>but glory and honor and peace to everyone who does good, to the Jew first and to the Greek. <verse-number id="Ro 2:11">11</verse-number>For <supplied>there</supplied> is no partiality with God. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 2:12">12</verse-number>For as many as have sinned without law will also perish without law, and as many as have sinned under the law will be judged by the law. <verse-number id="Ro 2:13">13</verse-number>For it is not the hearers of the law <supplied>who are</supplied> righteous in the sight of God, but the doers of the law will be declared righteous.<note>Or “will be justified”</note> <verse-number id="Ro 2:14">14</verse-number>For whenever the Gentiles, who do not have the law, do by nature the things of the law, these, <supplied>although they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>although</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“have”) which is understood as concessive</note> do not have the law, are a law to themselves, <verse-number id="Ro 2:15">15</verse-number>who show the work of the law written on their hearts, their conscience bearing witness and their thoughts <supplied>one</supplied> after another accusing or even defending them <verse-number id="Ro 2:16">16</verse-number>on the day when God judges the secret things of people, according to my gospel, through<note>Or “by”</note> Christ Jesus. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jews also Condemned by the Law</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 2:17">17</verse-number>But if you call yourself a Jew and rely on the law and boast in God <verse-number id="Ro 2:18">18</verse-number>and know his will and approve the things that are superior, <supplied>because you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“are instructed”) which is understood as causal</note> are instructed by the law, <verse-number id="Ro 2:19">19</verse-number>and are confident <supplied>that</supplied> you yourself are a guide of the blind, a light of those in darkness, <verse-number id="Ro 2:20">20</verse-number>an instructor of the foolish, a teacher of the immature, having the embodiment of knowledge and of the truth in the law. <verse-number id="Ro 2:21">21</verse-number>Therefore, the one who teaches someone else, do you not teach yourself? The one who preaches not to steal, do you steal? <verse-number id="Ro 2:22">22</verse-number>The one who says not to commit adultery, do you commit adultery? The one who abhors idols, do you rob temples? <verse-number id="Ro 2:23">23</verse-number>Who boast in the law, by the transgression of the law you dishonor God!<note>Or “do you dishonor God?” (a number of translators and interpreters take this phrase as a final rhetorical question; the present translation regards it as a final summary statement to be taken ironically)</note> <verse-number id="Ro 2:24">24</verse-number>For just as it is written, “The name of God is blasphemed among the Gentiles because of you.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 52:5">Isa 52:5</cite></note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 2:25">25</verse-number>For circumcision is of value if you do the law, but if you should be a transgressor of the law, your circumcision has become uncircumcision. <verse-number id="Ro 2:26">26</verse-number>Therefore, if the uncircumcised person follows the requirements of the law, will not his uncircumcision be credited for circumcision? <verse-number id="Ro 2:27">27</verse-number>And the uncircumcised person by nature who carries out the law will judge you who, <supplied>though provided</supplied> with <idiom-start/>the precise written code<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the letter”</note> and circumcision <supplied>are</supplied> a transgressor of the law. <verse-number id="Ro 2:28">28</verse-number>For the Jew is not <idiom-start/>one outwardly<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the open”</note>, nor <supplied>is</supplied> circumcision <idiom-start/>outwardly<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the open”</note>, in the flesh. <verse-number id="Ro 2:29">29</verse-number>But the Jew <idiom-start/>is one inwardly<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in secret”</note>, and circumcision <supplied>is</supplied> of the heart, by the Spirit, not by the letter, whose praise <supplied>is</supplied> not from people but from God. </p>
		</chapter>