<chapter id="Ro 3">
			<pericope>Jews Still Have an Advantage</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 3:1">1</verse-number> Therefore, what <supplied>is</supplied> the advantage of the Jew, or what <supplied>is</supplied> the use of circumcision? <verse-number id="Ro 3:2">2</verse-number>Much in every way. For first, that they were entrusted with the oracles of God. <verse-number id="Ro 3:3">3</verse-number><idiom-start/>What is the result<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for what”</note> if some refused to believe? Their unbelief will not nullify the faithfulness of God, <supplied>will it</supplied>? <verse-number id="Ro 3:4">4</verse-number>May it never be! But let God be true but every human being a liar, just as it is written, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“In order that you may be justified in your words, </li1>
				<li2>and may prevail when you are<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Or, if the form is understood as middle voice, “when you yourself judge”</note> judged.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 51:4">Ps 51:4</cite></note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 3:5">5</verse-number>But if our unrighteousness demonstrates the righteousness of God, what shall we say? God, who inflicts wrath, <supplied>is</supplied> not unjust, <supplied>is he</supplied>? (I am speaking according to a human perspective.) <verse-number id="Ro 3:6">6</verse-number>May it never be! For otherwise, how will God judge the world? <verse-number id="Ro 3:7">7</verse-number>But if by my lying, the truth of God abounded to his glory, why am I also still condemned as a sinner? <verse-number id="Ro 3:8">8</verse-number>And <supplied>why</supplied> not (as we are slandered, and as some affirm that we say), “Let us do evil, in order that good may come <supplied>of it</supplied>? Their<note>Literally “whose”</note> condemnation is just! </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Entire World Guilty of Sin</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 3:9">9</verse-number>What then? Do we have an advantage? Not at all. For we have already charged both Jews and Greeks are all under sin, <verse-number id="Ro 3:10">10</verse-number>just as it is written, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“<supplied>There</supplied> is no one righteous, not even one; </li1>
				<li2><verse-number id="Ro 3:11">11</verse-number><supplied>there</supplied> is no one who understands; </li2>
				<li2><supplied>there</supplied> is no one who seeks God. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ro 3:12">12</verse-number>All have turned aside together; they have become worthless; </li1>
				<li2><supplied>There</supplied> is no one who practices kindness; </li2>
				<li2><supplied>there</supplied> is not even one.<note>Verses <cite title="BibleLEB2:Ro 3:10–12">10–12</cite> are a quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 14:1–3">Ps 14:1–3</cite></note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ro 3:13">13</verse-number>Their throat <supplied>is</supplied> an opened grave; </li1>
				<li2>they deceive with their tongues; </li2>
				<li1>the venom of asps <supplied>is</supplied> under their lips,<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 5:9">Ps 5:9 </cite>and <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 140:3">Ps 140:3</cite></note> </li1>
				<li2><verse-number id="Ro 3:14">14</verse-number>whose mouth is full of cursing and bitterness.<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 10:7">Ps 10:7</cite></note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ro 3:15">15</verse-number>Their feet <supplied>are</supplied> swift to shed blood; </li1>
				<li2><verse-number id="Ro 3:16">16</verse-number>destruction and distress <supplied>are</supplied> in their paths, </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ro 3:17">17</verse-number>and they have not known the way of peace.<note>Verses <cite title="BibleLEB2:Ro 3:15–17">15–17</cite> are a quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 59:7–8">Isa 59:7–8</cite></note> </li1>
				<li2><verse-number id="Ro 3:18">18</verse-number>The fear of God is not before their eyes.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 36:1">Ps 36:1</cite></note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 3:19">19</verse-number>Now we know that whatever the law says, it speaks to those under the law, in order that every mouth may be closed and the whole world may become accountable to God. <verse-number id="Ro 3:20">20</verse-number>For by the works of the law <idiom-start/>no person will be declared righteous<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all flesh will not be declared righteous”</note> before him, for through the law <supplied>comes</supplied> knowledge of sin. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Righteousness through Faith Revealed</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 3:21">21</verse-number>But now, apart from the law, the righteousness of God has been revealed, being testified about by the law and the prophets—<verse-number id="Ro 3:22">22</verse-number>that is, the righteousness of God through faith in Jesus Christ<note>Or “through the faithfulness of Jesus Christ”</note> to all who believe. For <supplied>there</supplied> is no distinction, <verse-number id="Ro 3:23">23</verse-number>for all have sinned and fall short of the glory of God, <verse-number id="Ro 3:24">24</verse-number>being justified as a gift by his grace, through the redemption which is in Christ Jesus, <verse-number id="Ro 3:25">25</verse-number>whom God made publicly available as the mercy seat<note>Or “as the place of propitiation”</note> through faith in his blood, for a demonstration of his righteousness, because of the passing over of previously committed sins, <verse-number id="Ro 3:26">26</verse-number>in the forbearance of God, for the demonstration of his righteousness in the present time, so that he should be just and the one who justifies the <supplied>person</supplied> by faith<note>Or “by Jesus’ faithfulness”</note> in Jesus. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 3:27">27</verse-number>Therefore, where <supplied>is</supplied> boasting? It has been excluded. By what kind of law? Of works? No, but by a law<note>Or “a principle”</note> of faith. <verse-number id="Ro 3:28">28</verse-number>For we consider a person to be justified by faith apart from the works of the law. <verse-number id="Ro 3:29">29</verse-number>Or <supplied>is God</supplied> the God of the Jews only? <supplied>Is he</supplied> not also <supplied>the God</supplied> of the Gentiles? Yes, also of the Gentiles, <verse-number id="Ro 3:30">30</verse-number>since God <supplied>is</supplied> one, who will justify <idiom-start/>those who are circumcised<idiom-end/><note>Literally “circumcision”</note> by faith and <idiom-start/>those who are uncircumcised<idiom-end/><note>Literally “uncircumcision”</note> through faith. <verse-number id="Ro 3:31">31</verse-number>Therefore, do we nullify the law through faith? May it never be! But we uphold the law. </p>
		</chapter>