<chapter id="Ro 4">
			<pericope>Abraham’s Faith Counted as Righteousness</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 4:1">1</verse-number> What then shall we say <supplied>that</supplied> Abraham, our ancestor according to the flesh, has found? <verse-number id="Ro 4:2">2</verse-number>For if Abraham was justified by works, he has something to boast about, but not before God. <verse-number id="Ro 4:3">3</verse-number>For what does the scripture say? “And Abraham believed God, and it was credited to him for righteousness.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ge 15:6">Gen 15:6</cite></note> <verse-number id="Ro 4:4">4</verse-number>Now to the one who works, his pay is not credited according to grace, but according to his due. <verse-number id="Ro 4:5">5</verse-number>But to the one who does not work, but who believes in the one who justifies the ungodly, his faith is credited for righteousness, <verse-number id="Ro 4:6">6</verse-number>just as David also speaks about the blessing of the person to whom God credits righteousness apart from works: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ro 4:7">7</verse-number>“Blessed <supplied>are they</supplied> whose lawless deeds have been forgiven, </li1>
				<li2>and whose sins are covered over. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ro 4:8">8</verse-number>Blessed <supplied>is</supplied> the person against whom the Lord will never count sin.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 32:1–2">Ps 32:1–2</cite></note> </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 4:9">9</verse-number>Therefore, <supplied>is</supplied> this blessing for <idiom-start/>those who are circumcised<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the circumcision”</note>, or also for <idiom-start/>those who are uncircumcised<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the uncircumcision”</note>? For we say, “Faith was credited to Abraham for righteousness.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ge 15:6">Gen 15:6</cite></note> <verse-number id="Ro 4:10">10</verse-number>How then was it credited? <supplied>While he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was”) which is understood as temporal</note> was <idiom-start/>circumcised<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in circumcision”</note> or <idiom-start/>uncircumcised<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in uncircumcision”</note>? Not <idiom-start/>while circumcised<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in circumcision”</note> but <idiom-start/>while uncircumcised<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in uncircumcision”</note>! <verse-number id="Ro 4:11">11</verse-number>And he received the sign of circumcision <supplied>as</supplied> a seal<note>Or “confirmation”</note> of the righteousness by faith which <supplied>he had</supplied> <idiom-start/>while uncircumcised<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in uncircumcision”</note>, so that he could be the father of all who believe <idiom-start/>although they are uncircumcised<idiom-end/><note>Literally “through uncircumcision”</note>, so that righteousness could be credited to them,<note>Some manuscripts have “could be credited to them also”</note> <verse-number id="Ro 4:12">12</verse-number>and the father <idiom-start/>of those who are circumcised<idiom-end/><note>Literally “of the circumcision”</note> to those who are not only from the circumcision, but who also follow in the footsteps of the faith of our father Abraham <idiom-start/>which he had while uncircumcised<idiom-end/><note>Literally “of the in uncircumcision faith of our father Abraham”</note>. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Promise to Abraham Secured through Faith</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 4:13">13</verse-number>For the promise to Abraham or to his descendants, <supplied>that</supplied> he would be heir of the world, <supplied>was</supplied> not through the law, but through the righteousness by faith. <verse-number id="Ro 4:14">14</verse-number>For if those of the law <supplied>are</supplied> heirs, faith is rendered void and the promise is nullified. <verse-number id="Ro 4:15">15</verse-number>For the law produces wrath, but where <supplied>there</supplied> is no law, neither <supplied>is there</supplied> transgression. <verse-number id="Ro 4:16">16</verse-number>Because of this, <supplied>it is</supplied> by faith, in order that <supplied>it may be</supplied> according to grace, so that the promise may be secure to all the descendants, not only to those of the law, but also to those of the faith of Abraham, who is the father of us all <verse-number id="Ro 4:17">17</verse-number>(just as it is written, “I have made you the father of many nations”)<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ge 17:5">Gen 17:5</cite></note> before God, in whom he believed, the one who makes the dead alive and who calls the things that are not as <supplied>though</supplied> they are, <verse-number id="Ro 4:18">18</verse-number>who against hope believed in hope, so that he became the father of many nations, according to what was said, “so will your descendants be.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ge 15:5">Gen 15:5</cite></note> <verse-number id="Ro 4:19">19</verse-number>And not being weak in faith, he considered his own body as good as dead, <note>Some manuscripts have “already as good as dead”</note> <supplied>because he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was”) which is understood as causal</note> was approximately a hundred years old, and the deadness of Sarah’s womb. <verse-number id="Ro 4:20">20</verse-number>And he did not waver in unbelief at the promise of God, but was strengthened in faith, giving glory to God <verse-number id="Ro 4:21">21</verse-number>and being fully convinced that what he had promised, he was also able to do. <verse-number id="Ro 4:22">22</verse-number>Therefore<note>Some manuscripts have “Therefore, indeed,”</note> it was credited to him for righteousness. <verse-number id="Ro 4:23">23</verse-number>But it was not written for the sake of him alone that it was credited to him, <verse-number id="Ro 4:24">24</verse-number>but also for the sake of us to whom it is going to be credited, to those who believe in the one who raised Jesus our Lord from the dead, <verse-number id="Ro 4:25">25</verse-number>who was handed over on account of our trespasses, and was raised up in the interest of our justification.<note>Or “vindication”; or “acquittal”</note> </p>
		</chapter>