<chapter id="Ro 6">
			<pericope>Formerly Dead to Sin, Now Alive in Christ</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 6:1">1</verse-number> What therefore shall we say? Shall we continue in sin, in order that grace may increase? <verse-number id="Ro 6:2">2</verse-number>May it never be! How can we who died to sin still live in it? <verse-number id="Ro 6:3">3</verse-number>Or do you not know that as many as were baptized into Christ Jesus were baptized into his death? <verse-number id="Ro 6:4">4</verse-number>Therefore we have been buried with him through baptism into death, in order that just as Christ was raised from the dead through the glory of the Father, so also we may live <idiom-start/>a new way of life<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in newness of life”</note>. <verse-number id="Ro 6:5">5</verse-number>For if we have become identified with <supplied>him</supplied> in the likeness of his death, certainly also we will be <supplied>identified with him in the likeness</supplied><note>The elliptical phrase “identified with him in the likeness” has been supplied in the translation for clarity</note> of <supplied>his</supplied> resurrection, <verse-number id="Ro 6:6">6</verse-number>knowing this, that our old man was crucified together with <supplied>him</supplied>, in order that the body of sin may be done away with, <supplied>that</supplied> we may no longer be enslaved to sin. <verse-number id="Ro 6:7">7</verse-number>For the one who has died has been freed from sin. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 6:8">8</verse-number>Now if we died with Christ, we believe that we will also live with him, <verse-number id="Ro 6:9">9</verse-number>knowing that Christ, <supplied>because he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“has been raised”) which is understood as causal</note> has been raised from the dead, is going to die no more, death no longer being master over him. <verse-number id="Ro 6:10">10</verse-number>For that <supplied>death</supplied> he died, he died to sin once and never again, but that <supplied>life</supplied> he lives, he lives to God. <verse-number id="Ro 6:11">11</verse-number>So also you, consider yourselves to be dead to sin, but alive to God in Christ Jesus. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 6:12">12</verse-number>Therefore do not let sin reign in your mortal body, so that <supplied>you</supplied> obey its desires, <verse-number id="Ro 6:13">13</verse-number>and do not present your members to sin <supplied>as</supplied> instruments of unrighteousness, but present yourselves to God as those who are alive from the dead, and your members to God <supplied>as</supplied> instruments of righteousness. <verse-number id="Ro 6:14">14</verse-number>For sin will not be master over you, because you are not under law, but under grace. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Set Free from Sin</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 6:15">15</verse-number>What then? Shall we sin because we are not under law but under grace? May it never be! <verse-number id="Ro 6:16">16</verse-number>Do you not know that to whomever you present yourselves <supplied>as</supplied> slaves for obedience, you are slaves to whomever you obey, whether sin, <supplied>leading</supplied> to death, or obedience, <supplied>leading</supplied> to righteousness? <verse-number id="Ro 6:17">17</verse-number>But thanks <supplied>be</supplied> to God that you were slaves of sin, but you have obeyed from the heart the pattern of teaching to which you were entrusted, <verse-number id="Ro 6:18">18</verse-number>and having been set free from sin, you became enslaved to righteousness. <verse-number id="Ro 6:19">19</verse-number>(I am speaking in human terms because of the weakness of your flesh.) For just as you presented your members <supplied>as</supplied> slaves to immorality and lawlessness, <supplied>leading</supplied> to lawlessness, so now present your members <supplied>as</supplied> slaves to righteousness, <supplied>leading</supplied> to sanctification. <verse-number id="Ro 6:20">20</verse-number>For when you were slaves of sin, you were free with respect to righteousness. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 6:21">21</verse-number>Therefore what sort of fruit did you have then, about which you are now ashamed? For the end of those <supplied>things</supplied> <supplied>is</supplied> death. <verse-number id="Ro 6:22">22</verse-number>But now, having been set free from sin and having been enslaved to God, you have your fruit <supplied>leading</supplied> to sanctification, and its end <supplied>is</supplied> eternal life. <verse-number id="Ro 6:23">23</verse-number>For the compensation due sin <supplied>is</supplied> death, but the gift of God <supplied>is</supplied> eternal life in Christ Jesus our Lord. </p>
		</chapter>