<chapter id="Ro 7">
			<pericope>Released from the Law through Death</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 7:1">1</verse-number> Or do you not know, brothers (for I am speaking to those who know the law), that the law is master of a person for as long a time <supplied>as</supplied> he lives? <verse-number id="Ro 7:2">2</verse-number>For the married woman is bound by law to <supplied>her</supplied> husband while he lives, but if her husband dies, she is released from the law of the husband. <verse-number id="Ro 7:3">3</verse-number>Therefore as a result, if she belongs to another man <supplied>while</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“is living”) which is understood as temporal</note> her husband is living, she will be called an adulteress. But if her husband dies, she is free from the law, so that she is not an adulteress <supplied>if she</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>if</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“belongs”) which is understood as conditional</note> belongs to another man. <verse-number id="Ro 7:4">4</verse-number>So then, my brothers, you also were brought to death with respect to the law through the body of Christ, so that you may belong to another, to the one who was raised from the dead, in order that we may bear fruit for God. <verse-number id="Ro 7:5">5</verse-number>For when we were in the flesh, sinful desires were working through the law in our members, to bear fruit for death. <verse-number id="Ro 7:6">6</verse-number>But now we have been released from the law, <supplied>because we</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“have died”) which is understood as causal</note> have died <supplied>to that</supplied> by which we were bound, so that we may serve in newness of the Spirit and not in oldness of the letter <supplied>of the law</supplied>. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Knowledge of Sin Comes through the Law</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 7:7">7</verse-number>What then shall we say? <supplied>Is</supplied> the law sin? May it never be! But I would not have known sin except through the law, for I would not have known covetousness if the law had not said, “Do not covet.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ex 20:17">Exod 20:17</cite>; <cite title="BibleLEB2: Dt 5:21">Deut 5:21</cite></note> <verse-number id="Ro 7:8">8</verse-number>But sin, seizing an opportunity through the commandment, produced in me all <supplied>kinds of</supplied> covetousness. For apart from the law, sin <supplied>is</supplied> dead. <verse-number id="Ro 7:9">9</verse-number>And I was alive once, apart from the law, but <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“came”) which is understood as temporal</note> the commandment came, sin sprang to life <verse-number id="Ro 7:10">10</verse-number>and I died, and this commandment which <supplied>was</supplied> to <supplied>lead to</supplied> life was found with respect to me to <supplied>lead to</supplied> death. <verse-number id="Ro 7:11">11</verse-number>For sin, seizing the opportunity through the commandment, deceived me and through it killed <supplied>me</supplied>. <verse-number id="Ro 7:12">12</verse-number>So then, the law <supplied>is</supplied> holy, and the commandment <supplied>is</supplied> holy and righteous and good. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Internal Conflict with Sin</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 7:13">13</verse-number>Therefore, <supplied>did that which is</supplied> good become death to me? May it never be! Rather <supplied>it was</supplied> sin, in order that it might be recognized <supplied>as</supplied> sin, producing death through <supplied>what is</supplied> good for me, in order that sin might become sinful to an extraordinary degree through the commandment. <verse-number id="Ro 7:14">14</verse-number>For we know that the law is spiritual, but I am fleshly, <idiom-start/>sold into slavery to sin<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sold under sin”</note>. <verse-number id="Ro 7:15">15</verse-number>For what I am doing I do not understand, because what I want <supplied>to do</supplied>, this I do not practice, but what I hate, this I do. <verse-number id="Ro 7:16">16</verse-number>But if what I do not want <supplied>to do</supplied>, this I do, I agree with the law that <supplied>it is</supplied> good. <verse-number id="Ro 7:17">17</verse-number>But now I am no longer the one doing it, but sin that lives in me. <verse-number id="Ro 7:18">18</verse-number>For I know that good does not live in me, that is, in my flesh. For the willing is present in me, but the doing <supplied>of</supplied> the good <supplied>is</supplied> not. <verse-number id="Ro 7:19">19</verse-number>For the good that I want <supplied>to do</supplied>, I do not do, but the evil that I do not want <supplied>to do</supplied>, this I do. <verse-number id="Ro 7:20">20</verse-number>But if what I do not want <supplied>to do</supplied>, this I am doing, I am no longer the one doing it, but sin that lives in me. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 7:21">21</verse-number>Consequently, I find the principle with me, the one who wants to do good, that evil is present with me.<note>Or “in me”</note> <verse-number id="Ro 7:22">22</verse-number>For I joyfully agree with the law of God in my inner person, <verse-number id="Ro 7:23">23</verse-number>but I observe another law in my members, at war with the law of my mind and making me captive to the law of sin that exists in my members. <verse-number id="Ro 7:24">24</verse-number>Wretched man <supplied>that</supplied> I <supplied>am</supplied>! Who will rescue me from this body of death? <verse-number id="Ro 7:25">25</verse-number>Thanks <supplied>be</supplied><note>Some manuscripts have “But thanks <supplied>be</supplied>”</note> to God through Jesus Christ our Lord! So then, I myself with my mind am enslaved to the law of God, but with my flesh <supplied>I am enslaved</supplied> to the law of sin. </p>
		</chapter>