<chapter id="Ro 8">
			<pericope>Set Free from the Law of Sin and Death</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 8:1">1</verse-number> Consequently, <supplied>there is</supplied> now no condemnation for those <supplied>who are</supplied> in Christ Jesus. <verse-number id="Ro 8:2">2</verse-number>For the law of the Spirit of life in Christ Jesus has set you free from the law of sin and death. <verse-number id="Ro 8:3">3</verse-number>For what <supplied>was</supplied> impossible for the law, in that it was weak through the flesh, God <supplied>did</supplied>. <supplied>By</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“sending”) which is understood as means</note> sending his own Son in the likeness of sinful flesh and concerning sin, he condemned sin in the flesh, <verse-number id="Ro 8:4">4</verse-number>in order that the requirement of the law would be fulfilled in us, who do not live according to the flesh but according to the Spirit. <verse-number id="Ro 8:5">5</verse-number>For those who are <supplied>living</supplied> according to the flesh are intent on the things of the flesh, but those <supplied>who are living</supplied> according to the Spirit <supplied>are intent on</supplied> the things of the Spirit. <verse-number id="Ro 8:6">6</verse-number>For the mindset of the flesh <supplied>is</supplied> death, but the mindset of the Spirit <supplied>is</supplied> life and peace, <verse-number id="Ro 8:7">7</verse-number>because the mindset of the flesh <supplied>is</supplied> enmity toward God, for <supplied>it is</supplied> not subjected to the law of God, for <supplied>it is</supplied> not able <supplied>to do so</supplied>, <verse-number id="Ro 8:8">8</verse-number>and those who are in the flesh are not able to please God. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 8:9">9</verse-number>But you are not in the flesh but in the Spirit, if indeed the Spirit of God lives in you. But if anyone does not have the Spirit of Christ, this person <idiom-start/>does not belong to him<idiom-end/><note>Literally “is not of him”</note>. <verse-number id="Ro 8:10">10</verse-number>But if Christ <supplied>is</supplied> in you, the body <supplied>is</supplied> dead because of sin, but the Spirit <supplied>is</supplied> life because of righteousness. <verse-number id="Ro 8:11">11</verse-number>And if the Spirit of the one who raised Jesus from the dead lives in you, the one who raised Christ Jesus<note>Some manuscripts omit “Jesus”</note> from the dead will also make alive your mortal bodies through his Spirit who lives in you. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 8:12">12</verse-number>So then, brothers, we are obligated not to the flesh, to live according to the flesh. <verse-number id="Ro 8:13">13</verse-number>For if you live according to the flesh, you are going to die, but if by the Spirit you put to death the deeds of the body, you will live. <verse-number id="Ro 8:14">14</verse-number>For all those who are led by the Spirit of God, these are sons of God. <verse-number id="Ro 8:15">15</verse-number>For you have not received a spirit of slavery <supplied>leading</supplied> to fear again, but you have received the Spirit of adoption, by whom we cry out, “Abba!<note>“Abba” means “father” in Aramaic</note> Father!” <verse-number id="Ro 8:16">16</verse-number>The Spirit himself confirms to our spirit that we are children of God, <verse-number id="Ro 8:17">17</verse-number>and if children, also heirs—heirs of God and fellow heirs with Christ, if indeed we suffer together <supplied>with him</supplied> so that we may also be glorified together <supplied>with him</supplied>. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Glory that is to be Revealed</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 8:18">18</verse-number>For I consider that the sufferings of the present time are not worthy <supplied>to be compared</supplied> with the glory that is about to be revealed to us. <verse-number id="Ro 8:19">19</verse-number>For the eagerly expecting creation awaits eagerly the revelation of the sons of God. <verse-number id="Ro 8:20">20</verse-number>For the creation has been subjected to futility, not willingly, but because of the one who subjected <supplied>it</supplied>, in hope <verse-number id="Ro 8:21">21</verse-number>that the creation itself also will be set free from its servility to decay, into the glorious freedom of the children of God. <verse-number id="Ro 8:22">22</verse-number>For we know that the whole creation groans together and suffers agony together until now. <verse-number id="Ro 8:23">23</verse-number>Not only <supplied>this</supplied>, but we ourselves also, having the first fruits of the Spirit, even we ourselves groan within ourselves <supplied>while we</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“await eagerly”) which is understood as temporal</note> await eagerly <supplied>our</supplied> adoption, the redemption of our body. <verse-number id="Ro 8:24">24</verse-number>For in hope we were saved, but hope that is seen is not hope, for who hopes for what he sees? <verse-number id="Ro 8:25">25</verse-number>But if we hope for what we do not see, we await <supplied>it</supplied> eagerly with patient endurance. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 8:26">26</verse-number>And likewise also, the Spirit helps <supplied>us</supplied> in our weakness, for we do not know how to pray as one ought, but the Spirit himself intercedes <supplied>for us</supplied> <supplied>with</supplied> unexpressed groanings. <verse-number id="Ro 8:27">27</verse-number>And the one who searches our hearts knows what the mindset of the Spirit <supplied>is</supplied>, because he intercedes on behalf of the saints according to <supplied>the will of</supplied> God. <verse-number id="Ro 8:28">28</verse-number>And we know that all <supplied>things</supplied> work together for good for those who love God, for those who are called according to <supplied>his</supplied> purpose, <verse-number id="Ro 8:29">29</verse-number>because <supplied>those</supplied> whom he foreknew, he also predestined <supplied>to be</supplied> conformed to the image of his Son, so that he should be the firstborn among many brothers. <verse-number id="Ro 8:30">30</verse-number>And <supplied>those</supplied> whom he predestined, these <supplied>he</supplied> also called, and <supplied>those</supplied> whom he called, these <supplied>he</supplied> also justified, and <supplied>those</supplied> whom he justified, these <supplied>he</supplied> also glorified. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Victory in Christ</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 8:31">31</verse-number>What then shall we say about these <supplied>things</supplied>? If God <supplied>is</supplied> for us, who <supplied>can be</supplied> against us? <verse-number id="Ro 8:32">32</verse-number>Indeed, <supplied>he</supplied> who did not spare his own Son, but gave him up for us all, how will he not also, together with him, freely give us all <supplied>things</supplied>? <verse-number id="Ro 8:33">33</verse-number>Who will bring charges against God’s elect? God <supplied>is</supplied> the one who justifies. <verse-number id="Ro 8:34">34</verse-number>Who <supplied>is</supplied> the one who condemns? Christ<note>Some manuscripts have “Christ Jesus”</note> <supplied>is</supplied> the one who died, and more than that, who was raised, who is also at the right hand of God, who also intercedes for us. <verse-number id="Ro 8:35">35</verse-number>Who will separate us from the love of Christ? <supplied>Will</supplied> affliction or distress or persecution or hunger or lack of sufficient clothing or danger or the sword? <verse-number id="Ro 8:36">36</verse-number>Just as it is written, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“On account of you we are being put to death the whole day <supplied>long</supplied>; </li1>
				<li2>we are considered as sheep for slaughter.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 44:22">Ps 44:22</cite></note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 8:37">37</verse-number><supplied>No</supplied>, but in all these <supplied>things</supplied> we prevail completely through the one who loved us. <verse-number id="Ro 8:38">38</verse-number>For I am convinced that neither death, nor life, nor angels, nor rulers, nor things present, nor things to come, nor powers, <verse-number id="Ro 8:39">39</verse-number>nor height, nor depth, nor any other created thing, will be able to separate us from the love of God that is in Christ Jesus our Lord. </p>
		</chapter>