<chapter id="Ro 9">
			<pericope>Israel’s Rejection</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 9:1">1</verse-number> I am telling the truth in Christ—<supplied>I am</supplied> not lying; my conscience bears witness to me in the Holy Spirit—<verse-number id="Ro 9:2">2</verse-number>that my grief is great and <supplied>there is</supplied> constant distress in my heart. <verse-number id="Ro 9:3">3</verse-number>For I could wish myself to be accursed from Christ for the sake of my brothers, my fellow countrymen according to the flesh, <verse-number id="Ro 9:4">4</verse-number>who are Israelites, <supplied>to</supplied> whom <supplied>belong</supplied> the adoption, and the glory, and the covenants, and the giving of the law, and the <supplied>temple</supplied> service, and the promises, <verse-number id="Ro 9:5">5</verse-number><supplied>to</supplied> whom <supplied>belong</supplied> the patriarchs, and from whom <supplied>is</supplied> the Christ according to human descent, who is God over all, blessed <idiom-start/>forever<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for eternity”</note>! Amen. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 9:6">6</verse-number>But <supplied>it is</supplied> not as if the word of God had failed. For not all those <supplied>who are descended</supplied> from Israel <supplied>are truly</supplied> Israel, <verse-number id="Ro 9:7">7</verse-number>nor <supplied>are they</supplied> all children because they are descendants of Abraham, but “In Isaac will your descendants be named.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ge 21:12">Gen 21:12</cite></note> <verse-number id="Ro 9:8">8</verse-number>That is, <supplied>it is</supplied> not the children <idiom-start/>by human descent<idiom-end/><note>Literally “of the flesh”</note> <supplied>who are</supplied> children of God, but the children of the promise are counted as descendants. <verse-number id="Ro 9:9">9</verse-number>For the statement of the promise <supplied>is</supplied> this: “At this time I will return and <idiom-start/>Sarah will have<idiom-end/><note>Literally “there will be to Sarah”</note> a son.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ge 18:10">Gen 18:10</cite>, <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ge 18:14">14</cite></note> <verse-number id="Ro 9:10">10</verse-number>And not only <supplied>this</supplied>, but also <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“having conception” = “conceived”) which is understood as temporal</note> Rebecca conceived children by one <supplied>man</supplied>,<note>Or perhaps “by one <supplied>act of sexual intercourse</supplied>”</note> Isaac our father—<verse-number id="Ro 9:11">11</verse-number>for <supplied>although they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>although</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“been born”) which is understood as concessive</note> had not yet been born, or done anything good or evil, in order that the purpose of God according to election might remain, <verse-number id="Ro 9:12">12</verse-number>not by works but by the one who calls—it was said to her, “The older will serve the younger,”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ge 25:23">Gen 25:23</cite></note> <verse-number id="Ro 9:13">13</verse-number>just as it is written, “Jacob I loved, but Esau I hated.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Mal 1:2–3">Mal 1:2–3</cite></note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>God’s Sovereign Choice to Show Mercy</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 9:14">14</verse-number>What then shall we say? <supplied>There is</supplied> no injustice with God, <supplied>is there</supplied>?<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here</note> May it never be! <verse-number id="Ro 9:15">15</verse-number>For to Moses he says, “I will have mercy on whomever I have mercy, and I will have compassion on whomever I have compassion.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ex 33:19">Exod 33:19</cite></note> <verse-number id="Ro 9:16">16</verse-number>Consequently therefore, <idiom-start/>it does not depend on the<idiom-end/><note>Literally “not of the”</note> one who wills or on the one who runs, but on God who shows mercy. <verse-number id="Ro 9:17">17</verse-number>For the scripture says to Pharaoh, “For this very <supplied>reason</supplied> I have raised you up, so that I may demonstrate my power in you, and so that my name might be proclaimed in all the earth.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ex 9:16">Exod 9:16</cite></note> <verse-number id="Ro 9:18">18</verse-number>Consequently therefore, he has mercy on whomever he wishes, and he hardens whomever he wishes. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 9:19">19</verse-number>Therefore you will say to me, “Why then does he still find fault? For who has resisted<note>Or “who resists”</note> his will? <verse-number id="Ro 9:20">20</verse-number>On the contrary, O man, who are you who answers back to God? Will what is molded say to the one who molded <supplied>it</supplied>, “Why did you make me like this”?<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 29:16">Isa 29:16</cite>; <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 45:9">45:9</cite></note> <verse-number id="Ro 9:21">21</verse-number>Or does the potter not have authority over the clay, to make from the same lump a vessel that <supplied>is</supplied> for <idiom-start/>honorable use<idiom-end/><note>Literally “honor”</note> and <supplied>one</supplied> that <supplied>is</supplied> for <idiom-start/>ordinary use<idiom-end/><note>Literally “dishonor”</note>? <verse-number id="Ro 9:22">22</verse-number>And <supplied>what</supplied> if God, wanting to demonstrate his wrath and to make known his power, endured with much patience vessels of wrath prepared for destruction? <verse-number id="Ro 9:23">23</verse-number>And <supplied>he did so</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The words “he did so” are not in the Greek text, but are an understood repetition from the previous clause</note> in order that he could make known the riches of his glory upon vessels of mercy that he prepared beforehand for glory, <verse-number id="Ro 9:24">24</verse-number>us whom he also called, not only from the Jews but also from the Gentiles? <verse-number id="Ro 9:25">25</verse-number>As he also says in Hosea, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“I will call those <supplied>who were</supplied> not my people, ‘My people,’ </li1>
				<li2>and those <supplied>who were</supplied> not loved, ‘Loved.’<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ho 2:23">Hos 2:23</cite></note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ro 9:26">26</verse-number>And it will be in the place where it was said to them, ‘You <supplied>are</supplied> not my people,’ </li1>
				<li2>there they will be called ‘sons of the living God.’ ”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ho 1:10">Hos 1:10</cite></note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 9:27">27</verse-number>And Isaiah cries out concerning Israel, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“<supplied>Even</supplied> if the number of the sons of Israel is like the sand of the sea, </li1>
				<li2>the remnant will be saved, </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Ro 9:28">28</verse-number><idiom-start/>for the Lord will execute his sentence thoroughly and decisively<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for the Lord will act, closing the account and cutting short”</note> upon the earth.”<note>A paraphrased quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 10:22–23">Isa 10:22–23</cite></note> </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 9:29">29</verse-number>And just as Isaiah foretold, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“If the Lord of hosts had not left us descendants, </li1>
				<li2>we would have become like Sodom </li2>
				<li3>and would have resembled Gomorrah.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 1:9">Isa 1:9</cite></note> </li3>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 9:30">30</verse-number>What then shall we say? That the Gentiles, who did not pursue righteousness, attained righteousness—even the righteousness <supplied>that is</supplied> by faith. <verse-number id="Ro 9:31">31</verse-number>But Israel, pursuing the law of righteousness, did not attain to the law. <verse-number id="Ro 9:32">32</verse-number>Why that? Because <supplied>they did</supplied> not <supplied>pursue it</supplied> by faith, but as <supplied>if</supplied> by works. They stumbled over the <idiom-start/>stone that causes people to stumble<idiom-end/><note>Literally “stone of stumbling”</note>, <verse-number id="Ro 9:33">33</verse-number>just as it is written, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Behold, I am laying in Zion <idiom-start/>a stone that causes people to stumble<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a stone of stumbling”</note>, </li1>
				<li2>and <idiom-start/>a rock that causes them to fall<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a rock of offense”</note>, </li2>
				<li1>and the one who believes in him will not be put to shame.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 28:16">Isa 28:16</cite>; <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 8:14">8:14</cite></note> </li1>
			</ul>
		</chapter>