<chapter id="Ro 10">
			<pericope>The Righteousness of God through Faith in Christ</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 10:1">1</verse-number> Brothers, the desire of my heart and my prayer to God on behalf of them <supplied>is</supplied> for <supplied>their</supplied> salvation. <verse-number id="Ro 10:2">2</verse-number>For I testify about them that they have a zeal for God, but not according to knowledge. <verse-number id="Ro 10:3">3</verse-number>For ignoring the righteousness of God, and seeking to establish their own,<note>Some manuscripts have “their own righteousness”</note> they did not subject themselves to the righteousness of God. <verse-number id="Ro 10:4">4</verse-number>For Christ <supplied>is the</supplied> end of the law for righteousness to everyone who believes. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 10:5">5</verse-number>For Moses writes about the righteousness <supplied>that is</supplied> from the law: “The person who does <supplied>this</supplied><note>Some manuscripts explicitly state “these <supplied>things</supplied>”</note> will live by it.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Le 18:5">Lev 18:5</cite></note><note>Some manuscripts have “them”</note> <verse-number id="Ro 10:6">6</verse-number>But the righteousness from faith speaks like this: “Do not say in your heart,<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Dt 9:4">Deut 9:4</cite></note> ‘Who will ascend into heaven?’ ”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Dt 30:12">Deut 30:12</cite></note> (that is, to bring Christ down), <verse-number id="Ro 10:7">7</verse-number>or “Who will descend into the abyss?”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Dt 30:13">Deut 30:13</cite></note> (that is, to bring Christ up from the dead). <verse-number id="Ro 10:8">8</verse-number>But what does it say? “The word is near to you, in your mouth and in your heart”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Dt 30:14">Deut 30:14</cite></note> (that is, the word of faith that we proclaim), <verse-number id="Ro 10:9">9</verse-number>that<note>Or “because”</note> if you confess with your mouth “Jesus <supplied>is</supplied> Lord” and believe in your heart that God raised him from the dead, you will be saved. <verse-number id="Ro 10:10">10</verse-number>For with the heart one believes, resulting in righteousness, and with the mouth one confesses, resulting in salvation. <verse-number id="Ro 10:11">11</verse-number>For the scripture says, “Everyone who believes in him will not be put to shame.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 28:16">Isa 28:16</cite></note> <verse-number id="Ro 10:12">12</verse-number>For <supplied>there</supplied> is no distinction between Jew and Greek, for the same <supplied>Lord</supplied> <supplied>is</supplied> Lord of all, who is rich to all who call upon him. <verse-number id="Ro 10:13">13</verse-number>For “everyone who calls upon the name of the Lord will be saved.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Joe 2:32">Joel 2:32</cite></note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 10:14">14</verse-number>How then will they call upon <supplied>him</supplied> in whom they have not believed? And how will they believe <supplied>in him</supplied> about whom they have not heard? And how will they hear about <supplied>him</supplied> without one who preaches <supplied>to them</supplied>? <verse-number id="Ro 10:15">15</verse-number>And how will they preach, unless they are sent? Just as it is written, “How timely <supplied>are</supplied> the feet of those who bring good news of good things.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 52:7">Isa 52:7</cite>; <cite title="BibleLEB2: Na 1:15">Nah 1:15</cite></note> <verse-number id="Ro 10:16">16</verse-number>But not all have obeyed the good news, for Isaiah says, “Lord, who has believed our report?”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 53:1">Isa 53:1</cite></note> <verse-number id="Ro 10:17">17</verse-number>Consequently, faith <supplied>comes</supplied> by hearing, and hearing through the word about Christ. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 10:18">18</verse-number>But I say, they have not heard, have they?<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here</note> On the contrary, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Their voice has gone out to all the earth, </li1>
				<li2>and their words to the ends of the inhabited world.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 19:4">Ps 19:4</cite></note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 10:19">19</verse-number>But I say, Israel did not know, did they?<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here</note> First, Moses says, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“I will provoke you <supplied>to jealousy</supplied> by <supplied>those who are</supplied> not a nation; </li1>
				<li2>by a senseless nation I will provoke you <supplied>to anger</supplied>.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Dt 32:21">Deut 32:21</cite></note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 10:20">20</verse-number>And Isaiah is very bold and says, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“I was found by those who did not seek me; </li1>
				<li2>I became known to those who did not ask for me.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 65:1">Isa 65:1</cite></note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 10:21">21</verse-number>But about Israel he says, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“The whole day <supplied>long</supplied> I held out my hands </li1>
				<li2>to a disobedient and resistant people.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 65:2">Isa 65:2</cite></note> </li2>
			</ul>
		</chapter>