<chapter id="Ro 12">
			<pericope>A Life Dedicated to God</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 12:1">1</verse-number> Therefore I exhort you, brothers, through the mercies of God, to present your bodies <supplied>as</supplied> a living sacrifice, holy <supplied>and</supplied> pleasing to God, <supplied>which is</supplied> your reasonable service. <verse-number id="Ro 12:2">2</verse-number>And do not be conformed to this age, but be transformed by the renewal of your mind, so that you may approve what <supplied>is</supplied> the good and well-pleasing and perfect will of God. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A Variety of Gifts in the Body of Christ</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 12:3">3</verse-number>For by the grace given to me I say to everyone who is among you not to think more highly of yourself than what one ought to think, but to think <idiom-start/>sensibly<idiom-end/><note>Literally “so as to be sensible”</note>, as God has apportioned a measure of faith to each one. <verse-number id="Ro 12:4">4</verse-number>For just as in one body we have many members, but all the members do not have the same function, <verse-number id="Ro 12:5">5</verse-number>in the same way we who are many are one body in Christ, and <idiom-start/>individually<idiom-end/><note>Literally “with respect to one”</note> members of one another, <verse-number id="Ro 12:6">6</verse-number>but having different gifts according to the grace given to us: if <supplied>it is</supplied> prophecy, according to the proportion of <supplied>his</supplied> faith; <verse-number id="Ro 12:7">7</verse-number>if <supplied>it is</supplied> service, by service; if <supplied>it is</supplied> one who teaches, by teaching; <verse-number id="Ro 12:8">8</verse-number>if <supplied>it is</supplied> one who exhorts, by exhortation; one who gives, with sincerity; one who leads, with diligence; one who shows mercy, with cheerfulness. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Living in Love</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 12:9">9</verse-number>Love must be without hypocrisy. Abhor what <supplied>is</supplied> evil; be attached to what <supplied>is</supplied> good, <verse-number id="Ro 12:10">10</verse-number>being devoted to one another in brotherly love, esteeming one another <supplied>more highly</supplied> in honor, <verse-number id="Ro 12:11">11</verse-number>not lagging in diligence, being enthusiastic in spirit, serving the Lord, <verse-number id="Ro 12:12">12</verse-number>rejoicing in hope, enduring in affliction, being devoted to prayer, <verse-number id="Ro 12:13">13</verse-number>contributing to the needs of the saints, pursuing hospitality. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 12:14">14</verse-number>Bless those who persecute,<note>Some manuscripts have “who persecute you”</note> bless and do not curse <supplied>them</supplied>. <verse-number id="Ro 12:15">15</verse-number>Rejoice with those who rejoice; weep with those who weep. <verse-number id="Ro 12:16">16</verse-number>Think the same <supplied>thing</supplied> toward one another; <idiom-start/>do not think arrogantly<idiom-end/><note>Literally “think not the arrogant”</note>, but associate with the lowly. Do not be wise <idiom-start/>in your own sight<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the sight of yourselves”</note>. <verse-number id="Ro 12:17">17</verse-number>Pay back no one evil for evil. Take thought for <supplied>what is</supplied> good in the sight of all people. <verse-number id="Ro 12:18">18</verse-number>If <supplied>it is</supplied> possible on your <supplied>part</supplied>, be at peace with all people. <verse-number id="Ro 12:19">19</verse-number>Do not take revenge yourselves, dear friends, but give place to <supplied>God’s</supplied> wrath, for it is written, “Vengeance <supplied>is</supplied> mine, I will repay,”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Dt 32:35">Deut 32:35</cite></note> says the Lord. <verse-number id="Ro 12:20">20</verse-number>But “if your enemy is hungry, feed him; if he is thirsty, give him <supplied>something</supplied> to drink; for <supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“doing”) which is understood as means</note> doing this, you will heap up coals of fire upon his head.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Pr 25:21–22">Prov 25:21–22</cite></note> <verse-number id="Ro 12:21">21</verse-number>Do not be overcome by evil, but overcome evil with good. </p>
		</chapter>