<chapter id="Ro 13">
			<pericope>Obedience to the Governing Authorities</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 13:1">1</verse-number> Let every person be subject to the governing authorities, for <supplied>there</supplied> is no authority except by God, and those that exist are put in place by God. <verse-number id="Ro 13:2">2</verse-number>So then, the one who resists authority resists the ordinance <supplied>which is</supplied> from God, and those who resist will receive condemnation on themselves. <verse-number id="Ro 13:3">3</verse-number>For rulers are not a <supplied>cause of</supplied> terror for a good deed, but for bad <supplied>conduct</supplied>. So do you want not to be afraid of authority? Do what <supplied>is</supplied> good, and you will have praise from it, <verse-number id="Ro 13:4">4</verse-number>for it is God’s servant to you for what <supplied>is</supplied> good. But if you do what <supplied>is</supplied> bad, be afraid, because it does not bear the sword to no purpose. For it is God’s servant, the one who avenges for punishment on the one who does <supplied>what is</supplied> bad. <verse-number id="Ro 13:5">5</verse-number>Therefore <supplied>it is</supplied> necessary to be in subjection, not only because of wrath but also because of conscience. <verse-number id="Ro 13:6">6</verse-number>For because of this you also pay taxes, for <supplied>the authorities</supplied><note>Literally “they”</note> are servants of God, busily engaged in this very <supplied>thing</supplied>. <verse-number id="Ro 13:7">7</verse-number>Pay to everyone <supplied>what is</supplied> owed: <supplied>pay</supplied> taxes to whom taxes <supplied>are due</supplied>; <supplied>pay</supplied> customs duties to whom customs duties <supplied>are due</supplied>; <supplied>pay</supplied> respect to whom respect <supplied>is due</supplied>; <supplied>pay</supplied> honor to whom honor <supplied>is due</supplied>.<note>Due to the very compressed style in this verse, many words must be supplied to make sense in English</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Love Fulfills the Law</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 13:8">8</verse-number>Owe nothing to anyone, except to love one another, for the one who loves someone else has fulfilled the law. <verse-number id="Ro 13:9">9</verse-number>For the <supplied>commandments</supplied>, “You shall not commit adultery, you shall not commit murder, you shall not steal, you shall not covet,”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ex 20:13–15">Exod 20:13–15</cite>, <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ex 20:17">17</cite>; <cite title="BibleLEB2: Dt 5:17–19">Deut 5:17–19</cite>, <cite title="BibleLEB2: Dt 5:21">21</cite></note> and if <supplied>there is</supplied> any other commandment, are summed up in this statement: “You shall love your neighbor as yourself.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Le 19:18">Lev 19:18</cite></note> <verse-number id="Ro 13:10">10</verse-number>Love does not commit evil against a neighbor. Therefore love <supplied>is the</supplied> fulfillment of the law. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 13:11">11</verse-number>And <supplied>do</supplied> this <supplied>because you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“know”) which is understood as causal</note> know the time, that <supplied>it is</supplied> already the hour for you to wake up from sleep. For our salvation <supplied>is</supplied> nearer now than when we believed. <verse-number id="Ro 13:12">12</verse-number>The night is far gone, and the day has drawn near. Therefore let us throw off<note>Some manuscripts have “let us lay aside”</note> the deeds of darkness and put on the weapons of light. <verse-number id="Ro 13:13">13</verse-number>Let us live decently, as in the day, not in carousing and drunkenness, not in sexual immorality and licentiousness, not in strife and jealousy. <verse-number id="Ro 13:14">14</verse-number>But put on the Lord Jesus Christ and do not make provision for the desires of the flesh. </p>
		</chapter>