<chapter id="Ro 14">
			<pericope>Do Not Pass Judgment on One Another</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 14:1">1</verse-number> Now receive the one who is weak in faith, <supplied>but</supplied> not for quarrels about opinions. <verse-number id="Ro 14:2">2</verse-number>One believes <supplied>he may</supplied> eat all <supplied>things</supplied>, but the one who is weak eats <supplied>only</supplied> vegetables. <verse-number id="Ro 14:3">3</verse-number>The one who eats must not despise the one who does not eat, and the one who does not eat must not judge the one who eats, because God has accepted him. <verse-number id="Ro 14:4">4</verse-number>Who are you, who passes judgment on the domestic slave belonging to someone else? To his own master he stands or falls, and he will stand, for the Lord is able to make him stand. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 14:5">5</verse-number>One person<note>Some manuscripts have “For one person”</note> prefers <supplied>one</supplied> day over <supplied>another</supplied> day, and another person regards every day <supplied>alike</supplied>. Each one must be fully convinced in his own mind. <verse-number id="Ro 14:6">6</verse-number>The one who is intent on the day is intent on <supplied>it</supplied> for the Lord, and the one who eats eats for the Lord, because he is thankful to God, and the one who does not eat does not eat for the Lord, and he is thankful to God. <verse-number id="Ro 14:7">7</verse-number>For none of us lives for himself and none dies for himself. <verse-number id="Ro 14:8">8</verse-number>For if we live, we live for the Lord, and if we die, we die for the Lord. Therefore whether we live <supplied>or</supplied> whether we die, we are the Lord’s. <verse-number id="Ro 14:9">9</verse-number>For Christ died and became alive again for this <supplied>reason</supplied>, in order that he might be Lord of both the dead and the living. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 14:10">10</verse-number>But why do you judge your brother? Or also, why do you despise your brother? For we will all stand before the judgment seat of God. <verse-number id="Ro 14:11">11</verse-number>For it is written, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“As I live, says the Lord, every knee will bow to me, </li1>
				<li1>and every tongue will praise God.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 45:23">Isa 45:23</cite></note> </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 14:12">12</verse-number>So<note>Some manuscripts have “So then,”</note> each one of us will give an account concerning himself.<note>Some manuscripts have “an account concerning himself to God”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 14:13">13</verse-number>Therefore, let us no longer pass judgment on one another, but rather decide this: not to place a cause for stumbling or a temptation before a brother. <verse-number id="Ro 14:14">14</verse-number>I know and am convinced in the Lord Jesus that nothing <supplied>is</supplied> unclean of itself, except to the one who considers something to be unclean; to that person <supplied>it is</supplied> unclean. <verse-number id="Ro 14:15">15</verse-number>For if because of food, your brother is grieved, you are no longer living according to love. Do not destroy by your food that person for whom Christ died. <verse-number id="Ro 14:16">16</verse-number>Therefore do not let your good be slandered. <verse-number id="Ro 14:17">17</verse-number>For the kingdom of God is not eating and drinking, but righteousness and peace and joy in the Holy Spirit. <verse-number id="Ro 14:18">18</verse-number>For the one who serves Christ in this <supplied>way</supplied> <supplied>is</supplied> well-pleasing to God and approved by people. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 14:19">19</verse-number>So then, let us pursue <idiom-start/>what promotes peace<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the things of peace”</note> and <idiom-start/>what edifies one another<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the things of edification toward one another”</note>. <verse-number id="Ro 14:20">20</verse-number>Do not destroy the work of God on account of food. All <supplied>things</supplied> <supplied>are</supplied> clean, but <supplied>it is</supplied> wrong for the person <idiom-start/>who eats and stumbles in the process<idiom-end/><note>Literally “who eats with stumbling”</note>. <verse-number id="Ro 14:21">21</verse-number><supplied>It is</supplied> good not to eat meat or to drink wine or <supplied>to do anything</supplied> by which your brother stumbles or is offended or is weakened.<note>Some manuscripts omit “or is offended or is weakened”</note> <verse-number id="Ro 14:22">22</verse-number>The faith that you have, have with respect to yourself before God. Blessed <supplied>is</supplied> the one who does not pass judgment on himself by what he approves. <verse-number id="Ro 14:23">23</verse-number>But the one who doubts is condemned if he eats, because he does not <supplied>do so</supplied> from faith, and everything that <supplied>is</supplied> not from faith is sin. </p>
		</chapter>