<chapter id="Ro 15">
			<pericope>Accept One Another according to Christ’s Example</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 15:1">1</verse-number> But we who are strong ought to bear the weaknesses of the weak, and not to please ourselves. <verse-number id="Ro 15:2">2</verse-number>Let each one of us please his neighbor for his good, for the purpose of edification. <verse-number id="Ro 15:3">3</verse-number>For even Christ did not please himself, but just as it is written, “The insults of those who insult you have fallen on me.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 69:9">Ps 69:9</cite></note> <verse-number id="Ro 15:4">4</verse-number>For whatever was written beforehand was written for our instruction, in order that through patient endurance and through the encouragement of the scriptures we may have hope. <verse-number id="Ro 15:5">5</verse-number>Now may the God of patient endurance and of encouragement grant you <idiom-start/>to be in agreement<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to think the same”</note> with one another, in accordance with Christ Jesus, <verse-number id="Ro 15:6">6</verse-number>so that with one mind you may glorify with one mouth the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ. <verse-number id="Ro 15:7">7</verse-number>Therefore accept one another, just as Christ also has accepted you, to the glory of God. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 15:8">8</verse-number>For I say, Christ has become a servant of the circumcision on behalf of the truth of God, in order to confirm the promises to the fathers, <verse-number id="Ro 15:9">9</verse-number>and that the Gentiles may glorify God for <supplied>his</supplied> mercy, just as it is written, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Because of this, I will praise you among the Gentiles, </li1>
				<li2>and I will sing praise to your name.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 18:49">Ps 18:49</cite></note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 15:10">10</verse-number>And again it says, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Rejoice, Gentiles, with his people.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Dt 32:43">Deut 32:43</cite></note> </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 15:11">11</verse-number>And again, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Praise the Lord, all the Gentiles, </li1>
				<li2>and let all the peoples praise him.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 117:1">Ps 117:1</cite></note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 15:12">12</verse-number>And again Isaiah says, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“The root of Jesse will come, </li1>
				<li2>even the one who rises to rule over the Gentiles; </li2>
				<li1>in him the Gentiles will put their hope.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 11:10">Isa 11:10</cite></note> </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 15:13">13</verse-number>Now may the God of hope fill you with all joy and peace in believing, so that you may abound in hope by the power of the Holy Spirit. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Paul’s Ministry to the Gentiles</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 15:14">14</verse-number>Now I myself also am convinced about you, my brothers, that <supplied>you</supplied> yourselves also are full of goodness, filled with all knowledge, able also to instruct one another. <verse-number id="Ro 15:15">15</verse-number>But I have written to you more boldly on <supplied>some</supplied> points, so as to remind you <supplied>again</supplied> because of the grace that has been given to me by God, <verse-number id="Ro 15:16">16</verse-number>with the result that I am a servant of Christ Jesus to the Gentiles, serving the gospel of God as a priest, in order that the offering of the Gentiles may become acceptable, sanctified by the Holy Spirit. <verse-number id="Ro 15:17">17</verse-number>Therefore I have a reason for boasting in Christ Jesus regarding the things concerning God. <verse-number id="Ro 15:18">18</verse-number>For I will not dare to speak about anything except <supplied>that</supplied> which Christ has accomplished through me, resulting in the obedience of the Gentiles by word and deed, <verse-number id="Ro 15:19">19</verse-number>by the power of signs and wonders, by the power of the Spirit,<note>Some manuscripts have “of the Spirit of God”</note> so that from Jerusalem and <supplied>traveling</supplied> around as far as Illyricum I have fully proclaimed the gospel of Christ. <verse-number id="Ro 15:20">20</verse-number>And so, having as my ambition to proclaim the gospel where Christ has not been named, in order that I will not build on the foundation belonging to someone else, <verse-number id="Ro 15:21">21</verse-number>but just as it is written, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“<supplied>Those</supplied> to whom <supplied>it was</supplied> not announced concerning him will see, </li1>
				<li1>and <supplied>those</supplied> who have not heard will understand.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 52:15">Isa 52:15</cite></note> </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Paul’s Travel Plans</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 15:22">22</verse-number>For this reason also I was hindered many <supplied>times</supplied> from coming to you, <verse-number id="Ro 15:23">23</verse-number>and now, no longer having a place in these regions, but having a desire for many years to come to you <verse-number id="Ro 15:24">24</verse-number>whenever I travel to Spain. For I hope <supplied>while I</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“passing through”) which is understood as temporal</note> am passing through to see you and to be sent on my way by you, whenever I have first enjoyed your <supplied>company</supplied> for a while. <verse-number id="Ro 15:25">25</verse-number>But now I am traveling to Jerusalem, serving the saints. <verse-number id="Ro 15:26">26</verse-number>For Macedonia and Achaia were pleased to make some contribution for the poor among the saints in Jerusalem. <verse-number id="Ro 15:27">27</verse-number>For they were pleased <supplied>to do so</supplied>, and they are obligated to them. For if the Gentiles have shared in their spiritual <supplied>things</supplied>, they ought also to serve them in material <supplied>things</supplied>. <verse-number id="Ro 15:28">28</verse-number>Therefore, <supplied>after I</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“have accomplished”) which is understood as temporal</note> have accomplished this and sealed this fruit <supplied>for delivery</supplied> to them, I will depart by way of you for Spain, <verse-number id="Ro 15:29">29</verse-number>and I know that <supplied>when I</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“come”) which is understood as temporal</note> come to you, I will come in the fullness of the blessing of Christ. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ro 15:30">30</verse-number>Now I exhort you, brothers, through our Lord Jesus Christ and through the love of the Spirit, to contend along with me in your prayers on my behalf to God, <verse-number id="Ro 15:31">31</verse-number>that I may be rescued from those who are disobedient in Judea, and my ministry in Jerusalem may be acceptable to the saints, <verse-number id="Ro 15:32">32</verse-number>so that, coming to you with joy by the will of God, I may rest with you. <verse-number id="Ro 15:33">33</verse-number>Now <supplied>may</supplied> the God of peace <supplied>be</supplied> with all of you. Amen. </p>
		</chapter>