<chapter id="Is 5">
			<pericope>The Song of the Vineyard</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 5:1">1</verse-number>Let me sing for my beloved </li1>
				<li2>a song of my love concerning his vineyard: </li2>
				<li1><idiom-start/>My beloved had a vineyard<idiom-end/><note>Literally “A vineyard was for my beloved”</note> on <idiom-start/>a fertile hill<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “a horn of a son of olive oil.” The Hebrew for horn, <i>qeren</i>, sounds like the Hebrew for vineyard, <i>kerem</i></note> </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 5:2">2</verse-number>And he dug it and cleared it of stones, </li1>
				<li2>and he planted it <supplied>with</supplied> choice vines,<note>Hebrew “vine”</note> </li2>
				<li1>and he built a watchtower in the middle of it, </li1>
				<li2>and he even hewed out a wine vat in it, </li2>
				<li1>and he waited for <supplied>it</supplied> to yield grapes— </li1>
				<li2>but it yielded wild grapes. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 5:3">3</verse-number>And now, inhabitants of Jerusalem </li1>
				<li2>and men<note>Hebrew “man”</note> of Judah, judge between me and my vineyard. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 5:4">4</verse-number>What more <supplied>was there</supplied> to do for my vineyard that I have not done in it? </li1>
				<li2>Why did I hope for <supplied>it</supplied> to yield grapes, and it yielded wild grapes? </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 5:5">5</verse-number>And now let me tell you what I myself am about to do to my vineyard. </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><supplied>I will</supplied> remove its hedge, and it shall become a devastation. </li1>
				<li2><supplied>I will</supplied> break down its wall, and it shall become a trampling. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 5:6">6</verse-number>And I will make it a wasteland; </li1>
				<li2>it shall not be pruned and hoed, </li2>
				<li1>and it shall be overgrown <supplied>with</supplied> briers<note>Hebrew “brier”</note> and thornbushes.<note>Hebrew “thornbush”</note> </li1>
				<li2>And concerning the clouds, I will command <idiom-start/>them not to send<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from sending”</note> rain down upon it. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 5:7">7</verse-number>For the vineyard of Yahweh of hosts <supplied>is</supplied> the house of Israel, </li1>
				<li2>and the man<note>Or “people”</note> of Judah <supplied>is</supplied> the plantation of his delight. </li2>
				<li1><supplied>And</supplied> he waited for justice,<note>The Hebrew word, <i>mishpat,</i> sounds like <i>mishpakh</i> in the next line</note> </li1>
				<li2>but look! Bloodshed!<note>The Hebrew word, <i>mishpakh</i>, sounds like <i>mishpat</i> in the previous line</note> </li2>
				<li1>For righteousness,<note>The Hebrew word, <i>tsedaqah,</i> sounds like <i>tsa`aqah</i> in the next line</note> </li1>
				<li2>but look! A cry of distress!<note>The Hebrew word, <i>tsa`aqah,</i> sounds like <i>tsedaqah</i> in the previous line</note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Woes on the Wicked</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 5:8">8</verse-number>Ah! Those who <idiom-start/>join<idiom-end/><note>Literally “touch”</note> house with house, </li1>
				<li2>they join field together with field </li2>
				<li1>until <idiom-start/>there is no place<idiom-end/><note>Literally “an end of place”</note> </li1>
				<li2>and you are caused to dwell alone in the midst of the land. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 5:9">9</verse-number>Yahweh of hosts <supplied>said</supplied> in my ears: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><idiom-start/>Surely<idiom-end/><note>Literally “If not”</note> many houses shall become a desolation, </li1>
				<li2>large and beautiful <supplied>ones</supplied> without inhabitant. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 5:10">10</verse-number>For ten acres of vineyard shall yield one bath,<note>A bath is a liquid measure</note> </li1>
				<li1>and <supplied>the</supplied> seed of a homer will yield an ephah.<note>An ephah is a dry measure equal to one-tenth of a homer</note> </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 5:11">11</verse-number>Ah! Those who rise early in the morning, </li1>
				<li2>they pursue strong drink. </li2>
				<li1>Those who linger in the evening, </li1>
				<li2>wine inflames them. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 5:12">12</verse-number>And <supplied>there</supplied> will be lyre and harp, </li1>
				<li2>tambourine and flute, </li2>
				<li2>and wine <supplied>at</supplied> their feasts, </li2>
				<li1>but they do not look at the deeds<note>Hebrew “deed”</note> of Yahweh, </li1>
				<li2>and they do not see the work of his hands. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 5:13">13</verse-number>Therefore my people will go into exile without knowledge, </li1>
				<li1><supplied>and</supplied> their<note>Hebrew “its”</note> nobles<note>Hebrew “noble”</note> <supplied>will be</supplied> men of hunger, </li1>
				<li1>and their<note>Hebrew “its”</note> multitude <supplied>is</supplied> parched <supplied>with</supplied> thirst. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 5:14">14</verse-number>Therefore Sheol has enlarged its throat, </li1>
				<li2>and it has opened wide its mouth without limit, </li2>
				<li1>and her<note>That is, Jerusalem’s</note> nobles<note>Hebrew “noble”</note> will go down, and her multitude, </li1>
				<li2>her tumult and those who revel in her. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 5:15">15</verse-number>And humankind is bowed down, </li1>
				<li2>and man is brought low, </li2>
				<li2>and <supplied>the</supplied> eyes of <supplied>the</supplied> haughty are humiliated. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 5:16">16</verse-number>But Yahweh of hosts is exalted by justice, </li1>
				<li2>and the holy God shows himself holy by righteousness. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 5:17">17</verse-number>And then <supplied>the</supplied> lambs will graze as <supplied>in</supplied> their pasture, </li1>
				<li2>and <idiom-start/>fatlings, kids<note>Following the Septuagint, which reads the Hebrew <i>grym</i> (resident aliens) as <i>gdym</i> (young goats/sheep)</note> will eat among the sites of ruins.<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and ruins, fatlings, resident aliens, will eat”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 5:18">18</verse-number>Ah! Those who drag iniquity along with the cords of falsehood </li1>
				<li2>and sin as with rope of the cart, </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 5:19">19</verse-number>those who say, </li1>
				<li1>“Let him make haste; </li1>
				<li2>let him hurry his work </li2>
				<li3>so that we may see it </li3>
				<li1>and let it draw near </li1>
				<li2>and let the plan of the holy one of Israel come </li2>
				<li3>so that we may know <supplied>it</supplied>!” </li3>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 5:20">20</verse-number>Ah! Those who call evil good and good evil, </li1>
				<li2>those who put darkness for light and light for darkness, </li2>
				<li2>those who put bitter for sweet and sweet for bitter! </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 5:21">21</verse-number>Ah! <supplied>Those who are</supplied> wise in their own eyes </li1>
				<li2>and have understanding <idiom-start/>in their view<idiom-end/>!<note>Literally “before their faces”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 5:22">22</verse-number>Ah! Heroes at drinking wine, </li1>
				<li2>and men of capability at mixing strong drink! </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 5:23">23</verse-number>Those who acquit the guilty because of a bribe </li1>
				<li2>and remove <supplied>the</supplied> justice of <supplied>the</supplied> innocent from him. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 5:24">24</verse-number>Therefore as the tongue of fire devours the stubble, </li1>
				<li2>and dry grass sinks down <supplied>in the</supplied> flame, </li2>
				<li1>so their root will become like <supplied>the</supplied> stench, </li1>
				<li2>and their blossom will go up like <supplied>the</supplied> dust. </li2>
				<li1>For they have rejected the instruction of Yahweh of hosts, </li1>
				<li2>and they have treated the word of the holy one of Israel with contempt. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 5:25">25</verse-number>Therefore <idiom-start/>Yahweh’s wrath was kindled<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the anger of Yahweh became hot”</note> against his people, </li1>
				<li2>and he stretched out his hand against them<note>Hebrew “it”</note> and struck them,<note>Hebrew “it”</note> </li2>
				<li1>and the mountains quaked, </li1>
				<li2>and their corpses<note>Hebrew “corpse”</note> were like refuse in <supplied>the</supplied> middle of <supplied>the</supplied> streets. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Yahweh’s Outstretched Hand</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>In all of this his anger has not turned back, </li1>
				<li2>and still his hand is stretched out. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 5:26">26</verse-number>And he will raise a signal for a nation<note>The Hebrew is plural, but the following verses refer to the nation as singular</note> from afar, </li1>
				<li1>and he will whistle for it from the end of the earth. </li1>
				<li1>And look! It comes quickly, swiftly! </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 5:27">27</verse-number>None <supplied>is</supplied> weary, </li1>
				<li2>and none among him stumbles; </li2>
				<li2>none slumbers and none sleeps. </li2>
				<li1>And no loincloth on his waist is opened, </li1>
				<li2>and no thong of his sandals is drawn away. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 5:28">28</verse-number>Whose arrows are sharp, </li1>
				<li2>and all of his bows are bent. </li2>
				<li1>The hoofs of his horses are reckoned like flint, </li1>
				<li2>and his wheels like the storm wind. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 5:29">29</verse-number>His roaring <supplied>is</supplied> like the lion, </li1>
				<li2>and he roars like young lions. </li2>
				<li1>And he growls and seizes his prey, </li1>
				<li2>and he carries <supplied>it</supplied> off, </li2>
				<li2>and not one can rescue <supplied>it</supplied>. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 5:30">30</verse-number>And he will roar over him on that day </li1>
				<li2>like <supplied>the</supplied> roaring of <supplied>the</supplied> sea, </li2>
				<li1>and <supplied>if</supplied> one looks to the land, look! Darkness! Distress! </li1>
				<li2>And <supplied>the</supplied> light grows dark with its<note>Presumably the land’s</note> clouds. </li2>
			</ul>
		</chapter>