<chapter id="Is 6">
			<pericope>Isaiah’s Commission</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 6:1">1</verse-number>In the year of the death of Uzziah the king, I saw the Lord sitting on a high and raised throne, and the hem of his robe <supplied>was</supplied> filling the temple. <verse-number id="Is 6:2">2</verse-number>Seraphs <supplied>were</supplied> standing above him. <idiom-start/>Each had six wings<idiom-end/>:<note>Literally “six wings six wings for one”</note> with two he covered his face, and with two he covered his feet, and with two he flew. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 6:3">3</verse-number>And the one called to the other and said, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Holy, holy, holy <supplied>is</supplied> Yahweh of hosts! </li1>
				<li2>The <idiom-start/>whole earth is full of his glory<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “fullness of all of the earth glory him”</note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 6:4">4</verse-number>And the pivots of the thresholds shook from the sound of those who called, and the house<note>Or “temple”</note> was filled <supplied>with</supplied> smoke. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 6:5">5</verse-number>And I said, “Woe to me! For I am destroyed!<note>Or “silenced”</note> For I <supplied>am</supplied> a man <idiom-start/>of unclean lips<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “unclean of lips”</note> and I <supplied>am</supplied> living among<note>With an emphatic sense: “in the very heart and midst of”</note> a people <idiom-start/>of unclean lips<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “unclean of lips”</note> for my eyes have seen the king, Yahweh of hosts!” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 6:6">6</verse-number>Then one of the seraphs flew to me, and in his hand <supplied>was</supplied> a hot coal he had taken from the altar with tongs. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 6:7">7</verse-number>And he touched my mouth, and he said, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Look! This has touched your lips </li1>
				<li2>and has removed your guilt, </li2>
				<li2>and your sin is annulled.” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 6:8">8</verse-number>Then I heard <supplied>the</supplied> voice of the Lord saying, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Whom shall I send? </li1>
				<li2>And who will go for us?” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p>And I said, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“I <supplied>am</supplied> here! </li1>
				<li2>Send me!” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 6:9">9</verse-number>And he said, “Go and say to this people, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>‘Keep on listening and do not comprehend! </li1>
				<li2>And keep on looking and do not understand!’ </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 6:10">10</verse-number>Make the heart of this people insensitive, </li1>
				<li2>and make its ears unresponsive, </li2>
				<li2>and shut its eyes </li2>
				<li1>so that it may not look with its eyes </li1>
				<li2>and listen with its ears </li2>
				<li2>and comprehend <supplied>with</supplied> its mind </li2>
				<li2>and turn back, and it may be healed <supplied>for</supplied> him.” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 6:11">11</verse-number>Then I said, “Until when, Lord?” </p>
			<p>And he said, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Until <supplied>the</supplied> cities lie wasted without inhabitant, </li1>
				<li2>and houses without people, </li2>
				<li2>and the land is ruined <supplied>and</supplied> a waste, </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 6:12">12</verse-number>and Yahweh sends the people far away, </li1>
				<li2>and the abandonment is great in the midst of the land. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 6:13">13</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>even if only a tenth part remain<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “still in her a tenth”</note> <idiom-start/>again she will be destroyed<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and she will again and she will be to burn”</note> </li1>
				<li2>like <supplied>a</supplied> terebinth or like <supplied>an</supplied> oak, </li2>
				<li2>which although felled, a tree stump <supplied>remains</supplied> in them. </li2>
				<li1><supplied>The</supplied> seed of holiness <supplied>will be</supplied> her tree stump.” </li1>
			</ul>
		</chapter>