<chapter id="Is 7">
			<pericope>The Sign to Ahaz</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 7:1">1</verse-number>This happened in the days of Ahaz, son of Jotham, son of Uzziah, king of Judah. Rezin, king of Aram, and Pekah, son of Remaliah, king of Israel, went<note>The Hebrew is singular</note> up <supplied>to</supplied> Jerusalem for warfare against it,<note>Literally “her”</note> but he was not able to fight against it.<note>Literally “her”</note> <verse-number id="Is 7:2">2</verse-number>When it was reported to the house of David, saying “Aram stands by Ephraim,” his heart and the heart of his people shook like the shaking of the trees of <supplied>the</supplied> forest because of <supplied>the</supplied> wind. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 7:3">3</verse-number>Then Yahweh said to Isaiah, “Go out to meet Ahaz, you and Shear-Jashub your son, at the end of the conduit of the upper pool on <supplied>the</supplied> highway of <supplied>the</supplied> washer’s field. <verse-number id="Is 7:4">4</verse-number>And you must say to him, ‘Take heed and be quiet! You must not fear, and your heart must not be faint because of these two stumps of smoldering firebrands, <idiom-start/>because of the fierce anger of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “because of the fierceness of the anger of”</note> Rezin and Aram and the son of Remaliah. <verse-number id="Is 7:5">5</verse-number>Because Aram has plotted evil against you <supplied>with</supplied> Ephraim and the son of Remaliah, saying, <verse-number id="Is 7:6">6</verse-number>“Let us go up against Judah and let us tear her apart, <idiom-start/>and let us lay it open and so bring it unto ourselves<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “and let us break through her to us”</note> and let us install the son of Tabeel <supplied>as</supplied> king in her midst.” <verse-number id="Is 7:7">7</verse-number>Thus says the Lord Yahweh, “It shall not stand, and it shall not come to pass. <verse-number id="Is 7:8">8</verse-number>For the head of Aram <supplied>is</supplied> Damascus, and the head of Damascus <supplied>is</supplied> Rezin, and in sixty-five years from now Ephraim will be too shattered to be a people. <verse-number id="Is 7:9">9</verse-number>And the head of Ephraim <supplied>is</supplied> Samaria, and the head of Samaria <supplied>is</supplied> the son of Remaliah. If you do not believe then you will not endure.” ’ ” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 7:10">10</verse-number>And Yahweh continued to speak to Ahaz, saying, <verse-number id="Is 7:11">11</verse-number>“Ask for a sign for yourself from Yahweh God; make <supplied>it</supplied> deep <supplied>as</supplied> Sheol or make <supplied>it</supplied> high as above.” <verse-number id="Is 7:12">12</verse-number>But Ahaz said, “I will not ask, and I will not put Yahweh to the test.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 7:13">13</verse-number>Then he said, “Hear, house of David! <supplied>Is it</supplied> too little for you to make men weary, that you should also make my God weary? <verse-number id="Is 7:14">14</verse-number>Therefore the Lord himself will give you<note>The Hebrew is plural</note> a sign. Look! the virgin<note>Or “young woman”</note> <supplied>is</supplied> with child and she is about to give birth <supplied>to</supplied> a son, and she shall call his name ‘God with us.’ <verse-number id="Is 7:15">15</verse-number>He shall eat curds and honey until he knows to reject the evil and to choose the good. <verse-number id="Is 7:16">16</verse-number>For before the boy knows to reject the evil and to choose the good, <idiom-start/>the land whose two kings you dread will be abandoned.<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the land which you dread will be abandoned because of the face of her two kings”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>That Day</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 7:17">17</verse-number>“Yahweh will bring on you and on your people and on the house of your ancestor<note>Or “father”</note> days that have not come since <supplied>the</supplied> day Ephraim departed from Judah: the king of Assyria.” <verse-number id="Is 7:18">18</verse-number>And this shall happen: On that day, Yahweh will whistle for the fly that <supplied>is</supplied> at the end of the stream of Egypt and the bee that <supplied>is</supplied> in the land of Assyria. <verse-number id="Is 7:19">19</verse-number>And all of them will come and settle in the rivers of the cliffs and in the clefts of the rocks and on all of the thornbushes and watering places. <verse-number id="Is 7:20">20</verse-number>On that day, the Lord will shave the head and the hair of the feet with a razor of the one hired from beyond <supplied>the</supplied> river—with the king of Assyria—and it will even take off the beard. <verse-number id="Is 7:21">21</verse-number>And this shall happen: on that day, a young man will keep a young cow of <supplied>the</supplied> herd and two sheep alive. <verse-number id="Is 7:22">22</verse-number>And this shall happen: because of the abundance of milk production, he will eat curds, for every one that is left in the midst of the land will eat curds and honey. <verse-number id="Is 7:23">23</verse-number>And this shall happen on that day: Every place where there are a thousand vines<note>Hebrew “vine”</note> for a thousand silver <supplied>pieces</supplied> will become briers,<note>Hebrew “brier”</note> and it will be thornbushes.<note>Hebrew “thornbush”</note> <verse-number id="Is 7:24">24</verse-number>One will go there with arrows and bow, for all of the land will be briers<note>Hebrew “brier”</note> and thornbushes.<note>Hebrew “thornbush”</note> <verse-number id="Is 7:25">25</verse-number>And <supplied>as for</supplied> all of the hills that they hoed with the hoe, you will not go there, <supplied>for</supplied> fear of briers<note>Hebrew “brier”</note> and thornbushes.<note>Hebrew “thornbush”</note> And it will become like pastureland <supplied>for</supplied> cattle and overtrodden land <supplied>for</supplied> sheep. </p>
		</chapter>