<chapter id="Is 8">
			<pericope>Signs of the Assyrian Invasion</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 8:1">1</verse-number>Then Yahweh said to me, “Take yourself a large tablet and write on it with a common stylus pen: Maher-Halal-Hash-Baz. <verse-number id="Is 8:2">2</verse-number>And I will require reliable witnesses as a witness for me: Uriah the priest and Zechariah son of Jeberekiah.” <verse-number id="Is 8:3">3</verse-number>And I approached the prophetess, and she conceived, and she gave birth to a son. And Yahweh said to me, “Call his name Maher-Halal-Hash-Baz. <verse-number id="Is 8:4">4</verse-number>For before the boy knows to call ‘my father’ and ‘my mother,’ <supplied>one</supplied> will carry away the wealth of Damascus and the spoil of Samaria in the presence of the king of Assyria.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Shiloah Waters and Euphrates Flood</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 8:5">5</verse-number>And Yahweh continued to speak to me again, saying, </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 8:6">6</verse-number>“Because this people has refused the gently flowing waters of Shiloah and rejoices <supplied>over</supplied> Rezin and the son of Remaliah, <verse-number id="Is 8:7">7</verse-number>therefore look! The Lord <supplied>is</supplied> bringing up the waters of the great and mighty river against them, the king of Assyria and all his glory. </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>And he will rise above all his channels, </li1>
				<li2>and he will flow over all his banks. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 8:8">8</verse-number>And he will sweep into Judah; </li1>
				<li2>he will overflow and he will flood up to <supplied>the</supplied> neck. </li2>
				<li1>He will reach, and <idiom-start/>he will spread his wings out over your entire land<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the outspreading of his wings will be the fullness of the breadth of your land”</note> God with us.” </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 8:9">9</verse-number>Be broken, <supplied>you</supplied> peoples, and be dismayed. </li1>
				<li2>And listen, all distant <supplied>parts of the</supplied> earth; </li2>
				<li1>gird yourselves and be dismayed; </li1>
				<li2>gird yourselves and be dismayed! </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 8:10">10</verse-number><idiom-start/>Make a plan<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “Plan counsel”</note> but it will be frustrated! </li1>
				<li2>Speak a word, but it will not stand, </li2>
				<li3>for God is with us! </li3>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Wait for Yahweh</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 8:11">11</verse-number>For Yahweh said this to me <idiom-start/>while his hand weighed heavily on me<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “with the strength of the hand”</note> </li1>
				<li2>and he <idiom-start/>warned me not to walk<idiom-end/><note>Literally “instructed me from walking”</note> in the way of this people, saying, </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 8:12">12</verse-number>“You must not call conspiracy everything that this people calls conspiracy, </li1>
				<li2>and you must not <idiom-start/>share its fear<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “fear its fear”</note> and you must not be in dread. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 8:13">13</verse-number>You shall regard Yahweh of hosts as holy, </li1>
				<li2>and he <supplied>is</supplied> your<note>The Hebrew is plural</note> fear, and he <supplied>is</supplied> your dread. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 8:14">14</verse-number>And he will become like a sanctuary and a stumbling-stone, </li1>
				<li2>and like a stumbling-rock for the two houses of Israel, </li2>
				<li2>like a trap and a snare for the inhabitants of Jerusalem. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 8:15">15</verse-number>And many shall stumble among them, </li1>
				<li2>and they shall fall and they shall be broken, </li2>
				<li2>and they shall be ensnared and they shall be caught.” </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 8:16">16</verse-number>Bind up <supplied>the</supplied> testimony; </li1>
				<li2>seal <supplied>the</supplied> teaching among my disciples. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 8:17">17</verse-number>And I will wait for Yahweh, </li1>
				<li2>who hides his face from the house of Jacob, </li2>
				<li1>and I will await him. </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 8:18">18</verse-number>Look! I and the children whom Yahweh has given to me <supplied>are</supplied> like signs and portents in Israel from Yahweh of hosts, the one who dwells on the mountain of Zion. <verse-number id="Is 8:19">19</verse-number>Now if they tell you, “Consult the ghosts and the spirits, those who chirp and those who mutter. Should not a people consult its gods, the dead on behalf of the living, <verse-number id="Is 8:20">20</verse-number>for teaching and for testimony?” <idiom-start/>surely they <supplied>who</supplied> speak like this have no dawn<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “if not, they say like this word that there is no dawn for him,” which could also mean “if not, let them say a word like this: that there is no dawn for him”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 8:21">21</verse-number>And it<note>That is, the nation</note> will pass through it<note>That is, the land</note> distressed and hungry, and this shall happen: when it is hungry, it will be enraged, and it will curse its king and its gods,<note>Or “God”</note> and it will face upwar <verse-number id="Is 8:22">22</verse-number>or look to <supplied>the</supplied> earth. But look! Distress and darkness, <supplied>the</supplied> gloom of affliction! And <supplied>it will be</supplied> thrust <supplied>into</supplied> darkness! </p>
		</chapter>