<chapter id="Is 9">
			<pericope>New Light: The Birth of a King</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 9:1">1</verse-number><note><cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 9:1–21">Isaiah 9:1–21 </cite>in the English Bible is 8:23–9:20 in the Hebrew Bible</note> <idiom-start/>But there will be no gloom for those who were in distress<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “Indeed there is no gloom for the one to whom there was anxiety for her”</note> </p>
			<p>In former times he<note>That is, Yahweh</note> treated <supplied>the</supplied> land of Zebulun and Naphtali with contempt, but in the future he will honor the way of the sea beyond the Jordan, Galilee <supplied>of</supplied> the nations. </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 9:2">2</verse-number>The people who walked in darkness have seen a great light; </li1>
				<li2>light has shined on those who lived in a land of darkness. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 9:3">3</verse-number>You have made the nation numerous; </li1>
				<li2>you have not<note>The written text (<i>Kethib</i>) is “not,” but the reading tradition (<i>Qere</i>) is “for it”</note> made the joy great. </li2>
				<li1>They rejoice in your presence as <supplied>with</supplied> joy at the harvest, </li1>
				<li2>as they rejoice when they divide plunder. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 9:4">4</verse-number>For you have shattered the yoke of its burden </li1>
				<li2>and the stick of its shoulder, </li2>
				<li2>the rod of its oppressor, on<note>Hebrew “like”; the Hebrew letters for “like” and “on” look alike</note> the day of Midian. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 9:5">5</verse-number>For every boot <idiom-start/>that marches and shakes the earth<idiom-end/><note>Literally “marching with shaking,” which might mean “marching <supplied>is</supplied> with shaking”</note> </li1>
				<li2>and garment rolled in blood </li2>
				<li1><idiom-start/>will<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and it will”</note> be for burning—fire fuel. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 9:6">6</verse-number>For a child has been born for us; </li1>
				<li2>a son has been given to us. </li2>
				<li1>And the dominion will be on his shoulder, </li1>
				<li2>and his name is called Wonderful Counselor, Mighty God, </li2>
				<li3>Everlasting Father, Prince of Peace. </li3>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 9:7">7</verse-number><idiom-start/>His dominion will grow continually, </li1>
				<li2>and to peace there will be no end<idiom-end/><note>Literally “There is no end to the increase of the dominion and to peace”</note> </li2>
				<li1>on<note>Or “for”</note> the throne of David and over<note>Or “for”</note> his kingdom, </li1>
				<li2>to establish it<note>That is, the kingdom</note> and sustain it </li2>
				<li1>with justice and righteousness </li1>
				<li2>now and forever. </li2>
				<li1>The zeal of Yahweh of hosts will do this. </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Yahweh’s Anger against Arrogance</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 9:8">8</verse-number>The Lord has sent out a word against Jacob, </li1>
				<li2>and it fell on Israel. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 9:9">9</verse-number>And all of the people knew it, </li1>
				<li2>Ephraim and the inhabitants of Samaria </li2>
				<li1>in pride and arrogance of heart, saying, </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 9:10">10</verse-number>“<supplied>The</supplied> bricks have fallen, but we will build <supplied>with</supplied> dressed stone. </li1>
				<li2><supplied>The</supplied> sycamore-fig trees were felled, but we will replace <supplied>them with</supplied> cedars.” </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 9:11">11</verse-number>So Yahweh strengthened <idiom-start/>the adversaries of Rezin<idiom-end/><note>Or “his adversaries” if a copyist added “of Rezin” in error</note> against him, </li1>
				<li2>and he provoked his enemies— </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 9:12">12</verse-number>Aram from <supplied>the</supplied> east </li1>
				<li2>and Philistines<note>Hebrew “Philistine”</note> from <supplied>the</supplied> west— </li2>
				<li1>and they devoured Israel with the whole mouth. </li1>
				<li1>He has not turned away his anger in all of this, </li1>
				<li2>and his hand is still stretched out. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 9:13">13</verse-number>And the people did not turn to the one who struck it,<note>That is, the people</note> </li1>
				<li2>and they did not seek Yahweh of hosts. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 9:14">14</verse-number>So Yahweh cut off head and tail from Israel, </li1>
				<li2>palm branch and reed <supplied>in</supplied> one day. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 9:15">15</verse-number>Elders<note>Hebrew “Elder”</note> and <idiom-start/>the respectable<idiom-end/><note>Literally “one lifted up of face”</note> <supplied>are</supplied> the head, </li1>
				<li2>and prophets<note>Hebrew “prophet”</note> who teach lies<note>Hebrew “lie”</note> <supplied>are</supplied> the tail. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 9:16">16</verse-number>And the leaders of this people were misleading <supplied>them</supplied>, </li1>
				<li2>and those who were led <supplied>were</supplied> confused. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 9:17">17</verse-number>Therefore the Lord did not rejoice over its young men, </li1>
				<li2>and he did not have compassion on its orphans and widows, </li2>
				<li1>for everyone <supplied>was</supplied> godless and an evildoer, </li1>
				<li2>and every mouth <supplied>was</supplied> speaking folly. </li2>
				<li1>In all of this his anger did not turn away, </li1>
				<li2>and still his hand <supplied>is</supplied> stretched out. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 9:18">18</verse-number>For wickedness burned like fire; </li1>
				<li2>it consumed brier and thorn. </li2>
				<li1>And it kindled the thickets of the forest, </li1>
				<li2>and they swirled upward <supplied>in</supplied> a column of smoke. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 9:19">19</verse-number>The land was burned through the wrath of Yahweh of hosts, </li1>
				<li2>and the people became like fire fuel. </li2>
				<li1><idiom-start/>People had no compassion toward each other<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “A man does not have compassion toward his brother”</note> </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 9:20">20</verse-number>They devoured on <supplied>the</supplied> right but <supplied>still</supplied> were hungry </li1>
				<li2>and devoured on <supplied>the</supplied> left but they were not satisfied. </li2>
				<li1>Each one devoured the flesh of his arm, </li1>
				<li2><verse-number id="Is 9:21">21</verse-number>Manasseh <supplied>devoured</supplied> Ephraim, and Ephraim Manasseh; </li2>
				<li3>together they <supplied>were</supplied> against Judah. </li3>
				<li1>In all of this his anger has not turned away, </li1>
				<li2>and still his hand <supplied>is</supplied> stretched out. </li2>
			</ul>
		</chapter>