<chapter id="Is 10">
			<pericope>Woes on the Wicked</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 10:1">1</verse-number>Ah! Those who decree decrees of evil, </li1>
				<li2>and writers who have written harm, </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 10:2">2</verse-number>to guide <supplied>the</supplied> needy away from legal claims,<note>Hebrew “claim”</note> </li1>
				<li2>and to rob the justice from the poor of my people, </li2>
				<li2>to make widows their spoil; </li2>
				<li1>and they plunder orphans. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 10:3">3</verse-number>And what will you do at <supplied>the</supplied> day of punishment, </li1>
				<li2>and at calamity? It comes from afar! </li2>
				<li1>To whom will you flee for help, </li1>
				<li2>and where will you leave your wealth, </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 10:4">4</verse-number><idiom-start/>save that they bow down under the prisoners </li1>
				<li2>and fall under the slain<idiom-end/>?<note>Literally “except he will bow down under a prisoner and under slain they will fall”; “under” could also mean “in the place of”</note> </li2>
				<li1>In all of this his anger has not turned away, </li1>
				<li2>and still his hand <supplied>is</supplied> stretched out. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Judgment on Assyria’s Arrogance</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 10:5">5</verse-number>Ah! Assyria, the rod of my anger, </li1>
				<li2>and a staff is in their hand: my wrath! </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 10:6">6</verse-number>I send him against a godless nation, </li1>
				<li2>and I command him against the people of my wrath, </li2>
				<li1>to capture spoil </li1>
				<li2>and to carry off plunder, </li2>
				<li1>and to make them<note>Hebrew “him”</note> a trampling place, </li1>
				<li2>like <supplied>the</supplied> clay of <supplied>the</supplied> streets. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 10:7">7</verse-number>But he does not think this,<note>Or “so”</note> </li1>
				<li2>and his heart does not plan this. </li2>
				<li1>For <supplied>it is</supplied> in his heart to destroy </li1>
				<li2>and to cut off not a few nations. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 10:8">8</verse-number>For he says, “<supplied>Are</supplied> not my commanders altogether kings? </li1>
				<li2><verse-number id="Is 10:9">9</verse-number><supplied>Is</supplied> not Calno like Carchemish? </li2>
				<li2><supplied>Is</supplied> not Hamath like Arpad? </li2>
				<li2><supplied>Is</supplied> not Samaria like Damascus? </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 10:10">10</verse-number>As my hand has reached to the kingdoms of the idols<note>Hebrew “idol”</note> </li1>
				<li2>—and their images were <idiom-start/>greater than those of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> Jerusalem and Samaria— </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 10:11">11</verse-number>shall I not do to Jerusalem and its idols </li1>
				<li2>what I have done to Samaria and her idols?” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 10:12">12</verse-number>And this shall happen: when the Lord has finished all his work against <idiom-start/>Mount Zion<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the mountain of Zion”</note> and Jerusalem, “I will punish the <idiom-start/>arrogance<idiom-end/><note>Literally “fruit of the greatness of the heart”</note> of the king of Assyria and <idiom-start/>his haughtiness<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “the pride of the height of his eyes”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 10:13">13</verse-number>For he says, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“I have done <supplied>it</supplied> by the strength of my hand </li1>
				<li2>and by my wisdom, for I have understanding, </li2>
				<li1>and I have removed <supplied>the</supplied> boundaries of peoples, </li1>
				<li2>and I have plundered their stores, </li2>
				<li2>and like a bull I have brought down <idiom-start/>the inhabitants<idiom-end/>.<note>Or, “those sitting,” that is, rulers sitting on thrones</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 10:14">14</verse-number>And my hand has found, like <supplied>a</supplied> nest, the wealth of the peoples, </li1>
				<li2>and like the gathering of forsaken eggs, I myself have gathered all the earth. </li2>
				<li3>And <supplied>there</supplied> was no fluttering wing or open mouth or chirp.” </li3>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 10:15">15</verse-number>Does the ax boast against the one who cuts with it, </li1>
				<li2>or the saw magnify itself against <supplied>the</supplied> one who moves it to and fro? </li2>
				<li1><idiom-start/>As if a rod should move the one who lifts it<idiom-end/>!<note>Literally “As a rod waving even the one who lifts it up”</note> </li1>
				<li2><idiom-start/>As if a staff should lift up that which is not wood<idiom-end/>!<note>Literally “As a staff lifting up not wood”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 10:16">16</verse-number>Therefore the Lord, Yahweh of hosts, will send leanness among his sturdy warriors, </li1>
				<li2>and a burning like <supplied>the</supplied> burning of fire will burn under his glory. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 10:17">17</verse-number>And the light of Israel will become like a fire, </li1>
				<li2>and his holy one like a flame, </li2>
				<li1>and it will burn and devour his thorns<note>Hebrew “thorn”</note> and briers<note>Hebrew “brier”</note> in one day. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 10:18">18</verse-number>And he will destroy the glory of his forest and orchard <idiom-start/>completely<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from soul and to body”</note> </li1>
				<li2>and it will be like the wasting away of one who is sick. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 10:19">19</verse-number>And the rest of the trees<note>Hebrew “tree”</note> of his forest will be a small number, </li1>
				<li2>and a boy can write them <supplied>down</supplied>. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Return of the Remnant</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 10:20">20</verse-number>And this shall happen: on that day, the remnant of Israel and the survivors<note>Hebrew “survivor”</note> of the house of Jacob will not continue to lean on <supplied>the</supplied> one who struck it </li1>
				<li2>but will lean on Yahweh, the holy one of Israel, in truth. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 10:21">21</verse-number>A remnant will return— </li1>
				<li2>the remnant of Jacob—to <supplied>the</supplied> mighty God. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 10:22">22</verse-number>For though your people Israel was like the sand of the sea, </li1>
				<li2><supplied>only</supplied> a remnant of it will return. </li2>
				<li1>Annihilation <supplied>is</supplied> determined, </li1>
				<li2>overflowing <supplied>with</supplied> righteousness. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 10:23">23</verse-number>For the Lord Yahweh of hosts <supplied>is</supplied> about to make a complete destruction </li1>
				<li2>and a determined end in the midst of all the earth. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 10:24">24</verse-number>Therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh of hosts: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“My people who live <supplied>in</supplied> Zion, </li1>
				<li2>you must not be afraid of Assyria. </li2>
				<li1>It beats you with the rod, </li1>
				<li2>and it lifts up its staff against you <idiom-start/>as the Egyptians did<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “in the way of Egypt”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 10:25">25</verse-number><supplied>My</supplied> indignation will come to an end <idiom-start/>in just a very little while<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “for still a little a trifle”</note> </li1>
				<li2>and my anger <supplied>will be</supplied> directed to their destruction.” </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 10:26">26</verse-number>And Yahweh of hosts is going to swing a whip against him, </li1>
				<li2>as when Midian was defeated at the rock of Oreb; </li2>
				<li1>and his staff <supplied>will be</supplied> over the sea, </li1>
				<li2>and he will lift him up <idiom-start/>as he did in Egypt<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “in the way of Egypt”</note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 10:27">27</verse-number>And this shall happen: on that day, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>he will remove his burden from your shoulder </li1>
				<li2>and his yoke from your neck, </li2>
				<li2><idiom-start/>and a yoke will be destroyed because of fat<idiom-end/>.<note>The meaning of this phrase is uncertain, leading to the conjecture that it belongs with the next verse and by a different word division could mean “he has gone up from Jeshimon”; alternatively, “fat” could be a metaphor for prosperity</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 10:28">28</verse-number>He has come to Aiath, </li1>
				<li2>he has passed through Migron; </li2>
				<li2>at Micmash he deposited his baggage. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 10:29">29</verse-number>They crossed over <supplied>the</supplied> pass; </li1>
				<li2>Geba <supplied>is</supplied> a place of overnight lodging for us. </li2>
				<li1>Ramah trembles; </li1>
				<li2>Gibeah of Saul has fled. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 10:30">30</verse-number>Daughter of Gallim, cry out <supplied>with</supplied> your voice; </li1>
				<li2>Laishah, listen! </li2>
				<li2><idiom-start/>Anathoth is poor<idiom-end/>.<note>Or with different vocalization, “Answer her, Anathoth!” which fits the parallelism better</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 10:31">31</verse-number>Madmenah flees! </li1>
				<li2>The inhabitants of Gebim bring themselves into safety! </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 10:32">32</verse-number><idiom-start/>This day<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Yet today”</note> <idiom-start/>taking a stand<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to stand”</note> at Nob, </li1>
				<li1>he will shake his fist <supplied>at</supplied> the mountain of the daughter<note>Following the reading tradition (<i>Qere</i>); the consonantal text has “house”</note> of Zion, </li1>
				<li2><supplied>at</supplied> the hill of Jerusalem. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 10:33">33</verse-number>Look! The Lord Yahweh of hosts is about to lop off <supplied>the</supplied> branches<note>Hebrew “branch”</note> with great power, </li1>
				<li2>and <idiom-start/>the towering trees<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the haughty of the height”</note> will be felled, </li2>
				<li2>and the <idiom-start/>tall trees<idiom-end/><note>Literally “height”</note> will be brought low. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 10:34">34</verse-number>And he will cut down the thickets of the forest with the axe, </li1>
				<li2>and Lebanon will fall by <supplied>the</supplied> mighty <supplied>one</supplied>. </li2>
			</ul>
		</chapter>