<chapter id="Is 11">
			<pericope>The Branch’s Righteous Reign</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 11:1">1</verse-number>And a shoot will come out from the stump of Jesse, </li1>
				<li2>and a branch from its roots will bear fruit. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 11:2">2</verse-number>And the spirit of Yahweh shall rest on him— </li1>
				<li2>a spirit of wisdom and understanding, </li2>
				<li2>a spirit of counsel and might, </li2>
				<li2>a spirit of knowledge and the fear of Yahweh. </li2>
				<li2><verse-number id="Is 11:3">3</verse-number>And his <idiom-start/>breath<idiom-end/><note>Hebrew “smelling,” perhaps metaphorically as “delight” as in <cite title="BibleLEB2: Am 5:14">Amos 5:14; </cite>perhaps this line was accidentally copied twice from the preceding line</note> <supplied>is</supplied> in the fear of Yahweh. </li2>
				<li1>And he shall judge not by his eyesight, </li1>
				<li2>and he shall rebuke not by <idiom-start/>what he hears with<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the rumors of”</note> his ears. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 11:4">4</verse-number>But he shall judge <supplied>the</supplied> poor with righteousness, </li1>
				<li2>and he shall decide for <supplied>the</supplied> needy of <supplied>the</supplied> earth with rectitude. </li2>
				<li1>And he shall strike <supplied>the</supplied> earth with the rod of his mouth, </li1>
				<li2>and he shall kill <supplied>the</supplied> wicked person with the breath of his lips. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 11:5">5</verse-number>And righteousness shall be the belt around his waist, </li1>
				<li2>and faithfulness the belt around his loins. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 11:6">6</verse-number>And a wolf shall <idiom-start/>stay<idiom-end/><note>Literally “dwell as an alien”</note> with a lamb, </li1>
				<li2>and a leopard shall lie down with a kid, </li2>
				<li1>and a calf and a lion and a fatling together </li1>
				<li2><idiom-start/>as a small boy leads<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and a small boy leading”</note> them. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 11:7">7</verse-number>And a cow and a bear shall graze; </li1>
				<li2>their young shall lie down together. </li2>
				<li2>And a lion shall eat straw like the cattle. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 11:8">8</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>an infant<idiom-end/><note>Literally “one nursing”</note> shall play over a serpent’s hole, </li1>
				<li2>and <idiom-start/>a toddler<idiom-end/><note>Literally “one who is weaned”</note> shall put his hand on a viper’s hole. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 11:9">9</verse-number>They will not injure and they will not destroy on all of my <idiom-start/>holy mountain<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “mountain of holiness”</note> </li1>
				<li2>for the earth will be full <supplied>of the</supplied> knowledge <supplied>of</supplied> Yahweh, </li2>
				<li3>as the waters cover the sea. </li3>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 11:10">10</verse-number>And this shall happen on that day: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><supplied>the</supplied> nations shall inquire of the root of Jesse, </li1>
				<li1>which shall be standing as a signal to <supplied>the</supplied> peoples, </li1>
				<li1>and his resting place shall be glorious. </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Regathered Remnant</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 11:11">11</verse-number>And this shall happen on that day: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>The Lord will again <supplied>extend</supplied> his hand a second <supplied>time</supplied> </li1>
				<li1>to acquire the remnant of his people that is left, </li1>
				<li1>from Assyria, Egypt, Pathros, Cush, Elam, Shinar, Hamath, and the coastlands of the sea, </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 11:12">12</verse-number>and he will raise a signal for the nations. </li1>
				<li1>And he will gather the outcasts of Israel, </li1>
				<li2>and he will gather the scattered ones of Judah together from the four <idiom-start/>corners<idiom-end/><note>Literally “wings”</note> of the earth. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 11:13">13</verse-number>And the jealousy of Ephraim shall depart, </li1>
				<li2>and the enemies of Judah shall be cut off. </li2>
				<li1>Ephraim shall not be jealous <supplied>of</supplied> Judah, </li1>
				<li2>and Judah shall not be an enemy <supplied>of</supplied> Ephraim. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 11:14">14</verse-number>But they shall <idiom-start/>swoop<idiom-end/><note>Literally “fly”</note> upon <supplied>the</supplied> Philistine shoulder,<note>That is, the hill country west of Judah</note> <idiom-start/>westward<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sea”</note> </li1>
				<li2>Together they shall plunder <supplied>the</supplied> sons of <supplied>the</supplied> east. </li2>
				<li1>Edom and Moab <idiom-start/>will be under their command<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the stretching of their hand”</note> </li1>
				<li2>and the sons of Ammon <supplied>will be</supplied> their subjugated people. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 11:15">15</verse-number>And Yahweh will divide<note>Or “utterly destroy”</note> the tongue<note>Probably the “gulf”</note> of the sea of Egypt,<note>That is, the Red Sea</note> </li1>
				<li2>and he will wave his hand over the river<note>That is, the Euphrates River</note> with his scorching wind; </li2>
				<li1>and he will strike it into seven streams, </li1>
				<li2>and he will <idiom-start/>make it passable by foot<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “cause to walk with the sandal”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 11:16">16</verse-number>So there shall be a highway from Assyria for the remnant of his people that remains, </li1>
				<li2>as there was for Israel <idiom-start/>when<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in <supplied>the</supplied> day”</note> it went up from the land of Egypt. </li2>
			</ul>
		</chapter>