<chapter id="Is 17">
			<pericope>Oracle of Judgment on Damascus</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 17:1">1</verse-number>An oracle of Damascus: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Look! Damascus <supplied>will</supplied> cease being a city </li1>
				<li2>and will become a heap of ruins. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 17:2">2</verse-number>The cities of Aroer will be deserted;<note>These words in Hebrew (and “flocks” in the next line) all begin with the same letter, Ayin</note> </li1>
				<li2>they will be for the flocks, </li2>
				<li3>and they will lie down and <idiom-start/>no one will frighten<idiom-end/><note>Literally “there is not one who frightens”</note> <supplied>them</supplied>. </li3>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 17:3">3</verse-number>And <supplied>the</supplied> fortified city will disappear from Ephraim, </li1>
				<li2>and <supplied>the</supplied> kingdom from Damascus; </li2>
				<li3>and the remnant of Aram will be like the glory of the children of Israel,” </li3>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> Yahweh of hosts. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 17:4">4</verse-number>“And this shall happen: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>On that day, the glory of Jacob will be brought low, </li1>
				<li2>and the fat of his flesh will become lean. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 17:5">5</verse-number>And it shall be as <idiom-start/>when a reaper gathers<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a gathering of a reaper of”</note> standing grain </li1>
				<li2>and he reaps grain <supplied>with</supplied> his arm, </li2>
				<li1>and it shall be like one who gathers ears of grain </li1>
				<li2>in the valley of Rephaim. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 17:6">6</verse-number>And gleanings will be left over in it, as <idiom-start/>when an olive tree is beaten<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “beating of an olive tree”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>two <supplied>or</supplied> three ripe olive berries in <supplied>the</supplied> top of a branch, </li1>
				<li2>four <supplied>or</supplied> five on its fruitful branches,” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> Yahweh, the God of Israel. </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 17:7">7</verse-number>On that day, mankind will look to its maker, </li1>
				<li2>and its eyes will look to the holy one of Israel; </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 17:8">8</verse-number>it will not look to the altars, </li1>
				<li2>the work of its hands, </li2>
				<li1>and it will not see what its fingers made </li1>
				<li2>and the poles of Asherah worship and the incense altars. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 17:9">9</verse-number>On that day, <idiom-start/>its fortified cities<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the cities of his fortress”</note> will be like the <idiom-start/>abandonment of the wooded place and the summit<idiom-end/>,<note>Perhaps this difficult phrase originally read “abandonment of the wooded heights of the Amorites”</note> which they deserted because of the children of Israel; and there will be desolation. </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 17:10">10</verse-number>For you have forgotten the God of your salvation, </li1>
				<li2>and you have not remembered the rock of your refuge; </li2>
				<li1>therefore you plant plants of pleasantness, </li1>
				<li2>and you <idiom-start/>plant<idiom-end/><note>Literally “plant it”</note> a vine of a foreigner. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 17:11">11</verse-number>On your planting day you make <supplied>them</supplied> grow, </li1>
				<li2>and in the morning <supplied>of</supplied> your sowing you bring <supplied>them</supplied> into bloom, </li2>
				<li1><supplied>yet</supplied> the harvest will flee<note>Reading the same consonants as a verb, <i>nad</i>, rather than the noun <i>ned,</i> which would mean “a heap <supplied>of</supplied><supplied>the</supplied> harvest”</note> in a day <supplied>of</supplied> sickness and incurable pain. </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Roar of the Peoples</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 17:12">12</verse-number>Ah! <supplied>The</supplied> noise of many peoples, they make a noise like <supplied>the</supplied> noise of <supplied>the</supplied> seas! </li1>
				<li2>And <supplied>the</supplied> roar of nations, they roar like <supplied>the</supplied> roar of mighty waters! </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 17:13">13</verse-number><supplied>The</supplied> nations roar like <supplied>the</supplied> roar of many waters, </li1>
				<li2>but he will rebuke him, and he will flee far away. </li2>
				<li1>And they are chased like chaff of <supplied>the</supplied> mountains before <supplied>the</supplied> wind </li1>
				<li2>and like tumbleweed before <supplied>the</supplied> storm. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 17:14">14</verse-number>At <supplied>the</supplied> time of evening, and look, terror! </li1>
				<li2>Before morning he is no more. </li2>
				<li1>This <supplied>is</supplied> the fate of those who plunder us </li1>
				<li2>and <supplied>the</supplied> lot of those who plunder us. </li2>
			</ul>
		</chapter>