<chapter id="Is 19">
			<pericope>Oracle of Judgment on Egypt</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 19:1">1</verse-number>An oracle of Egypt: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>Look! Yahweh <supplied>is</supplied> riding on a swift cloud </li1>
				<li2>and <supplied>is</supplied> coming <supplied>to</supplied> Egypt. </li2>
				<li1>And the idols of Egypt will tremble in front of him, </li1>
				<li2>and the heart of Egypt melts in his inner parts. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 19:2">2</verse-number>“And I will stir up <idiom-start/>Egyptians<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Egypt”</note> against <idiom-start/>Egyptians<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “Egypt”</note> </li1>
				<li2>and each one will fight against his brother </li2>
				<li1>and each one against his neighbor, </li1>
				<li2>city against city, kingdom against kingdom. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 19:3">3</verse-number>And the spirit of <idiom-start/>the Egyptians<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Egypt”</note> will be disturbed in his midst, </li1>
				<li2>and I will <idiom-start/>confuse<idiom-end/><note>Literally “engulf”</note> his plans,<note>Hebrew “plan”</note> </li2>
				<li1>and they will consult the idols and the spirits of the dead, </li1>
				<li2>and the ghosts and the spiritists. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 19:4">4</verse-number>And I will hand over <idiom-start/>the Egyptians<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Egypt”</note> into <supplied>the</supplied> hand of a hard master, </li1>
				<li2>and a powerful king will rule over them,” </li2>
				<li1><idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> the Lord Yahweh of hosts. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 19:5">5</verse-number>And <supplied>the</supplied> waters will be dried up from the sea, </li1>
				<li2>and <supplied>the</supplied> river will be parched and dry. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 19:6">6</verse-number>And <supplied>the</supplied> rivers will become foul-smelling; </li1>
				<li2>the branches of the Nile of Egypt will become little and dry up; </li2>
				<li2>reed and rush will wither. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 19:7">7</verse-number>Bare places by <supplied>the</supplied> Nile will be dried up, </li1>
				<li2>by the edge of <supplied>the</supplied> Nile and all the sown land of <supplied>the</supplied> Nile; </li2>
				<li2>it will be driven about, and <idiom-start/>it will be no more<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “there is none of it”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 19:8">8</verse-number>And the fishers will mourn, </li1>
				<li2>and all of those who cast fishhooks<note>Hebrew “fishhook”</note> in the Nile will lament, </li2>
				<li2>and those who spread out fishing nets<note>Hebrew “net”</note> on <supplied>the</supplied> <idiom-start/>surface<idiom-end/><note>Literally “face”</note> of <supplied>the</supplied> water will languish. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 19:9">9</verse-number>And <supplied>the</supplied> workers of combed flax will be ashamed, </li1>
				<li2>and those who weave white linen. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 19:10">10</verse-number>And her weavers will be crushed; </li1>
				<li2>all <supplied>the</supplied> <idiom-start/>hired workers<idiom-end/><note>Literally “workers of wage”</note> <supplied>will be</supplied> grieved of heart. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 19:11">11</verse-number>Surely the princes of Zoan <supplied>are</supplied> foolish; </li1>
				<li2>the wise of the counselors of Pharaoh <supplied>give</supplied> senseless counsel. </li2>
				<li1>How can you say to Pharaoh, </li1>
				<li2>“I myself <supplied>am</supplied> a son of sages, </li2>
				<li2>a <idiom-start/>descendant<idiom-end/><note>Literally “son”</note> of ancient kings”? </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 19:12">12</verse-number>Where <supplied>are</supplied> your sages then? </li1>
				<li2>Now, let them tell you, </li2>
				<li2>and let them know what Yahweh of hosts has planned against Egypt. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 19:13">13</verse-number>The princes of Zoan have become foolish; </li1>
				<li2>the princes of Memphis are deceived; </li2>
				<li2>the leaders of her tribes have led Egypt astray. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 19:14">14</verse-number>Yahweh has mixed a spirit of confusion into her midst, </li1>
				<li2>and they have caused Egypt to stagger in all of its doings, </li2>
				<li3>as <idiom-start/>when a drunkard staggers<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the staggering of a drunkard”</note> in his vomit. </li3>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 19:15">15</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>there will be nothing for Egypt to do<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “not it will be for Egypt a deed which he can do”</note> </li1>
				<li2>head or tail, palm branch or reed. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Future Blessing of Egypt, Assyria, and Egypt</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 19:16">16</verse-number>On that day, Egypt will be like women, and will tremble and be afraid before the waving hand of Yahweh of hosts that he <supplied>is</supplied> waving against it. <verse-number id="Is 19:17">17</verse-number>And the land of Judah will become a terror to Egypt, everyone <supplied>to</supplied> whom one mentions it will be afraid in himself because of the plan of Yahweh of hosts that he <supplied>is</supplied> planning against him. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 19:18">18</verse-number>On that day, there will be five cities in the land of Egypt that speak the <idiom-start/>language<idiom-end/><note>Literally “lip”</note> of Canaan and swear an oath to Yahweh of hosts. One will be called “City of the Sun.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 19:19">19</verse-number>On that day, there will be an altar for Yahweh <supplied>in</supplied> in the middle of the land of Egypt, and a stone pillar for Yahweh at her border. <verse-number id="Is 19:20">20</verse-number>And it will be a sign and a witness to Yahweh of hosts in the land of Egypt; when they cry out to Yahweh because of oppressors, he will send them a savior and a <idiom-start/>defender<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “contender”</note> and he will deliver them. <verse-number id="Is 19:21">21</verse-number>And Yahweh will make himself known to Egypt, and Egypt will know Yahweh on that day, and they will worship <supplied>with</supplied> sacrifice and offering, and they will make vows<note>Hebrew “vow”</note> to Yahweh, and they will fulfill <supplied>them</supplied>. <verse-number id="Is 19:22">22</verse-number>And Yahweh will strike Egypt, striking and healing; and they will return to Yahweh, and he will respond to their prayer, and he will heal them. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 19:23">23</verse-number>On that day, there will be a highway from Egypt to Assyria, and Assyria will come into Egypt, and Egypt into Assyria, and Egypt will worship together with Assyria. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 19:24">24</verse-number>On that day, Israel will be <supplied>the</supplied> third with Egypt and Assyria, a blessing in the midst of the earth, <verse-number id="Is 19:25">25</verse-number>whom Yahweh of hosts blessed, saying, “May Egypt my people be blessed, and Assyria, the work of my hands, and my inheritance, Israel.” </p>
		</chapter>