<chapter id="Is 27">
			<pericope>Israel Rescued</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 27:1">1</verse-number>On that day, Yahweh will punish with his cruel, great and strong sword Leviathan, <supplied>the</supplied> fleeing serpent, and Leviathan, <supplied>the</supplied> twisting serpent, and he will kill the sea monster that <supplied>is</supplied> in the sea. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 27:2">2</verse-number>On that day: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“A vineyard of beauty! Sing in praise of it! </li1>
				<li2><verse-number id="Is 27:3">3</verse-number>I, Yahweh, <supplied>am</supplied> her keeper; </li2>
				<li2>I water it <idiom-start/>again and again<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “by moments”</note> </li2>
				<li1>Lest one afflict <supplied>harm</supplied> on it, </li1>
				<li2>I guard it night and day; </li2>
				<li2><verse-number id="Is 27:4">4</verse-number><idiom-start/>I have no wrath<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “There is no wrath for me”</note> </li2>
				<li1>Whatever gives me thorns <supplied>and</supplied> briers, </li1>
				<li2>I will step forth against in battle. </li2>
				<li2>I will set it on fire altogether. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 27:5">5</verse-number>Or let it grasp at my protection; </li1>
				<li2>let it make peace with me; </li2>
				<li2>peace let it make with me.” </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 27:6">6</verse-number><idiom-start/>Days are coming<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “The coming ones”</note> let Jacob take root; </li1>
				<li2>Israel will blossom and send out shoots, </li2>
				<li2>and they will fill <supplied>the</supplied> face of <supplied>the</supplied> world <supplied>with</supplied> fruit. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 27:7">7</verse-number>Does he strike him <idiom-start/>as he struck down those who struck him<idiom-end/>?<note>Literally “like the striking of one striking him”</note> </li1>
				<li2>Or is he killed <idiom-start/>as those who killed him were killed<idiom-end/>?<note>Literally “like the killing of his killed ones”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 27:8">8</verse-number>By expelling<note>Meaning uncertain, derived from the following parallel expression</note> her, by her sending away, you argue with her. </li1>
				<li2>He removed <supplied>them</supplied> with his strong wind, </li2>
				<li2>in <supplied>the</supplied> day of <supplied>the</supplied> east wind. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 27:9">9</verse-number>Therefore by this he will make atonement <supplied>for</supplied> the guilt of Jacob, </li1>
				<li2>and this <supplied>will be</supplied> all of <supplied>the</supplied> fruit <supplied>of</supplied> the removal of his sin: </li2>
				<li1><idiom-start/>when he makes<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in his setting”</note> all <supplied>the</supplied> stones of <supplied>the</supplied> altar like crushed stones of chalk, </li1>
				<li2>no poles of Asherah worship or incense altars will stand. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 27:10">10</verse-number>For <supplied>the</supplied> fortified city <supplied>is</supplied> solitary, </li1>
				<li2>a settlement deserted and forsaken, like the wilderness; </li2>
				<li1><supplied>the</supplied> calf grazes there, </li1>
				<li2>lies down there and destroys its branches. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 27:11">11</verse-number><idiom-start/>When its branches are dry<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “In her branch being dry”</note> they are broken; </li1>
				<li1>women <supplied>are</supplied> coming <supplied>and</supplied> setting light to it. </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p>For it <supplied>is</supplied> not a people of understanding; </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>therefore his maker will not have compassion on him, </li1>
				<li2>and his creator will not show him favor. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 27:12">12</verse-number>And this shall happen: </p>
			<p>on that day, Yahweh will thresh from the floodwaters of the Euphrates to the wadi<note>A seasonal stream that is often dry</note> of Egypt, and <supplied>as for</supplied> you, you will be gathered one by one, sons of Israel. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 27:13">13</verse-number>And this shall happen: </p>
			<p>on that day, a great trumpet will be blown, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>and those who were lost in the land of Assyria will come, </li1>
				<li2>and those who were scattered in the land of Egypt, </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p>and they will bow down to Yahweh on the <idiom-start/>holy mountain<idiom-end/><note>Literally “mountain of holiness”</note> at Jerusalem. </p>
		</chapter>