<chapter id="Is 29">
			<pericope>Woe to Jerusalem</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 29:1">1</verse-number>Ah! Ariel, Ariel, <supplied>the</supplied> city <supplied>where</supplied> David encamped! </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>Add year to year, </li1>
				<li2>let festivals recur. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 29:2">2</verse-number>Yet<note>Or “And”</note> I will inflict Ariel, </li1>
				<li2>and there shall be mourning and lamentation, </li2>
				<li2>and it shall be to me like an altar hearth.<note>Hebrew “Ariel,” which might mean “altar hearth”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 29:3">3</verse-number>And I will encamp <idiom-start/>in a circle<idiom-end/><note>The Hebrew text literally reads “like the ball”; the LXX supports an emendation to “David”</note> against you, </li1>
				<li2>and I will lay siege to you <supplied>with</supplied> towers<note>Hebrew “tower”</note> </li2>
				<li2>and I will raise up siegeworks against you. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 29:4">4</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> you shall be low; </li1>
				<li2>you shall speak from <supplied>the</supplied> earth, </li2>
				<li2>and your words<note>Hebrew “word”</note> will be low, from dust. </li2>
				<li1>And your voice will be from <supplied>the</supplied> earth, like a ghost, </li1>
				<li2>and your word will whisper from <supplied>the</supplied> dust. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 29:5">5</verse-number>But<note>Or “And”</note> the multitude of your strangers shall be like fine dust, </li1>
				<li2>and <supplied>the</supplied> multitude of tyrants like chaff that passes by. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p>And it will happen <supplied>in</supplied> an instant, suddenly. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 29:6">6</verse-number>You will be punished by Yahweh of hosts </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>with thunder and earthquake and great sound, </li1>
				<li2>storm wind and tempest and <supplied>the</supplied> flame of a devouring fire. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 29:7">7</verse-number>And the multitude of all the nations who fight against Ariel, </li1>
				<li2>all those who fight <supplied>against</supplied> her and her stronghold, </li2>
				<li3>and those who inflict her shall be like <supplied>a</supplied> dream, a vision of <supplied>the</supplied> night. </li3>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 29:8">8</verse-number>And it shall be as when the hungry person dreams—look, <supplied>he is</supplied> eating! </li1>
				<li2>And he wakes up and his inner self <supplied>is</supplied> empty. </li2>
				<li1>Or<note>Or “And”</note> as when the thirsty person dreams—look, <supplied>he is</supplied> drinking! </li1>
				<li2>And he wakes up and look, <supplied>he is</supplied> faint, </li2>
				<li2>and his inner self <supplied>is</supplied> longing for water. </li2>
				<li1>So shall be the multitude of all the nations who fight against Mount Zion. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 29:9">9</verse-number>Be astonished and be amazed! </li1>
				<li2>Blind yourselves and be blinded! </li2>
				<li1>They are drunk but<note>Or “and”</note> not <supplied>from</supplied> wine; </li1>
				<li2>they stagger but<note>Or “and”</note> not <supplied>from</supplied> strong drink. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 29:10">10</verse-number>For Yahweh has poured out upon you a spirit of deep sleep, </li1>
				<li2>and he has shut your eyes, the prophets, </li2>
				<li2>and he has covered your heads, the seers. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 29:11">11</verse-number>And the vision of all this has become for you like <supplied>the</supplied> words of <supplied>a</supplied> sealed document. When they give it to one who knows the<note>The reading tradition (<i>Qere</i>) has “a” instead of “the”</note> document, saying, “<idiom-start/>Read<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Call”</note> this now!” He says, “I am not able, for it <supplied>is</supplied> sealed.” <verse-number id="Is 29:12">12</verse-number>And <supplied>if</supplied> the document is given to <supplied>one</supplied> who does not <idiom-start/>know how to read<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “know a document”</note> saying, “<idiom-start/>Read<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Call”</note> this now!” he says, “I do not <idiom-start/>know how to read<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “know a document”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 29:13">13</verse-number>And the Lord said, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Because this people draw near with its mouth, </li1>
				<li2>and with its lips it honors me, </li2>
				<li1>and its heart is far from me, </li1>
				<li2>and their fear of me is a commandment of men that has been taught, </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 29:14">14</verse-number>therefore look, I am again doing something spectacular </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>and a spectacle with this spectacular people. </li1>
				<li1>And the wisdom of its wise men shall perish, </li1>
				<li2>and the discernment of its discerning ones shall keep itself hidden.” </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 29:15">15</verse-number>Ah! Those who make a plan deep, to hide <supplied>it</supplied> from Yahweh, </li1>
				<li2>and their deeds are<note>The Hebrew is singular</note> in a dark place. </li2>
				<li1>And they say, “Who sees us? </li1>
				<li2>And who knows us?” </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 29:16">16</verse-number>Your perversity! </li1>
				<li2>As if <idiom-start/>a potter<idiom-end/><note>Literally “of the one who creates”</note> shall be regarded as <supplied>the</supplied> clay! </li2>
				<li1>That <supplied>the</supplied> product of its maker <supplied>says</supplied>, </li1>
				<li2>“He did not make me,” </li2>
				<li1>and <supplied>the</supplied> thing made into shape says of its <idiom-start/>potter<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “one who creates”</note> </li1>
				<li2>“He has no understanding.” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Blessing after Punishment</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 29:17">17</verse-number><idiom-start/>In a very little while<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Not still a trifling <supplied>of time</supplied>”</note> shall not Lebanon change into <supplied>a</supplied> fruitful land, </li1>
				<li2>and the fruitful land be regarded as <supplied>a</supplied> forest? </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 29:18">18</verse-number>And on that day, the deaf shall hear <supplied>the</supplied> words of a scroll, </li1>
				<li2>and <supplied>the</supplied> eyes of <supplied>the</supplied> blind shall see out of gloom and darkness. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 29:19">19</verse-number>And <supplied>the</supplied> meek <idiom-start/>have joy after joy<idiom-end/><note>Literally “shall add joy”</note> in Yahweh, </li1>
				<li2>and <supplied>the</supplied> needy of <supplied>the</supplied> people shall rejoice in the holy one of Israel. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 29:20">20</verse-number>For <supplied>the</supplied> tyrant shall be no more, </li1>
				<li2>and <supplied>the</supplied> scoffer shall come to an end. </li2>
				<li1>And all those lying in wait for evil shall be cut off; </li1>
				<li2><verse-number id="Is 29:21">21</verse-number>those who mislead a person into sin with a word </li2>
				<li1>and set a trap for the <idiom-start/>arbitrator<idiom-end/><note>Literally “one who argues”</note> in the gate </li1>
				<li2>and guide away <supplied>the</supplied> righteous by emptiness. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 29:22">22</verse-number>Therefore Yahweh, who redeemed Abraham, says this to the house of Jacob: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Jacob will no longer be ashamed, </li1>
				<li2>and his face will no longer grow pale. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 29:23">23</verse-number>For when he sees his children, </li1>
				<li2>the work of my hands, in his midst, </li2>
				<li1>they will treat my name as holy, </li1>
				<li2>and they will treat the holy one of Jacob as holy, </li2>
				<li2>and they will stand in awe <supplied>of</supplied> the God of Israel. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 29:24">24</verse-number>And those who err <supplied>in</supplied> spirit will <idiom-start/>acquire<idiom-end/><note>Literally “know”</note> understanding, </li1>
				<li2>and those who grumble will learn instruction. </li2>
			</ul>
		</chapter>