<chapter id="Is 30">
			<pericope>Warning against Alliance with Egypt</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 30:1">1</verse-number>“Oh rebellious children!” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> Yahweh, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“to make a plan, but<note>Or “and”</note> not from me, </li1>
				<li2>and pour out a libation, but<note>Or “and”</note> not <supplied>from</supplied> my Spirit, </li2>
				<li2><idiom-start/>so as to add<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for the sake of adding”</note> sin to sin. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 30:2">2</verse-number>Who go to go down <supplied>to</supplied> Egypt, </li1>
				<li2>but<note>Or “and”</note> they do not ask <supplied>of</supplied> my mouth, </li2>
				<li1>to take refuge in the protection of Pharaoh </li1>
				<li2>and to take refuge in the shadow of Egypt. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 30:3">3</verse-number>And the protection of Pharaoh shall be shame to you, </li1>
				<li2>and the refuge in the shadow of Egypt, humiliation. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 30:4">4</verse-number>For his officials are at Zoan, </li1>
				<li2>and his envoys reach to Hanes. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 30:5">5</verse-number>Everyone will start to stink because of a people <supplied>that</supplied> cannot profit them, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>not for help and not for profiting, </li1>
				<li2>but for shame and also for disgrace.” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Oracle regarding the Negev</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 30:6">6</verse-number>An oracle of the animals of the Negev: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>Through a land of trouble and distress, </li1>
				<li2><supplied>of</supplied> lioness and lion, </li2>
				<li2><idiom-start/>among<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> them <supplied>are</supplied> snake and flying serpent; </li2>
				<li1>they carry their wealth on <supplied>the</supplied> <idiom-start/>backs<idiom-end/><note>Literally “shoulder”</note> of male donkeys </li1>
				<li2>and their treasures on <supplied>the</supplied> humps<note>Hebrew “hump”</note> of camels, </li2>
				<li2>to a people <supplied>that</supplied> cannot profit <supplied>them</supplied>. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 30:7">7</verse-number>For<note>Or “And”</note> <idiom-start/>Egyptians<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Egypt”</note> help <supplied>with</supplied> vanity and emptiness, </li1>
				<li2>therefore I have called this one “Rahab, they <supplied>are</supplied> sitting.” </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 30:8">8</verse-number>Now go, write it on a tablet with them, </li1>
				<li2>and inscribe it on a scroll, </li2>
				<li1><idiom-start/>that<idiom-end/><note>Or “and”</note> it may be <idiom-start/>for the time to come<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “for last day”</note> </li1>
				<li2>forever, forever. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 30:9">9</verse-number>For it <supplied>is</supplied> a people of rebellion, deceitful children, </li1>
				<li2>children <supplied>who are</supplied> not willing to hear the instruction of Yahweh, </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 30:10">10</verse-number>who say to those who do see, “You must not see!” </li1>
				<li2>and to the seers, “You must not see truth for us; </li2>
				<li1>speak smooth things to us, </li1>
				<li2>see illusions, </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 30:11">11</verse-number>turn aside from <supplied>the</supplied> way, turn aside from <supplied>the</supplied> path, </li1>
				<li2>put an end to the holy one of Israel from our face.” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 30:12">12</verse-number>Therefore the holy one of Israel says this: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Because you <supplied>are</supplied> rejecting this word </li1>
				<li2>and you trust in oppression and <idiom-start/>cunning<idiom-end/><note>Literally “going wrong”</note> </li2>
				<li2>and you rely on it, </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 30:13">13</verse-number>therefore this iniquity shall come for you like a breach about to fall, </li1>
				<li2>bulging out on a high wall <idiom-start/>that breaks<idiom-end/><note>Literally “whose breaking comes”</note> suddenly, <supplied>in</supplied> an instant. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 30:14">14</verse-number>And he breaks it like a vessel of <idiom-start/>a potter<idiom-end/><note>Literally “someone who forms”</note> breaks, </li1>
				<li2><supplied>that</supplied> is crushed; he has no compassion, </li2>
				<li1>and no potsherd is found among its fragments<note>Hebrew “fragment”</note> <idiom-start/>to take fire<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for the taking away of fire”</note> from <supplied>the</supplied> hearth, </li1>
				<li2>or <idiom-start/>to skim<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for the skimming off of”</note> water from <supplied>the</supplied> cistern.” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 30:15">15</verse-number>For the Lord Yahweh, the holy one of Israel, said this: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“In returning and rest you shall be saved; </li1>
				<li2>your strength shall be in quietness and in trust.” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p>But<note>Or “And”</note> you were not willing, <verse-number id="Is 30:16">16</verse-number>and you said, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“No! For we will flee on horses!”<note>Hebrew “horse”</note> Therefore you shall flee! </li1>
				<li2>And, “We will ride on swift horses!”<note>Hebrew “horse”</note> Therefore your pursuers shall be swift! </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 30:17">17</verse-number>One thousand <idiom-start/>because of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from <supplied>the</supplied> face of”</note> a threat of one, </li1>
				<li2><idiom-start/>because<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from <supplied>the</supplied> face”</note> of a threat of five you shall flee, </li2>
				<li1>until you are left like <supplied>a</supplied> flagstaff on <idiom-start/>top<idiom-end/><note>Literally “head”</note> of <supplied>a</supplied> mountain, </li1>
				<li2>and like <supplied>a</supplied> signal on <supplied>a</supplied> hill. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Yahweh Will Show Mercy</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 30:18">18</verse-number>Therefore Yahweh waits to be gracious <supplied>to</supplied> you, </li1>
				<li2>and therefore he will rise up to show you mercy, </li2>
				<li1>for Yahweh <supplied>is</supplied> a God of justice; </li1>
				<li2>blessed <supplied>are</supplied> all those who wait for him. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 30:19">19</verse-number>For people will live in Zion; </li1>
				<li2>in Jerusalem, you will surely not weep. </li2>
				<li1>Surely he will be gracious to you; </li1>
				<li2>when he hears the sound of your cry, he will answer you. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 30:20">20</verse-number>And the Lord will give you <supplied>the</supplied> bread <supplied>of</supplied> distress </li1>
				<li2>and <supplied>the</supplied> water <supplied>of</supplied> oppression, </li2>
				<li1>but<note>Or “and”</note> your teachers will not hide themselves<note>Hebrew “himself”</note> any longer. </li1>
				<li2>And your eyes <idiom-start/>shall see<idiom-end/><note>Literally “be seeing”</note> your teachers. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 30:21">21</verse-number>And your ears shall hear a word from behind you, saying, </li1>
				<li2>“this <supplied>is</supplied> the way; walk in it,” </li2>
				<li1>when you go to your right </li1>
				<li2>and when you go to your left. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 30:22">22</verse-number>And you will defile the plating of your silver idols </li1>
				<li2>and the covering of your gold image. </li2>
				<li1>You will scatter them like contaminated things;<note>Hebrew “contaminated thing”</note> </li1>
				<li2>you will say to it, “Filth!”<note>Or “Get out!”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 30:23">23</verse-number>And he will give rain for your seed <supplied>with</supplied> which you sow the ground, </li1>
				<li2>and grain, the produce of the ground, and it will be rich and <idiom-start/>fertile<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “fat”</note> </li2>
				<li1>On that day, your cattle will graze <supplied>in</supplied> broad pastures;<note>Hebrew “pasture”</note> </li1>
				<li2><verse-number id="Is 30:24">24</verse-number>and the oxen and the donkeys that till<note>Or “tilling”</note> the ground will eat fodder, sorrel </li2>
				<li3>that <supplied>has</supplied> been winnowed with shovel and pitchfork. </li3>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 30:25">25</verse-number>And there will be streams on every high mountain and elevated hill, </li1>
				<li2>watercourses of water, on a day of great slaughter, when towers fall. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 30:26">26</verse-number>And the light of the full moon will be like the light of the sun, </li1>
				<li2>and the light of the sun will be sevenfold, like the light of seven days, </li2>
				<li1>on <supplied>the</supplied> day <supplied>when</supplied> Yahweh binds up the breakage of his people, </li1>
				<li2>and he heals the wound of his blow. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Judgment against Assyria</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 30:27">27</verse-number>Look! The name of Yahweh comes from afar, </li1>
				<li2>burning <supplied>with</supplied> his anger and heaviness of cloud. </li2>
				<li1>His lips are full <supplied>of</supplied> indignation, </li1>
				<li2>and his tongue <supplied>is</supplied> like a devouring fire. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 30:28">28</verse-number>And his breath <supplied>is</supplied> like an overflowing river; </li1>
				<li2>it reaches up to <supplied>the</supplied> neck </li2>
				<li1>to shake <supplied>the</supplied> nations with <supplied>the</supplied> sieve of worthlessness; </li1>
				<li2>and a bridle that leads astray <supplied>is</supplied> on <supplied>the</supplied> jawbones of <supplied>the</supplied> peoples. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 30:29">29</verse-number><idiom-start/>You shall have a song<idiom-end/><note>Literally “There shall be a song for you”</note> as <supplied>in</supplied> <supplied>the</supplied> night when a holy festival is kept, </li1>
				<li2>and a gladness of heart like one who goes with the flute, </li2>
				<li3>to go to the mountain of Yahweh, to the rock of Israel. </li3>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 30:30">30</verse-number>And Yahweh will cause the majesty of his voice to be heard, </li1>
				<li2>and he will cause the descent of his arm to be seen, </li2>
				<li1>in furious anger and a flame of devouring fire, </li1>
				<li2><supplied>with</supplied> a cloudburst and a rainstorm and stones<note>Hebrew “stone”</note> of hail. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 30:31">31</verse-number>Indeed, Assyria will be shattered by the voice of Yahweh; </li1>
				<li2>he strikes with the rod. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 30:32">32</verse-number>And every stroke of <supplied>the</supplied> staff of foundation<note>Some translations emend this to “discipline”</note> that Yahweh lays will be on it with timbrels and lyres, </li1>
				<li2>and he will fight against it<note>The reading tradition (<i>Qere</i>) has “them”</note> with battles of brandishing. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 30:33">33</verse-number>For Topheth has been prepared from yesterday; </li1>
				<li2>indeed, it is made ready for the king. </li2>
				<li1>He makes its pile of wood deep and wide; </li1>
				<li2>he makes fire and wood <idiom-start/>abundant<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “numerous”</note> </li2>
				<li3>The breath of Yahweh burns in it like a stream of sulfur. </li3>
			</ul>
		</chapter>