<chapter id="Is 37">
			<pericope>Hezekiah Consults Isaiah</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 37:1">1</verse-number>And this happened: When King Hezekiah heard, he tore his garments, covered himself with sackcloth, and entered the temple<note>Or “house”</note> of Yahweh. <verse-number id="Is 37:2">2</verse-number>And he sent Eliakim, who <supplied>was</supplied> <idiom-start/>in charge of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “over”</note> the palace,<note>Or “house”</note> and Shebna the secretary, and the elders of the priests <idiom-start/>covered<idiom-end/><note>Literally “covering themselves”</note> with sackcloth to Isaiah son of Amoz, the prophet. <verse-number id="Is 37:3">3</verse-number>And they said to him, “Thus says Hezekiah: ‘This day <supplied>is</supplied> a day of distress, rebuke, and disgrace, for children have come to <supplied>the</supplied> cervical opening, and there is no strength to give birth. <verse-number id="Is 37:4">4</verse-number>Maybe Yahweh your God heard <supplied>the</supplied> words of Rabshakeh whom the king of Assyria, his master, has sent to taunt <supplied>the</supplied> living God, and he will rebuke the words that Yahweh your God hears. And you must lift up a prayer for the benefit of the remnant that is found.’ ” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 37:5">5</verse-number>When<note>Or “And”</note> the servants of King Hezekiah came to Isaiah, <verse-number id="Is 37:6">6</verse-number>Isaiah said to them, “You must say this to your master: ‘Thus says Yahweh: “You must not be afraid because of the words that you have heard, <supplied>with</supplied> which the servants of the king of Assyria have blasphemed me. <verse-number id="Is 37:7">7</verse-number>Look! I <supplied>am</supplied> about to <idiom-start/>put<idiom-end/><note>Literally “give”</note> a spirit in him <idiom-start/>so that<idiom-end/><note>Or “and”</note> he shall hear a rumor and he shall return to his land, and I will cause him to fall by the sword in his land.” ’ ” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 37:8">8</verse-number>And Rabshakeh returned and found the king of Assyria fighting against Libnah, for he had heard that he had left from Lachish. <verse-number id="Is 37:9">9</verse-number>Now<note>Or “And”</note> he<note>That is, the king</note> heard concerning Tirhakah the king of Cush, saying, “He has set out to fight against<note>Or “with”</note> you.” </p>
			<p>When<note>Or “And”</note> he heard <supplied>it</supplied>, he sent messengers to Hezekiah, saying, <verse-number id="Is 37:10">10</verse-number>“You shall say this to Hezekiah, king of Judah: ‘<supplied>Do</supplied> not let your God in whom you trust in him deceive you by saying, “Jerusalem will not be given into the hand of the king of Assyria.” <verse-number id="Is 37:11">11</verse-number>Look! you have heard what the kings of Assyria have done to all lands to destroy them, and you—shall you be delivered? <verse-number id="Is 37:12">12</verse-number>Did the gods of the nations that my <idiom-start/>predecessors<idiom-end/><note>Literally “fathers”</note> destroyed deliver them—Gozan, Haran, Rezeph, and the sons of Eden who <supplied>were</supplied> in Telassar? <verse-number id="Is 37:13">13</verse-number>Where <supplied>is</supplied> the king of Hamath, the king of Arpad, the king of the city of Sepharvaim, Hena, or<note>Or “and”</note> Ivvah?’ ” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Hezekiah’s Prayer</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 37:14">14</verse-number>And Hezekiah took the letter from the hand of the messengers, and he read<note>Or “called”</note> it. Then<note>Or “And”</note> he went up <supplied>to</supplied> the temple<note>Or “house”</note> of Yahweh, and Hezekiah spread it out before the <idiom-start/>presence<idiom-end/><note>Literally “face”</note> of Yahweh. <verse-number id="Is 37:15">15</verse-number>And Hezekiah prayed to Yahweh, saying, <verse-number id="Is 37:16">16</verse-number>“Yahweh of hosts, God of Israel <idiom-start/>who is enthroned on<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sitting”</note> the cherubim, you <supplied>are</supplied> the one, God by yourself, of all the kingdoms of the earth; you are the one who made the heavens and the earth. <verse-number id="Is 37:17">17</verse-number>Yahweh, extend your ear and hear! Yahweh, open your eyes and see, and hear all the words of Sennacherib that he has sent to taunt the living God! <verse-number id="Is 37:18">18</verse-number>Truly, Yahweh, the kings of Assyria have laid waste all the lands<note>The parallel text in 2 Kings has “nations”</note> and their land, <verse-number id="Is 37:19">19</verse-number>to <idiom-start/>set<idiom-end/><note>Literally “give”</note> their gods in the fire, for they <supplied>were</supplied> not gods, but <supplied>the</supplied> work of human hands, wood and stone, and they destroyed them. <verse-number id="Is 37:20">20</verse-number>So<note>Or “And”</note> now, Yahweh, our God, save us from his hand so that<note>Or “and”</note> all the kingdoms of the earth may know that you <supplied>are</supplied> Yahweh, you alone!” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>God’s Answer</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 37:21">21</verse-number>And Isaiah son of Amoz sent to Hezekiah, saying, “Thus says Yahweh the God of Israel: ‘Because you have prayed to me <idiom-start/>concerning<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to”</note> Sennacherib, king of Assyria, <verse-number id="Is 37:22">22</verse-number>this <supplied>is</supplied> the word that Yahweh has spoken concerning him: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>She shows contempt for you; she derides you, virgin daughter of Zion; </li1>
				<li2>she shakes <supplied>her</supplied> head behind you, daughter of Jerusalem. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 37:23">23</verse-number>Whom have you taunted and blasphemed, </li1>
				<li2>and against whom have you raised up <supplied>your</supplied> voice and lifted your eyes upward? </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p>To the holy one of Israel! </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 37:24">24</verse-number>By the hand of your servants you have taunted the Lord, </li1>
				<li2>and you have said, “With my many chariots,<note>Hebrew “chariot”</note> </li2>
				<li1>I myself have gone up <supplied>the</supplied> height of <supplied>the</supplied> mountains, </li1>
				<li2><supplied>to</supplied> the remote areas of Lebanon. </li2>
				<li1>And I cut off <idiom-start/>its tall cedars<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the height of its cedars”</note> </li1>
				<li2>the choicest of its junipers. </li2>
				<li1>And I came <supplied>to</supplied> the height of its limit, </li1>
				<li2>the forest of its orchard.<note>Or “Carmel”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 37:25">25</verse-number>I myself dug and drank waters, </li1>
				<li2>and I caused all the streams of Egypt to dry up by the sole of my feet.” </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 37:26">26</verse-number>Have you not heard from <idiom-start/>a long time ago<idiom-end/>?<note>Literally “distant”</note> I have made it </li1>
				<li2>from days of primeval time, and I formed it. </li2>
				<li1>Now I have brought it <supplied>about</supplied>, </li1>
				<li2>and it is for fortified cities to collapse into heaps of destroyed stones. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 37:27">27</verse-number>And their inhabitants <supplied>are</supplied> <idiom-start/>weak<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “short of hand”</note> </li1>
				<li2>they are dismayed, and they are ashamed; </li2>
				<li1>they have become <supplied>like</supplied> plants<note>Hebrew “plant”</note> of <supplied>the</supplied> field, </li1>
				<li2>and <supplied>like</supplied> greens of grass, </li2>
				<li1><supplied>like</supplied> grass on<note>Or “of”</note> <supplied>the</supplied> roofs </li1>
				<li2>and a cultivated field <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “before the face of”</note> the standing grain. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 37:28">28</verse-number>And I know your sitting down and your going out, </li1>
				<li2>and your coming in, and your raging <idiom-start/>against<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to”</note> me. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 37:29">29</verse-number>Because you were enraged <idiom-start/>against<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to”</note> me, </li1>
				<li2>and your noise<note>Or “complacency”</note> has come up to<note>Literally “in”</note> my ears, </li2>
				<li1>I will put my hook in your nose </li1>
				<li2>and my bridle on your lips, </li2>
				<li1>and I will turn you back </li1>
				<li2>on the way <supplied>by</supplied> which you came. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 37:30">30</verse-number>And this <supplied>shall be</supplied> the sign for you: the eating of volunteer plants<note>Hebrew “plant”</note> this<note>Literally “the”</note> year, and in the second year self-seeded plants,<note>Hebrew “plant”</note> and in the third year sow, reap, plant vineyards, and eat their fruit. <verse-number id="Is 37:31">31</verse-number>And the remnant of the house of Judah that remain shall <idiom-start/>grow<idiom-end/><note>Literally “add”</note> roots<note>Hebrew “root”</note> downwards and make fruit upwards. </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 37:32">32</verse-number>For a remnant shall go out from Jerusalem </li1>
				<li2>and survivors<note>Hebrew “survivor”</note> from mountain Zion. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p>The zeal of Yahweh of hosts will do this.’ </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 37:33">33</verse-number>Therefore thus says Yahweh concerning<note>Or “to”</note> the king of Assyria: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>‘He shall not come to this city, </li1>
				<li2>and he shall not shoot an arrow there, </li2>
				<li1>and he shall not meet it <supplied>with</supplied> a shield, </li1>
				<li2>and he shall not heap a siege ramp up against her. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 37:34">34</verse-number>He shall return by the way that he came, </li1>
				<li2>and he shall not come to this city,’ </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 37:35">35</verse-number>‘And I will defend this city, to save it for my sake and for the sake of David, my servant.’ ” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Sennacherib’s Defeat</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 37:36">36</verse-number>And the angel of Yahweh set out and struck one hundred and eighty-five thousand in the camp of the Assyrians. When<note>Or “And”</note> they rose in the morning, look! All of them <supplied>were</supplied> dead corpses. <verse-number id="Is 37:37">37</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Sennacherib king of Assyria left, went, and returned and lived at Nineveh. <verse-number id="Is 37:38">38</verse-number>And this happened: he <supplied>was</supplied> bowing in worship <supplied>in</supplied> the house of Nisroch his god, and Adrammelech and Sharezer, his sons, struck him with the sword. And they themselves escaped <supplied>to</supplied> the land of Ararat, and Esar-haddon his son reigned as king in his place. </p>
		</chapter>