<chapter id="Is 38">
			<pericope>Hezekiah’s Illness</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 38:1">1</verse-number>In those days, Hezekiah became sick to death, and Isaiah son of Amoz, the prophet, came to him and said to him, “Thus says Yahweh: ‘Order your house, for you <supplied>are</supplied> about to die, and you shall not recover.’ ” <verse-number id="Is 38:2">2</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Hezekiah turned his face to the wall and prayed to Yahweh, <verse-number id="Is 38:3">3</verse-number>and he said, “O Yahweh, please remember how<note>Or “that”</note> I have walked before your <idiom-start/>presence<idiom-end/><note>Literally “face”</note> in faithfulness with a whole heart, and I have done the good in your eyes!” And Hezekiah wept <supplied>with</supplied> great weeping. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 38:4">4</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> the word of Yahweh came<note>Or “was”</note> to Isaiah, saying, <verse-number id="Is 38:5">5</verse-number>“Go and say to Hezekiah, ‘Thus says Yahweh, the God of David your ancestor:<note>Or “father”</note> “I have heard your prayer; I have seen your tears. <idiom-start/>Look, I am going to<idiom-end/><note>Literally, “Behold me; he will add,” but in this context it makes better sense to change the “he” to “I”; most translations follow this emendation</note> add fifteen years to your days. <verse-number id="Is 38:6">6</verse-number>And I will deliver you and this city from the hand of the king of Assyria, and I will defend this city.” ’ </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 38:7">7</verse-number>And this <supplied>is</supplied> the sign to you from Yahweh, that Yahweh will do this thing that he has spoken: <verse-number id="Is 38:8">8</verse-number>Look! I will cause <supplied>the</supplied> shadow of the steps, which it had gone down on the steps of Ahaz with the sun, to turn backwards ten steps.” And the sun turned back ten steps on the steps which it had gone down. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 38:9">9</verse-number>A writing of Hezekiah, king of Judah, when he was sick and had recovered from his sickness: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 38:10">10</verse-number>I was the one who said, “I must go in the quiet of my days; </li1>
				<li2>I am summoned through the gates of Sheol <supplied>for</supplied> the rest of my years.” </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 38:11">11</verse-number>I said, “I shall not see Yah! Yah in the land of the living! </li1>
				<li2>I shall no more look at humankind among <supplied>the</supplied> inhabitants of <supplied>the</supplied> world. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 38:12">12</verse-number>My dwelling place is pulled up and removed from me like the tent of my shepherd; </li1>
				<li2>I have rolled up my life like <supplied>a</supplied> weaver. </li2>
				<li1>He cuts me off from <supplied>the</supplied> thrum; </li1>
				<li2>from day to night you bring me to an end. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 38:13">13</verse-number>I lie down<note>Or “cry out”</note> until morning; </li1>
				<li2>like <supplied>a</supplied> lion, so he breaks all my bones; </li2>
				<li2>from day to night you bring me to an end. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 38:14">14</verse-number>Like a horse or a crane, so I chirp; </li1>
				<li2>I moan like <supplied>a</supplied> dove. </li2>
				<li1>My eyes are weak toward the height. </li1>
				<li2>Lord, I have oppression; lend me support! </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 38:15">15</verse-number>What can I say? For<note>Or “And”</note> he has spoken to me, </li1>
				<li2>and he himself has done <supplied>it</supplied>. </li2>
				<li1>I will walk slowly all my years because of the bitterness of my soul. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 38:16">16</verse-number>Lord, they live by them, and the life of my spirit belongs to all among them. </li1>
				<li1>And restore me to health and keep me alive! </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 38:17">17</verse-number>Look! Bitterness was bitter to me for peace. </li1>
				<li1>And you were the one who loved<note>Or possibly “kept back,” which sounds similar in Hebrew</note> my life from <supplied>the</supplied> pit of destruction, </li1>
				<li2>for you have cast all my sins behind your back. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 38:18">18</verse-number>For Sheol cannot praise you; death <supplied>cannot</supplied> praise you. </li1>
				<li2>Those who go down <supplied>to the</supplied> pit cannot hope for your faithfulness. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 38:19">19</verse-number><supplied>The</supplied> living, <supplied>the</supplied> living one praises you like me today; </li1>
				<li2>a father will make your faithfulness known to children. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 38:20">20</verse-number>Yahweh, save me, and we will play my music <supplied>on</supplied> stringed instruments all the days of our lives at the temple<note>Or “house”</note> of Yahweh.” </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 38:21">21</verse-number>And Isaiah said, “Let them <idiom-start/>take<idiom-end/><note>Literally “lift up”</note> a lump of figs, and let them rub <supplied>it</supplied> on the boil <idiom-start/>so that<idiom-end/><note>Or “and”</note> he may recover.” <verse-number id="Is 38:22">22</verse-number>And Hezekiah said, “What <supplied>is the</supplied> sign that I shall go up <supplied>to</supplied> the temple<note>Or “house”</note> of Yahweh?” </p>
		</chapter>