<chapter id="Is 39">
			<pericope>The Delegation from Babylon</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 39:1">1</verse-number>At that time, Merodach-Baladan, son of Baladan, king of Babylon, sent letters and a present to Hezekiah, for<note>Or “and”</note> he heard that he had been sick and recovered. <verse-number id="Is 39:2">2</verse-number>And Hezekiah rejoiced over them and showed them his house of aromatic gum, the silver, gold, spices, good oil, all the house of his weapons, and all that was found in his storehouses. There was nothing that Hezekiah had not shown them in his house or in all his dominion. <verse-number id="Is 39:3">3</verse-number>And Isaiah the prophet came to King Hezekiah and said to him, “What did these men say, and from where did they come to you?” And Hezekiah <idiom-start/>answered<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “said”</note> “They came to me from a distant country, from Babylon.” <verse-number id="Is 39:4">4</verse-number>And he<note>That is, Isaiah</note> said, “What have they seen in your house?” And Hezekiah <idiom-start/>answered<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “said”</note> “They have seen all that <supplied>is</supplied> in my house. There is nothing that I have not shown them in my storehouses.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 39:5">5</verse-number>And Isaiah said to Hezekiah, “Hear the word of Yahweh of hosts: <verse-number id="Is 39:6">6</verse-number>‘Look! days <supplied>are</supplied> coming, and all that <supplied>is</supplied> in your house and that which your ancestors<note>Or “fathers”</note> have stored up to this day shall be carried off <supplied>to</supplied> Babylon. Nothing shall be left,’ says Yahweh. <verse-number id="Is 39:7">7</verse-number>‘And some of your sons who go out from you, whom you fathered, shall be taken, and they shall be eunuchs in the palace of the king of Babylon.’ ” <verse-number id="Is 39:8">8</verse-number>And Hezekiah said to Isaiah, “The word of Yahweh that you have spoken <supplied>is</supplied> good,” for<note>Or “and”</note> he <idiom-start/>thought<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “said”</note> “Surely there will be peace and security in my days.” </p>
		</chapter>