<chapter id="Is 52">
			<pericope>Yahweh Redeems Zion</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 52:1">1</verse-number>Awake! Awake; put on your strength, Zion! </li1>
				<li2>Put on the garments of your beauty, Jerusalem, <idiom-start/>holy city<idiom-end/>!<note>Literally “city of <supplied>the</supplied> holiness”</note> </li2>
				<li3>For <supplied>the</supplied> uncircumcised and <supplied>the</supplied> unclean shall not <idiom-start/>continue to<idiom-end/><note>Literally “do again he shall”</note> enter you any longer. </li3>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 52:2">2</verse-number>Shake yourself free from <supplied>the</supplied> dust! Rise up; sit, Jerusalem! </li1>
				<li2>Free yourselves <supplied>from</supplied> the bonds of your neck, captive daughter of Zion! </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 52:3">3</verse-number>For thus says Yahweh: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“You were sold for nothing, </li1>
				<li2>and you shall be redeemed without money.” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 52:4">4</verse-number>For thus says the Lord Yahweh: </p>
			<p>“My people went down <supplied>to</supplied> Egypt in the beginning, to dwell as aliens there, and Assyria oppressed him <idiom-start/>without cause<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “in nothing”</note> <verse-number id="Is 52:5">5</verse-number>And now what do I have here?”<idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> Yahweh, “for my people is taken without cause. Its rulers howl,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> Yahweh—“and my name <supplied>is</supplied> reviled continually, all day. <verse-number id="Is 52:6">6</verse-number>Therefore my people shall know my name, therefore in that day, that I <supplied>am</supplied> the one who speaks. <idiom-start/>Here am I<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “Look at me”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 52:7">7</verse-number>How delightful on the mountains are the feet of him who brings good news, </li1>
				<li2>who announces peace, who brings good news, who announces salvation, </li2>
				<li2>who says to Zion, “Your God reigns as a king.” </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 52:8">8</verse-number>The voices<note>Hebrew “voice”</note> of your watchmen! They lift up <supplied>their</supplied> voices;<note>Hebrew “voice”</note> </li1>
				<li2>together they sing for joy; </li2>
				<li3>for they <idiom-start/>clearly<idiom-end/><note>Literally “eye in eye “</note> see Yahweh’s return <supplied>to</supplied> Zion. </li3>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 52:9">9</verse-number>Break forth, </li1>
				<li2>sing for joy together, ruins of Jerusalem, </li2>
				<li1>for Yahweh has comforted his people; </li1>
				<li2>he has redeemed Jerusalem. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 52:10">10</verse-number>Yahweh has bared <idiom-start/>his holy arm<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the arm of his holiness”</note> to the eyes of all the nations, </li1>
				<li2>and all <supplied>the</supplied> ends<note>Hebrew “end”</note> of <supplied>the</supplied> earth shall see the salvation of our God. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 52:11">11</verse-number>Depart, depart, go out from there! You must not touch any unclean thing. </li1>
				<li2>Go out from the midst of it, keep clean, you who carry the vessels of Yahweh. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 52:12">12</verse-number>For you shall not go out in haste, </li1>
				<li2>and you shall not go in flight, </li2>
				<li1>for Yahweh <supplied>is</supplied> going before you, </li1>
				<li2>and your rear guard <supplied>is</supplied> the God of Israel. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Servant’s Suffering and Exaltation</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 52:13">13</verse-number>Look, my servant shall achieve success; </li1>
				<li2>he shall be exalted, </li2>
				<li1>and he shall be lifted up, </li1>
				<li2>and he shall be very high. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 52:14">14</verse-number>Just as many were appalled at you— </li1>
				<li2>such <supplied>was</supplied> his appearance beyond human disfigurement, </li2>
				<li3>and his form beyond the sons of mankind— </li3>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 52:15">15</verse-number>so he shall sprinkle many nations; </li1>
				<li2>because of him, kings shall shut their mouths.<note>Hebrew “mouth”</note> </li2>
				<li1>For they shall see what has not been told them, </li1>
				<li2>and they shall consider with full attention what they have not heard. </li2>
			</ul>
		</chapter>