<chapter id="Is 54">
			<pericope>The Fertile Wife of Yahweh</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 54:1">1</verse-number>“Sing for joy, barren <supplied>woman</supplied>; <supplied>who</supplied> has not borne! </li1>
				<li2>Burst forth <supplied>into</supplied> rejoicing and rejoice, <supplied>she who</supplied> has not been in labor! </li2>
				<li3>For <supplied>the</supplied> children of <supplied>the</supplied> desolate woman <supplied>are</supplied> more than <supplied>the</supplied> children of <supplied>the</supplied> married woman,” says Yahweh. </li3>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 54:2">2</verse-number>“Enlarge the site of your tent, </li1>
				<li2>and let them stretch out the tent curtains of your dwelling place. </li2>
				<li1>You must not spare; make your tent cords long </li1>
				<li2>and strengthen your pegs, </li2>
				<li3><verse-number id="Is 54:3">3</verse-number>for you will spread out <supplied>to the</supplied> right and <supplied>to the</supplied> left. </li3>
				<li1>And your descendants<note>Hebrew “descendant”</note> will be heir <supplied>to the</supplied> nations, </li1>
				<li2>and they will inhabit desolate towns. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 54:4">4</verse-number>You must not fear, for you will not be ashamed, </li1>
				<li2>and you must not be confounded, for you will not feel abashed, </li2>
				<li1>for you will forget the shame of your youth, </li1>
				<li2>and you will no longer remember the disgrace of your widowhood. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 54:5">5</verse-number>For your husband<note>The Hebrew is plural</note> <supplied>is</supplied> your maker,<note>The Hebrew is plural</note> his name <supplied>is</supplied> Yahweh of hosts; </li1>
				<li2>and your redeemer <supplied>is</supplied> the holy one of Israel, he is called the God of all of the earth. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 54:6">6</verse-number>For Yahweh has called you like a wife forsaken and hurt of spirit, </li1>
				<li2>like<note>Or “and”</note> <supplied>the</supplied> wife of childhood when she is rejected, says your God. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 54:7">7</verse-number>I abandoned you <idiom-start/>for a short<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in a small”</note> moment, </li1>
				<li2>but<note>Or “and”</note> I will gather you with great compassion. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 54:8">8</verse-number>I hid my face from you <supplied>for</supplied> a moment, in the flowing of anger, </li1>
				<li2>but<note>Or “and”</note> I will have compassion on you with everlasting faithfulness” says your redeemer, Yahweh. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 54:9">9</verse-number>“For this <supplied>is like</supplied> the waters of Noah to me, </li1>
				<li2>when I swore <idiom-start/>that the waters of Noah would never again pass<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from the passing over of the waters of Noah again”</note> over the earth, </li2>
				<li2>so I swore <idiom-start/>that I would not be<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from being “</note> angry at you and rebuke you. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 54:10">10</verse-number>For the mountains may depart, </li1>
				<li2>and the hills may sway, </li2>
				<li1>but<note>Or “and”</note> my faithfulness shall not depart from you, </li1>
				<li2>and my covenant of peace shall not sway,” </li2>
				<li1>says Yahweh, who has compassion on you, </li1>
				<li2><verse-number id="Is 54:11">11</verse-number>“O afflicted <supplied>one</supplied>, driven away, <supplied>who</supplied> is not consoled. </li2>
				<li1>Look! I <supplied>am</supplied> about to set your stones in hard mortar, </li1>
				<li2>and I will lay your foundation with sapphires. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 54:12">12</verse-number>And I will <idiom-start/>make<idiom-end/><note>Literally “place”</note> your battlements of ruby, </li1>
				<li2>and your gates of stones of beryl, </li2>
				<li2>and all your wall of precious stones. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 54:13">13</verse-number>And all your children <supplied>shall be</supplied> pupils of Yahweh, </li1>
				<li2>and the peace of your children <supplied>shall be</supplied> great. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 54:14">14</verse-number>In righteousness you shall be established. </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>Be far from oppression, for you shall not fear, </li1>
				<li2>and from terror, for it shall not come near you. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 54:15">15</verse-number>If indeed one attacks, <supplied>it is</supplied> not from me; </li1>
				<li2>whoever attacks you shall fall because of you. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 54:16">16</verse-number>Look! I myself have created <supplied>the</supplied> craftsman who blows<note>Or “blowing”</note> <supplied>the</supplied> fire <supplied>of</supplied> coals, </li1>
				<li2>and who produces<note>Or “producing”</note> a weapon for his work; </li2>
				<li2>also<note>Or “and”</note> I myself have created <supplied>the</supplied> destroyer to destroy. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 54:17">17</verse-number>Every weapon formed against you shall not succeed, </li1>
				<li2>and you shall declare guilty every tongue <supplied>that</supplied> rises against you for judgment. </li2>
				<li1>This <supplied>is</supplied> the inheritance of the servants of Yahweh, </li1>
				<li2>and their <idiom-start/>legal right<idiom-end/><note>Literally “justice”</note> from me,” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> Yahweh. </p>
		</chapter>