<chapter id="Is 60">
			<pericope>Zion Glorified</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 60:1">1</verse-number>“Arise, shine! For your light has come, </li1>
				<li2>and the glory of Yahweh has risen on you. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 60:2">2</verse-number>For look! darkness shall cover <supplied>the</supplied> earth, </li1>
				<li2>and thick darkness <supplied>the</supplied> peoples, </li2>
				<li1>but<note>Or “and”</note> Yahweh will rise on you, </li1>
				<li2>and his glory will appear over you. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 60:3">3</verse-number>And nations shall come to your light, </li1>
				<li2>and kings to the bright light of your sunrise. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 60:4">4</verse-number>Lift up your eyes all around and see! </li1>
				<li2>All of them gather; they come to you. </li2>
				<li1>Your sons shall come from afar, </li1>
				<li2>and your daughters shall be looked after on <supplied>the</supplied> hip. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 60:5">5</verse-number>Then you shall see </li1>
				<li2>and you shall be radiant; </li2>
				<li1>and your heart shall tremble </li1>
				<li2>and open itself wide, </li2>
				<li1>because <supplied>the</supplied> abundance of <supplied>the</supplied> sea shall fall upon you; </li1>
				<li2><supplied>the</supplied> wealth of <supplied>the</supplied> nations shall come to you. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 60:6">6</verse-number>A multitude of camels shall cover you, </li1>
				<li2>the young male camels of Midian and Ephah. </li2>
				<li1>All those from Sheba shall come; </li1>
				<li2>they shall bring gold and frankincense, </li2>
				<li3>and they shall proclaim the praise of Yahweh. </li3>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 60:7">7</verse-number>All the flocks of Kedar shall be gathered to you; </li1>
				<li2>the rams of Nebaioth shall serve you. </li2>
				<li1>They shall present a sacrifice for favor <supplied>on</supplied> my altar, </li1>
				<li2>and I will glorify <idiom-start/>my honorable house<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “house of my honor”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 60:8">8</verse-number>Who <supplied>are</supplied> these? They fly like <supplied>a</supplied> cloud, </li1>
				<li2>and like doves to their coops. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 60:9">9</verse-number>Because <supplied>the</supplied> coastlands wait for me, </li1>
				<li2>and the ships of Tarshish <supplied>are</supplied> first </li2>
				<li1>to bring your children from afar, </li1>
				<li2>their silver and gold with them, </li2>
				<li1>for the name of Yahweh your God, </li1>
				<li2>and for the holy one of Israel, because he has glorified you. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 60:10">10</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>foreigners<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons of a foreign country”</note> shall build your walls, </li1>
				<li2>and their kings shall serve you, </li2>
				<li1>for in my anger I struck you, </li1>
				<li2>but<note>Or “and”</note> in my favor I have taken pity on you. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 60:11">11</verse-number>And your gates shall continually be open, </li1>
				<li2>day and night they shall not be shut, </li2>
				<li1>to bring you <supplied>the</supplied> wealth of nations, </li1>
				<li2>and their kings shall be led. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 60:12">12</verse-number>For the nation and the kingdom that will not serve you shall perish, </li1>
				<li2>and the nations shall be utterly devastated. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 60:13">13</verse-number>The glory of Lebanon shall come to you; </li1>
				<li2><supplied>the</supplied> cypress, <supplied>the</supplied> plane, and <supplied>the</supplied> pine together, </li2>
				<li1>to glorify the place of my sanctuary, </li1>
				<li2>and I will do honor to the place of my feet. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 60:14">14</verse-number>And the children of those who oppressed you shall come to you bending low, </li1>
				<li2>and all those who treated you disrespectfully shall bow down at the soles of your feet. </li2>
				<li1>And they shall call you the city of Yahweh, </li1>
				<li2>Zion <supplied>of</supplied> the holy one of Israel. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 60:15">15</verse-number>Instead of you being forsaken </li1>
				<li2>and hated <idiom-start/>with no one passing through,<idiom-end/><note>Or “and there is not one who passes through”</note> </li2>
				<li1>I will <idiom-start/>make<idiom-end/><note>Literally “place”</note> you an everlasting <idiom-start/>object of pride<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “pride”</note> </li1>
				<li2>a joy of <idiom-start/>coming generations<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “generation and generation”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 60:16">16</verse-number>And you shall suck <supplied>the</supplied> milk of nations, </li1>
				<li2>and suck <supplied>the</supplied> breast of kings, </li2>
				<li1>and you shall know that I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh your Savior, </li1>
				<li2>and your Redeemer, the Strong One of Jacob. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 60:17">17</verse-number>Instead of bronze I will bring gold, </li1>
				<li2>and instead of iron I will bring silver, </li2>
				<li1>and instead of wood, bronze, </li1>
				<li2>and instead of stones, iron. </li2>
				<li1>And I will <idiom-start/>appoint<idiom-end/><note>Literally “put”</note> peace <supplied>as</supplied> your overseer, </li1>
				<li2>and righteousness <supplied>as</supplied> <idiom-start/>your ruling body<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “they who force you to work”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 60:18">18</verse-number>Violence shall no longer be heard in your land; </li1>
				<li2>devastation or<note>Or “and”</note> destruction on your borders. </li2>
				<li1>And you shall call your walls Salvation, </li1>
				<li2>and your gates, Praise. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 60:19">19</verse-number>The sun shall no longer be your light by day, </li1>
				<li2>and for bright light the moon shall not give you light, </li2>
				<li1>but<note>Or “and”</note> Yahweh will be your everlasting light, </li1>
				<li2>and your God your glory. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 60:20">20</verse-number>Your sun shall no longer go <supplied>down</supplied>, </li1>
				<li2>and your moon shall not <idiom-start/>wane<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “be taken away”</note> </li2>
				<li1>for Yahweh himself will be your everlasting light, </li1>
				<li2>and your days of mourning shall come to an end. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 60:21">21</verse-number>And all your people <supplied>shall be</supplied> righteous; </li1>
				<li2>they shall take possession of <supplied>the</supplied> land forever, </li2>
				<li1>the shoot of his<note>The reading tradition (<i>Qere</i>) has “my”</note> planting, </li1>
				<li2>the work of my hands, to show my glory. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 60:22">22</verse-number>The small <supplied>one</supplied> shall become <supplied>a</supplied> tribe, </li1>
				<li2>and the smallest one a mighty nation. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p>I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh; I will hasten it in its time.” </p>
		</chapter>