<chapter id="Is 62">
			<pericope>Zion’s New Identity</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 62:1">1</verse-number>For the sake of Zion I will not be silent, </li1>
				<li2>and for the sake of Jerusalem I will not maintain a quiet attitude, </li2>
				<li1>until her righteousness goes out like the bright light, </li1>
				<li2>and her salvation burns like a torch. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 62:2">2</verse-number>And <supplied>the</supplied> nations shall see your righteousness, </li1>
				<li2>and all <supplied>the</supplied> kings your glory, </li2>
				<li1>and <idiom-start/>you will be called<idiom-end/><note>Literally “it shall be called to you”</note> a new name </li1>
				<li2>that the mouth of Yahweh will designate. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 62:3">3</verse-number>And you shall be a crown of beauty in the hand of Yahweh, </li1>
				<li2>and a headband of royalty in the hand of your God. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 62:4">4</verse-number>It shall no longer be said of you, “Forsaken,” </li1>
				<li2>and it shall no longer be said of your land, “Desolation!” </li2>
				<li1>but <idiom-start/>you will<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to you it shall”</note> be called “My Delight <supplied>Is</supplied> In Her,” </li1>
				<li2>and your land, “Married,” </li2>
				<li1>for Yahweh delights in you, </li1>
				<li2>and your land shall be married. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 62:5">5</verse-number>For <supplied>as</supplied> a young man marries a virgin, </li1>
				<li2><supplied>so</supplied> shall your sons marry you, </li2>
				<li1>and <supplied>as is the</supplied> joy of <supplied>the</supplied> bridegroom over <supplied>the</supplied> bride, </li1>
				<li2><supplied>so</supplied> shall your God rejoice over you. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 62:6">6</verse-number>I have appointed watchmen upon your walls, Jerusalem; </li1>
				<li2>all day and all night they shall never be silent. </li2>
				<li1>You who profess Yahweh have no rest. </li1>
				<li2><verse-number id="Is 62:7">7</verse-number>And you must not give him rest until he establishes, </li2>
				<li3>and until he <idiom-start/>makes<idiom-end/><note>Literally “places”</note> Jerusalem <idiom-start/>an object of praise<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a praise”</note> in the earth. </li3>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 62:8">8</verse-number>Yahweh has sworn by his right hand, </li1>
				<li2>and by <idiom-start/>his mighty arm<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the arm of his might”</note> </li2>
				<li1>“Surely I will never again give your grain <supplied>as</supplied> food to <idiom-start/>your enemies<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “those who are hostile to you”</note> </li1>
				<li2>and surely <idiom-start/>foreigners<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons of a foreign country”</note> shall not drink your new wine at which you have labored.” </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 62:9">9</verse-number>But those who gather it shall eat it, and they shall praise Yahweh, </li1>
				<li2>and those who gather it shall drink it in <idiom-start/>my holy courts<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the courts of my holiness”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 62:10">10</verse-number>Pass through, pass through the gates! </li1>
				<li2>Make the way clear <idiom-start/>for<idiom-end/><note>Literally “of”</note> the people! </li2>
				<li1>Pile up, pile up the highway; clear <supplied>it</supplied> of stones!<note>Hebrew “stone”</note> </li1>
				<li2>Lift up an ensign over the peoples! </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 62:11">11</verse-number>Look! Yahweh has proclaimed to the end of the earth: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>Say to daughter Zion, “Look, your salvation <supplied>is</supplied> coming! </li1>
				<li2>Look, his reward <supplied>is</supplied> with him, </li2>
				<li2>and his reward before him. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 62:12">12</verse-number>And they shall call them “The <idiom-start/>Holy People<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “People of the Holiness”</note> The Redeemed Of Yahweh,” </li1>
				<li2>and <idiom-start/>you<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to you it”</note> shall be called “Sought After, A City Is Not Forsaken.” </li2>
			</ul>
		</chapter>