<chapter id="Is 65">
			<pericope>Judgment and Salvation</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 65:1">1</verse-number>“I let myself be sought by <supplied>those who</supplied> did not ask; </li1>
				<li2>I let myself be found by <supplied>those who</supplied> did not seek me. </li2>
				<li1>I said, ‘Here I am; here I am!’ to a nation <supplied>that</supplied> did not call on my name; </li1>
				<li2><verse-number id="Is 65:2">2</verse-number>I spread out my hands all day to a stubborn people, </li2>
				<li1>those who walk after their thoughts <supplied>in</supplied> the way <supplied>that is</supplied> not good, </li1>
				<li2><verse-number id="Is 65:3">3</verse-number>the people <idiom-start/>who provoke<idiom-end/><note>Literally “provoking”</note> me to anger continually to my face, </li2>
				<li1>slaughtering for sacrifices in the garden, </li1>
				<li2>and making smoke offerings on bricks, </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 65:4">4</verse-number><idiom-start/>who sit<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sitting”</note> in graves </li1>
				<li2>and spend the night in <idiom-start/>secret places<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “watches”</note> </li2>
				<li1><idiom-start/>who eat<idiom-end/><note>Literally “eating”</note> the flesh of swine </li1>
				<li2>with<note>Or “and”</note> a fragment<note>The reading tradition (<i>Qere</i>) has “broth”</note> of impurity <supplied>in</supplied> their vessels, </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 65:5">5</verse-number><idiom-start/>who say<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “saying”</note> “<idiom-start/>Keep to yourself<idiom-end/>!<note>Literally “Come near to you”</note> </li1>
				<li2>You must not come near me, for I am <supplied>too</supplied> holy for you!” </li2>
				<li1>These <supplied>are</supplied> a smoke in my <idiom-start/>nostrils<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “nose”</note> </li1>
				<li2>a fire burning all day. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 65:6">6</verse-number>Look! <supplied>It</supplied> is written before me: I will not be silent, but I will repay; </li1>
				<li2>and I will repay in<note>Or “on”</note> the fold of their garment </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 65:7">7</verse-number>your iniquities and the iniquities of your ancestors<note>Or “fathers”</note> together, says Yahweh, </li1>
				<li1>because they made smoke offerings on the mountains </li1>
				<li2>and they taunted me on the hills, </li2>
				<li1>I will measure their punishment <supplied>from the</supplied> beginning into the fold of their garment.” </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 65:8">8</verse-number>Thus says Yahweh: “Just as the new wine is found in the cluster, and they say ‘You must not destroy it, for <supplied>there is</supplied> a blessing in it,’ so I will do for the sake of my servants <idiom-start/>by<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to”</note> not destroying <idiom-start/>everyone<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “all”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 65:9">9</verse-number>And I will bring descendant s<note>Hebrew “descendant”</note> out from Jacob, </li1>
				<li2>and a <idiom-start/>people<idiom-end/><note>Literally “man”</note> from Judah to take possession of my mountain, </li2>
				<li1>and my chosen ones shall inherit it, </li1>
				<li2>and my servants shall settle there. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 65:10">10</verse-number>And Sharon shall become a pasture for<note>Literally “of”</note> flocks,<note>Hebrew “flock”</note> </li1>
				<li2>and the valley of Achor a resting place for<note>Or “of”</note> herds<note>Hebrew “herd”</note> </li2>
				<li2>for my people who have sought me. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 65:11">11</verse-number>But<note>Or “and”</note> you <idiom-start/>who forsake<idiom-end/><note>Literally “forsaking”</note> Yahweh, </li1>
				<li2>forgetting <idiom-start/>my holy mountain<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the mountain of my holiness”</note> </li2>
				<li1>who set a table for Fortune, </li1>
				<li2>and who <idiom-start/>pour out<idiom-end/><note>Literally “fill”</note> a jug of mixed wine for Destiny, </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 65:12">12</verse-number>and I will remit you to the sword, </li1>
				<li2>and all of you shall bow down to the slaughter, </li2>
				<li1>because I called, but<note>Or “and”</note> you did not answer; </li1>
				<li2>I spoke, but<note>Or “and”</note> you did not listen, </li2>
				<li1>but<note>Or “and”</note> you did the evil in my eyes, </li1>
				<li2>and you chose that in which I do not delight.” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 65:13">13</verse-number>Therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Look! My servants shall eat but<note>Or “and”</note> you, you shall be hungry. </li1>
				<li1>Look! My servants shall drink but<note>Or “and”</note> you, you shall be thirsty. </li1>
				<li1>Look! My servants shall rejoice but<note>Or “and”</note> you, you shall be ashamed. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 65:14">14</verse-number>Look! My servants shall shout <idiom-start/>for joy<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from goodness of heart”</note> but<note>Or “and”</note> you, you shall cry out <idiom-start/>for pain<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from pain of heart”</note> and howl <idiom-start/>for sadness<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “from a breaking of <supplied>the</supplied> spirit”</note> </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 65:15">15</verse-number>And you shall leave your name to my chosen ones as a curse, </li1>
				<li2>and the Lord Yahweh will kill you, and he will <idiom-start/>give<idiom-end/><note>Literally “call”</note> his servants another name. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 65:16">16</verse-number>Whoever blesses himself in the land shall bless himself by the God of trustworthiness, </li1>
				<li2>and the one who swears an oath in the land shall swear by the God of trustworthiness, </li2>
				<li1>because the former troubles are forgotten, </li1>
				<li2>and they are hidden from my eyes. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>New Creation</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 65:17">17</verse-number>For look! I <supplied>am</supplied> about to create new heavens and a new earth, </li1>
				<li2>and the former things shall not be remembered, </li2>
				<li1>and they shall not <idiom-start/>come to mind<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “go up to heart”</note> </li1>
				<li2><verse-number id="Is 65:18">18</verse-number>But rejoice and shout in exultation forever and ever <supplied>over</supplied> what I <supplied>am</supplied> about to create! </li2>
				<li1>For look! I <supplied>am</supplied> about to create Jerusalem <supplied>as a source of</supplied> rejoicing, </li1>
				<li2>and her people <supplied>as a source of</supplied> joy. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 65:19">19</verse-number>And I will shout in exultation over Jerusalem, </li1>
				<li2>and I will rejoice over my people, </li2>
				<li1>and <supplied>the</supplied> sound of weeping shall no longer be heard in it, </li1>
				<li2>or<note>Or “and”</note> <supplied>the</supplied> sound of a cry for help. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 65:20">20</verse-number>There will no longer be a nursing infant <idiom-start/>who lives only a few<idiom-end/><note>Literally “of”</note> days, </li1>
				<li2>or<note>Or “and”</note> an old man who does not fill his days, </li2>
				<li1>for the boy will die <idiom-start/>a hundred years old<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “a son of a hundred year”</note> </li1>
				<li2>and the one who <idiom-start/>fails to reach<idiom-end/><note>Literally “misses”</note> <idiom-start/>a hundred years<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a son of a hundred year”</note> will be <idiom-start/>considered<idiom-end/><note>Literally “treated”</note> accursed. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 65:21">21</verse-number>And they shall build houses and inhabit <supplied>them</supplied>, </li1>
				<li2>and they shall plant vineyards and eat their fruit. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 65:22">22</verse-number>They shall not build and another inhabit; </li1>
				<li2>they shall not plant and another eat. </li2>
				<li1>For the days of my people <supplied>shall be</supplied> like the days of <supplied>a</supplied> tree, </li1>
				<li2>and my chosen ones shall enjoy the work of their hands. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 65:23">23</verse-number>They shall not labor for nothing, </li1>
				<li2>and they shall not give birth to horror, </li2>
				<li1>for they <idiom-start/>shall be offspring blessed by<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the offspring of the blessing of”</note> Yahweh, </li1>
				<li2>and their descendants with them. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 65:24">24</verse-number>And this will happen: before they call, I myself will answer; </li1>
				<li2><supplied>while</supplied> still they <supplied>are</supplied> speaking, I myself will hear. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 65:25">25</verse-number><supplied>The</supplied> wolf and <supplied>the</supplied> lamb shall feed like one, </li1>
				<li2>and <supplied>the</supplied> lion shall eat straw like the ox, </li2>
				<li3>but<note>Or “and”</note> dust <supplied>shall be</supplied> <supplied>the</supplied> serpent’s food. </li3>
				<li1>They shall do no evil, </li1>
				<li2>and they shall not destroy on all <idiom-start/>my holy mountain<idiom-end/>,”<note>Literally “the mountain of my holiness”</note> says Yahweh. </li2>
			</ul>
		</chapter>