<chapter id="Is 66">
			<pericope>Proper Worship</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 66:1">1</verse-number>Thus says Yahweh: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Heaven <supplied>is</supplied> my throne, </li1>
				<li2>and the earth <supplied>is</supplied> the footstool for my feet. </li2>
				<li1>Where <supplied>is</supplied> this house that you would build for me? </li1>
				<li2>And where <supplied>is</supplied> this resting place for me? </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 66:2">2</verse-number>And my hand has made all these <supplied>things</supplied>, </li1>
				<li2>and all these <idiom-start/>came to be<idiom-end/>,”<note>Literally “were”</note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> Yahweh, “but<note>Or “and”</note> I look to this <supplied>one</supplied>: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>to <supplied>the</supplied> humble and <supplied>the</supplied> contrite of spirit </li1>
				<li2>and <supplied>the one</supplied> frightened at my word. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 66:3">3</verse-number>The one who slaughters <supplied>a</supplied> bull strikes a man; </li1>
				<li2>the one who slaughters <supplied>a</supplied> lamb for sacrifice breaks the neck <supplied>of</supplied> a dog. </li2>
				<li1>The one who offers an offering, <supplied>the</supplied> blood of swine; </li1>
				<li2>the one who offers frankincense blesses an idol. </li2>
				<li1>Indeed, they themselves have chosen their ways, </li1>
				<li2>and their soul delights in their abhorrence. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 66:4">4</verse-number>Indeed, I myself I will choose their ill treatment, </li1>
				<li2>and I will bring them objects of their dread, </li2>
				<li1>because I called, and <idiom-start/>no one answered<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “there was no one who answers”</note> </li1>
				<li2>I spoke and they did not listen, </li2>
				<li1>but<note>Or “and”</note> they did the evil in my eyes, </li1>
				<li2>and they chose that in which I do not delight.” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 66:5">5</verse-number>Hear the word of Yahweh, you who are frightened at his word: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>Your brothers who hate you, </li1>
				<li2>who exclude you for my name’s sake have said, </li2>
				<li1>“Let Yahweh be honored so that<note>Or “and”</note> we may see your joy!” </li1>
				<li2>But<note>Or “And”</note> they themselves shall be ashamed. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 66:6">6</verse-number>A voice, an uproar from <supplied>the</supplied> city! </li1>
				<li2>A voice from <supplied>the</supplied> temple! </li2>
				<li3>The voice of Yahweh <idiom-start/>paying back<idiom-end/><note>Literally “rewarding retribution to”</note> his enemies! </li3>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Zion’s Delivery</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 66:7">7</verse-number>Before she was in labor she gave birth; </li1>
				<li2>before labor pains<note>Hebrew “pain”</note> came to her, she gave birth to a son. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 66:8">8</verse-number>Who has heard <supplied>anything</supplied> like this? </li1>
				<li2>Who has seen <supplied>anything</supplied> like these <supplied>things</supplied>? </li2>
				<li1>Can a land be born in one day? </li1>
				<li2>Or can a nation be born in a moment? </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><supplied>Yet</supplied> when she was in labor, Zion indeed gave birth <supplied>to</supplied> her children. </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 66:9">9</verse-number>Shall I myself I break open and not <idiom-start/>deliver<idiom-end/>?”<note>Literally “cause to bring forth”</note> says Yahweh, </li1>
				<li1>“or I who <idiom-start/>delivers<idiom-end/><note>Literally “causes to bring forth”</note> lock up <supplied>the womb</supplied>?” says your God. </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 66:10">10</verse-number>“Rejoice with Jerusalem </li1>
				<li2>and shout in exultation with her, all those who love her! </li2>
				<li2>Rejoice with her <supplied>in</supplied> joy, all those who mourn over her, </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 66:11">11</verse-number>so that you may suck and be satisfied from her <idiom-start/>consoling breast<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “breast of consolation”</note> </li1>
				<li2>so that you may drink deeply and refresh yourselves from her <idiom-start/>heavy breast<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “breast of heaviness “</note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 66:12">12</verse-number>For thus says Yahweh: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Look! I <supplied>am</supplied> about to spread prosperity out to her like a river, </li1>
				<li2>and <supplied>the</supplied> wealth of <supplied>the</supplied> nations like an overflowing stream, </li2>
				<li1>and you shall suck and be carried on the hip; </li1>
				<li2>and you shall you shall be played with on the knees. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 66:13">13</verse-number>As a man whose mother comforts him, so I myself will comfort you, </li1>
				<li2>and you shall be comforted in Jerusalem. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Yahweh’s Final Judgment</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 66:14">14</verse-number>And you shall see and your heart shall rejoice, </li1>
				<li2>and your bones shall <idiom-start/>flourish<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sprout”</note> like the grass, </li2>
				<li1>and the hand of Yahweh shall make itself known <idiom-start/>to<idiom-end/><note>Literally “with”</note> his servants, </li1>
				<li2>and he shall curse his enemies. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 66:15">15</verse-number>For look! Yahweh will come in fire, </li1>
				<li2>and his chariots like the storm wind, </li2>
				<li1>to <idiom-start/>give back<idiom-end/><note>Literally “cause to turn around”</note> his anger in wrath, </li1>
				<li2>and his rebuke in flames of fire. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 66:16">16</verse-number>For Yahweh enters into judgment <supplied>on</supplied> all flesh with fire and his sword, </li1>
				<li2>and <idiom-start/>those slain by<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the slain of”</note> Yahweh shall be many. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 66:17">17</verse-number>Those who sanctify themselves </li1>
				<li2>and those who cleanse themselves <idiom-start/>to go into<idiom-end/><note>Literally “toward”</note> the gardens after <supplied>the</supplied> one in the middle, </li2>
				<li1>eating the flesh of swine </li1>
				<li2>and detestable things<note>Hebrew “thing”</note> and rodents<note>Hebrew “rodent”</note> together </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p>shall come to an end!” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> Yahweh. </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 66:18">18</verse-number>“And I—their works and thoughts!—<supplied>am</supplied> about to come to gather all nations and tongues, </li1>
				<li2>and they shall come and see my glory. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Is 66:19">19</verse-number>And I will set a sign among them, </li1>
				<li2>and I will send survivors from them to the nations: </li2>
				<li1>Tarshish, Pul, and Lud, who draw <supplied>the</supplied> bow; </li1>
				<li2>Tubal and Javan, the faraway coastlands </li2>
				<li1>that have not heard <supplied>of</supplied> my fame, </li1>
				<li2>and have not seen my glory. </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p>And they shall declare my glory among the nations, <verse-number id="Is 66:20">20</verse-number>and bring all your countrymen<note>Or “brothers”</note> from all the nations <supplied>as</supplied> an offering to Yahweh on horses and chariots<note>Hebrew “chariot”</note> and in litters and on mules and camels, to<note>Or “on”</note> <idiom-start/>my holy mountain<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the mountain of holiness me”</note> Jerusalem,” says Yahweh, “just as the sons of Israel bring <supplied>an</supplied> offering in a clean vessel <supplied>to</supplied> the house of Yahweh. <verse-number id="Is 66:21">21</verse-number>And indeed, I will take some of them as priests <supplied>and</supplied> the Levites,” says Yahweh. <verse-number id="Is 66:22">22</verse-number>“For just as the new heavens and earth that I <supplied>am</supplied> about to make shall stand before me,” <idiom-start/>declares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “declaration of”</note> Yahweh, “so shall your descendants<note>Hebrew “descendant”</note> and your name stand. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Is 66:23">23</verse-number>And this shall happen: From <idiom-start/>new moon to new moon<idiom-end/><note>Literally “enough of new moon in his new moon”</note> and from <idiom-start/>Sabbath to Sabbath<idiom-end/><note>Literally “enough of Sabbath in his Sabbath”</note> all flesh shall come to bow in worship before me,” says Yahweh. <verse-number id="Is 66:24">24</verse-number>“And they shall go out and look at the corpses of the people<note>Or “men”</note> <idiom-start/>who have rebelled<idiom-end/><note>Literally “rebelling”</note> against me, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>for their worm shall not die, </li1>
				<li2>and their fire shall not be quenched, </li2>
				<li3>and they shall be an abhorrence to all flesh.” </li3>
			</ul>
		</chapter>