<chapter id="Ru 1">
			<pericope>Elimelech Takes His Family to Live in Moab</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ru 1:1">1</verse-number>And it happened in the days <supplied>when</supplied> <idiom-start/>the judges ruled<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the judging of the judges”</note> there was a famine in the land, and a man from Bethlehem <supplied>of</supplied> Judah went <idiom-start/>to reside<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to dwell as an alien”</note> in the countryside of Moab—he and his wife and his two sons. <verse-number id="Ru 1:2">2</verse-number>And the name of the man <supplied>was</supplied> Elimelech, and the name of his wife <supplied>was</supplied> Naomi, and the name<supplied>s</supplied> of his two sons <supplied>were</supplied> Mahlon and Kilion. <supplied>They were</supplied> Ephraimites from Bethlehem <supplied>in</supplied> Judah. And they went <supplied>to</supplied> the countryside of Moab and remained there. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ru 1:3">3</verse-number>But Elimelech the husband of Naomi died and she was left behind <supplied>with</supplied> <idiom-start/>her two sons<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “she and her two sons”</note> <verse-number id="Ru 1:4">4</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>they took<idiom-end/><note>Literally “they lifted up”</note> for themselves Moabite wives. The name of the one <supplied>was</supplied> Orpah and the name of the other <supplied>was</supplied> Ruth. And they lived there about ten years. <verse-number id="Ru 1:5">5</verse-number>But <idiom-start/>both<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the two of them”</note> Mahlon and Kilion died, and the woman was left without her two sons and without her husband. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Naomi Returns with Ruth</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ru 1:6">6</verse-number>And she got up, she and her daughters-in-law, and returned from the countryside of Moab, because she had heard in the countryside of Moab that Yahweh had <idiom-start/>come to the aid of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “had considered”</note> his people to give food to them. <verse-number id="Ru 1:7">7</verse-number>So she set out from the place <idiom-start/>where she was<idiom-end/><note>Literally “which she was there”</note> and her two daughters-in-law with her, and they went on the way to return to the land of Judah. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ru 1:8">8</verse-number>But Naomi said to her two daughters-in-law, “Go, each <supplied>of you</supplied> return to her mother’s house. May Yahweh <idiom-start/>show kindness to you<idiom-end/><note>Literally “do loyal love with you”</note> <supplied>just</supplied> as you did with the dead and with me. <verse-number id="Ru 1:9">9</verse-number>May Yahweh <idiom-start/>grant that you<idiom-end/><note>Literally “give to you”</note> find a resting place, each <supplied>in</supplied> the house of her husband.” And she kissed them, and they lifted up their voice<supplied>s</supplied> and cried. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ru 1:10">10</verse-number>And they said to her, “<supplied>No,</supplied> we want to return with you to your people.” <verse-number id="Ru 1:11">11</verse-number>And Naomi said, “Return, my daughters. <idiom-start/>Why do you still want to go with me<idiom-end/>?<note>Literally “To what do you want to go still for me?”</note> <supplied>Are there</supplied> sons <idiom-start/>in my womb<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in my intestines”</note> that may be husbands for you? <verse-number id="Ru 1:12">12</verse-number>Turn back, my daughters! Go, for <idiom-start/>I am too old to have a husband<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “I am too old from being to a man”</note> If I should think there is hope for me, even if I should have a husband <supplied>this</supplied> night, and even if I should bear sons, <verse-number id="Ru 1:13">13</verse-number>would you therefore wait until they were grown? Would you therefore <idiom-start/>refrain from marrying<idiom-end/>?<note>Literally “Would you therefore let yourself be hindered to not belong to a man?”</note> No, my daughters, for it is far more bitter to me than <supplied>to</supplied> you. For the hand of Yahweh has gone out against me.” <verse-number id="Ru 1:14">14</verse-number>And they lifted up their voices and cried again. And Orpah kissed her mother-in-law <supplied>goodbye</supplied>, but Ruth clung to her. <verse-number id="Ru 1:15">15</verse-number>And she said, “Look, your sister-in-law has returned to her people and to her gods. Return after your sister-in-law <supplied>too</supplied>.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ru 1:16">16</verse-number>But Ruth said, “<idiom-start/>Do not urge<idiom-end/><note>Literally “You shall not press me”</note> me to leave you <supplied>or</supplied> to return from <idiom-start/>following you<idiom-end/>!<note>Literally “from behind you”</note> For where you go, I will go, and where you lodge, I will lodge. Your people <supplied>will be</supplied> my people and your God <supplied>will be</supplied> my God. <verse-number id="Ru 1:17">17</verse-number>Where you die I will die, and there I will be buried. So may Yahweh do to me, <idiom-start/>and even more, unless<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and so may he do again, that”</note> death <idiom-start/>separates you and me<idiom-end/>!”<note>Literally “makes a separation between you and between me”</note> <verse-number id="Ru 1:18">18</verse-number><supplied>When Naomi</supplied> saw that she was determined to go with her, <idiom-start/>she said no more<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “she ceased to speak to her”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ru 1:19">19</verse-number><supplied>So</supplied> the two of them went until they came to Bethlehem. <idiom-start/>And when they came<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And it happened at the moment of coming”</note> to Bethlehem, all of the town was stirred because of them. And they said, “<supplied>Is</supplied> this Naomi?” <verse-number id="Ru 1:20">20</verse-number>And she said to them, “You should not call me Naomi; call me Mara, for Shaddai<note>Often translated “the Almighty”</note> has <idiom-start/>caused me to be very bitter<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “caused very bitterness to me”</note> <verse-number id="Ru 1:21">21</verse-number>I went <supplied>away</supplied> full, but Yahweh brought me back empty-handed! Why call me Naomi <idiom-start/>when Yahweh has testified against me<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and Yahweh answered against me”</note> and Shaddai<note>Often translated “the Almighty”</note> has brought calamity upon me?” <verse-number id="Ru 1:22">22</verse-number>So Naomi returned, and Ruth the Moabite her daughter-in-law with her, returning from the countryside of Moab. And they came <supplied>to</supplied> Bethlehem at <supplied>the</supplied> beginning of <supplied>the</supplied> harvest of barley. </p>
		</chapter>