<chapter id="Ru 3">
			<pericope>Ruth Meets Boaz at the Threshing Floor</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ru 3:1">1</verse-number>Now Naomi her mother-in-law said to her, “My daughter, should I not seek for you security that <supplied>things</supplied> may be good for you? <verse-number id="Ru 3:2">2</verse-number>So then, <supplied>is</supplied> not Boaz our kinsman whose maidservants you were with? Look, he <supplied>is</supplied> winnowing the barley at the threshing floor tonight. <verse-number id="Ru 3:3">3</verse-number>Wash, anoint yourself, put your clothing on, and go down to the threshing floor. Do not make yourself known to the man until he finishes eating and drinking. <verse-number id="Ru 3:4">4</verse-number>And when he lies, take notice of the place where he lies. And you shall go and <idiom-start/>uncover<idiom-end/><note>Literally “open”</note> his feet and lie <supplied>down</supplied>, and he shall tell you what to do.” <verse-number id="Ru 3:5">5</verse-number>And she said to her, “I will do all that you say.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ru 3:6">6</verse-number>And she went down to the threshing floor and did all that her mother-in-law had instructed her. <verse-number id="Ru 3:7">7</verse-number>And Boaz ate and drank <supplied>until</supplied> his heart was <idiom-start/>merry<idiom-end/><note>Literally “good”</note> <supplied>and then</supplied> he came to lie at the end of the grain heap. And she came in quietly and <idiom-start/>uncovered<idiom-end/><note>Literally “opened”</note> his feet and lay down. <verse-number id="Ru 3:8">8</verse-number>And it happened in the middle of the night the man was startled and he reached out and behold, a woman <supplied>was</supplied> lying at his feet. <verse-number id="Ru 3:9">9</verse-number>And he said, “Who <supplied>are</supplied> you?” And she said, “I <supplied>am</supplied> Ruth, your servant. Spread <idiom-start/>your garment<idiom-end/><note>Literally “your wing”</note> over your servant because you <supplied>are</supplied> a redeemer.” <verse-number id="Ru 3:10">10</verse-number>And he said, “You <supplied>are</supplied> blessed by Yahweh my daughter. You did better <supplied>in this</supplied> last kindness than the first by not going after young men, whether poor or rich. <verse-number id="Ru 3:11">11</verse-number>And so then my daughter, do not be afraid. All that you ask I will do for you, for the entire assembly of my people knows that you <supplied>are</supplied> a worthy woman. <verse-number id="Ru 3:12">12</verse-number>Now truly I <supplied>am</supplied> a redeemer, but there is also a redeemer <supplied>of a</supplied> closer relationship than me. <verse-number id="Ru 3:13">13</verse-number><idiom-start/>Stay tonight,<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Spend the night tonight”</note> and in the morning, if he wants to redeem you, good; but if he is not willing to redeem, <idiom-start/>then as Yahweh lives,<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the life of Yahweh”</note> I will redeem you. Lie down until the morning.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ru 3:14">14</verse-number>So she lay at his feet until morning and got up before <idiom-start/>anyone could recognize each other<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “a man could recognize his friend”</note> And he said, “It must not be known that <idiom-start/>you<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the woman”</note> came <supplied>to</supplied> the threshing floor.” <verse-number id="Ru 3:15">15</verse-number>And he said, “Bring the cloak that <supplied>is</supplied> on you and <idiom-start/>hold it out<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “hold on her”</note> And she held it out and he measured six <supplied>measures of</supplied> barley and put it on her <supplied>cloak</supplied>. Then she went <supplied>into</supplied> the city. <verse-number id="Ru 3:16">16</verse-number>And she came to her mother-in-law, and she said, “<idiom-start/>How did it go for you,<idiom-end/><note>Literally “who are you?”</note> my daughter?” And she told her all that the man did for her. <verse-number id="Ru 3:17">17</verse-number>And she said, “These six measures of barley he gave to me, for he said, ‘You shall not go empty-handed to your mother-in-law.’ ” <verse-number id="Ru 3:18">18</verse-number>And she said, “Wait, my daughter, until you know how the matter turns out, for the man will not rest but will settle the matter today.” </p>
		</chapter>