<chapter id="Ru 4">
			<pericope>Boaz Redeems Ruth</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ru 4:1">1</verse-number>And Boaz had gone up <supplied>to</supplied> the <supplied>city</supplied> gate and sat there. And look, the redeemer of whom Boaz had spoken <supplied>was</supplied> passing by. And he said, “Come over here to sit, <idiom-start/>friend<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “certain someone”</note> And he came over and sat. <verse-number id="Ru 4:2">2</verse-number>And he took ten men from the elders of the city and said, “Sit here.” And they sat. <verse-number id="Ru 4:3">3</verse-number>And he said to the redeemer, “Naomi, who returned from the countryside <supplied>of</supplied> Moab, is selling the tract of land which <supplied>was</supplied> for our brother Elimelech. <verse-number id="Ru 4:4">4</verse-number>And I thought <idiom-start/>I would tell you<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I would open your ear”</note> and say, ‘<idiom-start/>Buy it in the presence of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Buy before”</note> those sitting and before the elders of my people,’ if you want to redeem <supplied>it</supplied>, redeem <supplied>it</supplied>. But if you do not want to redeem, tell me so that I may know, for there is no one except you to redeem <supplied>it</supplied>, and I <supplied>am</supplied> after you.” And he said, “I want to redeem <supplied>it</supplied>.” <verse-number id="Ru 4:5">5</verse-number>And Boaz said, “On the day of your acquiring the field from the hand of Naomi, you also acquire Ruth the Moabite, the wife of the dead <supplied>man</supplied>, <supplied>in order</supplied> to raise up <supplied>for</supplied> the name of the dead his inheritance.” <verse-number id="Ru 4:6">6</verse-number>And the redeemer said, “I am not able to redeem for myself, lest I ruin my inheritance. You redeem for yourself my kinsman-redemption, for I am not able to redeem <supplied>it</supplied>.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ru 4:7">7</verse-number>(Now this <idiom-start/>was the custom in former times<idiom-end/><note>Literally “before faces”</note> in Israel concerning the kinsman-redemption and transfer of property: to confirm the matter, a man removed his sandal and gave <supplied>it</supplied> to his fellow countryman. This <supplied>was</supplied> the manner of attesting in Israel.) <verse-number id="Ru 4:8">8</verse-number>So the redeemer said to Boaz, “Acquire <supplied>it</supplied> for yourself,” and he removed his sandal. <verse-number id="Ru 4:9">9</verse-number>And Boaz said to the elders and all of the people, “You <supplied>are</supplied> witnesses today that I have acquired all that <supplied>was</supplied> for Elimelech and that <supplied>was</supplied> for Kilion and Mahlon from the hand of Naomi. <verse-number id="Ru 4:10">10</verse-number>And also Ruth the Moabite, the wife of Mahlon, I have acquired as a wife, to raise up the name of the dead over his inheritance, so that the name of the dead may not be cut off from his relatives and from the gate of his <supplied>birth</supplied> place. You <supplied>are</supplied> witnesses today.” <verse-number id="Ru 4:11">11</verse-number>And all of the people who <supplied>were</supplied> at the gate and the elders said, “<supplied>We are</supplied> witnesses. May Yahweh make the woman coming into your house as Rachel and as Leah, who <idiom-start/>together<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the two of them”</note> built the house of Israel. May you have strength in Ephrathah and bestow a name in Bethlehem. <verse-number id="Ru 4:12">12</verse-number>And may your house be like the house of Perez, whom Tamar bore to Judah from the offspring that Yahweh will give to you from this young woman.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Lineage of King David</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ru 4:13">13</verse-number>So Boaz took Ruth and she became his wife. And he went <supplied>in</supplied> to her, and Yahweh <idiom-start/>enabled her to conceive<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “gave to her conception”</note> and she bore a son. <verse-number id="Ru 4:14">14</verse-number>And the women said to Naomi, “Blessed be Yahweh who today <idiom-start/>did not leave you without a redeemer<idiom-end/>!<note>Literally “did not allow to be missing for you a redeemer”</note> And may his name be renowned in Israel! <verse-number id="Ru 4:15">15</verse-number>He shall be for you a restorer of life and a sustainer in your old age, for your daughter-in-law who loves you, who <supplied>is</supplied> better for you than seven sons, has borne him.” <verse-number id="Ru 4:16">16</verse-number>And Naomi took the child and she put him on her bosom and became his nurse. <verse-number id="Ru 4:17">17</verse-number>And the women of the neighborhood gave him a name, saying, “A son has been born to Naomi.” And they called his name Obed. He <supplied>was</supplied> the father of Jesse, the father of David. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ru 4:18">18</verse-number>Now these are the descendants of Perez: Perez fathered Hezron, <verse-number id="Ru 4:19">19</verse-number>and Hezron fathered Ram, and Ram fathered Amminadab, <verse-number id="Ru 4:20">20</verse-number>and Amminadab fathered Nahshon, and Nahshon fathered Salmon, <verse-number id="Ru 4:21">21</verse-number>and Salmon fathered Boaz, and Boaz fathered Obed, <verse-number id="Ru 4:22">22</verse-number>and Obed fathered Jesse, and Jesse fathered David. </p>
		</chapter>