<chapter id="2 Sa 1">
			<pericope>The Report of Saul’s Death by the Amalekite</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Sa 1:1">1</verse-number><idiom-start/>After<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And it happened after”</note> the death of Saul, David returned from defeating the Amalekites and he stayed at Ziklag two days. <verse-number id="2 Sa 1:2">2</verse-number>On the third day, a man came from the camp from <supplied>being with</supplied> Saul, with his clothes torn and with dirt on his head. <idiom-start/>When he came<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And it happened at his coming”</note> to David, he fell to the ground and bowed down. <verse-number id="2 Sa 1:3">3</verse-number>David said to him, “Where did you come from?” He said to him, “I have escaped from the camp of Israel.” <verse-number id="2 Sa 1:4">4</verse-number>Then David said to him, “<idiom-start/>How did things go<idiom-end/>?<note>Literally “What <supplied>was</supplied> the thing”</note> Please tell me.” He answered, “<idiom-start/>When<idiom-end/><note>Literally “That”</note> the army fled from the battle, and many of the people fell; also, Saul and Jonathan his son died.” <verse-number id="2 Sa 1:5">5</verse-number>Then David asked the young man who <supplied>was</supplied> reporting to him, “How do you know that Saul and his son Jonathan died?” <verse-number id="2 Sa 1:6">6</verse-number>The young man who <supplied>was</supplied> reporting to him said, “I merely happened to be on Mount Gilboa. Here Saul <supplied>was</supplied> leaning on his spear, and look, the chariots and the horsemen <supplied>were</supplied> getting close to him. <verse-number id="2 Sa 1:7">7</verse-number>When he turned around and saw me, he called to me, and I said, ‘Here I <supplied>am</supplied>.’ <verse-number id="2 Sa 1:8">8</verse-number>Then he said to me, ‘Who <supplied>are</supplied> you?’ And I said to him, ‘I <supplied>am</supplied> an Amalekite.’ <verse-number id="2 Sa 1:9">9</verse-number>He said to me, ‘Please stand over me and kill me, for convulsions have seized me, even though my life <supplied>is still</supplied> in me.’ <verse-number id="2 Sa 1:10">10</verse-number>So I stood over him and killed him, for I knew that he could not live after his falling; I took the crown that <supplied>was</supplied> on his head and <supplied>the</supplied> bracelet which <supplied>was</supplied> on his arm; and here, I have brought them to my lord. <verse-number id="2 Sa 1:11">11</verse-number>David grabbed <supplied>at</supplied> his clothes and tore them, <supplied>as did</supplied> all of the men who <supplied>were</supplied> with him. <verse-number id="2 Sa 1:12">12</verse-number>Then they mourned and wept and fasted over Saul and Jonathan his son until the evening, <supplied>as well</supplied> as over the people of Yahweh and over the house of Israel because they had fallen by the sword. <verse-number id="2 Sa 1:13">13</verse-number>Then David said to the young man who <supplied>was</supplied> reporting to him, “Where <supplied>are</supplied> you from?” And he said, “I <supplied>am</supplied> the son of an alien man. I <supplied>am</supplied> an Amalekite.” <verse-number id="2 Sa 1:14">14</verse-number>David said to him, “How <supplied>is it that</supplied> you <supplied>were</supplied> not afraid to stretch out your hand to destroy Yahweh’s anointed one?” <verse-number id="2 Sa 1:15">15</verse-number>Then David called to one of the young men and said to him, “Come near; strike him.” So he struck him down and he died. <verse-number id="2 Sa 1:16">16</verse-number>David said to him, “Your blood <supplied>is</supplied> on your head, for your mouth has testified against you by saying, ‘I killed Yahweh’s anointed one!’ ” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>David Laments Jonathan with the “Song of the Bow”</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Sa 1:17">17</verse-number>Then David sang this funeral song over Saul and over Jonathan his son. <verse-number id="2 Sa 1:18">18</verse-number>And he ordered “The Bow” to be taught to the children of Judah. Look, it <supplied>is</supplied> written on the scroll of Jashar.<note>The Book of Jashar (“the upright”) is also mentioned in Josh 10:13.</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="2 Sa 1:19">19</verse-number>“The glory of Israel <supplied>is</supplied> on your high places; how <supplied>the</supplied> mighty have fallen! </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="2 Sa 1:20">20</verse-number>Do not tell it in Gath; do not proclaim it in the streets of Ashkelon, </li1>
				<li2>lest the daughters of <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines rejoice, </li2>
				<li2>lest the daughters of the uncircumcised exult. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="2 Sa 1:21">21</verse-number>O mountains of Gilboa, <supplied>let there be</supplied> no dew or rain upon you </li1>
				<li2>or on the fields of <supplied>grain for</supplied> offerings, </li2>
				<li2>for there the small shield of <supplied>the</supplied> mighty <supplied>was</supplied> defiled, </li2>
				<li2>the small shield of Saul <supplied>was</supplied> not anointed with oil. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="2 Sa 1:22">22</verse-number>From the blood of <supplied>the</supplied> slain, from the fat of <supplied>the</supplied> mighty, </li1>
				<li2>the bow of Jonathan did not turn back, </li2>
				<li2>and the sword of Saul did not return <idiom-start/>without effect<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “empty handedly”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="2 Sa 1:23">23</verse-number>Saul and Jonathan <supplied>were</supplied> beloved and pleasant in their lives </li1>
				<li2>and <supplied>were</supplied> not separated in their death. </li2>
				<li2>They <supplied>were</supplied> swifter than eagles, stronger than lions. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="2 Sa 1:24">24</verse-number>O daughters of Israel, weep over Saul, </li1>
				<li2>the one who clothed you with crimson, </li2>
				<li2>the one who <idiom-start/>adorned your clothing with golden ornaments<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “put gold ornaments on your clothing”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="2 Sa 1:25">25</verse-number>How <supplied>the</supplied> mighty have fallen in the midst of the battle; </li1>
				<li2>Jonathan <supplied>lies</supplied> slain on your high places. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="2 Sa 1:26">26</verse-number><idiom-start/>I am distressed<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Distress <supplied>is</supplied> for me”</note> over you, my brother Jonathan. </li1>
				<li2>you <supplied>were</supplied> very dear to me; </li2>
				<li2>your love <supplied>was</supplied> more wonderful to me than the love of women. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="2 Sa 1:27">27</verse-number>How <supplied>the</supplied> mighty have fallen and the weapons of warfare perished.” </li1>
			</ul>
		</chapter>