<chapter id="2 Sa 2">
			<pericope>David Moves to Hebron</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Sa 2:1">1</verse-number>It happened after this that David inquired of Yahweh, saying, “Shall I go up into one of the cities of Judah?” And Yahweh said to him, “Go up.” David asked, “Where shall I go up?” And he said, “To Hebron.” <verse-number id="2 Sa 2:2">2</verse-number>So David went up there <idiom-start/>along with<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and also”</note> his two wives, Ahinoam <idiom-start/>from Jezreel<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the Jezreelitess”</note> and Abigail the wife of Nabal the Carmelite. <verse-number id="2 Sa 2:3">3</verse-number>Also, David brought up his men who <supplied>were</supplied> with him, each <idiom-start/>with<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and”</note> his household, and they settled in the towns of Hebron. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>David Anointed King over Judah at Hebron</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Sa 2:4">4</verse-number>Then the men of Judah came, and they anointed David there as king over the house of Judah, and they told David, “The men of Jabesh-Gilead buried Saul.” <verse-number id="2 Sa 2:5">5</verse-number>So David sent messengers to the men of Jabesh-Gilead and said to them, “May you be blessed by Yahweh because you did this loyal love with your lord, with Saul, and you buried him. <verse-number id="2 Sa 2:6">6</verse-number>Now may Yahweh show loyal love and faithfulness with you. I will also show the good with you that you have done in this matter. <verse-number id="2 Sa 2:7">7</verse-number>So then, let your hands be strong and <idiom-start/>be valiant<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “as sons of ability”</note> for your lord Saul <supplied>is</supplied> dead, and the house of Judah has anointed me as king over them.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Ish-Bosheth over Israel</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Sa 2:8">8</verse-number>But Abner the son of Ner, the commander of Saul’s army, had taken Ish-Bosheth the son of Saul and brought him over <supplied>to</supplied> Mahanaim. <verse-number id="2 Sa 2:9">9</verse-number>He made him king over Gilead, over the Ashurites, over Jezreel, over Ephraim, over Benjamin, and over Israel, all of it. <verse-number id="2 Sa 2:10">10</verse-number>Ish-Bosheth the son of Saul <supplied>was</supplied> forty years old when he became king over Israel and he reigned two years; however, the house of Judah <idiom-start/>followed<idiom-end/><note>Literally “were after”</note> David. <verse-number id="2 Sa 2:11">11</verse-number>The number of days that David was king over Hebron, over the house of Judah, <supplied>was</supplied> seven years and six months. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>War between Judah and Israel</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Sa 2:12">12</verse-number>Abner the son of Ner and the servants of Ish-Bosheth the son of Saul went out from Mahanaim to Gibeon. <verse-number id="2 Sa 2:13">13</verse-number>Then Joab the son of Zeruiah and the servants of David went out, and they met at the pool of Gibeon. The one group sat on one side of the pool, and the other sat on the other side. <verse-number id="2 Sa 2:14">14</verse-number>Abner said to Joab, “Let the young men come up and fight in our presence.” And Joab said, “Let them come up.” <verse-number id="2 Sa 2:15">15</verse-number>So they came forward and passed by in number: twelve for Benjamin and for Ish-Bosheth the son of Saul, and twelve from the servants of David. <verse-number id="2 Sa 2:16">16</verse-number>Then each seized his <idiom-start/>opponent<idiom-end/><note>Literally “neighbor”</note> by the head and <supplied>each thrust</supplied> his sword in the side of his opponent, so they fell together. So they<note>Hebrew “he”</note> called the name of that place Helkath Hazzurim,<note>Helkath Hazzurim possibly means “the slippery slope”</note> which <supplied>is</supplied> in Gibeon. <verse-number id="2 Sa 2:17">17</verse-number>Then the battle <idiom-start/>became increasingly fierce<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and it was/became strong/fierce until very”</note> on that day, and Abner and the men of Israel <supplied>were</supplied> defeated before the servants of David. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Sa 2:18">18</verse-number>The three sons of Zeruiah were there, Joab and Abishai and Asahel. Now Asahel <supplied>was</supplied> swift with his feet as one of the gazelles which <supplied>is</supplied> in the open field. <verse-number id="2 Sa 2:19">19</verse-number>So Asahel pursued<note>Hebrew “pursued after”</note> Abner, and he did not turn aside to the right or to the left from going after Abner. <verse-number id="2 Sa 2:20">20</verse-number>Abner turned around and said, “<supplied>Are</supplied> you this Asahel?” And he said, “Yes.” <verse-number id="2 Sa 2:21">21</verse-number>Abner said to him, “Turn aside to your right or to your left; seize for yourself one of the young men, and take his belongings for yourself.” But Asahel <supplied>was</supplied> not willing to turn aside from him. <verse-number id="2 Sa 2:22">22</verse-number>So Abner said to Asahel <idiom-start/>once again<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “and he again did again”</note> “<idiom-start/>For your own sake<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “for yourself”</note> turn aside <idiom-start/>from following me<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “from after me”</note> Why should I strike you down to the ground? How could I <idiom-start/>show my face<idiom-end/><note>Literally “lift up my face”</note> to Joab your brother?” <verse-number id="2 Sa 2:23">23</verse-number>But he refused to turn away, so Abner struck him in the stomach with the butt of the spear, and the spear went out of his back. He fell there and he died <idiom-start/>on the spot<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “in his place”</note> <idiom-start/>Then<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And it happened”</note> all who came to the place where Asahel fell and died <supplied>just</supplied> stood there. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Sa 2:24">24</verse-number>So Joab and Abishai pursued<note>Hebrew “pursued after”</note> Abner <idiom-start/>when<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and”</note> the sun went down. And they came to the hill <supplied>country</supplied> of Ammah, which <supplied>is</supplied> <idiom-start/>before Giah<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<supplied>lies</supplied> on the face of Giah”</note> <supplied>on</supplied> the way to the wilderness of Gibeon. <verse-number id="2 Sa 2:25">25</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Benjamin rallied after Abner, and they became as one fighting group and stood on the top of a certain hill. <verse-number id="2 Sa 2:26">26</verse-number>Then Abner called to Joab and said, “Will <supplied>the</supplied> sword devour forever? Do you not know that <supplied>there</supplied> will be bitterness in the end? <idiom-start/>How long<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And up to when”</note> will you not tell the people to turn <idiom-start/>away from pursuing<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from after”</note> their brothers?” <verse-number id="2 Sa 2:27">27</verse-number>Joab said, “<idiom-start/>As God lives<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “The life of God”</note> for if you had not spoken, the people would surely have gone up in the morning, each <supplied>one of them</supplied> <idiom-start/>from following after<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from after”</note> his brother.” <verse-number id="2 Sa 2:28">28</verse-number>Then Joab blew on the trumpet and all the people stopped, and they no longer pursued after Israel, and they did not fight with them again. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Sa 2:29">29</verse-number>Then Abner and his men went through the Arabah all that night, and they crossed over the Jordan. They went all the forenoon and came to Mahanaim. <verse-number id="2 Sa 2:30">30</verse-number>After Joab returned from <supplied>pursuing</supplied><note>Hebrew “after”</note> Abner, he gathered all the people; nineteen of the servants of David <supplied>were</supplied> missing <supplied>along</supplied> with Asahel. <verse-number id="2 Sa 2:31">31</verse-number>The servants of David had killed some of the Benjaminites among the men of Abner; three hundred and sixty men had died. <verse-number id="2 Sa 2:32">32</verse-number>Then they picked up Asahel and buried him in the grave of his father, which <supplied>was at</supplied> Bethlehem. Joab and his men went all that night <idiom-start/><supplied>arriving</supplied> in Hebron at first light<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “it became light for them in Hebron”</note> </p>
		</chapter>