<chapter id="2 Sa 4">
			<pericope>Ish-Bosheth is Assassinated</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Sa 4:1">1</verse-number>When the son of Saul heard that Abner had died in Hebron, <idiom-start/>his courage failed<idiom-end/><note>Literally “his hands hung limp”</note> and all of Israel <supplied>was</supplied> horrified. <verse-number id="2 Sa 4:2">2</verse-number>Two of the men, commanders of the raiding bands, were <supplied>for</supplied> the son of Saul. The name of one <supplied>was</supplied> Baanah, and the name of the other <supplied>was</supplied> Recab, the sons of Rimmon the Beerothite from the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Benjamin; also, Beeroth <supplied>was</supplied> regarded <supplied>as belonging</supplied> to Benjamin. <verse-number id="2 Sa 4:3">3</verse-number>The Beerothites fled to Gittaim, and they are resident aliens there until this day. <verse-number id="2 Sa 4:4">4</verse-number>(Now Jonathan the son of Saul had a son who <supplied>was</supplied> crippled in the feet. He <supplied>was</supplied> five years old when the message of Saul and Jonathan came from Jezreel, and his nurse had picked him up and fled. It happened that as she <supplied>was</supplied> hurrying away to flee, he fell and became crippled. His name <supplied>was</supplied> Mephibosheth.) <verse-number id="2 Sa 4:5">5</verse-number>When the sons of Rimmon the Beerothite, Recab and Baanah, set out, they came at the heat of the day to the house of Ish-Bosheth while <idiom-start/>he <supplied>was</supplied> taking a noontime rest<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “he <supplied>was</supplied> lying with the bed at noon”</note> <verse-number id="2 Sa 4:6">6</verse-number>They came as far as the middle of the house <supplied>as if</supplied> takers of wheat, and they struck him in the stomach. Then Recab and Baanah his brother escaped. <verse-number id="2 Sa 4:7">7</verse-number>When they had come <supplied>into</supplied> the house, he <supplied>was</supplied> lying on his couch <idiom-start/>in his bedchamber<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “in the room of his lying”</note> and they attacked him and killed him. Then they <idiom-start/>beheaded him<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “they took away his head”</note> and they took his head and went on the way of the Arabah all night. <verse-number id="2 Sa 4:8">8</verse-number>They brought the head of Ish-Bosheth to David at Hebron, and they said to the king, “Here <supplied>is</supplied> the head of Ish-Bosheth, the son of Saul your enemy, who sought your life. Yahweh has given to my lord the king vengeance this day on Saul and on his offspring.” <verse-number id="2 Sa 4:9">9</verse-number>Then David answered Recab and Baanah his brother, the sons of Rimmon the Beerothite, and he said to them, “<idiom-start/>As Yahweh lives<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “The life of Yahweh”</note> who redeemed my soul from all trouble, <verse-number id="2 Sa 4:10">10</verse-number>when the <supplied>one</supplied> who told me, “Look, Saul <supplied>is</supplied> dead,” <idiom-start/>thought that he <supplied>was</supplied> bringing good news<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “and he was as <supplied>one</supplied> bringing good news in his eyes”</note> I seized him and killed him at Ziklag, which <supplied>was</supplied> as my giving the news <supplied>back</supplied> to him. <verse-number id="2 Sa 4:11">11</verse-number><idiom-start/>How much more<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Also”</note> when wicked men kill a righteous man in his house, on his bed! So then, shall I not seek his lifeblood from your hand, so that I may destroy you from the earth?” <verse-number id="2 Sa 4:12">12</verse-number>Then David commanded the young men, and they killed them, and they cut off their hands and their feet, and they hung <supplied>them</supplied> at the pool at Hebron, but the head of Ish-Bosheth they took and buried in the grave of Abner at Hebron. </p>
		</chapter>