<chapter id="2 Sa 5">
			<pericope>David Anointed as King over All of Israel</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Sa 5:1">1</verse-number>So all the tribes of Israel came to David at Hebron, and they said, “Here we <supplied>are</supplied>, <idiom-start/>we are your flesh and blood<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “We <supplied>are</supplied> your bone and your flesh”</note> <verse-number id="2 Sa 5:2">2</verse-number><idiom-start/>For some time<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “Both yesterday and three days before”</note> when Saul was king over us, <idiom-start/>you were leading Israel in and out<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “you were going out and coming in, Israel.” (So <i>Kethib</i>; <i>Qere</i> reads “bringing out and bringing in Israel”)</note> Yahweh had said to you, ‘You shall be the shepherd of my people Israel, and you will be the leader over Israel.’ ” <verse-number id="2 Sa 5:3">3</verse-number>All the elders of Israel came to the king at Hebron, and King David <idiom-start/>made a covenant<idiom-end/><note>Literally “cut a covenant”</note> with them at Hebron in the presence of Yahweh; then they anointed David as king over Israel. <verse-number id="2 Sa 5:4">4</verse-number>David <supplied>was</supplied> thirty years old when he began to reign; he reigned forty years. <verse-number id="2 Sa 5:5">5</verse-number>He reigned over Judah at Hebron <supplied>for</supplied> seven years and six months; and he reigned over all Israel and Judah at Jerusalem <supplied>for</supplied> thirty-three years. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Capture and Growth of Jerusalem</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Sa 5:6">6</verse-number>The king and his men went to Jerusalem, to the Jebusites, the inhabitants of the land. They said to David, “You will not come here, for even the blind and the lame can turn you back, saying, ‘David cannot come here.’ ” <verse-number id="2 Sa 5:7">7</verse-number>David captured the fortress of Zion, the city of David. <verse-number id="2 Sa 5:8">8</verse-number>David had said, “On that day <idiom-start/>when we attack the Jebusites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “in all of the striking down the Jebusites”</note> one must attack the lame and the blind, <supplied>those</supplied> who hate the soul of David, by <supplied>means of</supplied> the water supply.” For thus the blind and the lame would say, “He cannot come into the house.” <verse-number id="2 Sa 5:9">9</verse-number>David occupied the fortress and called it the city of David. And David built all around <supplied>it</supplied> from the Millo and <idiom-start/>inward<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to the house”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Sa 5:10">10</verse-number>David <idiom-start/>continued growing stronger and stronger<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “went going and great”</note> and Yahweh the God of hosts <supplied>was</supplied> with him. <verse-number id="2 Sa 5:11">11</verse-number>So Hiram, the king of Tyre, sent messengers to David, <supplied>along with</supplied> cedar trees and <idiom-start/>craftsmen skilled in wood and in stone masonry<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “skilled craftsmen of wood and skilled craftsmen of stone wall”</note> and they built a house for David. <verse-number id="2 Sa 5:12">12</verse-number>David realized that Yahweh had established him as king over Israel and that he had exalted his kingdom because of his people Israel. <verse-number id="2 Sa 5:13">13</verse-number>David took more concubines and wives from Jerusalem after he came from Hebron, and more sons and daughters <supplied>were</supplied> born to him. <verse-number id="2 Sa 5:14">14</verse-number>These <supplied>are</supplied> the names of the ones born to him in Jerusalem: Shammua and Shobab and Nathan and Solomon; <verse-number id="2 Sa 5:15">15</verse-number>Ibhar and Elishua and Nepheg and Japhia; <verse-number id="2 Sa 5:16">16</verse-number>Elishama and Eliada and Eliphelet. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>War with the Philistines</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Sa 5:17">17</verse-number>When <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines heard that they had anointed David as king over Israel, all <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines went up to seek David, but David heard and went down to the stronghold.<note>Thought by many to be the stronghold of Masada</note> <verse-number id="2 Sa 5:18">18</verse-number>Now <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines had come, and they spread out in the Valley of Rephaim. <verse-number id="2 Sa 5:19">19</verse-number>And David inquired of Yahweh, saying, “Shall I go up to the Philistines? Will you give them into my hands?” Yahweh said to David, “Go up, for <idiom-start/>I will certainly give<idiom-end/><note>Literally “giving I will give”</note> <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines into your hand.” <verse-number id="2 Sa 5:20">20</verse-number>So David came to Baal Perazim and defeated them there; and David said, “Yahweh has burst through my enemies before me like the bursting of water.” Therefore he called the name of that place Baal Perazim.<note>Baal Perazim may mean “the master of the bursting through”</note> <verse-number id="2 Sa 5:21">21</verse-number>They had left their idols there, so David and his men carried them away. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Sa 5:22">22</verse-number><idiom-start/>Once again<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And they again did again”</note> <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines came up and spread out in the Valley of Rephaim. <verse-number id="2 Sa 5:23">23</verse-number>So David inquired of Yahweh, but he said, “You shall not go up. <supplied>Rather,</supplied> go around to their rear and come to them from opposite the balsam trees. <verse-number id="2 Sa 5:24">24</verse-number><idiom-start/>And it shall be<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And it shall happen”</note> that when you hear the sound of marching in the tops of the balsam trees, then pay attention, for then Yahweh has gone out before you to strike down the army of <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines.” <verse-number id="2 Sa 5:25">25</verse-number>So David did thus, just as Yahweh had commanded him, and he struck down <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines from Geba <idiom-start/>all the way<idiom-end/><note>Literally “as you go up”</note> to Gezer. </p>
		</chapter>