<chapter id="2 Sa 7">
			<pericope>Yahweh Makes a Covenant with David</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Sa 7:1">1</verse-number>It happened that the king settled in his house. (Now Yahweh had given rest to him from all his enemies all around.) <verse-number id="2 Sa 7:2">2</verse-number>And the king said to Nathan the prophet, “Look, please, I <supplied>am</supplied> living in a house of cedar, but the ark of God <supplied>is</supplied> staying in the middle of the tent.” <verse-number id="2 Sa 7:3">3</verse-number>Nathan said to the king, “Go and do all that <supplied>is</supplied> in your heart, for Yahweh <supplied>is</supplied> with you.” <verse-number id="2 Sa 7:4">4</verse-number>But it happened <idiom-start/>that night<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “in the night the that”</note> the word of Yahweh came<note>Hebrew “was”</note> to Nathan, saying, <verse-number id="2 Sa 7:5">5</verse-number>“Go and tell my servant David, ‘Thus says Yahweh: “<supplied>Are</supplied> you the one to build for me a house for my dwelling? <verse-number id="2 Sa 7:6">6</verse-number>For I have not dwelt in a house from the day I brought up the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> from Egypt until this day; <supplied>rather,</supplied> I <supplied>was</supplied> going about in a tent and in a tabernacle. <verse-number id="2 Sa 7:7">7</verse-number>In all of my going about among all the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> did I speak a word with one of the tribes of Israel whom I commanded to shepherd my people Israel, saying, ‘Why did you not build me a cedar house?’ ” ’ <verse-number id="2 Sa 7:8">8</verse-number>So then, thus you shall say to my servant David, ‘Thus says Yahweh of hosts, “I took you from the pasture <idiom-start/>from following<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from behind”</note> the sheep to be a leader over my people, over Israel, <verse-number id="2 Sa 7:9">9</verse-number>and I have been with you <idiom-start/>everywhere you went<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “in all that you went”</note> I have cut off all of your enemies from in front of you, and I will make a great name for you, as the name of the great <supplied>ones</supplied> who <supplied>are</supplied> on the earth. <verse-number id="2 Sa 7:10">10</verse-number>I will make a place for my people Israel, and I will plant them<note>Hebrew “him”</note> so that they<note>Hebrew “he”</note> can dwell <idiom-start/>in their own place<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “under him”</note> They will not tremble <supplied>any</supplied> longer, and the children of wickedness will not afflict them again, as in the former days. <verse-number id="2 Sa 7:11">11</verse-number><idiom-start/>In the manner that<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And as far as” or “And from the day”</note> I appointed judges over my people Israel, I will give you rest from all your enemies. And Yahweh declares to you that Yahweh will build a house for you. <verse-number id="2 Sa 7:12">12</verse-number>When your days <supplied>are</supplied> full and you lie down with your ancestors,<note>Or “fathers”</note> I will raise up your offspring after you who will go out from your body, and I will establish his kingdom. <verse-number id="2 Sa 7:13">13</verse-number>He will build a house for my name, and I will establish the throne of his kingdom forever. <verse-number id="2 Sa 7:14">14</verse-number>I will be a father to him, and he will be a son for me, whom I will punish when he does wrong, with a rod of men and with blows of the <idiom-start/>human beings<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “children of men”</note> <verse-number id="2 Sa 7:15">15</verse-number>But my loyal love shall not depart from him as I took <supplied>it</supplied> from Saul, whom I removed from before you. <verse-number id="2 Sa 7:16">16</verse-number>Your house and your kingdom shall endure forever before you; your throne shall be established forever.” ’ ” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>David Responds to Yahweh’s Covenant</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Sa 7:17">17</verse-number>According to all these words and according to all this vision, this Nathan spoke to David. <verse-number id="2 Sa 7:18">18</verse-number>Then King David went and sat before Yahweh and said, “Who <supplied>am</supplied> I, my lord Yahweh, and what <supplied>is</supplied> my house that you have brought me up to <idiom-start/>this place<idiom-end/>?<note>Literally “here”</note> <verse-number id="2 Sa 7:19">19</verse-number>Still, this <supplied>was</supplied> <idiom-start/>insignificant<idiom-end/><note>Literally “small”</note> in your eyes, my lord Yahweh, and also you have spoken about the house of your servant from afar, and this <supplied>may be</supplied> the teaching of humans, my lord Yahweh. <verse-number id="2 Sa 7:20">20</verse-number><idiom-start/>What more can David say to you<idiom-end/>?<note>Literally “And what can David still add to say”</note> You know your servant, my lord Yahweh. <verse-number id="2 Sa 7:21">21</verse-number>Because of your word and according to your heart, you have done all of this great thing, <supplied>in order</supplied> to let your servant know. <verse-number id="2 Sa 7:22">22</verse-number>Therefore you <supplied>are</supplied> great, my lord Yahweh, for there is no one like you, and there <supplied>is</supplied> no god except you, in all that we have heard with our ears. <verse-number id="2 Sa 7:23">23</verse-number>Who <supplied>is</supplied> like your people, like Israel? <supplied>Israel is</supplied> the one nation on earth whose God <idiom-start/>led them<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “went”; LXX reads “led”</note> <supplied>in order</supplied> to redeem a people for himself, and to make a name for himself, and to do for you<note>David switches pronouns from the third person to the second person</note> the great and awesome things for your land in the presence of your people whom he redeemed for himself from Egypt, <supplied>from the</supplied> nations and their gods. <verse-number id="2 Sa 7:24">24</verse-number>You have established your people Israel for yourself as a people forever, and you, O Yahweh, have become their God. <verse-number id="2 Sa 7:25">25</verse-number>So then, Yahweh God, the word that you have spoken concerning your servant and concerning his house, confirm it forever, and do just as you have promised. <verse-number id="2 Sa 7:26">26</verse-number>Your name shall be great forever, <idiom-start/>and they will say<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “saying”</note> ‘Yahweh of hosts <supplied>is</supplied> God over Israel’; and the house of your servant David shall be established before you. <verse-number id="2 Sa 7:27">27</verse-number>For you, O Yahweh of hosts, <supplied>are</supplied> God of Israel! You have revealed to the ear of your servant, ‘I will build a house for you’; therefore your servant <idiom-start/>has found courage<idiom-end/><note>Literally “has found his heart”</note> to pray this prayer to you. <verse-number id="2 Sa 7:28">28</verse-number>Now, my Lord Yahweh, you alone <supplied>are</supplied> God, and your words <supplied>are</supplied><note>Hebrew “will be”</note> true. You have promised this good to your servant. <verse-number id="2 Sa 7:29">29</verse-number>So then, be content and bless the house of your servant to be forever in your presence, for you, my Lord Yahweh, have spoken, and because of your blessing, may the house of your servant be blessed forever.” </p>
		</chapter>