<chapter id="2 Sa 10">
			<pericope>The Ammonites Refuse David’s Loyal Love</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Sa 10:1">1</verse-number><idiom-start/>Afterwards the king of the Ammonites died<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “And it happened afterwards <supplied>that</supplied> the king of the sons of Ammon died”</note> and his son Hanun ruled in his place. <verse-number id="2 Sa 10:2">2</verse-number>David said, “I will show loyal love with Hanun, the son of Nahash, as his father showed loyal love with me.” So David sent to console him concerning his father, by the hand of his servants. And the servants of David came to the land of the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sons/children of Ammon”</note> <verse-number id="2 Sa 10:3">3</verse-number>But the commanders of the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Ammon”</note> said to Hanun their master, “<idiom-start/>In your opinion<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “In your eyes”</note> <supplied>is</supplied> David honoring your father because he has sent condolences to you? <supplied>Is</supplied> it not in order to search the city, to spy it out, and to overthrow it <supplied>that</supplied> David sent his servants to you?” <verse-number id="2 Sa 10:4">4</verse-number>Then Hanun took the servants of David, and he shaved off half of their beards and cut their garments off in the middle up to their buttocks, then sent them away. <verse-number id="2 Sa 10:5">5</verse-number>When they told David, he sent to meet them, for the men were greatly ashamed. And the king said, “Remain in Jericho until your beards have grown, and then you can return.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Israel Fights Ammon and Aram</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Sa 10:6">6</verse-number>When the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Ammon”</note> saw that they had become odious to David, the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Ammon”</note> sent <supplied>word</supplied> and hired Aram Beth-Rehob and Aram-Zobah, twenty thousand infantry; and <supplied>they also hired</supplied> the king of Maacah, a thousand men, and the men of Tob, twelve thousand men. <verse-number id="2 Sa 10:7">7</verse-number>When David heard, he sent Joab and all the army of mighty warriors. <verse-number id="2 Sa 10:8">8</verse-number>The <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Ammon”</note> came out and <idiom-start/>drew up a battle formation<idiom-end/><note>Literally “drew up battle”</note> at the entrance of the gate, but Aram-Zobah and Rehob and the men of Tob and Maacah <supplied>were</supplied> alone in the open field. <verse-number id="2 Sa 10:9">9</verse-number>When Joab saw that <idiom-start/>the battle was to be fought on two fronts<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the face of the battle <supplied>was</supplied> against him in front and in the rear”</note> he chose from all <supplied>the</supplied> members of the elite troops of Israel and <idiom-start/>lined them up for battle<idiom-end/><note>Literally “arrayed”</note> to meet Aram. <verse-number id="2 Sa 10:10">10</verse-number>The rest of the army he placed into the hand of his brother Abishai, who <idiom-start/>arranged them in battle lines<idiom-end/><note>Literally “arrayed”</note> to meet the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sons/children of Ammon”</note> <verse-number id="2 Sa 10:11">11</verse-number>Then he said, “If Aram <supplied>is</supplied> stronger than I <supplied>am</supplied>, you must become my deliverer; but if the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Ammon”</note> <supplied>are</supplied> too strong for you, then I will come to rescue you. <verse-number id="2 Sa 10:12">12</verse-number>Be strong, and let us strengthen ourselves for the sake of the people and for the sake of the cities of our God. May Yahweh do <supplied>what is</supplied> good in his eyes. <verse-number id="2 Sa 10:13">13</verse-number>Joab and all the people who <supplied>were</supplied> with him moved forward into the battle against Aram, and they fled from before him. <verse-number id="2 Sa 10:14">14</verse-number>When the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Ammon”</note> saw that Aram had fled, they fled from before Abishai and entered the city. Then Joab returned from <supplied>fighting</supplied> against the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Ammon”</note> and came to Jerusalem. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Arameans Regroup for Attack</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Sa 10:15">15</verse-number>When the Arameans saw that they <supplied>were</supplied> defeated before Israel, they gathered themselves together. <verse-number id="2 Sa 10:16">16</verse-number>Then Hadadezer sent and brought out the Arameans who <supplied>were</supplied> beyond the Euphrates, and they came to Helam. Now Shobach, the commander of the army of Hadadezer, <idiom-start/>was at their head<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “before the face of them”</note> <verse-number id="2 Sa 10:17">17</verse-number>David <supplied>was</supplied> told, so he gathered all Israel and crossed over the Jordan and came to Helam. Aram <idiom-start/>arranged themselves in battle lines<idiom-end/><note>Literally “arrayed”</note> to meet David, and they fought with him. <verse-number id="2 Sa 10:18">18</verse-number>And Aram fled before Israel, and David killed from <supplied>the</supplied> Arameans seven hundred chariot teams and forty thousand horsemen. He struck down Shobach, the commander of his army, and he died there. <verse-number id="2 Sa 10:19">19</verse-number>When all the kings, the servants of Hadadezer, saw that he had been defeated before Israel, they made peace with Israel and served them, and Aram <supplied>was</supplied> afraid to help the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Ammon”</note> any longer. </p>
		</chapter>