<chapter id="2 Sa 12">
			<pericope>Nathan Reproves David</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Sa 12:1">1</verse-number>So Yahweh sent Nathan to David, and he came to him and said, “Two men were in a certain city; one <supplied>was</supplied> rich and the other <supplied>was</supplied> poor. <verse-number id="2 Sa 12:2">2</verse-number>The rich <supplied>man</supplied> had very many flocks and herds, <verse-number id="2 Sa 12:3">3</verse-number>but the poor <supplied>man</supplied> had nothing except for one small ewe lamb which he had bought. He had nurtured her, and she grew up with him and with his children together. She used to eat from his morsel and drink from his cup, and she used to lie in his lap and became like a daughter for him. <verse-number id="2 Sa 12:4">4</verse-number>And a visitor came to the rich man, but he <idiom-start/>was reluctant<idiom-end/><note>Literally “felt sorry”</note> to take from his flocks or from his herds to prepare a meal for the traveler when he came to him. So he took the ewe lamb of the poor man and prepared it for the man who had come to him.” <verse-number id="2 Sa 12:5">5</verse-number>Then <idiom-start/>the anger of David was kindled<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the nose of David became very hot”</note> against the man, and he said to Nathan, “<idiom-start/>As Yahweh lives<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “The life of Yahweh”</note> the man who has done this <idiom-start/>deserves to die<idiom-end/>!<note>Literally “<supplied>is</supplied> a son of death”</note> <verse-number id="2 Sa 12:6">6</verse-number>He shall restore the ewe lamb fourfold because he has done this thing, and because he had no pity.” <verse-number id="2 Sa 12:7">7</verse-number>Then Nathan said to him, “You <supplied>are</supplied> the man! Thus says Yahweh the God of Israel: ‘I anointed you as king over Israel, and I delivered you from the hand of Saul. <verse-number id="2 Sa 12:8">8</verse-number>I gave you the household of your master and the women of your master into your lap. I also gave you the house of Israel and Judah; if <supplied>that had been too</supplied> little, I would have added to you <idiom-start/>much more<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “as here and as here”</note> <verse-number id="2 Sa 12:9">9</verse-number>Why have you despised the word of Yahweh by doing evil in his eyes?<note>Thus <i>Kethib</i>; the reading tradition (<i>Qere)</i> reads “my eyes”</note> Uriah the Hittite you have struck down with the sword, and his wife you have taken to yourself as wife! You have killed him with the sword of the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/>!<note>Literally “sons/children of Ammon”</note> <verse-number id="2 Sa 12:10">10</verse-number>So then, a sword will not turn away from your house forever, because you have despised me and have taken the wife of Uriah the Hittite to be your wife!’ <verse-number id="2 Sa 12:11">11</verse-number>Thus says Yahweh, ‘Look, I <supplied>am</supplied> going to raise up evil against you from <supplied>within</supplied> your house, and I will take your women before your eyes, and I will give them to your neighbor, and he shall sleep with your wives <idiom-start/>in broad daylight<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “before the eyes of this sun”</note> <verse-number id="2 Sa 12:12">12</verse-number>Though you did this in secret, I will do this thing before all of Israel <idiom-start/>in broad daylight<idiom-end/>!’ ”<note>Literally “before the sun”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>David Repents, But the Child Dies</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Sa 12:13">13</verse-number>Then David said to Nathan, “I have sinned against Yahweh!”<note>See Pss 32:1–5; 51:1–13</note> Nathan said to David, “Yahweh has also forgiven your sin; you shall not die. <verse-number id="2 Sa 12:14">14</verse-number>But because you have <idiom-start/>utterly scorned<idiom-end/><note>Literally “scorning you have scorned.” The term “enemies of” in the MT is likely a textual corruption and is deleted here</note> Yahweh in this matter, the son born for you <idiom-start/>will certainly die<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “dying will die” (compare Gen 2:17)</note> <verse-number id="2 Sa 12:15">15</verse-number>Then Nathan went to his house, and Yahweh struck the child that the wife of Uriah bore for David, and he became ill. <verse-number id="2 Sa 12:16">16</verse-number>David pleaded <supplied>with</supplied> God on behalf of the boy and David fasted. He went to spend the night and lay upon the ground. <verse-number id="2 Sa 12:17">17</verse-number>The elders of his household stood over him to lift him up from the ground, but he <supplied>was</supplied> not willing, and he did not eat <supplied>any</supplied> food with them. <verse-number id="2 Sa 12:18">18</verse-number>It happened on the seventh day that the child died, and the servants of David <supplied>were</supplied> afraid to tell him that the child <supplied>was</supplied> dead, for they said, “Look, when the child <supplied>was</supplied> alive, we spoke to him, but he would not listen to our voice. How can we tell him, ‘The child <supplied>is</supplied> dead’? He may do <supplied>something</supplied> evil.” <verse-number id="2 Sa 12:19">19</verse-number>When David saw that his servants <supplied>were</supplied> whispering together, he realized that the child <supplied>was</supplied> dead. Then David said to his servants, “<supplied>Is</supplied> the child dead?” And they said, “He <supplied>is</supplied> dead.” <verse-number id="2 Sa 12:20">20</verse-number>David stood up from the ground and washed and anointed himself and changed his clothing. Then he went <supplied>to</supplied> the house of Yahweh and worshiped, and he went to his <supplied>own</supplied> house. He asked, so they served him food, and he ate. <verse-number id="2 Sa 12:21">21</verse-number>Then his servants said to him, “What <supplied>is</supplied> this thing that you have done? While the child <supplied>was</supplied> alive, you fasted and wept; <supplied>now</supplied> that the child has died, you get up and eat food!” <verse-number id="2 Sa 12:22">22</verse-number>He said, “When the child <supplied>was</supplied> still alive, I fasted and I wept because I thought, ‘Who knows? Yahweh may have mercy on me that the child will live.’ <verse-number id="2 Sa 12:23">23</verse-number>But now he <supplied>is</supplied> dead. Why <supplied>should I be</supplied> fasting? <supplied>Am</supplied> I able to return him again? I <supplied>am</supplied> going to him, but he cannot return to me.” <verse-number id="2 Sa 12:24">24</verse-number>David consoled Bathsheba his wife, and he went to her and slept with her. She bore a son, and he called<note>So <i>Kethib</i>; <i>Qere</i> reads “she called”</note> him Solomon, and Yahweh loved him. <verse-number id="2 Sa 12:25">25</verse-number>He sent <supplied>word</supplied> by the hand of Nathan the prophet, so he called him Jedidiah<note>Jedidiah means “beloved of Yahweh”</note> because of Yahweh. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Battle with the Ammonites</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Sa 12:26">26</verse-number>And Joab fought against Rabbah of the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Ammon”</note> and he captured <idiom-start/>the royal city<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “city of the kingship”</note> <verse-number id="2 Sa 12:27">27</verse-number>Then Joab sent messengers to David and said, “We have fought against Rabbah, and we captured the city of the waters. <verse-number id="2 Sa 12:28">28</verse-number>So then, gather the remainder of the army and encamp against the city and capture it, lest I capture the city and my name be proclaimed over it.” <verse-number id="2 Sa 12:29">29</verse-number>So David gathered all of the army, and he went to Rabbah and fought against it and captured it. <verse-number id="2 Sa 12:30">30</verse-number>He took the crown of their king from his head. (Now its weight <supplied>was</supplied> a talent of gold, and there <supplied>was</supplied> a precious stone <supplied>in it</supplied> and it <supplied>was</supplied> put on David’s head.) He brought out the plunder of the city <idiom-start/>in great abundance<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “very many”</note> <verse-number id="2 Sa 12:31">31</verse-number>He also brought out the people who <supplied>were</supplied> in it and put them to the saws and to the iron picks and to the iron axes, and he sent them to the place of the brickmakers. Thus he used to do to all the cities of the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Ammon”</note> and he and all of the army returned to Jerusalem. </p>
		</chapter>