<chapter id="2 Sa 13">
			<pericope>Amnon Assaults His Sister Tamar</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Sa 13:1">1</verse-number>It happened afterwards that Absalom the son of David had a beautiful sister whose name <supplied>was</supplied> Tamar, and Amnon the son of David fell in love with her. <verse-number id="2 Sa 13:2">2</verse-number>And Amnon <idiom-start/>was so frustrated that he felt ill<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<supplied>was</supplied> distressed to the point of sickness”</note> because of Tamar his sister, because she <supplied>was</supplied> a virgin, and it <supplied>was</supplied> too difficult in Amnon’s eyes to do anything with her. <verse-number id="2 Sa 13:3">3</verse-number>Now Amnon had a friend whose name <supplied>was</supplied> Jonadab the son of Shimeah, the brother of David. (Now Jonadab <supplied>was</supplied> a very crafty man.) <verse-number id="2 Sa 13:4">4</verse-number>And he said to him, “Why <supplied>are</supplied> you so sullen <idiom-start/>every morning<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “in the morning, in the morning”</note> O son of the king? Will you not tell me?” And Amnon said to him, “I <supplied>am</supplied> in love with Tamar, the sister of my brother Absalom.” <verse-number id="2 Sa 13:5">5</verse-number>Then Jonadab said to him, “Lie down on your bed and appear ill. If your father comes to see you, you shall say to him, ‘Please let Tamar my sister come and give me food to eat, and let her prepare the food before my eyes, in order that I may see it and eat from her hand.’ ” <verse-number id="2 Sa 13:6">6</verse-number>So Amnon lay down and pretended to be ill, and the king came to see him. Amnon said to the king, “Please let Tamar my sister come, and let her bake two cakes before my eyes that I may eat from her hand.” <verse-number id="2 Sa 13:7">7</verse-number>So David sent to the house for Tamar, saying, “Please go to the house of Amnon your brother and prepare food for him.” <verse-number id="2 Sa 13:8">8</verse-number>Tamar went to the house of Amnon her brother. Now he <supplied>was</supplied> lying down, and she took the dough and kneaded <supplied>it</supplied> and made cakes before his eyes, and she baked the cakes. <verse-number id="2 Sa 13:9">9</verse-number>Then she took the pan and poured it out before him, but he refused to eat. Then Amnon said, “Let all <supplied>the</supplied> men go out from me.” So all <supplied>the</supplied> men went out from him. <verse-number id="2 Sa 13:10">10</verse-number>Then Amnon said to Tamar, “Bring the food <supplied>to</supplied> the private room that I may eat from your hand.” So Tamar took the cakes which she had made and brought them to Amnon her brother in<note>Hebrew “to”</note> the private room. <verse-number id="2 Sa 13:11">11</verse-number>When she brought them near to him to eat, he took hold of her and said to her, “Come, lie with me, my sister!” <verse-number id="2 Sa 13:12">12</verse-number>Then Tamar said to him, “No, my brother! Do not force me, for such a thing has not been done in Israel. Do not do this disgraceful thing! <verse-number id="2 Sa 13:13">13</verse-number>As for me, where should I take my disgrace? You will be as one of the fools in Israel. So please, speak to the king, for he will not withhold me from you.” <verse-number id="2 Sa 13:14">14</verse-number>But he <supplied>was</supplied> not willing to listen to her voice. He <supplied>was</supplied> stronger than she, and he forced her and lay with her. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Sa 13:15">15</verse-number>Then Amnon hated her <idiom-start/>very deeply<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “with a great hatred”</note> for the hatred with which he hated her <supplied>was</supplied> greater than <supplied>the</supplied> love with which he had loved her. So Amnon said to her, “Get up <supplied>and</supplied> go.” <verse-number id="2 Sa 13:16">16</verse-number>She said to him, “No, because this evil in sending me away <supplied>is</supplied> greater than the other you have done to me.” But he <supplied>was</supplied> not willing to listen to her. <verse-number id="2 Sa 13:17">17</verse-number>Then he called his young man who <supplied>was</supplied> serving him and said, “Please send this woman from me to the outside, and bolt the door behind her!” <verse-number id="2 Sa 13:18">18</verse-number>Now there <supplied>was</supplied> a long-sleeved robe on her, for so they clothed the daughters of the king who <supplied>were</supplied> virgins, in robes. His servant put her outside, and he bolted the door behind her. <verse-number id="2 Sa 13:19">19</verse-number>Tamar put ashes on her head, and she tore the long-sleeved robe which <supplied>was</supplied> on her. She put her hand on her head, and <idiom-start/>she went away, crying out as she went<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “she went, going and crying aloud”</note> <verse-number id="2 Sa 13:20">20</verse-number>Absalom her brother said to her, “<supplied>Was</supplied> Amnon your brother with you? But now, my sister, be quiet; he <supplied>is</supplied> your brother. <idiom-start/>Do not take this matter to heart<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “Do not place/set your heart to this matter”</note> So Tamar remained a desolate woman in the house of Absalom her brother. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Absalom Kills Amnon</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Sa 13:21">21</verse-number>Now King David heard all these things, and <idiom-start/>he became very angry<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “it became very hot for him”</note> <verse-number id="2 Sa 13:22">22</verse-number>Absalom did not speak with Amnon <idiom-start/>either bad or good<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “as far as from bad and up to good”</note> for Absalom hated Amnon <idiom-start/>over the matter when<idiom-end/><note>Literally “because of the thing that”</note> he raped Tamar his sister. <verse-number id="2 Sa 13:23">23</verse-number><idiom-start/>About two full years later<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “And it happened at two years <supplied>of</supplied> days”</note> Absalom’s shearers were in Baal Hazor, which <supplied>is</supplied> near Ephraim, and Absalom summoned all the sons of the king. <verse-number id="2 Sa 13:24">24</verse-number>Then Absalom went to the king and said, “Look, here <supplied>are</supplied> your servant’s shearers; please let the king and his servants go with your servant. <verse-number id="2 Sa 13:25">25</verse-number>The king said to Absalom, “No my son, not all of us shall go, so that we not be a burden to you.” And he urged him, but he <supplied>was</supplied> not willing to go, but he blessed him. <verse-number id="2 Sa 13:26">26</verse-number>So Absalom said, “But <supplied>will you</supplied> not let Amnon my brother go with us?” And the king said to him, “Why should he go with you?” <verse-number id="2 Sa 13:27">27</verse-number>But Absalom pressed him, so he sent Amnon with him and all of the sons of the king. <verse-number id="2 Sa 13:28">28</verse-number>Absalom commanded his servants, saying, “Please watch. At the moment the heart of Amnon <supplied>is</supplied> <idiom-start/>tipsy<idiom-end/><note>Literally “good”</note> with wine, then I shall say to you, ‘Strike Amnon down,’ and you shall kill him! Don’t be afraid. <supplied>Is</supplied> it not I myself who has commanded you? Be courageous and be <idiom-start/>valiant!<idiom-end/><note>Literally “as sons of ability”</note> <verse-number id="2 Sa 13:29">29</verse-number>So Absalom’s servants did to Amnon just as Absalom commanded, and all the sons of the king got up, and each mounted his mule and fled. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Sa 13:30">30</verse-number><idiom-start/>While they were on the way<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “And it happened they <supplied>were</supplied> on the way”</note> the message came to David, “Absalom has killed all the sons of the king, and not one of them <supplied>was</supplied> left.” <verse-number id="2 Sa 13:31">31</verse-number>Then the king rose and tore his garments, and he lay on the ground, and all his servants standing by <supplied>were</supplied> tearing their garments. <verse-number id="2 Sa 13:32">32</verse-number>Then Jonadab the son of Shimeah, the brother of David, responded and said, “My lord should not think that all the young men, the sons of the king, <supplied>are</supplied> dead, because only Amnon <supplied>is</supplied> dead. <idiom-start/>Absalom was talking about it<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “For it was on the mouth of Absalom”</note> as it was being determined from the day he<note>Amnon</note> raped Tamar his sister. <verse-number id="2 Sa 13:33">33</verse-number>So then, let not my lord the king set his heart on this matter, thinking, ‘All the sons of the king <supplied>are</supplied> dead,’ for only Amnon alone <supplied>is</supplied> dead.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Absalom Flees</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Sa 13:34">34</verse-number>So Absalom fled, and the young man who <supplied>was</supplied> keeping watch lifted up his eyes and saw, and there were many people coming from the road behind him from the side of the mountain. <verse-number id="2 Sa 13:35">35</verse-number>Jonadab said to the king, “Look, the sons of the king have come. According to the word of your servant, so it has come about.” <verse-number id="2 Sa 13:36">36</verse-number>When he finished speaking, look, the sons of the king came and they lifted up their voice and wept. Also, the king and all his servants wept a very great weeping. <verse-number id="2 Sa 13:37">37</verse-number>Absalom fled and went to Talmai the son of Ammihur, the king of Geshur. <supplied>David</supplied> mourned over his son <idiom-start/>day after day<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “all the days”</note> <verse-number id="2 Sa 13:38">38</verse-number>But Absalom had fled and went <supplied>to</supplied> Geshur, and he <supplied>was</supplied> there three years. <verse-number id="2 Sa 13:39">39</verse-number>King David longed to go out to Absalom, for he was consoled that Amnon had died. </p>
		</chapter>