<chapter id="2 Sa 15">
			<pericope>Absalom Leads a Rebellion</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Sa 15:1">1</verse-number>It happened afterward that Absalom made himself a chariot with horses and fifty men running before him. <verse-number id="2 Sa 15:2">2</verse-number>Absalom used to rise early in the morning, and he stood <idiom-start/>beside<idiom-end/><note>Literally “on hand of”</note> the road <supplied>at</supplied> the gate; <idiom-start/>anyone<idiom-end/><note>Literally “every man”</note> who had a legal dispute to bring to the king for judgment Absalom would call to him and say, “<idiom-start/>Where are you from?<idiom-end/>”<note>Literally “Where from this city are you?”</note> And he would say, “Your servant <supplied>is</supplied> from one of the tribes of Israel.” <verse-number id="2 Sa 15:3">3</verse-number>Then Absalom would say to him, “Look, your case <supplied>is</supplied> good and right, but for you there is no hearing with the king.” <verse-number id="2 Sa 15:4">4</verse-number>Then Absalom would say, “<idiom-start/>Oh, that someone would<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Who will …?”</note> appoint me as judge in the land, that <idiom-start/>anyone<idiom-end/><note>Literally “every man”</note> might come to me who had a legal dispute or a case, and I would give him justice.” <verse-number id="2 Sa 15:5">5</verse-number>It happened whenever anyone drew near to do obeisance to him, that he would stretch his hand and take hold of him and kiss him. <verse-number id="2 Sa 15:6">6</verse-number>Absalom did like this to all of Israel who came to the king for judgment; so Absalom stole the hearts<note>Hebrew “heart”</note> of the people of Israel. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Sa 15:7">7</verse-number>It happened at the end of four<note>So LXX, followed by Syriac and Vulgate; MT has “forty”</note> years <supplied>that</supplied> Absalom said to the king, “Please let me go and pay my vow which I have made to Yahweh in Hebron, <verse-number id="2 Sa 15:8">8</verse-number>for your servant made a vow while I <supplied>was</supplied> staying in Geshur in Aram, saying, ‘<idiom-start/>If Yahweh will indeed let me return<idiom-end/><note>Literally (following <i>Qere</i>) “If returning Yahweh will return me”</note> to Jerusalem, then I will worship Yahweh.’ ” <verse-number id="2 Sa 15:9">9</verse-number>Then the king said to him, “Go in peace.” So he got up and went to Hebron. <verse-number id="2 Sa 15:10">10</verse-number>Then Absalom sent scouts throughout all the tribes of Israel, saying, “When you hear the sound of the trumpet, you shall shout ‘Absalom has become king in Hebron!’ ” <verse-number id="2 Sa 15:11">11</verse-number>Two hundred men from Jerusalem went with Absalom as invited guests, going in their innocence as they did not know anything. <verse-number id="2 Sa 15:12">12</verse-number>Absalom sent for Ahithophel the Gilonite, the advisor of David, from his city Giloh, while he offered the sacrifices. The conspiracy <idiom-start/>grew in strength<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “became strong”</note> and the people <supplied>were</supplied> going and <idiom-start/>increasing<idiom-end/><note>Literally “many”</note> with Absalom. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>David Flees from Jerusalem</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Sa 15:13">13</verse-number>Then the messenger came to David, saying, “The hearts<note>Hebrew “heart”</note> of the men of Israel have gone after Absalom.” <verse-number id="2 Sa 15:14">14</verse-number>Then David said to all his servants who <supplied>were</supplied> with him in Jerusalem, “Get up and let us flee, for there will be no escape for us from Absalom! Hurry to go, otherwise he will come quickly and overtake us! And he will bring disaster on us and evil! He will attack the city with the edge of the sword!” <verse-number id="2 Sa 15:15">15</verse-number>Then the servants of the king said to the king, “According to all that my lord the king chooses, <idiom-start/>your servants are ready to act<idiom-end/>!”<note>Literally “here are your servants”</note> <verse-number id="2 Sa 15:16">16</verse-number>The king went out with<note>Hebrew “and”</note> all his household <idiom-start/>following him<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “at his feet”</note> but the king left behind ten concubines to look after the house. <verse-number id="2 Sa 15:17">17</verse-number>So the king went out with<note>Hebrew “and”</note> all the people <idiom-start/>following him<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “at his feet”</note> and they stopped <idiom-start/>at the last house<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “<supplied>at</supplied> the house of the distance”</note> <verse-number id="2 Sa 15:18">18</verse-number>All his servants <supplied>were</supplied> passing <idiom-start/>by him<idiom-end/>:<note>Literally “on his hand”</note> all of the Kerethites and all of the Pelethites and all of the Gittites—six hundred men <idiom-start/>who had followed him<idiom-end/><note>Literally “who had come at his feet”</note> from Gath—passing <idiom-start/>before the king<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “on the face of the king”</note> <verse-number id="2 Sa 15:19">19</verse-number>The king said to Ittai the Gittite, “Why <supplied>are</supplied> you also coming with us? Return and stay with the king, for you <supplied>are</supplied> a foreigner; moreover, you <supplied>are</supplied> an exile. <idiom-start/>You <supplied>are</supplied> far from your place<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “You as far as your place”</note> <verse-number id="2 Sa 15:20">20</verse-number>Yesterday when you came and <idiom-start/>today<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the day”</note> I have caused you to wander by going with us. Now I <supplied>am</supplied> going to where I <supplied>am</supplied> going; return and let your brothers return. <supplied>May</supplied> loyal love and faithfulness <supplied>be</supplied> with you.” <verse-number id="2 Sa 15:21">21</verse-number>But Ittai answered the king and said, “<idiom-start/>As Yahweh lives<idiom-end/><note>Literally “The life of Yahweh”</note> and <idiom-start/>my lord the king lives<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the life of my lord the king”</note> surely in the place wherever my lord the king shall be, if for death or if for life, surely there your servant will be.” <verse-number id="2 Sa 15:22">22</verse-number>Then David said to Ittai, “Go and pass over.” So Ittai the Gittite passed over and all his men and all of the little children who <supplied>were</supplied> with him. <verse-number id="2 Sa 15:23">23</verse-number>All of the land <supplied>was</supplied> weeping <supplied>with</supplied> a loud voice as all the people <supplied>were</supplied> passing by and the king <supplied>was</supplied> crossing through the Wadi Kidron, and all the people <supplied>were</supplied> passing <idiom-start/>on the road to the wilderness<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “on the face of the road with the wilderness”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Priests Offer Sacrifices for David</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Sa 15:24">24</verse-number>Suddenly Zadok <supplied>was</supplied> there, and all of the Levites with him, carrying the ark of the covenant of God. They set the ark of God down, and Abiathar offered sacrifices until all the people passed out of the city. <verse-number id="2 Sa 15:25">25</verse-number>The king said to Zadok, “Let the ark of God return to the city. If I find favor in the eyes of Yawheh, he will let me return and let me see him in his dwelling place. <verse-number id="2 Sa 15:26">26</verse-number>But if he says, ‘I take no pleasure in you,’ then <idiom-start/>I am ready<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “here I <supplied>am</supplied>”</note> Let him do to me that which <supplied>is</supplied> good in his eyes. <verse-number id="2 Sa 15:27">27</verse-number>Then the king said to Zadok the priest, “<supplied>Are</supplied> you a seer? Return to the city in peace, <supplied>with</supplied> Ahimaaz your son and Jonathan the son of Abiathar, your two sons with you. <verse-number id="2 Sa 15:28">28</verse-number>See, I <supplied>am</supplied> waiting at the fords of the wilderness until a word comes from you all to inform me.” <verse-number id="2 Sa 15:29">29</verse-number>So Zadok and Abiathar returned the ark of God to Jerusalem and they remained there. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Hushai Offers to Serve King David</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Sa 15:30">30</verse-number>Now David <supplied>was</supplied> going up on the Ascent of the Olives, <idiom-start/>weeping as he went<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “going up and weeping”</note> with his head covered and going barefoot. All the people who <supplied>were</supplied> with him each covered their head <idiom-start/>and wept as they went<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “going up and weeping”</note> <verse-number id="2 Sa 15:31">31</verse-number>Now David <supplied>was</supplied> told, “Ahithophel <supplied>was</supplied> among the conspirators with Absalom.” Then David said, “Please frustrate the counsel of Ahithophel, O Yahweh.” <verse-number id="2 Sa 15:32">32</verse-number>It happened that as David <supplied>was</supplied> coming up to the summit where he used to worship God, suddenly Hushai the Arkite <supplied>was</supplied> there to meet him. His coat <supplied>was</supplied> torn and dirt <supplied>was</supplied> on his head. <verse-number id="2 Sa 15:33">33</verse-number>David said to him, “If you move on with me, you will be a burden to me, <verse-number id="2 Sa 15:34">34</verse-number>but if you want to return to the city and say to Absalom, ‘I <supplied>am</supplied> your servant, O king. I used to be a servant of your father, but from then and now I <supplied>will be</supplied> your servant,’ then you can frustrate the counsel of Ahithophel for me. <verse-number id="2 Sa 15:35">35</verse-number><supplied>Will</supplied> not Zadok and Abiathar the priests <supplied>be</supplied> with you there? It shall be that all the words you hear from the house of the king you shall tell Zadok and Abiathar the priests. <verse-number id="2 Sa 15:36">36</verse-number>Look, there with them <supplied>are</supplied> their two sons, Ahimaaz of Zadok and Jonathan of Abiathar. You shall send to me <idiom-start/>by means of them<idiom-end/><note>Literally “by their hand”</note> all the words that you hear.” <verse-number id="2 Sa 15:37">37</verse-number>So Hushai the friend of David came to the city <supplied>as</supplied> Absalom was entering Jerusalem. </p>
		</chapter>