<chapter id="2 Sa 16">
			<pericope>Ziba Brings Provisions</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Sa 16:1">1</verse-number>Now David passed a little from beyond the summit, and suddenly Ziba the servant of Mephibosheth <supplied>was</supplied> there to meet him <supplied>with</supplied> a pair of saddled donkeys; on them <supplied>were</supplied> two hundred loaves of bread and a hundred raisin cakes, <supplied>with</supplied> a hundred summer fruits and a skin of wine. <verse-number id="2 Sa 16:2">2</verse-number>The king said to Ziba, “<idiom-start/>What do you want to accomplish by bringing these<idiom-end/>?”<note>Literally “What are these to you?”</note> And Ziba said, “The donkeys <supplied>are</supplied> for the king’s household to ride <supplied>on</supplied>; the bread and the summer fruit <supplied>are</supplied> for the young men to eat, and the wine <supplied>is</supplied> for the faint in the wilderness to drink. <verse-number id="2 Sa 16:3">3</verse-number>Then the king said, “Where <supplied>is</supplied> the son of your lord?” And Ziba said to the king, “He <supplied>is</supplied> living in Jerusalem for he said, ‘Today the house of Israel shall return the kingdom of my father to me.’ ” <verse-number id="2 Sa 16:4">4</verse-number>The king said to Ziba, “Look, all that <supplied>was</supplied> Mephibosheth’s is yours.” Ziba said, “I hereby do obeisance; may I find favor in your eyes, my lord the king.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Shimei Curses David</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Sa 16:5">5</verse-number>King David came up to Bahurim and suddenly a man from there <supplied>was</supplied> coming out from the family of the house of Saul, and his name <supplied>was</supplied> Shimei the son of Gera. <idiom-start/>He was cursing as he came out<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “<supplied>He was</supplied> coming out, coming out and cursing”</note> <verse-number id="2 Sa 16:6">6</verse-number>And he threw stones at David and at all the servants of King David and at all the people and at all the mighty warriors on his right and on his left. <verse-number id="2 Sa 16:7">7</verse-number>Shimei said while cursing him, “Go out, go out, <supplied>you</supplied> <idiom-start/>man of bloodshed<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “man of bloods”</note> <supplied>you</supplied> <idiom-start/>man of wickedness<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “and man of the wickedness”</note> <verse-number id="2 Sa 16:8">8</verse-number>Yahweh has returned on you all the blood of the household of Saul <idiom-start/>whom you have supplanted as king<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “who you have reigned in place of him”</note> and Yahweh has given the kingship into the hand of Absalom your son. Look, you <supplied>are</supplied> in disaster for you <supplied>are</supplied> a man of blood.” <verse-number id="2 Sa 16:9">9</verse-number>Then Abishai the son of Zeruiah said to the king, “Why should this dead dog curse my lord the king? Please let me go over and take off his head.” <verse-number id="2 Sa 16:10">10</verse-number>The king said, “<idiom-start/>What do we have in common<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “What <supplied>is</supplied> for me and what <supplied>is</supplied> for you”</note> sons of Zeruiah? If<note>Hebrew “Because”</note> he curses because Yahweh has said to him ‘Curse David,’ who can say, “Why have you done this?” <verse-number id="2 Sa 16:11">11</verse-number>David said to Abishai and to all his servants, “Look, my son who came out of my loins<note>Hebrew “intestines”</note> <supplied>is</supplied> seeking my life. Now <idiom-start/>as far as<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and even that now”</note> <supplied>this</supplied> Benjaminite, leave him alone and let him curse, for Yahweh has spoken to him. <verse-number id="2 Sa 16:12">12</verse-number>Perhaps Yahweh will look <idiom-start/>in my eye<idiom-end/><note>According to the reading tradition (<i>Qere)</i>; <i>Kethib</i> has “at my guilt”</note> and repay good for me in place of his curse this day. <verse-number id="2 Sa 16:13">13</verse-number>Then David and his men went on the road, with Shimei going on the side of the hill beside him, <idiom-start/>cursing as he went<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “going and cursing”</note> He threw stones beside him and threw<note>Hebrew “flung”</note> dust in the air. <verse-number id="2 Sa 16:14">14</verse-number>When the king and all of the people who were with him arrived, he was weary, so he recovered there. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Hushai Comes to Absalom</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Sa 16:15">15</verse-number>Now Absalom and all the people, the men of Israel, had come to Jerusalem, and Ahithophel <supplied>was</supplied> with him. <verse-number id="2 Sa 16:16">16</verse-number>When Hushai the Arkite the friend of David came to Absalom, Hushai said to Absalom, “<supplied>Long</supplied> live the king, <supplied>long</supplied> live the king!” <verse-number id="2 Sa 16:17">17</verse-number>Absalom said to Hushai, “This <supplied>is</supplied> your loyal love with your friend? Why did you not go with your friend?” <verse-number id="2 Sa 16:18">18</verse-number>Then Hushai said to Absalom, “No, rather, whom Yahweh and this people and all the men of Israel have chosen, to him<note>According to the reading tradition (<i>Qere</i>); <i>Kethib</i> has “no”</note> I will be, and with him I will remain. <verse-number id="2 Sa 16:19">19</verse-number><idiom-start/>Furthermore<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “And the second <supplied>thing</supplied>”</note> for whom have I served? <supplied>Is</supplied> it not in the presence of his son that I have served before your father? <idiom-start/>So shall I serve you<idiom-end/>!”<note>Literally “So shall I be in your presence”</note> <verse-number id="2 Sa 16:20">20</verse-number>Then Absalom said to Ahithophel, “Give your advice. What shall we do?” <verse-number id="2 Sa 16:21">21</verse-number>And Ahithophel said to Absalom, “Go to the concubines of your father whom he left behind to watch over the house, then all of Israel will hear that you made yourself odious to your father, and <idiom-start/>all of your followers will be motivated<idiom-end/>!”<note>Literally “the hands of all who <supplied>are</supplied> with you will be strengthened”</note> <verse-number id="2 Sa 16:22">22</verse-number>Then they pitched a tent for Absalom on the roof, and he went <supplied>in</supplied> to the concubines of his father before the eyes of all Israel. <verse-number id="2 Sa 16:23">23</verse-number>The counsel that Ahithophel gave in those days <supplied>was</supplied> regarded as when a man<note><i>Qere</i> reads “a man inquired”; <i>Kethib</i> omits “a man”</note> inquired of the word of God, so all the counsel of Ahithophel <supplied>was esteemed</supplied> both by David and by Absalom. </p>
		</chapter>