<chapter id="2 Sa 20">
			<pericope>Sheba Leads a Revolt</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Sa 20:1">1</verse-number>Now a man of wickedness was found there whose name <supplied>was</supplied> Sheba the son of Bichri, a Benjaminite. He blew the horn and said, “There is no share for us in David, and there <supplied>is</supplied> no inheritance for us in the son of Jesse; each to his tents, O Israel!” <verse-number id="2 Sa 20:2">2</verse-number>Then all the men of Israel went up from <supplied>following</supplied> after David, <supplied>following instead</supplied> after Sheba the son of Bicri, but the men of Judah stuck to their king from the Jordan up to Jerusalem. <verse-number id="2 Sa 20:3">3</verse-number>David went up to his house in Jerusalem, then the king took the ten concubines whom he had left to look after the house, and he put them <idiom-start/>under confinement<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “<supplied>a</supplied> house of guard”</note> However, he provided for them, but <idiom-start/>he did not sleep with them<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “he did not come into them”</note> So they were confined until the day of their death, like a lifetime of widowhood. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Joab Assassinates Amasa</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Sa 20:4">4</verse-number>Then the king said to Amasa, “Summon for me the men of Judah <supplied>within</supplied> three days, <idiom-start/>and be here yourself<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “and you stand here”</note> <verse-number id="2 Sa 20:5">5</verse-number>So Amasa went to summon Judah, but he tarried more than the appointed time which he had set for him. <verse-number id="2 Sa 20:6">6</verse-number>Then David said to Abishai, “Now Sheba the son of Bicri will do us more harm than Absalom. You take the servants of your lord and pursue after him, lest he find fortified cities for himself and escape from us.” <verse-number id="2 Sa 20:7">7</verse-number>Then the men of Joab, the Kerethites and the Pelethites, and all the mighty warriors went out after him; they went out from Jerusalem to pursue after Sheba the son of Bicri. <verse-number id="2 Sa 20:8">8</verse-number>They <supplied>were</supplied> near the big rock that <supplied>is</supplied> in Gibeon, and Amasa came before them. Joab <idiom-start/>was dressed in his military clothing<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “<supplied>was</supplied> dressed his garment his clothing”</note> <supplied>with</supplied> a utility belt on him and a sword strapped to his waist in its scabbard. Now he went out, and it fell out. <verse-number id="2 Sa 20:9">9</verse-number>Then Joab said to Amasa, “Is it peace, O you my brother?” Then the right hand of Joab took hold of the beard of Amasa <supplied>as if</supplied> to kiss him. <verse-number id="2 Sa 20:10">10</verse-number>Now Amasa was not on his guard against the sword that <supplied>was</supplied> in Joab’s hand, and he struck him with it into the stomach, and his entrails poured out to the ground. He did not strike him again, and he died. Then Joab and Abishai his brother pursued after Sheba the son of Bicri. <verse-number id="2 Sa 20:11">11</verse-number>A young man stood over him, from the young men of Joab, and he said, “Whoever takes delight in Joab and whoever <supplied>is</supplied> for David, <supplied>follow</supplied> after Joab.” <verse-number id="2 Sa 20:12">12</verse-number>Now Amasa <supplied>was</supplied> wallowing in the blood in the middle of the highway; when the man saw that all the people stood <supplied>there</supplied>, he turned Amasa over from the highway into the field, and he threw a garment over him because he had seen that all who had come by him had stopped. <verse-number id="2 Sa 20:13">13</verse-number>After he was removed from the highway, all the men passed by after Joab to pursue after Sheba the son of Bicri. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Wisdom from a Woman under Siege</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Sa 20:14">14</verse-number>(He<note>i.e., “Sheba”</note> had passed through all the tribes of Israel to Abel and Beth Maacah; now all of the Berites had been treated badly, so they also followed after him.) <verse-number id="2 Sa 20:15">15</verse-number>And they came and besieged him in Abel Beth Maacah. They threw up a siege ramp against the city, and they stood against the ramparts. And all the army who <supplied>were</supplied> with Joab <supplied>were</supplied> battering to cause the wall to fall. <verse-number id="2 Sa 20:16">16</verse-number>Then a wise woman from the city called out, “Listen, listen! Please speak to Joab <supplied>to</supplied> come near here so that I may speak to you.” <verse-number id="2 Sa 20:17">17</verse-number>Then he came near to her, and the woman asked, “<supplied>Are</supplied> you Joab?” And he said, “I <supplied>am</supplied>.” Then she said to him, “Listen to the words of your servant.” He said, “I <supplied>am</supplied> listening.” <verse-number id="2 Sa 20:18">18</verse-number>Then she said, “In former times, <idiom-start/>they would always say<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “speaking they would speak”</note> ‘By all means, let them inquire in Abel,’ and so they settled things. <verse-number id="2 Sa 20:19">19</verse-number>I <supplied>am</supplied> one of the faithful representatives of Israel. You <supplied>are</supplied> seeking to destroy a city and a mother in Israel. Why do you want to swallow the inheritance of Yahweh?” <verse-number id="2 Sa 20:20">20</verse-number>Then Joab answered and said, “Far be it, far be it from me that I should swallow or I should destroy. <verse-number id="2 Sa 20:21">21</verse-number>That is not the matter. But a man from the mountains of Ephraim, whose name <supplied>is</supplied> Sheba the son Bicri, has lifted up his hand against the king, against David. Give only him to us, and I will depart from the city.” The woman said to Joab, “Look, his head <supplied>is</supplied> being thrown down to you over the wall.” <verse-number id="2 Sa 20:22">22</verse-number>The woman went to all of the people with her wise plan, so they cut off the head of Sheba the son of Bicri and threw <supplied>it</supplied> to Joab. Then he blew the horn and dispersed from the city, each to his tent. Then Joab returned to Jerusalem to the king. <verse-number id="2 Sa 20:23">23</verse-number>Now Joab <supplied>was</supplied> over all the army of Israel and Benaiah the son of Jehoiada <supplied>was</supplied> over the Carites and over the Pelethites. <verse-number id="2 Sa 20:24">24</verse-number>Adoram <supplied>was</supplied> over the forced labor, and Jehoshaphat the son of Ahilud <supplied>was</supplied> the recorder. <verse-number id="2 Sa 20:25">25</verse-number>Shiya <supplied>was</supplied> secretary, and Zadok and Abiathar <supplied>were</supplied> priests. <verse-number id="2 Sa 20:26">26</verse-number>Also Ira the Jairite <supplied>was</supplied> priest for David. </p>
		</chapter>