<chapter id="2 Sa 23">
			<pericope>David Extols Yahweh</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Sa 23:1">1</verse-number>These <supplied>are</supplied> the last words of David, the declaration of David the son of Jesse, and the declaration of the man exalted <supplied>by</supplied> the Most High, the anointed one of the God of Jacob and the darling of the songs of Israel. <verse-number id="2 Sa 23:2">2</verse-number>“The spirit of Yahweh speaks through me, and his word <supplied>is</supplied> upon my tongue. <verse-number id="2 Sa 23:3">3</verse-number>The God of Israel said to me, the rock of Israel has spoken; ‘He who rules over mankind rules righteously, in the fear of God. <verse-number id="2 Sa 23:4">4</verse-number>Like the light of <supplied>the</supplied> morning when the sun rises, shining with no clouds, <supplied>bringing</supplied> vegetation from the earth apart from rain.’<note>In other words, even men who rule rightly pass like the dew of the morning</note> <verse-number id="2 Sa 23:5">5</verse-number>Yet not so <supplied>is</supplied> my house with God, for he made an everlasting covenant for me, arranging everything. He has secured all my deliverance, and all my desire he will cause to happen. <verse-number id="2 Sa 23:6">6</verse-number>But evil persons <supplied>are</supplied> like thorns cast aside; all of them, because they cannot be picked up in the hand. <verse-number id="2 Sa 23:7">7</verse-number>And if a man wants to touch them, he must use an iron instrument or the shaft of a spear; then they <supplied>are</supplied> consumed entirely with fire on the spot.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>David’s Faithful Soldiers</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Sa 23:8">8</verse-number>These <supplied>are</supplied> the names of the mighty warriors who <supplied>were</supplied> David’s: Josheb-Basshebeth a Tahkemonite <supplied>was</supplied> chief of three officers; first Adino, whose spear <supplied>was</supplied> against eight hundred slain on one occurrence. <verse-number id="2 Sa 23:9">9</verse-number>Next to him Eleazar, the son of Dodo the son of an Ahohite, <supplied>was</supplied> among the three mighty warriors with David when they defied the Philistines and they gathered there for the battle and the men of Israel withdrew. <verse-number id="2 Sa 23:10">10</verse-number>He stood up and struck down the Philistines until his hand grew tired and his hand clung to the sword, and Yahweh brought about a great victory on that day. Then the army returned back to him only for stripping <supplied>the dead</supplied>. <verse-number id="2 Sa 23:11">11</verse-number>Next to him <supplied>was</supplied> Shamma, the son of Agee the Hararite. When <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines assembled at Lehi, a plot of the field was there filled with lentils, and the army fled there from the presence of <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines. <verse-number id="2 Sa 23:12">12</verse-number>But he took a stand in the middle of the plot of land and defended it. He killed <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines, and Yahweh brought about a great victory. <verse-number id="2 Sa 23:13">13</verse-number>Then three<note>So <i>Qere</i>; <i>Kethib</i> reads “thirty”</note> of the thirty leaders went down and came to David <idiom-start/>at the time of the harvest<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the harvest”</note> to the cave of Adullam, while a group of <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines <supplied>were</supplied> camping in the valley of <supplied>the</supplied> Rephaim. <verse-number id="2 Sa 23:14">14</verse-number>Now at that time, David <supplied>was</supplied> in the stronghold, and a garrison of <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines <supplied>was</supplied> in Bethlehem at that <supplied>same</supplied> time. <verse-number id="2 Sa 23:15">15</verse-number>David <idiom-start/>said longingly<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “desired and said”</note> “<idiom-start/>Oh that someone would bring me a drink<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Who will let me drink …?”</note> of water from the well of Bethlehem that <supplied>is</supplied> at the gate.” <verse-number id="2 Sa 23:16">16</verse-number>So three of the mighty warriors broke into the camp of <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines, and they drew water from the well of Bethlehem that <supplied>was</supplied> at the gate, and they carried <supplied>it</supplied> and brought <supplied>it</supplied> to David. But he <supplied>was</supplied> not willing to drink it, but poured it out to Yahweh. <verse-number id="2 Sa 23:17">17</verse-number>He said, “Far be it from me before Yahweh that I should do this. <supplied>Is this not</supplied> the blood of the men who went at the risk of their lives?” So he <supplied>was</supplied> not willing to drink it. These things the three mighty warriors did. <verse-number id="2 Sa 23:18">18</verse-number>Now Abishai the brother of Joab the son of Zeruiah <supplied>was</supplied> himself the leader of the thirty. He <supplied>was</supplied> wielding his spear against three hundred slain and <idiom-start/>gained a name<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and to him a name”</note> among the thirty. <verse-number id="2 Sa 23:19">19</verse-number>Among the thirty, is it not that he <supplied>was</supplied> honored and became a commander for them? But he did not come up to the three. <verse-number id="2 Sa 23:20">20</verse-number>Benaiah the son of Jehoiada, the son of Ish-Hai, <supplied>was</supplied> a great <supplied>man</supplied> of deeds from Kabzeel. He struck down two sons of Ariel of Moab, and he went down and killed a lion in the middle of a pit on a snowy day. <verse-number id="2 Sa 23:21">21</verse-number>He also killed a good-looking Egyptian man, in whose hand <supplied>was</supplied> a spear. He went down against him with the staff and snatched the spear from the hand of the Egyptian and killed him with his spear. <verse-number id="2 Sa 23:22">22</verse-number>These things Benaiah the son of Jehoiada did and gained a name for himself among the three mighty warriors. <verse-number id="2 Sa 23:23">23</verse-number>He <supplied>was</supplied> honored more than the thirty, but he did not come up to the three. David appointed him in charge of his bodyguard. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Mighty Men of David</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Sa 23:24">24</verse-number>Among the thirty <supplied>were</supplied> Asahel the brother of Joab, Elhanan the son of Dodo of Bethlehem, <verse-number id="2 Sa 23:25">25</verse-number>Shammah the Harodite, Elika the Harodite, <verse-number id="2 Sa 23:26">26</verse-number>Helez the Paltite, Ira the son of Ikkesh the Tekoite, <verse-number id="2 Sa 23:27">27</verse-number>Abiezer the Anathothite, Mebunnai the Hushathite, <verse-number id="2 Sa 23:28">28</verse-number>Zalmon the Ahohite, Maharai the Netophathite, <verse-number id="2 Sa 23:29">29</verse-number>Heleb the son of Baanah the Netophathite, Ittai the son of Ribai from Gibeah of the sons of Benjamin, <verse-number id="2 Sa 23:30">30</verse-number>Benaiah <supplied>the</supplied> Pirathonite, Hiddai from the wadis of Gaash, <verse-number id="2 Sa 23:31">31</verse-number>Abi-Albon the Arbathite, Azmaveth the Barhumite, <verse-number id="2 Sa 23:32">32</verse-number>Eliahba the Shaalbonite, the sons of Jashen, Jonathan <verse-number id="2 Sa 23:33">33</verse-number><supplied>the son</supplied> of Shammah the Hararite, Ahiam the son of Sharar the Ararite, <verse-number id="2 Sa 23:34">34</verse-number>Eliphelet the son of Ahasbai the son of the Maacathite, Eliam the son of Ahithophel the Gilonite, <verse-number id="2 Sa 23:35">35</verse-number>Hezro the Carmelite, Paarai the Arbite, <verse-number id="2 Sa 23:36">36</verse-number>Igal the son of Nathan from Zobah, Bani the Gadite, <verse-number id="2 Sa 23:37">37</verse-number>Zelek the Ammonite, Naharai the Beerothite, the carriers of the weapons of Joab the son of Zeruiah, <verse-number id="2 Sa 23:38">38</verse-number>Ira the Ithrite, Gareb the Ithrite, <verse-number id="2 Sa 23:39">39</verse-number>Uriah the Hittite; in all, thirty-seven. </p>
		</chapter>