<chapter id="Jdg 1">
			<pericope>Israel Continues Its Conquest</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 1:1">1</verse-number>After the death of Joshua, the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> inquired of Yahweh, saying, “Who will go up first for us against the Canaanites<note>Hebrew “Canaanite”</note> to fight against them?” <verse-number id="Jdg 1:2">2</verse-number>And Yahweh said, “Judah will go up. I hereby give the land into his hand.” <verse-number id="Jdg 1:3">3</verse-number>And Judah said to Simeon his brother, “Go up with me into my allotment, and let us fight against the Canaanites; then I too will go with you into your allotment.” And Simeon went with him. <verse-number id="Jdg 1:4">4</verse-number>And Judah went up, and Yahweh gave the Canaanites<note>Hebrew “Canaanite”</note> and the Perizzites<note>Hebrew “Perizzite”</note> into their hand, and they defeated ten thousand men at Bezek. <verse-number id="Jdg 1:5">5</verse-number>At Bezek they came upon Adoni-bezek, and they fought against him and defeated the Canaanites<note>Hebrew “Canaanite”</note> and the Perizzites.<note>Hebrew “Perizzite”</note> <verse-number id="Jdg 1:6">6</verse-number>And Adoni-bezek fled, but they pursued after him; they caught him and cut off <idiom-start/>his thumbs and big toes<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the thumbs of his hands and feet”</note> <verse-number id="Jdg 1:7">7</verse-number>Adoni-bezek said, “Seventy kings with <idiom-start/>their thumbs and big toes<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the thumbs of their hands and feet”</note> cut off used to pick up <supplied>scraps</supplied> under my table; just as I have done, so God has repaid to me. And they brought him <supplied>to</supplied> Jerusalem, and he died there. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 1:8">8</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons/children”</note> of Judah fought against Jerusalem, and they captured it, <idiom-start/>put it to the sword<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “they struck it with the mouth of the sword”</note> and <idiom-start/>set the city on fire<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the city they sent away with fire”</note> <verse-number id="Jdg 1:9">9</verse-number>Afterward the descendants<note>Or “sons/children”</note> of Judah pursued to fight against the Canaanites<note>Hebrew “Canaanite”</note> who were living in the hill country, the Negev,<note>An arid region south of the Judean hills</note> and the Shephelah.<note>A geographical region associated with an area of low country on the western edge of the Judaean hills.</note> <verse-number id="Jdg 1:10">10</verse-number>And Judah went against the Canaanites<note>Hebrew “Canaanite”</note> living in Hebron (the former name of Hebron <supplied>was</supplied> Kiriath Arba). And they defeated Sheshai, Ahiman, and Talmai. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 1:11">11</verse-number>And from there they went to the inhabitants of Debir (the former name of Debir <supplied>was</supplied> Kiriath Sepher). <verse-number id="Jdg 1:12">12</verse-number>And Caleb said, “Whoever attacks Kiriath Sepher and captures it, I will give to him Acsah my daughter as a wife.” <verse-number id="Jdg 1:13">13</verse-number>Othniel son of Kenaz, the younger brother of Caleb, captured it, and he gave to him Acsah his daughter as a wife. <verse-number id="Jdg 1:14">14</verse-number>When she came <supplied>to him</supplied>, she urged him to ask her father for a field. As she dismounted from the donkey, Caleb said to her, “<idiom-start/>What do you want<idiom-end/>?”<note>Literally “What <supplied>is</supplied> for you?”</note> <verse-number id="Jdg 1:15">15</verse-number>And she said to him, “Give me <idiom-start/>a gift<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “blessing”</note> you have given me the land of the Negev,<note>An arid region south of the Judaean hills</note> and give me also a spring of water.” And Caleb gave to her the upper and lower spring.<note><cite title="BibleLEB2: Jdg 1:11–15">Judges 1:11–15 </cite>is almost identical to <cite title="BibleLEB2: Jos 15:13–19">Joshua 15:13–19</cite></note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 1:16">16</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons/children”</note> of Hobab <supplied>the</supplied> Kenite, Moses’ father-in-law, went up with the descendants<note>Or “sons/children”</note> of Judah from the city of palms <supplied>into</supplied> the wilderness of Judah, which <supplied>is</supplied> in <supplied>the</supplied> Negev<note>An arid region south of the Judaean hills</note> <supplied>near</supplied> Arad. And they went<note>Hebrew “he went”</note> and settled with the people. <verse-number id="Jdg 1:17">17</verse-number>And Judah went with his brother Simeon, and they defeated the Canaanites<note>Hebrew “Canaanite”</note> inhabiting Zephath; they utterly destroyed it, so he called the name of the city Hormah. <verse-number id="Jdg 1:18">18</verse-number>Judah captured Gaza and its territory, Ashkelon and its territory, and Ekron and its territory. <verse-number id="Jdg 1:19">19</verse-number>And Yahweh was with Judah, and he took possession of the hill country, but they could not drive out the inhabitants of the plain because they <supplied>had</supplied> chariots of iron. <verse-number id="Jdg 1:20">20</verse-number>They gave Hebron to Caleb just as Moses said, and he drove out the three sons of Anak from there. <verse-number id="Jdg 1:21">21</verse-number>But the descendants<note>Or “sons/children”</note> of Benjamin did not drive out the Jebusites<note>Hebrew “Jebusite”</note> who lived in Jerusalem, so the Jebusites have lived among the descendants<note>Or “sons/children”</note> of Benjamin in Jerusalem to this day. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 1:22">22</verse-number>Likewise, the house of Joseph went up <supplied>against</supplied> Bethel, and Yahweh <supplied>was</supplied> with them. <verse-number id="Jdg 1:23">23</verse-number>And the house of Joseph spied out Bethel (the former name of the city was Luz). <verse-number id="Jdg 1:24">24</verse-number>And when the spies saw a man leaving the city,<note>Or “going out from the city”</note> they said to him, “Please show us the entrance of the city, and we will deal kindly<note>Or “do a loyal love”</note> with you.” <verse-number id="Jdg 1:25">25</verse-number>So he showed them the entrance of the city, and they struck the city with <idiom-start/>the edge of the sword<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “<supplied>the</supplied> mouth of <supplied>the</supplied> sword”</note> but they let go the man and all his family. <verse-number id="Jdg 1:26">26</verse-number>And the man went <supplied>to</supplied> the land of the Hittites, and he built a city and named it Luz; this <supplied>is</supplied> its name to this day. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 1:27">27</verse-number>Manasseh did not drive out Beth-Sean and its towns, or Taanach and its towns, or the inhabitants<note>Hebrew “inhabitant”</note> of Dor and its towns, or the inhabitants of Ibleam and its towns, or the inhabitants of Megiddo and its towns; the Canaanites<note>Hebrew “Canaanite”</note> <supplied>were</supplied> determined to live in this land. <verse-number id="Jdg 1:28">28</verse-number>And it happened, when Israel grew strong, they put the Canaanites<note>Hebrew “Canaanite”</note> to forced labor, but they never totally drove them out. <verse-number id="Jdg 1:29">29</verse-number>Ephraim did not drive out the Canaanites<note>Hebrew “Canaanite”</note> living in Gezer, so the Canaanites<note>Hebrew “Canaanite”</note> lived in their midst in Gezer. <verse-number id="Jdg 1:30">30</verse-number>Zebulun did not drive out the inhabitants of Kitron or Nahalol, so the Canaanites<note>Hebrew “Canaanite”</note> lived in their midst and became <supplied>subjected</supplied> to forced labor. <verse-number id="Jdg 1:31">31</verse-number>Asher did not drive out the inhabitants of Acco, Sidon, Ahlab, Aczib, Helbah, Aphik, or Rehob, <verse-number id="Jdg 1:32">32</verse-number>so the Asherites<note>Hebrew “Asherite”</note> lived in the midst of the Canaanites,<note>Hebrew “Canaanite”</note> the inhabitants of the land, for they did not drive them out. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 1:33">33</verse-number>Naphtali did not drive out the inhabitants of Beth Shemesh or Beth-anath, but lived in the midst of the Canaanites,<note>Hebrew “Canaanite”</note> the inhabitants of the land; the inhabitants of Beth Shemesh and Beth-anath became forced labor for them. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 1:34">34</verse-number>The Amorites pressed<note>Or “forced”</note> the descendants<note>Or “sons/children”</note> of Dan to the hill country, and they did not allow them to come down to the plain; <verse-number id="Jdg 1:35">35</verse-number>the Amorites <supplied>were</supplied> determined to live in Har-heres,<note>Or “Mount Heres”</note> in Aijalon, and in Shaalbim, but the hand of the house of Joseph was heavy <supplied>on them</supplied>, and they became <supplied>subjected</supplied> to forced labor. <verse-number id="Jdg 1:36">36</verse-number>The border of the Amorites<note>Hebrew “Amorite”</note> <supplied>ran</supplied> from the ascent of Akrabbim from Sela and upward. </p>
		</chapter>