<chapter id="Jdg 3">
			<pericope>Some Nations Remain in the Land</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 3:1">1</verse-number>These <supplied>are</supplied> the nations that Yahweh left, to test Israel by them (<supplied>that is, to test</supplied> all those who <idiom-start/>had not experienced<idiom-end/><note>Literally “did not know”</note> any of the wars of Canaan, <verse-number id="Jdg 3:2">2</verse-number>in order that the generations of Israel would know war, to teach those <idiom-start/>who had not experienced it<idiom-end/><note>Literally “who had not known it”</note> before): <verse-number id="Jdg 3:3">3</verse-number>the five rulers of the Philistines, all the Canaanites,<note>Hebrew “Canaanite”</note> the Sidonians,<note>Hebrew “Sidonian”</note> and the Hivites<note>Hebrew “Hivite”</note> living on Mount Lebanon, from Mount Baal Hermon up to Lebo-Hamath. <verse-number id="Jdg 3:4">4</verse-number>They were <supplied>left</supplied> for testing Israel, to know <supplied>whether</supplied> they would keep the commands of Yahweh that he commanded their ancestors<note>Or “fathers”</note> through the hand of Moses. <verse-number id="Jdg 3:5">5</verse-number>And the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> lived in the midst of the Canaanites,<note>Hebrew “Canaanite”</note> the Hittites,<note>Hebrew “Hittite”</note> the Amorites,<note>Hebrew “Amorite”</note> the Perizzites,<note>Hebrew “Perizzite”</note> the Hivites,<note>Hebrew “Hivite”</note> and the Jebusites.<note>Hebrew “Jebusite”</note> <verse-number id="Jdg 3:6">6</verse-number>And they took their daughters as wives for themselves, and they gave their daughters to their sons, and they served their gods.<note>Or “worshiped their gods”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Othniel</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 3:7">7</verse-number>The <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> did evil in the eyes of Yahweh. They forgot Yahweh their God, and they served the Baals and the Asheroth.<note>Asheroth are cultic poles set up next to an altar symbolizing the goddess Asherah</note> <verse-number id="Jdg 3:8">8</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>the anger of Yahweh was kindled<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the nose of Yahweh became hot”</note> against Israel, and he sold them into the hand of Cushan-Rishathaim, the king of Aram Naharaim; and the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> served Cushan-Rishathaim eight years. <verse-number id="Jdg 3:9">9</verse-number>The <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> cried out to Yahweh, and Yahweh raised up a deliverer for the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> who delivered them, Othniel son of Kenaz, Caleb’s younger brother. <verse-number id="Jdg 3:10">10</verse-number>And the spirit of Yahweh came upon him, and he judged Israel. He went out to war, and Yahweh gave Cushan-Rishathaim king of Aram into his hand, and <idiom-start/>he prevailed over<idiom-end/><note>Literally “his hand was strong over”</note> Cushan-Rishathaim. <verse-number id="Jdg 3:11">11</verse-number>So the land rested forty years. Then Othniel son of Kenaz died. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Ehud</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 3:12">12</verse-number>And again the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> did evil in the eyes of Yahweh. So Yahweh strengthened Eglon king of Moab against Israel, because they did evil in the eyes of Yahweh. <verse-number id="Jdg 3:13">13</verse-number>He gathered to himself the <idiom-start/>Ammonites and Amalekites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons of Ammon and Amalek” or “children of Ammon and Amalek”</note> and he went and defeated Israel, and they took possession of the city of palms. <verse-number id="Jdg 3:14">14</verse-number>And the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> served Eglon king of Moab eighteen years. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 3:15">15</verse-number>And the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> cried out to Yahweh, and Yahweh raised up for them a deliverer, Ehud son of Gera, a Benjaminite and <idiom-start/>a left-handed man<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “a man bound by his right hand”</note> And the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> sent a tribute to Eglon king of Moab <idiom-start/>through him<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “in his hand”</note> <verse-number id="Jdg 3:16">16</verse-number>Ehud made for himself a short, <idiom-start/>two-edged<idiom-end/><note>Literally “with two mouths”</note> sword (a cubit in length), and he fastened it under his clothes on his right thigh. <verse-number id="Jdg 3:17">17</verse-number>Then he presented the tribute to Eglon king of Moab. Now Eglon <supplied>was</supplied> a very fat man. <verse-number id="Jdg 3:18">18</verse-number>When Ehud<note>That is, Eglon</note> had finished presenting the tribute, he sent away the people who carried the tribute. <verse-number id="Jdg 3:19">19</verse-number>But he turned back from the sculptured stones<note>Or “Pesilim”; some translations translate the phrase as a proper name</note> that <supplied>were</supplied> near Gilgal, and he said, “I have <idiom-start/>a secret message<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a word of secrecy”</note> for you, O king.” And he<note>Hebrew “he”</note> said, “Silence!” So all those standing in his presence went out, <verse-number id="Jdg 3:20">20</verse-number>and Ehud came to him <supplied>while</supplied> he <supplied>was</supplied> sitting alone in his cool upper room. And Ehud said, “I have a <idiom-start/>message from God<idiom-end/><note>Literally “word of God”</note> for you.” So he got up from his seat. <verse-number id="Jdg 3:21">21</verse-number>Then Ehud reached with his left hand for the sword on his right thigh, and he thrust it into his<note>That is, Eglon’s</note> stomach. <verse-number id="Jdg 3:22">22</verse-number>And the handle also went <supplied>in</supplied> after the blade, and the fat closed over the blade because he did not draw back the sword from his stomach; and it went protruding out the back.<note>The Hebrew is uncertain; some translations have “and the dirt/entrails came out”</note> <verse-number id="Jdg 3:23">23</verse-number>And Ehud went out the vestibule, and he closed the doors of the upper room and locked <supplied>them</supplied> behind him. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 3:24">24</verse-number>After he left, his servants returned. When they saw <supplied>that</supplied> the doors of the upper room <supplied>were</supplied> locked, <idiom-start/>they thought<idiom-end/>,<note>Hebrew “they said”</note> “Surely he <supplied>is</supplied> <idiom-start/>relieving himself<idiom-end/><note>Literally “covering his feet”</note> in the cool inner room.” <verse-number id="Jdg 3:25">25</verse-number>And they waited so long they became embarrassed because he did not open the doors of the upper room. So they took the key and opened <supplied>the doors</supplied>, and there their lord was lying on the ground dead. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 3:26">26</verse-number>And Ehud escaped while they delayed. He passed by the sculptured stones<note>Or “Pesilim;” some translations to translate the phrase as a proper name</note> and escaped to Seirah. <verse-number id="Jdg 3:27">27</verse-number>And when he arrived he sounded the trumpet in the hill country of Ephraim, and the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> went down from the hill country with him leading them. <verse-number id="Jdg 3:28">28</verse-number>And he said to them, “Follow after me! Yahweh has given Moab your enemies into your hand.” So they went down after him, and they captured the fords of the Jordan toward Moab; and they did not allow anyone to cross over. <verse-number id="Jdg 3:29">29</verse-number>And they struck Moab at that time, about ten thousand men, <idiom-start/>all strong and able men<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “all fat and men of strength”</note> no one escaped. <verse-number id="Jdg 3:30">30</verse-number>And Moab was subdued on that day under the hand of Israel. And the land rested eighty years.<note>Hebrew “year”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Shamgar</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 3:31">31</verse-number>And Shamgar son of Anath came after him, and he killed six hundred Philistines with the goad of an ox; he also delivered Israel. </p>
		</chapter>