<chapter id="Jdg 4">
			<pericope>Deborah and Barak</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 4:1">1</verse-number>And again the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> did evil in the eyes of Yahweh, and Ehud died. <verse-number id="Jdg 4:2">2</verse-number>So Yahweh sold them into the hand of Jabin king of Canaan, who reigned in Hazor. The commander of his army <supplied>was</supplied> Sisera, and he <supplied>was</supplied> living in Harosheth Haggoyim. <verse-number id="Jdg 4:3">3</verse-number>And the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> cried to Yahweh, as he <supplied>had</supplied> nine hundred iron chariots,<note>Hebrew “chariot”</note> and he oppressed the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> <idiom-start/>cruelly<idiom-end/><note>Literally “with force”</note> for twenty years.<note>Hebrew “year”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 4:4">4</verse-number>Now at that time Deborah, a prophetess, the wife of Lappidoth, <supplied>was</supplied> judging<note>Or “leading”</note> Israel. <verse-number id="Jdg 4:5">5</verse-number>And she used to sit under the palm tree of Deborah between Ramah and Bethel in the hill country of Ephraim; and the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> went up to her for judgment. <verse-number id="Jdg 4:6">6</verse-number>She sent and called for Barak son of Abinoam from Kedesh Naphtali and said to him, “Has not Yahweh the God of Israel commanded you? ‘Go, <idiom-start/>march to<idiom-end/><note>Literally “take the lead at”</note> Mount Tabor, and take ten thousand men from the descendants<note>Or “sons/children”</note> of Naphtali and Zebulun. <verse-number id="Jdg 4:7">7</verse-number><idiom-start/>I will draw out<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I will draw to you”</note> Sisera, the commander of Jabin’s army, with his chariots and troops, to the wadi<note>A valley that is dry most of the year, but contains a stream during the rainy season</note> of Kishon, and I will give him into your hand.’ ” <verse-number id="Jdg 4:8">8</verse-number>Barak said to her, “If you go with me, I will go; but if you do not go with me, I will not go.” <verse-number id="Jdg 4:9">9</verse-number>She said, “Surely I will go with you; however, there will be no glory for you in <idiom-start/>the path you are taking<idiom-end/>,<note>Or “the way you <supplied>are</supplied> going”</note> for Yahweh will sell Sisera into <supplied>the</supplied> hand of a woman.” And Deborah stood up and went with Barak to Kedesh. <verse-number id="Jdg 4:10">10</verse-number>Barak summoned Zebulun and Naphtali to Kedesh; and <idiom-start/>they went up behind him<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “they went up in his feet”</note> ten thousand men, and Deborah went up with him. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 4:11">11</verse-number>And Heber the Kenite <supplied>was</supplied> separated from <supplied>the other</supplied> Kenites,<note>Hebrew “Kenite”</note> <supplied>that is</supplied>, from the descendants<note>Or “sons/children”</note> of Hobab the father-in-law of Moses. And <idiom-start/>he was encamped<idiom-end/><note>Literally “he spread his tent”</note> at Elon-bezaanannim, which <supplied>is</supplied> near Kedesh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 4:12">12</verse-number>When they<note>The subject is not specified in Hebrew</note> reported to Sisera that Barak son of Abinoam had gone up to Mount Tabor, <verse-number id="Jdg 4:13">13</verse-number>Sisera summoned all his chariots—all nine hundred chariots<note>Hebrew “chariot”</note> of iron—and the entire army that <supplied>was</supplied> with him from Harosheth Haggoyim to the wadi<note>A valley that is dry most of the year, but contains a stream during the rainy season</note> of Kishon. <verse-number id="Jdg 4:14">14</verse-number>And Deborah said to Barak, “Get up! This <supplied>is</supplied> the day that Yahweh has given Sisera into your hand. Has Yahweh not gone out before you?” So Barak went out from Mount Tabor with ten thousand men following him. <verse-number id="Jdg 4:15">15</verse-number>And Yahweh threw Sisera and all his chariots and army into confusion<note>Or “routed Sisera and all <supplied>his</supplied> chariot<supplied>s</supplied> and army”</note> before <idiom-start/>the edge of Barak’s sword<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “<supplied>the</supplied> mouth of <supplied>the</supplied> sword before Barak”</note> and Sisera dismounted from <supplied>his</supplied> chariot and fled on foot. <verse-number id="Jdg 4:16">16</verse-number>But Barak pursued after the chariots<note>Hebrew “chariot”</note> and army as far as Harosheth Haggoyim, and all of Sisera’s army fell to <idiom-start/>the edge of the sword<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “<supplied>the</supplied> mouth of <supplied>the</supplied> sword”</note> no one was left. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 4:17">17</verse-number>Sisera fled on foot to the tent of Jael, the wife of Heber the Kenite, because <supplied>there was</supplied> peace between Jabin king of Hazor and the house of Heber the Kenite. <verse-number id="Jdg 4:18">18</verse-number>And Jael came out to meet Sisera, and she said to him, “Turn aside, my lord; turn aside to me and do not be afraid.” So he turned aside into her tent, and she covered him <idiom-start/>with a blanket<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “with a covering/rug”</note> <verse-number id="Jdg 4:19">19</verse-number>And he said to her, “Please, give me a drink of water, because I am thirsty.” So she opened a skin vessel of milk and gave him a drink and covered him. <verse-number id="Jdg 4:20">20</verse-number>And he said to her, “Stand <supplied>at</supplied> the doorway of the tent, and if anyone comes and asks you, and says, ‘Is there anyone here?’ You must answer, ‘No.’ ” <verse-number id="Jdg 4:21">21</verse-number>But Jael, the wife of Heber the Kenite, took in her hand a tent peg and a hammer, and she went softly<note>Or “secretly”</note> to him and drove the peg into his temple, and it went through into the ground; he <supplied>was</supplied> fast asleep since he was exhausted, and he died. <verse-number id="Jdg 4:22">22</verse-number>And behold, Barak <supplied>was</supplied> pursuing Sisera, and Jael went out to meet him, and she said to him, “Come, and I will show you the man whom you <supplied>are</supplied> seeking.” And he came with her and saw that Sisera was lying dead with the peg in his temple. <verse-number id="Jdg 4:23">23</verse-number>On that day God subdued Jabin king of Canaan before the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> <verse-number id="Jdg 4:24">24</verse-number>And the hand of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> <idiom-start/>pressed harder<idiom-end/><note>Literally “went harder”</note> and harder on Jabin king of Canaan, until they destroyed Jabin king of Canaan. </p>
		</chapter>