<chapter id="Jdg 8">
			<pericope>Gideon Pursues Zebah and Zalmunna</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 8:1">1</verse-number>The men of Ephraim said to him, “What <supplied>is</supplied> this thing you have done to us, not calling us when you went to fight against the Midianites?”<note>Hebrew “Midianite”</note> And they quarreled with him severely. <verse-number id="Jdg 8:2">2</verse-number>And he said to them, “What I have done now in comparison with you? Are not the gleanings of Ephraim better than the grape harvest of Abiezer? <verse-number id="Jdg 8:3">3</verse-number>God has given into your hand the commanders of Midian, Oreb, and Zeeb. What have I been able to do in comparison with you?” And their <idiom-start/>anger<idiom-end/><note>Literally “spirit”</note> against him subsided when <idiom-start/>he said that<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “he said this thing/word”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 8:4">4</verse-number>Then Gideon came to the Jordan, crossing it with the three hundred men who <supplied>were</supplied> with him, weary and pursuing. <verse-number id="Jdg 8:5">5</verse-number>He said to the men of Succoth, “Please give loaves of bread to the people who <supplied>are</supplied> <idiom-start/>following me<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “at my feet”</note> for they <supplied>are</supplied> weary, and I am pursuing Zebah and Zalmunna, the kings of Midian.” <verse-number id="Jdg 8:6">6</verse-number>The officials of Succoth said, “Is the hand<note>Or “palm”</note> of Zebah and Zalmunna in your hand now, that we should give bread to your army?” <verse-number id="Jdg 8:7">7</verse-number>Gideon said, “Well then, when Yahweh gives Zebah and Zalmunna into my hand, I will trample your flesh with the thorns and briers of the wilderness.” <verse-number id="Jdg 8:8">8</verse-number>He went from there <supplied>to</supplied> Penuel, and he spoke similarly to them; and the men of Penuel answered him just as the men of Succoth answered. <verse-number id="Jdg 8:9">9</verse-number>And he said also to the men of Penuel, saying, “When I return <idiom-start/>safely<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “in peace”</note> I will tear down this tower.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 8:10">10</verse-number>Now Zebah and Zalmunna <supplied>were</supplied> in Karkor, and their armies with them, about fifteen thousand men remained from the entire army<note>Or “camp”</note> of the people of <supplied>the</supplied> east; those that fell <supplied>in battle were</supplied> one hundred and twenty thousand <idiom-start/>swordsmen<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sword-drawing men”</note> <verse-number id="Jdg 8:11">11</verse-number>And Gideon went up the route of those who dwell in tents on the east of Nobah and Jogbehah, and he attacked the army<note>Or “camp”</note> when it was off its guard.<note>Or “unsuspecting”</note> <verse-number id="Jdg 8:12">12</verse-number>And Zebah and Zalmunna fled, and he pursued them and captured the two kings of Midian, Zebah and Zalmunna, and he routed<note>Or “he frightened” or “he threw into panic”</note> the entire army.<note>Or “camp”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 8:13">13</verse-number>Then Gideon son of Jehoash returned from the battle <idiom-start/>by way of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from”</note> the ascent of Heres.<note>Or “pass of Heres”</note> <verse-number id="Jdg 8:14">14</verse-number>He captured a young man <idiom-start/>from Succoth<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from the men of Succoth”</note> and questioned him. <supplied>The young man</supplied> listed<note>Or “wrote down”</note> for him the commanders of Succoth and its elders, seventy-seven men. <verse-number id="Jdg 8:15">15</verse-number>He came to the men of Succoth, and he said, “Here <supplied>is</supplied> Zebah and Zalmunna, about whom you taunted me, saying, ‘<supplied>Is</supplied> the palm<note>Or “hand”</note> of Zebah and Zalmunna in your hand now, that we should give food to your weary men?’ ” <verse-number id="Jdg 8:16">16</verse-number>He took the elders of the city and <supplied>the</supplied> thorn bushes and briers of the wilderness, and <idiom-start/>he trampled<idiom-end/><note>Literally “he taught,” but see v. <cite title="BibleLEB2:Jdg 8:7">7</cite></note> the men of Succoth with them. <verse-number id="Jdg 8:17">17</verse-number>He broke down the tower of Penuel, and he killed the men of the city. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 8:18">18</verse-number>And he said to Zebah and Zalmunna, “What type <supplied>were</supplied> the men whom you killed at Tabor?” And they said, “<idiom-start/>They were like you<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally, “like you, like them”</note> each <supplied>one of them</supplied> had the appearance of the sons of the king.” <verse-number id="Jdg 8:19">19</verse-number>He said, “They <supplied>were</supplied> my brothers, the sons of my mother. As Yahweh lives, if you had kept them alive I would not kill you.” <verse-number id="Jdg 8:20">20</verse-number>And he said to Jether, his firstborn, “Get up, kill them.” But the boy did not draw his sword, for he was afraid because he <supplied>was</supplied> still a boy. <verse-number id="Jdg 8:21">21</verse-number>Zebah and Zalmunna said, “Get up yourself, and strike us, for as <supplied>is</supplied> the man, so <supplied>is</supplied> his power.”<note>Or “strength”</note> So Gideon got up and killed Zebah and Zalmunna, and he took the crescent ornaments that were on the necks of their camels. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 8:22">22</verse-number>The men of Israel said to Gideon, “Rule over us, both you and your sons, and your sons’ son, for you have delivered us from the hand of Midian. <verse-number id="Jdg 8:23">23</verse-number>But Gideon said to them, “I will not rule over you, and my son will not rule over you; Yahweh will rule over you.” <verse-number id="Jdg 8:24">24</verse-number>And Gideon said to them, “<idiom-start/>Let me make a request of you<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “Let me ask from you a request”</note> that each of you give to me an ornamental ring from his plunder.” (They <supplied>had</supplied> ornamental rings of gold, because they <supplied>were</supplied> Ishmaelites.) <verse-number id="Jdg 8:25">25</verse-number>They said, “We will gladly give <supplied>them</supplied>,” and they spread out a garment, and everyone threw there an ornamental ring of his plunder. <verse-number id="Jdg 8:26">26</verse-number>The weight of the ornamental rings of gold that he requested <supplied>was</supplied> one thousand seven hundred <supplied>shekels of</supplied> gold, apart from the crescents, pendants, and purple garments that <supplied>were</supplied> on the kings of Midian, and apart from the pendants that <supplied>were</supplied> on the necks of their camels. <verse-number id="Jdg 8:27">27</verse-number>Gideon made an ephod <supplied>out of</supplied> it, and he put it in his town in Ophrah, and all Israel prostituted <supplied>themselves</supplied> to it there, and it became a snare to Gideon and his family. <verse-number id="Jdg 8:28">28</verse-number>And Midian was subdued before the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and they did not again lift up their head, and the land rested for forty years in the days of Gideon. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Death of Gideon</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 8:29">29</verse-number>Jerub-Baal son of Joash lived in his own house. <verse-number id="Jdg 8:30">30</verse-number>Now Gideon had seventy sons, <idiom-start/>his own offspring<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from his own loins”</note> for he had many wives. <verse-number id="Jdg 8:31">31</verse-number>His concubine who <supplied>was</supplied> in Shechem also bore for him a son, and <idiom-start/>he named him<idiom-end/><note>Literally “he set his name”</note> Abimelech. <verse-number id="Jdg 8:32">32</verse-number>And Gideon son of Joash died at a good old age, and he was buried in the tomb of Jehoash his father, in Ophrah <supplied>of</supplied> the Abiezrites.<note>Hebrew “Abiezrite”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 8:33">33</verse-number>And it happened, as soon as Gideon died, the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> returned and prostituted <supplied>themselves</supplied> after the Baals, and they made for themselves Baal-Berith as god. <verse-number id="Jdg 8:34">34</verse-number>The <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> did not remember Yahweh their God, who had delivered them from the hand of their enemies from all around, <verse-number id="Jdg 8:35">35</verse-number>nor did they show favor<note>Or “loyalty”</note> to the house of Jerub-Baal (<supplied>that is</supplied>, Gideon) in accordance with all the good that he did for Israel. </p>
		</chapter>