<chapter id="Jdg 10">
			<pericope>The Philistines and Ammonites Afflict the Israelites</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 10:1">1</verse-number>After Abimelech, Tola son of Puah son of Dod, a man of Issachar, rose up to deliver Israel; and he <supplied>was</supplied> living at Shamir in the hill country of Ephraim. <verse-number id="Jdg 10:2">2</verse-number>And he judged Israel twenty-three years. And he died and was buried in Shamir. <verse-number id="Jdg 10:3">3</verse-number>After him Jair the Gileadite rose up, and he judged Israel twenty-two years. <verse-number id="Jdg 10:4">4</verse-number>And he had thirty sons who would ride on thirty donkeys, and they had thirty towns that <supplied>are</supplied> in the land of Gilead that they called Havvoth Jair until this day. <verse-number id="Jdg 10:5">5</verse-number>And Jair died and was buried in Kamon. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 10:6">6</verse-number>And again, the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> did evil in the eyes of Yahweh. They served the Baals, the Ashtaroth, the gods of Aram, Sidon, Moab, and the gods of the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Ammon”</note> and Philistines; they abandoned Yahweh and did not serve him. <verse-number id="Jdg 10:7">7</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>the anger of Yahweh burned<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the nose of Yahweh became hot”</note> against Israel, and he sold them into the hand of <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines and the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sons/children of Ammon”</note> <verse-number id="Jdg 10:8">8</verse-number>They crushed and oppressed the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> in that year; for eighteen years they <supplied>crushed</supplied> all the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> who <supplied>were</supplied> beyond the Jordan, in the land of the Amorites,<note>Hebrew “Amorite”</note> which <supplied>is</supplied> in Gilead. <verse-number id="Jdg 10:9">9</verse-number>The <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Ammon”</note> crossed the Jordan to fight also against Judah, Benjamin, and the house of Ephraim; and Israel was very distressed. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 10:10">10</verse-number>Then the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> cried out to Yahweh, saying, “We have sinned against you; we have abandoned our God and served the Baals.” <verse-number id="Jdg 10:11">11</verse-number>And Yahweh said to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> “<supplied>Did I</supplied> not <supplied>deliver you</supplied> from <supplied>the</supplied> Egyptians,<note>Hebrew “from Egypt”</note> the Amorites,<note>Hebrew “Amorite”</note> from the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Ammon”</note> and from the Philistines?<note>Hebrew “Philistine”</note> <verse-number id="Jdg 10:12">12</verse-number>And when <supplied>the</supplied> Sidonians, <supplied>the</supplied> Amalekites,<note>Hebrew “Amalekite”</note> and <supplied>the</supplied> Maonites<note>Hebrew “Maonite”</note> oppressed you, you cried out to me, and I delivered you from their hand. <verse-number id="Jdg 10:13">13</verse-number>Yet you have abandoned me and served other gods. Therefore I will no longer deliver you. <verse-number id="Jdg 10:14">14</verse-number>Go and cry out to the gods whom you have chosen; let them deliver you in the time of your trouble.” <verse-number id="Jdg 10:15">15</verse-number>And the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> said to Yahweh, “We have sinned; <idiom-start/>do to us accordingly as you see fit<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “do to us according to the good in your eyes”</note> only please deliver us this day.” <verse-number id="Jdg 10:16">16</verse-number>So they removed the foreign gods from their midst and served Yahweh; and <idiom-start/>he could no longer bear<idiom-end/><note>Literally “his soul was short with”</note> the misery of Israel. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 10:17">17</verse-number>And the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Ammon”</note> were summoned,<note>Or “were called to arms”</note> and they camped in Gilead. And the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> gathered and camped at Mizpah. <verse-number id="Jdg 10:18">18</verse-number>The people, the ones commanding Gilead, <idiom-start/>said to each other<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “said each to his neighbor”</note> “Who <supplied>is</supplied> the man that will begin to fight against the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/>?<note>Literally “sons/children of Ammon”</note> He will be as head over all the inhabitants of Gilead.” </p>
		</chapter>