<chapter id="Jdg 11">
			<pericope>Jephthah</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 11:1">1</verse-number>Jephthah the Gileadite was a mighty warrior; he was the son of a prostitute, and <idiom-start/>Gilead was his father<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “Gilead fathered Jephthah”</note> <verse-number id="Jdg 11:2">2</verse-number>Gilead’s wife also bore for him sons; and the sons of <supplied>his</supplied> wife grew up and drove Jephthah away, and they said to him, “You will not inherit the house of our father because you <supplied>are</supplied> the son of another woman.” <verse-number id="Jdg 11:3">3</verse-number>So Jephthah fled from the presence of his brothers, and he lived in the land of Tob. And <idiom-start/>outlaws<idiom-end/><note>Literally “unprincipled/worthless men”</note> gathered around Jephthah and went with him. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 11:4">4</verse-number>After a time the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Ammon”</note> made war with Israel. <verse-number id="Jdg 11:5">5</verse-number>When the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Ammon”</note> made war with Israel, the elders of Gilead went to bring Jephthah from the land of Tob. <verse-number id="Jdg 11:6">6</verse-number>And they said to Jephthah, “Come and be our commander, so that we may make war against the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “sons/children of Ammon”</note> <verse-number id="Jdg 11:7">7</verse-number>Jephthah said to the elders, “Did you not shun me and drive me out from the house of my father? Why do you come to me now when you have trouble?” <verse-number id="Jdg 11:8">8</verse-number>And the elders of Gilead said to Jephthah, “That being so, we have now returned to you, that you may go with us <idiom-start/>to fight<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to make war”</note> against the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Ammon”</note> and become for us as head of all the inhabitants of Gilead.” <verse-number id="Jdg 11:9">9</verse-number>So Jephthah said to the elders of Gilead, “If you bring me back <idiom-start/>to fight<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to make war”</note> against the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Ammon”</note> and Yahweh gives them <idiom-start/>over to me<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “before me”</note> will I be your head?” <verse-number id="Jdg 11:10">10</verse-number>And the elders of Gilead said to Jephthah, “Yahweh will be a <idiom-start/>witness<idiom-end/><note>Literally “hearer”</note> between us; we will act according to your word.” <verse-number id="Jdg 11:11">11</verse-number>So Jephthah went with the elders of Gilead, and the people made him head and commander over them. And Jephthah spoke all his words before Yahweh at Mizpah. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 11:12">12</verse-number>And Jephthah sent messengers to the king of the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Ammon”</note> saying, “What <supplied>is between</supplied> you and me that you have come to me to make war against my land?” <verse-number id="Jdg 11:13">13</verse-number>And the king of the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Ammon”</note> said to Jephthah’s messengers, “Because Israel took my land from <supplied>the</supplied> Arnon up to the Jabbok and the Jordan when they came up from Egypt; so then, restore it peacefully.” <verse-number id="Jdg 11:14">14</verse-number>Once again Jephthah sent messengers to the king of the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Ammon”</note> <verse-number id="Jdg 11:15">15</verse-number>and he said to him, “Thus says Jephthah, ‘Israel did not take the land of Moab or the land of the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Ammon”</note> <verse-number id="Jdg 11:16">16</verse-number>because when they came up from Egypt, Israel went through the wilderness to the <idiom-start/>Red Sea<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sea of reed”</note> and went to Kadesh. <verse-number id="Jdg 11:17">17</verse-number>Israel sent messengers to the king of Edom, saying, “Please let us cross through your land,” but the king of Edom would not listen. And they also sent <supplied>messengers</supplied> to the king of Moab, but he was not willing. So Israel stayed in Kadesh. <verse-number id="Jdg 11:18">18</verse-number>Then they traveled through the wilderness, went around the land of Edom and Moab, and came to <idiom-start/>the east<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<supplied>from</supplied> rise of sun”</note> side of the land of Moab, and they<note>Hebrew “he”</note> encamped beyond <supplied>the</supplied> Arnon; and they did not go into the territory of Moab because <supplied>the</supplied> Arnon <supplied>was</supplied> the border of Moab. <verse-number id="Jdg 11:19">19</verse-number>Israel sent messengers to Sihon king of the Amorites,<note>Hebrew “Amorite”</note> king of Heshbon; and Israel said to him, ‘Please let us cross through your land <idiom-start/>to our country<idiom-end/>.’<note>Literally “to our place”</note> <verse-number id="Jdg 11:20">20</verse-number>But Sihon did not trust Israel to cross through his territory, so Sihon gathered all his people and then encamped at Jahaz; and he made war with Israel. <verse-number id="Jdg 11:21">21</verse-number>And Yahweh, the God of Israel, gave Sihon and all his people into the hand of Israel, and they defeated them; and Israel occupied all the land of the Amorites<note>Hebrew “Amorite”</note> inhabiting that land. <verse-number id="Jdg 11:22">22</verse-number>They occupied all the territory of the Amorites<note>Hebrew “Amorite”</note> from <supplied>the</supplied> Arnon up to the Jabbok, and from the wilderness up to the Jordan. <verse-number id="Jdg 11:23">23</verse-number>So then Yahweh, the God of Israel, has driven out the Amorites<note>Hebrew “Amorite”</note> from before his people Israel, and you want to possess it? <verse-number id="Jdg 11:24">24</verse-number>Do you not possess what Chemosh your god gave you to possess? Whoever Yahweh our God has driven out before us, we will possess it. <verse-number id="Jdg 11:25">25</verse-number>So then, <supplied>are</supplied> you any better than Balak son of Zippor, king of Moab? Did he ever quarrel with Israel, or did he ever make war against them? <verse-number id="Jdg 11:26">26</verse-number>When Israel lived in Heshbon and its villages, and in Aroer and its villages, and in all the towns that <supplied>are</supplied> <idiom-start/>along the Arnon<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “on the hands of the Arnon”</note> for three hundred years,<note>Hebrew “year”</note> why did you not recover <supplied>them</supplied> at that time? <verse-number id="Jdg 11:27">27</verse-number>I have not sinned against you; but you <supplied>are</supplied> the one who is doing wrong by making war against me. <idiom-start/>Let Yahweh judge<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Let Yahweh the judge, judge”</note> today between the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “sons/children of Ammon”</note> <verse-number id="Jdg 11:28">28</verse-number>But the king of the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Ammon”</note> did not listen to the message that Jephthah sent to him. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Jephthah Makes a Vow</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 11:29">29</verse-number>And the Spirit of Yahweh came upon Jephthah, and he passed through Gilead and Manasseh. He passed through Mizpah of Gilead, and from Mizpah of Gilead he passed through <supplied>to</supplied> the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sons/children of Ammon”</note> <verse-number id="Jdg 11:30">30</verse-number>And Jephthah made a vow to Yahweh, and he said, “If indeed you will give the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Ammon”</note> into my hand, <verse-number id="Jdg 11:31">31</verse-number>whatever<note>Or “whoever”</note> comes out from the doors of my house to meet me when I return safely from the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Ammon”</note> will be Yahweh’s, and I will offer it <supplied>as</supplied> a burnt offering.” <verse-number id="Jdg 11:32">32</verse-number>And Jephthah crossed <supplied>over</supplied> to the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Ammon”</note> to make war against them; and Yahweh gave them into his hand. <verse-number id="Jdg 11:33">33</verse-number>And he defeated them <supplied>with</supplied> a very great blow, from Aroer as far as Minnith, twenty towns,<note>Hebrew “town”</note> up to Abel Keramim. And the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Ammon”</note> were subdued before the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 11:34">34</verse-number>Jephthah came to Mizpah, to his house, and behold his daughter came out to meet him with tambourines and dancing. She <supplied>was</supplied> his only child; he did not have a son or daughter except her. <verse-number id="Jdg 11:35">35</verse-number>And the moment he saw her, he tore his clothes and said, “Ah! My daughter, you have caused me to bow down, and you have become my trouble. <idiom-start/>I made an oath<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I have opened wide my mouth”</note> to Yahweh, and I cannot take <supplied>it</supplied> back.” <verse-number id="Jdg 11:36">36</verse-number>She said to him, “My father, <idiom-start/>you made an oath<idiom-end/><note>Literally “you have opened wide your mouth”</note> to Yahweh. Do to me according to what has gone out from your mouth, since Yahweh gave vengeance to you against your enemies, the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “sons/children of Ammon”</note> <verse-number id="Jdg 11:37">37</verse-number>And she said to her father, “Let this thing be done for me: grant me two months so that I may go wander<note>Hebrew “down”</note> on the mountains and lament over my virginity, I and my companions. <verse-number id="Jdg 11:38">38</verse-number>And he said, “Go.” He sent her away <supplied>for</supplied> two months, and she went with her friends, and she lamented over her virginity on the mountains. <verse-number id="Jdg 11:39">39</verse-number>At the end of the two months she returned to her father, and he did to her <supplied>according to</supplied> his vow; and <idiom-start/>she did not sleep with a man<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “she did not know a man”</note> And it became an annual custom in Israel <verse-number id="Jdg 11:40">40</verse-number>for the daughters of Israel to go and lament the daughter of Jephthah the Gileadite for forty days of the year. </p>
		</chapter>