<chapter id="Jdg 12">
			<pericope>Tribal Conflict Between Gilead and Ephraim</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 12:1">1</verse-number>The men of Ephraim were called to arms, and they crossed <supplied>over</supplied> to Zaphon and said to Jephthah, “Why did you cross <supplied>over</supplied> and make war against the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Ammon”</note> and why did you not call us to go with you? We will burn down your house over you with fire.” <verse-number id="Jdg 12:2">2</verse-number>And Jephthah said to them, “I and my people were engaged in great conflict with the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “sons/children of Ammon”</note> I called you, but you did not deliver me from their hand. <verse-number id="Jdg 12:3">3</verse-number>I saw that you would not deliver <supplied>us</supplied>; <idiom-start/>I risked my own life<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “I put my life in my hand”</note> and I crossed <supplied>over</supplied> to the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Ammon”</note> and Yahweh gave them into my hand. Why have you come up to me this day to fight against me?” <verse-number id="Jdg 12:4">4</verse-number>Jephthah gathered all the men of Gilead, and he made war with Ephraim; and the men of Gilead defeated Ephraim because they said, “You <supplied>are</supplied> fugitives of Ephraim, you Gileadites, in the midst of Ephraim and Manasseh.” <verse-number id="Jdg 12:5">5</verse-number>Then Gilead captured the fords of the Jordan from Ephraim, and whenever a fugitive of Ephraim said, “Let me cross <supplied>over</supplied>,” the men of Gilead said to him, “<supplied>Are</supplied> you an Ephraimite?” <supplied>When</supplied> he said, “No,” <verse-number id="Jdg 12:6">6</verse-number>they said to him, “Please say Shibboleth,” and <supplied>if</supplied> he said, “Sibboleth”—because he could not <idiom-start/>pronounce it<idiom-end/><note>Literally “speak it”</note> correctly—they grabbed him and executed him at the fords of Jordan. At that time forty-two thousand from Ephraim fell. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 12:7">7</verse-number>Jephthah judged Israel six years. Then Jephthah the Gileadite died, and he was buried in <supplied>one of</supplied> the cities of Gilead. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Ibzan, Elon, and Abdon</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 12:8">8</verse-number>After him Ibzan from Bethlehem judged Israel. <verse-number id="Jdg 12:9">9</verse-number>He had thirty sons. He gave his thirty daughters away in marriage outside <supplied>his clan</supplied> and brought in from outside thirty young women for his sons. He judged Israel for seven years. <verse-number id="Jdg 12:10">10</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Ibzan died and was buried in Bethlehem. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 12:11">11</verse-number>After him Elon the Zebulunite judged Israel, and he judged Israel ten years. <verse-number id="Jdg 12:12">12</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Elon the Zebulunite died and was buried in Aijalon in the land of Zebulun. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 12:13">13</verse-number>After him Abdon the son of Hillel the Pirathonite judged Israel. <verse-number id="Jdg 12:14">14</verse-number>He had forty sons and thirty grandsons that rode on seventy male donkeys. He judged Israel for eight years. <verse-number id="Jdg 12:15">15</verse-number>Then<note>Or “And”</note> Abdon the son of Hillel the Pirathonite died and was buried in Pirathon, in the land of Ephraim in the hill country of the Amalekites.<note>Hebrew “Amalekite”</note> </p>
		</chapter>