<chapter id="Jdg 14">
			<pericope>Samson Marries</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 14:1">1</verse-number>And Samson went down to Timnah, and he saw a woman in Timnah from the daughters of the Philistines. <verse-number id="Jdg 14:2">2</verse-number>He went up and told his father and mother, and he said, “I saw a woman in Timnah from the daughters of <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines; so then, take her for me as a wife.” <verse-number id="Jdg 14:3">3</verse-number>But his father and mother said to him, “Is there not a wife among the daughters of your relatives, or among all our<note>Hebrew “my”</note> people, that you must take a wife from <supplied>the</supplied> uncircumcised Philistines?” But Samson said to his father, “Take her for me because <idiom-start/>she pleases me<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “she is right in my eyes”</note> <verse-number id="Jdg 14:4">4</verse-number>His father and mother did not know that this <supplied>was</supplied> from Yahweh; he was seeking for an occasion against <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines. Now at that time <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines <supplied>were</supplied> ruling<note>Or “having control”</note> in Israel. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 14:5">5</verse-number>And Samson and his father and mother went down to Timnah, and they came to the vineyards of Timnah, and suddenly a young lion <supplied>came</supplied> roaring to meet him. <verse-number id="Jdg 14:6">6</verse-number>And the Spirit of Yahweh rushed upon him, and he tore the lion apart as one might tear apart a male kid goat (<idiom-start/>he was bare-handed<idiom-end/>).<note>Literally “there was nothing in his hand”</note> But he did not tell his father and mother what he had done. <verse-number id="Jdg 14:7">7</verse-number>Then he went down and talked to the woman, and <idiom-start/>she pleased Samson<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “she did what was right in the eyes of Samson”</note> <verse-number id="Jdg 14:8">8</verse-number>And he returned after awhile <idiom-start/>to marry her<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to take her”</note> and he turned aside to see the carcass of the lion, and there <supplied>was</supplied> a swarm of wild honey bees in the body of the lion, and honey. <verse-number id="Jdg 14:9">9</verse-number>He scraped it out into his hands, and he went on, eating <supplied>it</supplied> as he went. And he went to his father and mother and gave <supplied>some</supplied> to them, and they ate it. But he did not tell them that he had scraped the honey from the body of the lion. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 14:10">10</verse-number>His father went down to the woman, and Samson prepared there a feast, as young men were accustomed to doing this. <verse-number id="Jdg 14:11">11</verse-number>When they saw him, they took thirty companions, and they were with him. <verse-number id="Jdg 14:12">12</verse-number>And Samson said to them, “Let me tell you a riddle. If you can fully explain it to me within the seven days of the feast, and find <supplied>it out</supplied>, I will give to you thirty linen garments and thirty festal garments. <verse-number id="Jdg 14:13">13</verse-number>But if you are unable to explain it to me, you must give me thirty linen garments and thirty festal garments.” So they said to him, “Tell your riddle; let us hear it.” <verse-number id="Jdg 14:14">14</verse-number>He said to them, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“From the eater came out food, </li1>
				<li2>From <supplied>the</supplied> strong came out sweet.” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p>But they were unable to explain the riddle for three days. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 14:15">15</verse-number>When it was the fourth<note>Hebrew “seventh”; other ancient translations have “fourth”</note> day, they said to Samson’s wife, “Entice your husband and tell us the riddle, or we will burn you and your father’s house with fire. Have you invited us to rob us?” <verse-number id="Jdg 14:16">16</verse-number>And Samson’s wife wept before him, and she said, “You must hate me; you do not love me. You told the riddle to <idiom-start/>my people<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the sons/children of my people”</note> but you have not explained <supplied>it</supplied> to me.” He said to her, “I have not explained <supplied>it</supplied> to my father and mother. <supplied>Why</supplied> should I explain it to you?” <verse-number id="Jdg 14:17">17</verse-number>She wept before him the seven days of their feast; and it happened, because she nagged him, on the seventh day he explained <supplied>it</supplied> to her, and she told the riddle to <idiom-start/>her people<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the sons/children of her people”</note> <verse-number id="Jdg 14:18">18</verse-number>The men of the city said to him on the seventh day before the sun went <supplied>down</supplied>, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“What <supplied>is</supplied> sweeter than honey? </li1>
				<li2>What <supplied>is</supplied> stronger than a lion?” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p>And he said to them, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“If you had not plowed with my heifer, </li1>
				<li2>you would not have found out my riddle.” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 14:19">19</verse-number>And the Spirit of Yahweh rushed on him, and he went down to Ashkelon. He killed thirty men from them, and he took their belongings, and he gave festal garments to the ones that explained the riddle. <idiom-start/>He was angry<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “his nose was hot”</note> and he went up to his father’s house. <verse-number id="Jdg 14:20">20</verse-number>And Samson’s wife was <supplied>given</supplied> to his companion who <supplied>was</supplied> his best man.<note>Or “friend”</note> </p>
		</chapter>