<chapter id="Jdg 15">
			<pericope>Samson Defeats the Philistines</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 15:1">1</verse-number>After a while, at the time of the wheat harvest, Samson visited his wife with a <idiom-start/>young goat<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “kid of goat”</note> He said, “I want to go to my wife’s private room.” But her father would not allow him to enter. <verse-number id="Jdg 15:2">2</verse-number>Her father said, “I really thought that you hated her, so I gave her to your companion. <supplied>Is</supplied> not her younger sister more beautiful than she? Please, <idiom-start/>take her instead<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “let her be in the place of her”</note> <verse-number id="Jdg 15:3">3</verse-number>And Samson said to them, “This time, as far as the Philistines are concerned, when I do something evil I am without blame.” <verse-number id="Jdg 15:4">4</verse-number>And Samson went and captured three hundred foxes, and he took torches. He turned <supplied>them</supplied> tail to tail, and he put one torch between two tails. <verse-number id="Jdg 15:5">5</verse-number>He set fire to the torches and let <supplied>the foxes</supplied> go into the standing grain of <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines, and he burned both the stacks<note>Hebrew “stack”</note> of sheaves and the standing grain, up to the vineyards<note>Hebrew “vineyard”</note> of olive groves. <verse-number id="Jdg 15:6">6</verse-number>And <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines said, “Who has done this?” And they said, “Samson the son-in-law of the Timnite, because he took his wife and gave her to his companion.” And <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines went up and burned her and her father with fire. <verse-number id="Jdg 15:7">7</verse-number>Samson said to them, “If you want to behave like this, <supplied>I swear</supplied> I will not rest unless I have taken revenge on you.” <verse-number id="Jdg 15:8">8</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>he gave them a thorough beating<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “he struck them hip and thigh <supplied>with</supplied> a great blow”</note> and he went down and stayed in the cleft of the rock of Etam. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 15:9">9</verse-number>Then <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines came up and encamped in Judah, and they overran Lehi. <verse-number id="Jdg 15:10">10</verse-number>And the men of Judah said, “Why have you come up against us?” And they said, “To bind Samson; to do to him just as he did to us.” <verse-number id="Jdg 15:11">11</verse-number>Then three thousand men from Judah went down to the cleft of the rock of Etam, and they said to Samson, “Do you not know that the Philistines <supplied>are</supplied> ruling over us? What <supplied>is</supplied> this <supplied>that</supplied> you have done to us?” And he said to them, “Just as they did to me, so I have done to them.” <verse-number id="Jdg 15:12">12</verse-number>They said to him, “We have come down to bind you and give you over into the hand of <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines.” And Samson said to them, “Swear to me that you will not attack me yourselves.” <verse-number id="Jdg 15:13">13</verse-number>They said to him, “No, we will only bind you and give you into their hand; we will certainly not kill you.” So they bound him with two new ropes, and they brought him up from the rock. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 15:14">14</verse-number>As he came up to Lehi, <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines came shouting to meet him; and the Spirit of Yahweh rushed on him, and the ropes that <supplied>were</supplied> on his arms became like flax that has burned with fire, and his bindings melted from his hands. <verse-number id="Jdg 15:15">15</verse-number>And he found a fresh jawbone of a donkey; he reached down and took it and killed one thousand men with it. <verse-number id="Jdg 15:16">16</verse-number>And Samson said, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“With the jawbone of the donkey, </li1>
				<li2>heap upon heap; </li2>
				<li1>with the jawbone of the donkey, </li1>
				<li2>I struck dead one thousand men.” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 15:17">17</verse-number>And it happened, when he finished speaking he threw the jawbone from his hand; and he called that place Ramath Lehi.<note>That is, “Hill of the Jawbone”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 15:18">18</verse-number>And he was very thirsty, and he called to Yahweh and said, “You gave this great victory into the hand of your servant, but now I must die of thirst and fall into the hand of the uncircumcised?” <verse-number id="Jdg 15:19">19</verse-number>So God split the hollow place that <supplied>is</supplied> at Lehi, and water came out from it; and he drank, and his spirit returned, and he was revived. Thus he called its name <idiom-start/>The Spring of Ha-Qore<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the spring of the one who called” or “En-hakkore”</note> which <supplied>is</supplied> at Lehi to this day. <verse-number id="Jdg 15:20">20</verse-number>And he judged Israel in the days of <supplied>the</supplied> Philistines twenty years. </p>
		</chapter>