<chapter id="Jdg 17">
			<pericope>Micah’s Idolatry</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 17:1">1</verse-number>There was a man from the hill country of Ephraim; his name <supplied>was</supplied> Micah. <verse-number id="Jdg 17:2">2</verse-number>And he said to his mother, “The eleven hundred <supplied>pieces</supplied> of silver that were taken from you, and about which you also pronounced a curse <idiom-start/>in my hearing<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “In my ears”</note> are with me; I took it.” And his mother said, “Blessed be my son by Yahweh.” <verse-number id="Jdg 17:3">3</verse-number>He returned the eleven hundred pieces<note>Hebrew “piece”</note> of silver to his mother, and his mother thought, “I will certainly consecrate to Yahweh the pieces<note>Hebrew “piece”</note> of silver from my hand for my son to make an idol of cast metal; now then, I will return them<note>Hebrew “it”</note> to you.” <verse-number id="Jdg 17:4">4</verse-number>When he returned the pieces<note>Hebrew “piece”</note> of silver to his mother, his mother took two hundred pieces<note>Hebrew “piece”</note> of silver, and she gave it to the smith, and he made it <supplied>into</supplied> an idol of cast metal; and it was in the house of Micah. <verse-number id="Jdg 17:5">5</verse-number>The man Micah had for himself <idiom-start/>a shrine<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “a house of god”</note> and he made an ephod and teraphim, and <idiom-start/>he appointed one of his sons<idiom-end/><note>Literally “he filled the hand of one of his sons”</note> who became a priest for him. <verse-number id="Jdg 17:6">6</verse-number>In those days there was no king in Israel, and each one did what was right in his own eyes. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 17:7">7</verse-number>There was a young man from Bethlehem in Judah, from the clan of Judah; he <supplied>was</supplied> a Levite and <supplied>was</supplied> dwelling as a foreigner<note>Or “alien”</note> there. <verse-number id="Jdg 17:8">8</verse-number>And the man went from the town of Bethlehem in Judah to live as a foreigner<note>Or “alien”</note> wherever he could find <supplied>a place</supplied>. And he came <supplied>to</supplied> the hill country of Ephraim, to the house of Micah, to continue his journey. <verse-number id="Jdg 17:9">9</verse-number>And Micah said to him, “From where do you come?” And he said to him, “I <supplied>am</supplied> a Levite from Bethlehem in Judah; I <supplied>am</supplied> going to dwell as a foreigner<note>Or “alien”</note> wherever I can find <supplied>a place</supplied>.” <verse-number id="Jdg 17:10">10</verse-number>And Micah said to him, “Stay with me and be to me a father and a priest, and I will give to you ten pieces<note>Hebrew “piece”</note> of silver a year, a set of clothes, and your food.” So the Levite went <supplied>with him</supplied>. <verse-number id="Jdg 17:11">11</verse-number>The Levite agreed to stay with the man; and the young man became as one of his sons. <verse-number id="Jdg 17:12">12</verse-number>So Micah <idiom-start/>appointed the Levite<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “filled the hand of the Levite”</note> and the young man became a priest for him; and he was in the house of Micah. <verse-number id="Jdg 17:13">13</verse-number>And Micah said, “Now I know Yahweh will make me prosperous, because the Levite has become my priest.” </p>
		</chapter>