<chapter id="Jdg 18">
			<pericope>The Tribe of Dan Seeks Territory</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 18:1">1</verse-number>In those days there was no king in Israel. And in those days the tribe of the Danites <supplied>was</supplied> seeking territory for itself to live in, because until that day it had not been allotted territory among the tribes of Israel. <verse-number id="Jdg 18:2">2</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons/children”</note> of Dan sent from the whole number of their clan five <idiom-start/>capable men<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons of physical strength”</note> from Zorah and Eshtaol to spy out the land and to explore it. And they said to them, “Go, explore the land.” And they went to the hill country of Ephraim, to the house of Micah, and they spent the night there.<note>Or “they lodged there”</note> <verse-number id="Jdg 18:3">3</verse-number>While they <supplied>were</supplied> with the house of Micah, they recognized the voice of the young Levite, and they turned aside there and said to him, “Who brought you here? What <supplied>are</supplied> you doing in this place, and <idiom-start/>what is your business here<idiom-end/>?”<note>Literally “What is for you here?”</note> <verse-number id="Jdg 18:4">4</verse-number>And he said to them, “Micah did such and such for me and hired me, and I became his priest.” <verse-number id="Jdg 18:5">5</verse-number>And they said to him, “Please inquire of God that we may know whether our journey that we <supplied>are</supplied> going on will be successful.” <verse-number id="Jdg 18:6">6</verse-number>And the priest said to them, “Go in peace. Yahweh <supplied>is</supplied> in front of you on the journey you want to go on.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 18:7">7</verse-number>And the five men went and came to Laish, and they observed the people who <supplied>were</supplied> living according to the customs of <supplied>the</supplied> Sidonians, quiet and unsuspecting, and lacking nothing in the land, and possessing restraint.<note>Or perhaps “prosperity”; the Hebrew of this word is uncertain</note> And they <supplied>were</supplied> far from <supplied>the</supplied> Sidonians and had no word with anyone. <verse-number id="Jdg 18:8">8</verse-number>They came to their relatives<note>Or “brothers”</note> <supplied>at</supplied> Zorah and Eshtaol, and their relatives<note>Or “brothers”</note> said to them, “What <supplied>do</supplied> you <supplied>report</supplied>?” <verse-number id="Jdg 18:9">9</verse-number>And they said to them, “Come, let us go up against them; for we have seen the land, and <supplied>it is</supplied> very good. Will you do nothing? Do not hesitate to go, to enter, to possess the land. <verse-number id="Jdg 18:10">10</verse-number>When you go you will come to an unsuspecting people, and the land <idiom-start/>is spread out on all sides<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “<supplied>is</supplied> wide of hands”</note> God has given a place into your hands where there is no lack of anything that <supplied>is</supplied> on the earth.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 18:11">11</verse-number>Six hundred men from the clan of the Danites from Zorah and Eshtaol, armed <supplied>with</supplied> weapons of war, set out from there. <verse-number id="Jdg 18:12">12</verse-number>They went up and encamped at Kiriath Jearim in Judah. Therefore they called this place Camp of Dan<note>That is “Mahaneh-dan”</note> to this day; it is west of Kiriath Jearim. <verse-number id="Jdg 18:13">13</verse-number>From there they crossed <supplied>over to</supplied> the hill country of Ephraim, and they came to the house of Micah. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 18:14">14</verse-number>And the five men that went out to spy out the land (<supplied>that is</supplied>, Laish) responded and said to their relatives,<note>Or “brothers”</note> “Do you know that there are in these houses an ephod, teraphim, and an idol of cast metal? So then, consider what you must do.” <verse-number id="Jdg 18:15">15</verse-number>So they turned to that direction, and they came to the house of the young Levite, the house of Micah, and <idiom-start/>they greeted him<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “they asked for him in peace”</note> <verse-number id="Jdg 18:16">16</verse-number>And six hundred men from the descendants<note>Or “sons/children”</note> of Dan, armed <supplied>with</supplied> their weapons of war, <supplied>were</supplied> standing <supplied>at</supplied> the entrance of the gate. <verse-number id="Jdg 18:17">17</verse-number>And the five men that went to spy out the land went up, and they entered there <supplied>and</supplied> took the carved divine image, ephod, teraphim, and the molten image. The priest <supplied>was</supplied> standing <supplied>at</supplied> the entrance of the gate <supplied>with</supplied> the six hundred men armed <supplied>with</supplied> the weapons of war. <verse-number id="Jdg 18:18">18</verse-number>When these went to Micah’s house, they took the divine carved image, ephod, the teraphim, and the molten image, and the priest asked them, “What <supplied>are</supplied> you doing?” <verse-number id="Jdg 18:19">19</verse-number>And they said to him, “Keep quiet! Put your hand on your mouth and come with us and be for us a father and a priest. Is it better being a priest for a house of one man or being a priest for a tribe and clan in Israel?” <verse-number id="Jdg 18:20">20</verse-number><idiom-start/>The priest accepted the offer<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “It was good in the heart of the priest”</note> and he took the ephod, teraphim, and molten image and went along with the people. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 18:21">21</verse-number>And they turned<note>Or “resumed their journey”</note> and went and put the little children, the livestock, and the valuable property in front of them. <verse-number id="Jdg 18:22">22</verse-number>When they were at a distance from the house, Micah and the men who <supplied>were</supplied> in the houses that <supplied>were</supplied> near the house of Micah cried out, and they overtook the descendants<note>Or “sons/children”</note> of Dan. <verse-number id="Jdg 18:23">23</verse-number>And they called to the descendants<note>Or “sons/children”</note> of Dan, who turned around to face them, and they said to Micah, “What is the matter with you that you assembled together?” <verse-number id="Jdg 18:24">24</verse-number>He said, “You took away my gods that I had made, and the priest, and then you go <supplied>away</supplied>. What <supplied>is</supplied> now left for me? How can you say to me, ‘What is the matter?’ ” <verse-number id="Jdg 18:25">25</verse-number>And the descendants<note>Or “sons/children”</note> of Dan said to him, “You should not let your voice be heard among us, so that <idiom-start/>ill-tempered men<idiom-end/><note>Literally “men of bitter soul”</note> <idiom-start/>will not attack you<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “will not fall on you”</note> <idiom-start/>and take your life<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and you will lose your life”</note> and the lives of your household.” <verse-number id="Jdg 18:26">26</verse-number>And the descendants<note>Or “sons/children”</note> of Dan went their way. When Micah saw that they <supplied>were</supplied> stronger than him, he turned to return to his house. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 18:27">27</verse-number>And they took what Micah had made, and his priest, and they came to Laish, to a quiet and unsuspecting people, and <idiom-start/>they put them to the sword<idiom-end/><note>Literally “they put them to <supplied>the</supplied> mouth of <supplied>the</supplied> sword”</note> and burned the city with fire. <verse-number id="Jdg 18:28">28</verse-number>There was no deliverer, because it <supplied>was</supplied> far from Sidon, and <idiom-start/>they had had no dealings with anyone<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “a thing was not for them with anyone”</note> It <supplied>was</supplied> in the valley that belonged to Beth-rehob, and they rebuilt<note>Hebrew “built”</note> the city and lived in it. <verse-number id="Jdg 18:29">29</verse-number>And they called the name of the city Dan, after Dan their ancestor,<note>Or “father”</note> who was born to Israel; but the former name of the city <supplied>was</supplied> Laish. <verse-number id="Jdg 18:30">30</verse-number>And the descendants<note>Or “sons/children”</note> of Dan set up for themselves the carved divine image, and Jonathan son of Gershom, son of Manasseh,<note>Other ancient versions read “Moses”</note> he and his sons were priests for the tribe of the Danites until the time of the captivity of the land. <verse-number id="Jdg 18:31">31</verse-number>So they set up for themselves the carved divine image that Micah had made, all the days that the house of God <supplied>was</supplied> in Shiloh. </p>
		</chapter>