<chapter id="Jdg 19">
			<pericope>The Concubine and the Levite</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 19:1">1</verse-number>In those days there was no king in Israel; there was a man, a Levite, who dwelled as a foreigner<note>Or “alien”</note> in the remote areas of the hill country of Ephraim. And he took for himself a concubine from Bethlehem in Judah. <verse-number id="Jdg 19:2">2</verse-number>But his concubine felt repugnance toward him,<note>Other modern translations read “his concubine played the harlot against him”</note> and she left him and went to her father’s house, to Bethlehem in Judah; she was there some four months. <verse-number id="Jdg 19:3">3</verse-number>So her husband set out, and he went after her to speak <idiom-start/>tenderly to her<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “to her heart”</note> to bring her back. He took with him his servant and a pair of donkeys. And she brought him <supplied>to</supplied> her father’s house, and the father of the young woman saw him and was glad to meet him. <verse-number id="Jdg 19:4">4</verse-number>His father-in-law, the young woman’s father, urged him to stay with him three days; and they ate and drank, and they spent the night there. <verse-number id="Jdg 19:5">5</verse-number>On the fourth day, they rose early in the morning, and he prepared to go, but the father of the young woman said to his son-in-law, “<idiom-start/>Refresh yourself<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Refresh your heart”</note> <supplied>with</supplied> a bit of food, and afterward you may go.” <verse-number id="Jdg 19:6">6</verse-number>So the two of them sat and ate and drank together, and the father of the young woman said to the man, “Please, agree to spend the night and <idiom-start/>enjoy yourself<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “and let your heart be good”</note> <verse-number id="Jdg 19:7">7</verse-number>The man got up to go, but his father-in-law urged him, and he returned and spent the night there. <verse-number id="Jdg 19:8">8</verse-number>On the fifth day he rose early in the morning to go, and the father of the young woman said, “Please, <idiom-start/>enjoy yourself<idiom-end/>,”<note>Literally “and let your heart be good”</note> and they lingered until the day declined, and the two of them ate. <verse-number id="Jdg 19:9">9</verse-number>And the man got up to go—he, his concubine, and his servant—but his father-in-law, the father of the young woman, said to him, “Please, the day has worn on to evening; please, spend the night, the day has drawn to a close. Spend the night here and <idiom-start/>enjoy yourself<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “and let your heart be good”</note> You can rise early tomorrow for your journey and <idiom-start/>go to your home<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “go to your tent”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 19:10">10</verse-number>But the man was not willing to spend the night, and he got up and went; and he arrived opposite Jebus (that is, Jerusalem). <supplied>He had</supplied> with him a pair of saddled donkeys and his concubine. <verse-number id="Jdg 19:11">11</verse-number>They <supplied>were</supplied> near Jebus, and <idiom-start/>the day was far spent<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the day went down very”</note> and the servant said to his master, “Please, come, let us turn aside to this city of the Jebusites,<note>Hebrew “Jebusite”</note> and let us spend the night in it.” <verse-number id="Jdg 19:12">12</verse-number>But his master said to him, “We will not turn aside to the city of foreigners,<note>Hebrew “foreigner”</note> who <supplied>are</supplied> not from the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> we will cross over up to Gibeah.” <verse-number id="Jdg 19:13">13</verse-number>And he said to his servant, “Come, let us approach one of these places; we will spend the night in Gibeah or in Ramah.” <verse-number id="Jdg 19:14">14</verse-number>So they crossed over and went their way, and the sun went down on them beside Gibeah, which belongs to Benjamin. <verse-number id="Jdg 19:15">15</verse-number>And they turned aside there to enter <supplied>and</supplied> to spend the night at Gibeah. And they went and sat in the open square of the city, but no one <idiom-start/>took them in to spend the night<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “was receiving them to <supplied>their</supplied> house to spend the night”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 19:16">16</verse-number>Then behold, an old man <supplied>was</supplied> coming from his work from the field in the evening, and the man <supplied>was</supplied> from the hill country of Ephraim, and he <supplied>was</supplied> dwelling as a foreigner<note>Or “alien”</note> in Gibeah. (The people of the place <supplied>were</supplied> descendants<note>Or “sons/children”</note> of Benjamin.) <verse-number id="Jdg 19:17">17</verse-number>And the old man raised his eyes and saw the traveler in the open square of the city, and he said, “Where are you going, and from where do you come?” <verse-number id="Jdg 19:18">18</verse-number>And he said to him, “We <supplied>are</supplied> crossing over from Bethlehem in Judah up to the remote areas of the hill country of Ephraim, where I <supplied>am</supplied> from. I went to Bethlehem in Judah, but <supplied>now</supplied> I am going to Yahweh’s house,<note>Or “my house,” according to the LXX and some modern translations (NASB, NRSV)</note> but no one <idiom-start/>took me in to spend the night<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “was receiving me to <supplied>their</supplied> house”</note> <verse-number id="Jdg 19:19">19</verse-number>There is both straw and fodder for our donkeys, and also bread and wine for me, for your servant,<note>That is, the concubine</note> and for the young man who is with your servant; there is no lack of anything.” <verse-number id="Jdg 19:20">20</verse-number>And the old man said, “Peace to you. I will take care of your needs; however, you must not spend the night in the open square.” <verse-number id="Jdg 19:21">21</verse-number>So he brought him to his house, and he fed the donkeys; they washed their feet, ate, and drank. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 19:22">22</verse-number>While <idiom-start/>they were enjoying themselves<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “their hearts <supplied>were</supplied> being good”</note> behold, the men of the city, <idiom-start/>the perverse lot<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons of uselessness”</note> surrounded the house, pounding on the door. And they said to the old man, the owner of the house, “Bring out the man who came to your house so that <idiom-start/>we may have sex with him<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “we may know him”</note> <verse-number id="Jdg 19:23">23</verse-number>So the man, the owner of the house, went out to them and said to them, “No, my brothers, do not act wickedly; since this man has come into my house, do not do this disgraceful thing. <verse-number id="Jdg 19:24">24</verse-number>Here is my virgin daughter and his concubine. Please, let me bring them out; do violence to them,<note>Or “rape them”</note> and do to them <idiom-start/>whatever you please<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the good in your eyes”</note> Do not do this disgraceful thing to this man.” <verse-number id="Jdg 19:25">25</verse-number>But the men were not willing to listen to him, and the man seized his concubine and brought <supplied>her</supplied> out to them; and they had intercourse with her, and they abused her all night until the morning; they let her go at the approach of dawn. <verse-number id="Jdg 19:26">26</verse-number>And the woman came as the morning appeared, and she fell <supplied>at</supplied> the entrance of the man’s house where her master was, until daylight.<note>Hebrew “light”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 19:27">27</verse-number>In the morning her master got up, and he opened the doors of the house and went out to go on his journey, and behold, his concubine <supplied>was</supplied> falling<note>Or “spread out”</note> <supplied>at</supplied> the entrance of the house, with her hand on the threshold. <verse-number id="Jdg 19:28">28</verse-number>And he said to her, “Get up, let us go,” but there was no answer. So he put her on the donkey, and the man got up and went to his place. <verse-number id="Jdg 19:29">29</verse-number>When he entered his house he took a knife, and he grasped his concubine and cut her into twelve pieces; and he sent her throughout the whole territory of Israel. <verse-number id="Jdg 19:30">30</verse-number>All who saw <supplied>it</supplied> said, “Nothing like this has <supplied>ever</supplied> been since the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> went up from the land of Egypt until this day. Take note of it, consider <supplied>it</supplied>, and speak <supplied>up</supplied>.” </p>
		</chapter>