<chapter id="Jdg 20">
			<pericope>The Punishment of Benjamin</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 20:1">1</verse-number>All the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> went out, from Dan to Beersheba, including the land of Gilead, and they gathered as one body<note>Hebrew “man”</note> to Yahweh <supplied>at</supplied> Mizpah. <verse-number id="Jdg 20:2">2</verse-number>And the leaders of all the people, all the tribes of Israel, presented themselves in the assembly of the people of God, four hundred thousand sword-bearing infantry. <verse-number id="Jdg 20:3">3</verse-number>(The descendants<note>Or “sons/children”</note> of Benjamin heard that the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> had gone up <supplied>to</supplied> Mizpah.) And the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons of Israel” or “children of “Israel”</note> said, “Tell us, how did this evil act occur?” <verse-number id="Jdg 20:4">4</verse-number>The Levite, the husband of the murdered woman, answered and said, “I came to Gibeah, which belongs to Benjamin, I and my concubine, to spend the night. <verse-number id="Jdg 20:5">5</verse-number>The lords of Gibeah rose up against me and surrounded the house at night. They intended to kill me, and they raped my concubine, and she died. <verse-number id="Jdg 20:6">6</verse-number>Then I grabbed my concubine and cut her into pieces, and I sent her throughout all the territory of Israel’s inheritance; for they committed a shameful and disgraceful thing in Israel. <verse-number id="Jdg 20:7">7</verse-number>Look, all you <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>!<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> <idiom-start/>Make your decision<idiom-end/><note>Literally “give your word”</note> and advice here.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 20:8">8</verse-number>All the people got up as one body,<note>Hebrew “man”</note> saying, “Not one of us will go to his tent, or will any of us return to his house. <verse-number id="Jdg 20:9">9</verse-number>So then, this is what we will do to Gibeah: <supplied>we will go up</supplied> against her by lot. <verse-number id="Jdg 20:10">10</verse-number>We will take ten men of one hundred from all the tribes of Israel, and one hundred of one thousand, and one thousand of ten thousand, to bring provisions to the troops, to repay <supplied>them</supplied> when they come to Gibeah<note>Hebrew “Geba”</note> of Benjamin for all the disgraceful things<note>Hebrew “thing”</note> they did in Israel.” <verse-number id="Jdg 20:11">11</verse-number>And all the men of Israel were gathered to the city as one body<note>Hebrew “man”</note> united. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 20:12">12</verse-number>Then the tribes of Israel sent men throughout all the tribes of Benjamin, saying, “What <supplied>is</supplied> this wickedness that happened among you? <verse-number id="Jdg 20:13">13</verse-number>So then, hand over the men, <idiom-start/>the perverse lot<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons of uselessness”</note> who <supplied>are</supplied> in Gibeah, so that we may kill them and purge <supplied>this</supplied> wickedness from Israel.” But the descendants<note>Or “sons/children”</note> of Benjamin were not willing to listen to the voice of their relatives,<note>Or “brothers”</note> the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> <verse-number id="Jdg 20:14">14</verse-number>And the descendants<note>Or “sons/children”</note> of Benjamin were gathered from the cities to Gibeah to go out for battle against the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> <verse-number id="Jdg 20:15">15</verse-number>From the cities the descendants<note>Or “sons/children”</note> of Benjamin were counted on that day twenty-six thousand <idiom-start/>sword-wielding men<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “men drawing sword”</note> besides the inhabitants of Gibeah, who were counted seven hundred well-trained<note>Or “chosen”</note> men. <verse-number id="Jdg 20:16">16</verse-number>From all these troops <supplied>were</supplied> seven hundred well-trained<note>Or “choice/chosen”</note> men <idiom-start/>who were left-handed<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “bound <supplied>by</supplied> his right hand”</note> each one could sling with a stone at a hair and not miss. <verse-number id="Jdg 20:17">17</verse-number>And the men of Israel besides Benjamin were counted four hundred thousand <idiom-start/>sword-wielding men<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “men drawing sword”</note> <idiom-start/>all were warriors<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “all were men of war”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 20:18">18</verse-number>Then the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> got up and went up <supplied>to</supplied> Bethel, and they inquired of God, saying, “Who will go up first for the battle against the descendants<note>Or “sons/children”</note> of Benjamin?” And Yahweh said, “Judah <supplied>will go</supplied> first.” <verse-number id="Jdg 20:19">19</verse-number>And the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> got up in the morning, and they encamped against Gibeah. <verse-number id="Jdg 20:20">20</verse-number>Then the men of Israel marched out for the battle against Benjamin, and the men of Israel took up positions against them <supplied>for</supplied> battle at Gibeah. <verse-number id="Jdg 20:21">21</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons/children”</note> of Benjamin went out from Gibeah, and they struck down on that day twenty-two thousand men of Israel to the ground. <verse-number id="Jdg 20:22">22</verse-number>But the troops, the men of Israel, <idiom-start/>encouraged themselves<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “took heart”</note> and again they arranged <supplied>their</supplied> battle <supplied>lines</supplied> in the place where they had arranged themselves the first day. <verse-number id="Jdg 20:23">23</verse-number>The <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> went up and wept before Yahweh until evening and inquired of Yahweh, saying, “Should we again draw near from the battle against the descendants<note>Or “sons/children”</note> of Benjamin, our relatives?”<note>Hebrew “my brother”</note> And Yahweh said, “Go up against them.”<note>Hebrew “him”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 20:24">24</verse-number>And the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> drew near to the descendants<note>Or “sons/children”</note> of Benjamin on the second day. <verse-number id="Jdg 20:25">25</verse-number>And Benjamin went out from Gibeah to meet them on the second day, and they struck down the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> again, eighteen thousand men to the ground; all of these <supplied>were</supplied> <idiom-start/>sword-wielding<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “drawers of sword”</note> <verse-number id="Jdg 20:26">26</verse-number>And all the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and all the troops went up and came to Bethel and wept; and they sat there before Yahweh and fasted on that day until evening; and they offered burnt offerings and fellowship offerings before Yahweh. <verse-number id="Jdg 20:27">27</verse-number>And the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> inquired of Yahweh (In those days the ark of the covenant of God <supplied>was</supplied> there, <verse-number id="Jdg 20:28">28</verse-number>and Phinehas son of Eleazar, son of Aaron, <supplied>was</supplied> standing <idiom-start/>before it<idiom-end/><note>Literally “before presence of it/him”</note> <supplied>to minister</supplied> in those days), saying, “Should we go out once more to battle against the descendants<note>Or “sons/children”</note> of Benjamin our relatives,<note>Hebrew “my brother”</note> or should we stop?” And Yahweh said, “Go up tomorrow; I will give them<note>Hebrew “him”</note> into your hand.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 20:29">29</verse-number>So Israel stationed an ambush all around Gibeah. <verse-number id="Jdg 20:30">30</verse-number>And the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> went up against the descendants<note>Or “sons/children”</note> of Benjamin on the third day, and they took up positions against Gibeah as before. <verse-number id="Jdg 20:31">31</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons/children”</note> of Benjamin went out to meet the troops, and they lured <supplied>them</supplied> away from the city and began to inflict casualties on the troops as before, on the main road, one of which goes up <supplied>to</supplied> Bethel, the other to Gibeah; <supplied>and</supplied> in the field <supplied>there were</supplied> about thirty men of Israel. <verse-number id="Jdg 20:32">32</verse-number>And the descendants<note>Or “sons/children”</note> of Benjamin thought,<note>Or “said”</note> “They <supplied>are</supplied> being defeated before us <idiom-start/>as previously<idiom-end/>,”<note>Literally “on the first”</note> and the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> said, “Let us flee and lure them<note>Hebrew “him”</note> away from the city to the main roads.” <verse-number id="Jdg 20:33">33</verse-number>And all the men of Israel got up from their places<note>Hebrew “place”</note> and took up positions in Baal Tamar; and the ambush of Israel charged from their places,<note>Hebrew “place”</note> from the vicinity of Gibeah.<note>Hebrew “Geba”</note> <verse-number id="Jdg 20:34">34</verse-number>Then ten thousand well-trained<note>Or “choice/chosen”</note> men from all Israel came out against Gibeah, and the battle became fierce;<note>Or “the battle became heavy”</note> they did not know that disaster <supplied>was about to</supplied> <idiom-start/>close in<idiom-end/><note>Literally “touching”</note> on them. <verse-number id="Jdg 20:35">35</verse-number>And Yahweh defeated Benjamin in the presence of Israel, and the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> destroyed on that day twenty-five thousand one hundred men of Benjamin, all of them <idiom-start/>sword-wielding<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “drawing sword”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 20:36">36</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons/children”</note> of Benjamin saw that they were defeated, and the men of Israel gave ground<note>Or “a place” or “space”</note> to Benjamin because they trusted the ambush that they had set against Gibeah. <verse-number id="Jdg 20:37">37</verse-number>And the ambush came quickly and advanced against Gibeah, and it <idiom-start/>put the whole city to the sword<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “struck the whole city with <supplied>the</supplied> mouth of <supplied>the</supplied> sword”</note> <verse-number id="Jdg 20:38">38</verse-number>Now the appointed time for the men of Israel with the ambush was that they sent up for them a great amount of smoke from the city. <verse-number id="Jdg 20:39">39</verse-number>And the men of Israel turned in the battle, and Benjamin began to inflict casualties on about thirty men of Israel because they thought,<note>Or “said”</note> “They will be completely defeated before us as in the first battle.” <verse-number id="Jdg 20:40">40</verse-number>And the cloud of smoke began to go up from the city in a column of smoke, and Benjamin turned backward, and behold, the whole city was going up <idiom-start/>in smoke<idiom-end/>!<note>Literally “to heaven”</note> <verse-number id="Jdg 20:41">41</verse-number>And the men of Israel turned, and the men of Benjamin were dismayed because they saw that disaster was <idiom-start/>closing in<idiom-end/><note>Literally “touching”</note> on them. <verse-number id="Jdg 20:42">42</verse-number>And they retreated from before the men of Israel to the way of the wilderness, but the battle caught up to them, and <supplied>those</supplied> who <supplied>came</supplied> from the cities<note>Other ancient translations “city”</note> destroyed them in the midst of them. <verse-number id="Jdg 20:43">43</verse-number>They surrounded Benjamin; they pursued them<note>Hebrew “him”</note> without rest<note>Or “<supplied>at</supplied> Nohah,” a location</note> <supplied>and</supplied> trod them<note>Hebrew “him”</note> down opposite Gibeah to the east. <verse-number id="Jdg 20:44">44</verse-number>And eighteen thousand men from Benjamin fell, all of them <idiom-start/>able men<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “men of strength”</note> <verse-number id="Jdg 20:45">45</verse-number>And they turned and fled toward the wilderness, to the rock of Rimmon, but they cut down on the main roads five thousand men; and they pursued after them up to Gidom, and they struck down two thousand men. <verse-number id="Jdg 20:46">46</verse-number>So all of Benjamin who fell on that day were twenty-five thousand <idiom-start/>sword-wielding men<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “men drawing sword”</note> all of these <supplied>were</supplied> <idiom-start/>able men<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “men of strength”</note> <verse-number id="Jdg 20:47">47</verse-number>But six hundred turned and fled toward the wilderness, to the rock of Rimmon, and they remained at the rock of Rimmon <supplied>for</supplied> four months. <verse-number id="Jdg 20:48">48</verse-number>And the men of Israel returned to the descendants<note>Or “sons/children”</note> of Benjamin, and they put them to <idiom-start/>the edge of the sword<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally <supplied>the</supplied> mouth of <supplied>the</supplied> sword”</note> both the inhabitants of city and <supplied>the</supplied> animals that were found; they also set on fire all the cities that they found. </p>
		</chapter>