<chapter id="Jdg 21">
			<pericope>A Decision Is Made About the Tribe of Benjamin</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 21:1">1</verse-number>The men of Israel had sworn at Mizpah, saying, “None of us will give his daughter to Benjamin as a wife.” <verse-number id="Jdg 21:2">2</verse-number>And the people of Bethel came and sat there until evening before God, and they lifted their voices and <idiom-start/>wept bitterly<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “they cried a great weeping”</note> <verse-number id="Jdg 21:3">3</verse-number>And they said, “Why, Yahweh, God of Israel, has it happened today in Israel that one tribe is lacking from Israel?” <verse-number id="Jdg 21:4">4</verse-number>On the next day the people rose early, and they built there an altar and sacrificed burnt offerings and fellowship offerings. <verse-number id="Jdg 21:5">5</verse-number>And the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> said, “Who in the assembly has not come up from all the tribes of Israel to Yahweh?” For a solemn oath was <supplied>taken</supplied> concerning whoever did not come up to Yahweh at Mizpah, saying, “He will certainly be put to death.” <verse-number id="Jdg 21:6">6</verse-number>But the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> had compassion for Benjamin, their relatives,<note>Hebrew “his brother”</note> and they said, “Today one tribe is cut off from Israel. <verse-number id="Jdg 21:7">7</verse-number>What will we do for them—for the <supplied>ones</supplied> being left over—for wives? For we have sworn by Yahweh not to give to them our daughters as wives.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 21:8">8</verse-number>They asked, “Which one is there from the tribes of Israel who did not come up to Yahweh at Mizpah?” And behold, no one came from Jabesh-gilead to the camp, to the assembly. <verse-number id="Jdg 21:9">9</verse-number>The people were counted, and no one was there from the inhabitants of Jabesh-gilead. <verse-number id="Jdg 21:10">10</verse-number>And the congregation sent there twelve thousand men from the troops, and they commanded them, saying, “Go, strike the inhabitants of Jabesh-gilead with <idiom-start/>the edge of the sword<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “<supplied>the</supplied> mouth of <supplied>the</supplied> sword”</note> and the women and children. <verse-number id="Jdg 21:11">11</verse-number>This is the thing you will do: <idiom-start/>you will destroy<idiom-end/><note>Literally “you will devote to destruction”</note> every man and <idiom-start/>every woman who had sex with a man<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “every woman who knows the bed of a man”</note> <verse-number id="Jdg 21:12">12</verse-number>And they found among the inhabitants of Jabesh-gilead four hundred young virgins<note>Hebrew “virgin”</note> who had not <idiom-start/>had sex with a man<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “known a man, as far as <supplied>the</supplied> bed of a male”</note> and they brought them to the camp at Shiloh, which <supplied>is</supplied> in the land of Canaan. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 21:13">13</verse-number>Then the congregation sent and spoke all <supplied>this</supplied> to the descendants<note>Or “sons/children”</note> of Benjamin who <supplied>were</supplied> at the rock of Rimmon, and <idiom-start/>they assured them they would not be hurt<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “they proclaimed peace to them”</note> <verse-number id="Jdg 21:14">14</verse-number>And Benjamin returned at that time, and they gave to them the women whom they kept alive from Jabesh-gilead; but they were not enough for them. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jdg 21:15">15</verse-number>And the people felt sorry for Benjamin because <idiom-start/>Yahweh weakened the tribes of Israel<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “Yahweh make a breach with the tribes of Israel”</note> <verse-number id="Jdg 21:16">16</verse-number>So the elders of the congregation said, “What should we do for the remaining <supplied>ones</supplied> for wives, since the women from Benjamin have been destroyed?” <verse-number id="Jdg 21:17">17</verse-number>And they said, “<supplied>There must be</supplied> a remnant for Benjamin, so that a tribe will not be blotted out from Israel. <verse-number id="Jdg 21:18">18</verse-number>But we cannot give them wives from our daughters.” (For the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> swore, saying, “Cursed be <supplied>anyone</supplied> who gives a wife to Benjamin.”) <verse-number id="Jdg 21:19">19</verse-number>And they said, “Look, the annual feast of Yahweh <supplied>is</supplied> in Shiloh, which <supplied>is</supplied> to the north of Bethel, <idiom-start/>east<idiom-end/><note>Literally “rising of the sun”</note> of <supplied>the</supplied> main road that goes up from Bethel to Shechem, and south of Lebonah. <verse-number id="Jdg 21:20">20</verse-number>They instructed the descendants<note>Or “sons/children”</note> of Benjamin, saying, “Go, lie in ambush in the vineyards, <verse-number id="Jdg 21:21">21</verse-number>and watch and look; when the daughters of Shiloh dance in the dances, come out from the vineyards and seize for yourselves a wife from the daughters of Shiloh, and go to the land of Benjamin. <verse-number id="Jdg 21:22">22</verse-number>And if their fathers or their brothers complain to us, we will say to them, ‘Allow us to have them, because we did not capture a wife for each man in the battle, and because you did not give <supplied>them</supplied> to them, <idiom-start/>or else<idiom-end/><note>Literally “as the time”</note> you would have been guilty.’ ” <verse-number id="Jdg 21:23">23</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons/children”</note> of Benjamin did likewise, and they took wives for each of them from the dancers whom they seized, and they went and returned to their territory, and they rebuilt the cities and they lived in them. <verse-number id="Jdg 21:24">24</verse-number>So the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> dispersed from there at that time according to tribe and family; and they went out from there, each one to their own territory. <verse-number id="Jdg 21:25">25</verse-number>In those days there was no king in Israel; each one did what was right in his own eyes. </p>
		</chapter>