<chapter id="Pr 10">
			<pericope>Proverbs of Solomon</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 10:1">1</verse-number>The proverbs of Solomon: </li1>
				<li1>A wise child makes a father glad, </li1>
				<li2>but a foolish child grieves his mother. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 10:2">2</verse-number>Treasures of wickedness do not profit, </li1>
				<li2>but righteousness delivers from death. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 10:3">3</verse-number>Yahweh will not cause a righteous person<note>Or “soul,” or “inner self”</note> to go hungry, </li1>
				<li2>but the craving of the wicked he will thwart. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 10:4">4</verse-number>A slack hand causes poverty, </li1>
				<li2>but the hand of the diligent enriches. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 10:5">5</verse-number>He who gathers in the summer <supplied>is</supplied> a child who is prudent; </li1>
				<li2>he who sleeps at the harvest <supplied>is</supplied> a child who brings shame. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 10:6">6</verse-number>Blessings <supplied>belong</supplied> to the head of the righteous, </li1>
				<li2>but the mouth of the wicked conceals violence. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 10:7">7</verse-number>The memory of righteousness <supplied>is</supplied> like a blessing, </li1>
				<li2>but the name of the wicked will rot. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 10:8">8</verse-number>A heart of wisdom will heed commandments, </li1>
				<li2>but a babbling fool will come to ruin. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 10:9">9</verse-number>Whoever walks in integrity<note>Hebrew “in the integrity”</note> will walk securely, </li1>
				<li2>but whoever follows perversity, his ways will be made known. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 10:10">10</verse-number>The winking of an eye causes<note>Or “gives, sets up”</note> trouble, </li1>
				<li2>and the foolishness of lips comes to ruin. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 10:11">11</verse-number>A fountain of life <supplied>is</supplied> a mouth of righteousness, </li1>
				<li2>and a mouth of wickedness conceals violence. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 10:12">12</verse-number>Hatred stirs up strife, </li1>
				<li2>but love covers over all offenses. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 10:13">13</verse-number>On the lips of one who has understanding, wisdom is found, </li1>
				<li2>but a rod <supplied>is</supplied> for the back of one who lacks <idiom-start/>sense<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “heart”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 10:14">14</verse-number>Those who are wise lay up knowledge, </li1>
				<li2>but <supplied>to</supplied> the mouth of the fool, ruin draws near. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 10:15">15</verse-number>The wealth of the rich <supplied>is</supplied> the city of his strength; </li1>
				<li2>the ruin of the poor <supplied>is</supplied> their poverty. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 10:16">16</verse-number>The wage of the righteous <supplied>leads</supplied> to life; </li1>
				<li2>the gain of the wicked to sin. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 10:17">17</verse-number><supplied>On</supplied> the path to life is he who guards instruction, </li1>
				<li2>but he who rejects rebuke goes astray. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 10:18">18</verse-number>He who conceals hatred <supplied>has</supplied> lips of deceit, </li1>
				<li2>and he who utters slander—he is a fool. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 10:19">19</verse-number>In many words, transgression is not lacking, </li1>
				<li2>but he who restrains his lips is prudent. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 10:20">20</verse-number>Choice silver is a tongue of righteousness, </li1>
				<li2>a heart<note>Or “mind”</note> of wickedness is <idiom-start/>of little worth<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “like a little”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 10:21">21</verse-number>Lips of righteousness feed many, </li1>
				<li2>but fools <idiom-start/>die for lack of sense<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “in the lack of heart, they die”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 10:22">22</verse-number>The blessing of Yahweh makes <supplied>one</supplied> rich, </li1>
				<li2>and he does not increase sorrow with it. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 10:23">23</verse-number><supplied>It is</supplied> like a sport for a fool to do wrong, </li1>
				<li2>wisdom for a person of understanding. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 10:24">24</verse-number>The dread of the wicked will come upon him, </li1>
				<li2>but the desire of the righteous will be granted. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 10:25">25</verse-number>With the passing of the tempest, there is no wickedness, </li1>
				<li2>but <supplied>the</supplied> righteous have a foundation forever. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 10:26">26</verse-number>Like vinegar to the tooth and like smoke to the eyes, </li1>
				<li2>thus <supplied>is</supplied> the lazy to one who employs<note>Or “sends”</note> him. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 10:27">27</verse-number>The fear of Yahweh adds life, </li1>
				<li2>but the years of the wicked are shortened. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 10:28">28</verse-number>The hope of the righteous <supplied>is</supplied> gladness, </li1>
				<li2>but the expectation of the wicked comes to nothing. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 10:29">29</verse-number>A stronghold for the upright is the way of Yahweh, </li1>
				<li2>but ruin <supplied>belongs</supplied> to <idiom-start/>evildoers<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “them who do evil”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 10:30">30</verse-number>The righteous one is forever; he will not be removed. </li1>
				<li2>But the wicked will not remain in the land.<note>Or “earth”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 10:31">31</verse-number>The mouth of the righteous brings forth wisdom, </li1>
				<li2>but a tongue of perversity will be cut off. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 10:32">32</verse-number>The lips of the righteous know <supplied>the</supplied> acceptable, </li1>
				<li2>but the mouth of the wicked, the perverse. </li2>
			</ul>
		</chapter>