<chapter id="Pr 13">
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 13">13</verse-number><verse-number id="Pr 13:1">1</verse-number> A wise child <supplied>hears</supplied> the discipline of a father, </li1>
				<li2>but a scoffer does not listen to a rebuke. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 13:2">2</verse-number>From the fruit of the mouth of a man, he shall eat what is good, </li1>
				<li2>but the desire<note>Or “soul”</note> of the treacherous, wrongdoing. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 13:3">3</verse-number>He who keeps his mouth guards his life;<note>Or “soul,” or “inner self”</note> </li1>
				<li2>he who opens his lips, ruin <supplied>belongs</supplied> to him. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 13:4">4</verse-number>The soul<note>Or “life”</note> of the lazy craves, but there is nothing, </li1>
				<li2>but the person of diligence is richly supplied. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 13:5">5</verse-number>The righteous hates a word of falsehood; </li1>
				<li2>the wicked will bring shame and <idiom-start/>disgrace<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “he will bring disgrace”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 13:6">6</verse-number>Righteousness will guard the upright of way, </li1>
				<li2>but wickedness will overthrow sin. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 13:7">7</verse-number>There is one who acts rich but <idiom-start/>has nothing<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “there is no”</note> </li1>
				<li2>another who pretends to be poor but <supplied>has</supplied> wealth. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 13:8">8</verse-number>The ransom of the life of a man <supplied>is</supplied> his wealth, </li1>
				<li2>but the poor does not receive a threat. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 13:9">9</verse-number>The light of the righteous will rejoice, </li1>
				<li2>but the lamp of the wicked will die out. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 13:10">10</verse-number>Only by insolence is strife set up, </li1>
				<li2>and wisdom <supplied>is</supplied> with those who take advice. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 13:11">11</verse-number>Wealth <supplied>gained</supplied> from haste<note>Or “vanity”</note> will dwindle, </li1>
				<li2>but he who gathers <idiom-start/>little by little<idiom-end/><note>Literally “upon the hand”</note> will increase it. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 13:12">12</verse-number>Hope that is deferred makes the heart<note>Or “mind”</note> sick, </li1>
				<li2>but a desire fulfilled <supplied>is</supplied> a tree of life. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 13:13">13</verse-number>He who despises a word will bring destruction on himself, </li1>
				<li2>but he who respects a commandment will be rewarded. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 13:14">14</verse-number>The teaching of the wise <supplied>is</supplied> a fountain of life, </li1>
				<li2><supplied>in order</supplied> to avoid the snares of death. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 13:15">15</verse-number>Good sense grants favor, </li1>
				<li2>but the way of the faithless is coarse. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 13:16">16</verse-number>Anyone who is clever will act with intelligence, </li1>
				<li2>but the fool will display folly. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 13:17">17</verse-number>A messenger of wickedness will fall into trouble, </li1>
				<li2>but an envoy of the faithful <supplied>brings</supplied> healing. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 13:18">18</verse-number>Poverty and disgrace <supplied>belong to</supplied> him who ignores instruction, </li1>
				<li2>but he who guards reproof will be honored. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 13:19">19</verse-number>A desire <idiom-start/>fulfilled<idiom-end/><note>Literally “made to be,” “brought about”</note> will be sweet to the soul, </li1>
				<li2>but an abomination of fools is turning from evil. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 13:20">20</verse-number>Walk with the wise and be wise, </li1>
				<li2>but as for the companion of fools, he will suffer harm. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 13:21">21</verse-number>Misfortune will pursue sinners, </li1>
				<li2>but the righteous <idiom-start/>will be rewarded with prosperity<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “it will reward prosperity”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 13:22">22</verse-number>He who is good will leave an inheritance to <idiom-start/>his grandchildren<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons of sons”</note> </li1>
				<li2>and stored up for the righteous <supplied>is</supplied> the wealth of a sinner. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 13:23">23</verse-number><supplied>There is</supplied> much food <supplied>in</supplied> the field of the poor, </li1>
				<li2>but <idiom-start/>it is swept away<idiom-end/><note>Literally “there is sweeping away”</note> by <idiom-start/>injustice<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “no justice”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 13:24">24</verse-number>He who withholds his rod hates his child, </li1>
				<li2>but he who loves him <idiom-start/>gives him<idiom-end/><note>Literally “visits him”</note> discipline. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 13:25">25</verse-number>The righteous eats to satisfy his life,<note>Or “soul,” or “inner self”</note> </li1>
				<li2>but the belly of the wicked will lack. </li2>
			</ul>
		</chapter>