<chapter id="Pr 14">
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 14">14</verse-number><verse-number id="Pr 14:1">1</verse-number> The <idiom-start/>wisest of women<idiom-end/><note>Literally “wise ones of women”</note> builds her house, </li1>
				<li2>but the foolish tears it down with her hands. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 14:2">2</verse-number>He who walks in uprightness fears Yahweh, </li1>
				<li2>but he who is devious <supplied>in</supplied> his ways displeases him. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 14:3">3</verse-number>In the mouth of a fool is the rod of pride, </li1>
				<li2>but the lips of the wise preserve them. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 14:4">4</verse-number><idiom-start/>When there are no<idiom-end/><note>Literally “In there is no”</note> oxen the manger is empty, </li1>
				<li2>but an abundance of crops <supplied>comes</supplied> by the strength of an ox.<note>Hebrew “bull”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 14:5">5</verse-number>A faithful witness does not lie, </li1>
				<li2>but he who breathes out falsehood is a witness of deceit. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 14:6">6</verse-number>A scoffer seeks wisdom, but there is none, </li1>
				<li2>but knowledge <idiom-start/>comes easily to him who understands<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to one who understands it comes easy”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 14:7">7</verse-number>Leave <idiom-start/>the presence of a foolish man<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from the presence <supplied>belonging</supplied> to a man of foolishness”</note> </li1>
				<li2><supplied>for</supplied> you will not <supplied>come to</supplied> know <idiom-start/>words of knowledge<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “lips of knowledge”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 14:8">8</verse-number>The wisdom of the clever is understanding his ways, </li1>
				<li2>but the folly of fools is deceit. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 14:9">9</verse-number>Fools mock<note>Hebrew “he mocks”</note> <supplied>the</supplied> guilt offering, </li1>
				<li2>but among the upright, it is favorable. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 14:10">10</verse-number>The heart<note>Or “mind”</note> knows the bitterness of its soul,<note>Or “life,” or “inner self”</note> </li1>
				<li2>but in its joy, it will not share itself with a stranger. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 14:11">11</verse-number>The house of the wicked will be destroyed, </li1>
				<li2>but the tent of the upright will flourish. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 14:12">12</verse-number>There is a way <supplied>that seems</supplied> upright <idiom-start/>to<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of”</note> a man, </li1>
				<li2>but its end <supplied>is</supplied> the way of death. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 14:13">13</verse-number>Even in laughter, a heart may be sad, </li1>
				<li2>and the end of joy <supplied>may be</supplied> grief. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 14:14">14</verse-number>From his ways, the perverse of heart will be satisfied, </li1>
				<li2>and <idiom-start/>from his own<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “from upon him”</note> <supplied>so shall</supplied> a good man. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 14:15">15</verse-number>The simple will believe every word, </li1>
				<li2>but the clever will consider his step. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 14:16">16</verse-number>The wise is cautious and turns from evil, </li1>
				<li2>but the fool throws off restraint and is confident. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 14:17">17</verse-number>He who is short of <idiom-start/>temper<idiom-end/><note>Literally “nostril”</note> will act foolishly, </li1>
				<li2>and the man who schemes will be hated. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 14:18">18</verse-number>The simple are adorned <supplied>with</supplied> folly, </li1>
				<li2>but the clever are crowned with knowledge. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 14:19">19</verse-number>The evil bow down before the good, </li1>
				<li2>and the wicked at the gates of the righteous. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 14:20">20</verse-number>The poor is disliked even by his neighbor, </li1>
				<li2>but the lovers of the rich are many. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 14:21">21</verse-number>He who despises his neighbor is a sinner, </li1>
				<li2>but he who has mercy on the poor blesses him. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 14:22">22</verse-number>Have they not erred, those who plan evil? </li1>
				<li2>But loyalty and faithfulness <supplied>belong to</supplied> those who plan good. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 14:23">23</verse-number>In all toil, there is profit, </li1>
				<li2>but the <idiom-start/>talk<idiom-end/><note>Literally “word, matter, thing”</note> of lips <supplied>leads</supplied> only to poverty. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 14:24">24</verse-number>The crown of the wise <supplied>is</supplied> their wealth; </li1>
				<li2>the folly of fools is folly. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 14:25">25</verse-number>He who saves lives<note>Or “souls,” or “inner selves”</note> <supplied>is</supplied> a witness of truth, </li1>
				<li2>but he who utters lies <supplied>is</supplied> a betrayer. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 14:26">26</verse-number>In the fear of Yahweh, there is confidence of strength, </li1>
				<li2>and for his children, there will be refuge. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 14:27">27</verse-number>The fear of Yahweh <supplied>is</supplied> a fountain of life, </li1>
				<li2><supplied>in order</supplied> to turn from the snares of death. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 14:28">28</verse-number>In the multitude of people is the glory of the king, </li1>
				<li2>but without a population, a prince <supplied>is</supplied> ruined. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 14:29">29</verse-number><supplied>He who is</supplied> slow to anger <supplied>has</supplied> great understanding, </li1>
				<li2>but the hasty of spirit<note>Or “breath”</note> exalts folly. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 14:30">30</verse-number>A heart<note>Or “mind”</note> of tranquility<note>Or “he who heals”</note> <supplied>is</supplied> life <supplied>to the</supplied> flesh, </li1>
				<li2>but causes bones of passion to rot. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 14:31">31</verse-number>He who oppresses the poor insults him who made him, </li1>
				<li2>but he who has mercy on the poor honors him. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 14:32">32</verse-number>By his evildoing, the wicked will be overthrown, </li1>
				<li2>and the righteous will find refuge in his death. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 14:33">33</verse-number>In the heart<note>Or “mind”</note> of him who has understanding, wisdom rests, </li1>
				<li2>but <supplied>even</supplied> in the midst of fools it becomes known. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 14:34">34</verse-number>Righteousness will exalt a nation, </li1>
				<li2>but sin <supplied>is</supplied> a reproach to a people. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 14:35">35</verse-number>The favor of a king <supplied>is</supplied> for the servant who deals wisely, </li1>
				<li2>but his wrath will be <supplied>on</supplied> him who acts shamefully. </li2>
			</ul>
		</chapter>