<chapter id="Pr 18">
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 18">18</verse-number><verse-number id="Pr 18:1">1</verse-number> He who is selfish seeks a craving;<note>Or “boundary”</note> </li1>
				<li2>against all sound judgment he shows contempt. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 18:2">2</verse-number>A fool will not take pleasure in understanding, </li1>
				<li2>but in expressing his heart.<note>Or “mind”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 18:3">3</verse-number>With the coming of wickedness comes contempt also, </li1>
				<li2>and with dishonor, disgrace. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 18:4">4</verse-number>Deep waters <supplied>are</supplied> words of the mouth of a man; </li1>
				<li2>a gushing stream <supplied>is</supplied> a fountain of wisdom. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 18:5">5</verse-number>Being partial <supplied>to</supplied> faces of evil <supplied>is</supplied> not good, </li1>
				<li2><supplied>nor</supplied> to subvert the righteous at the judgment. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 18:6">6</verse-number>The lips of a fool will bring strife, </li1>
				<li2>and his mouth calls out for a flogging. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 18:7">7</verse-number>The mouth of a fool <supplied>is</supplied> ruin to him, </li1>
				<li2>and his lips <supplied>are</supplied> a snare to his soul.<note>Or “life,” or “inner self”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 18:8">8</verse-number>The words of a whisper <supplied>are</supplied> like delicious morsels, </li1>
				<li2>and they themselves go down <supplied>to</supplied> inner parts of the body. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 18:9">9</verse-number>Even he who is slack in his work, </li1>
				<li2>he is brother to a master<note>Or “owner”</note> of destruction. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 18:10">10</verse-number>A tower of strength is the name of Yahweh; </li1>
				<li2>into him<note>Or “it”</note> the righteous will run and be safe. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 18:11">11</verse-number>The wealth of the rich <supplied>is</supplied> <idiom-start/>his strong city<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “a city of his strength”</note> </li1>
				<li2>and like a wall, it is high in his imagination. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 18:12">12</verse-number>In the presence of destruction, the heart<note>Or “mind”</note> of a man will be haughty, </li1>
				<li2>but in the presence of honor, humble. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 18:13">13</verse-number>He who returns a word before he will hear, </li1>
				<li2>folly itself <supplied>belongs</supplied> to him as well as<note>Hebrew “and”</note> shame. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 18:14">14</verse-number>The spirit of a man will endure his sickness, </li1>
				<li2>but a broken spirit, who may bear it? </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 18:15">15</verse-number>An intelligent <idiom-start/>mind<idiom-end/><note>Literally “heart”</note> will acquire knowledge, </li1>
				<li2>and the ear of the wise will seek knowledge. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 18:16">16</verse-number>The gift of a person will open doors for him, </li1>
				<li2>and before the great, it gives him access. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 18:17">17</verse-number>The first in his dispute is <supplied>deemed</supplied> righteous, </li1>
				<li2><supplied>but</supplied> his neighbor will come and examine him. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 18:18">18</verse-number>The lot will put an end to disputes, </li1>
				<li2>and between powerful contenders it will decide. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 18:19">19</verse-number>A brother who is offended <supplied>is worse</supplied> than a city of strength, </li1>
				<li2>and quarrels <supplied>are</supplied> like the bars of a fortification. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 18:20">20</verse-number>From the fruit of a man’s mouth, his stomach will be satisfied, </li1>
				<li2>as for the yield of his lips, it will satisfy. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 18:21">21</verse-number>Death and life <supplied>are</supplied> in the <idiom-start/>power<idiom-end/><note>Literally “hand”</note> of the tongue, </li1>
				<li2>and those who love her<note>That is, the power of the tongue</note> will eat of her fruit. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 18:22">22</verse-number>He who finds a wife<note>Or “woman”</note> finds good, </li1>
				<li2>and he will obtain favor from Yahweh. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 18:23">23</verse-number>The poor may speak entreaties, </li1>
				<li2>but the rich will answer roughly. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 18:24">24</verse-number>A man of <supplied>many</supplied> friends will come to ruin, </li1>
				<li2>but there is a friend who sticks closer than a brother. </li2>
			</ul>
		</chapter>