<chapter id="Pr 19">
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 19">19</verse-number><verse-number id="Pr 19:1">1</verse-number> Better a poor person walking in integrity </li1>
				<li2>than one who is perverse <idiom-start/>in his speech<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in his lips”</note> and is a fool. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 19:2">2</verse-number>Also, a life<note>Or “soul,” or “inner self”</note> without knowledge is not good, </li1>
				<li2>and he who moves quickly with <supplied>his</supplied> feet <idiom-start/>misses the mark<idiom-end/>.<note>Or “sins”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 19:3">3</verse-number>As for the folly of humankind, its way leads to ruin, </li1>
				<li2>and against Yahweh his heart<note>Or “mind”</note> will rage. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 19:4">4</verse-number>Wealth adds many friends, </li1>
				<li2>but the poor will be left by his friends. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 19:5">5</verse-number>A witness of falsehood will not go unpunished, </li1>
				<li2>and he who breathes lies will not escape. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 19:6">6</verse-number>Many will seek favor before the generous, </li1>
				<li2>and everyone <supplied>is</supplied> the friend of a man of gifts.<note>Hebrew “gift”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 19:7">7</verse-number>All the brothers of the poor, <supplied>if</supplied> they hate him, </li1>
				<li2>how much more will his friends keep away from him. </li2>
				<li2>He pursues <supplied>them with</supplied> words, <supplied>and</supplied> they are gone.<note>Or “<supplied>when</supplied> he pursues words <supplied>and</supplied> not them”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 19:8">8</verse-number>He who acquires wisdom loves himself;<note>Or “soul,” or “inner self”</note> </li1>
				<li2>he who guards understanding <supplied>loves</supplied> to find good. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 19:9">9</verse-number>A false witness will not go unpunished, </li1>
				<li2>and he who breathes lies will perish. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 19:10">10</verse-number>For a fool living in luxury is not fitting, </li1>
				<li2><supplied>any</supplied> more <supplied>than it is</supplied> for a slave to rule over princes. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 19:11">11</verse-number>The understanding of a person makes him slow to his <idiom-start/>anger<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “nostril”</note> </li1>
				<li2>and his glory overlooks offense. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 19:12">12</verse-number>The rage of a king growls like a lion, </li1>
				<li2>but his favor is like dew on the grass. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 19:13">13</verse-number>A foolish child is a ruin to his father, </li1>
				<li2>and the quarreling of a woman<note>Or “wife”</note> is a continuous dripping. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 19:14">14</verse-number>A house and wealth <supplied>are</supplied> an inheritance <supplied>from</supplied> fathers, </li1>
				<li2>but from Yahweh <supplied>comes</supplied> a woman<note>Or “wife”</note> who is prudent. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 19:15">15</verse-number>Laziness will bring on a deep sleep, </li1>
				<li2>and a person<note>Or “soul,” or “life”</note> of idleness will suffer hunger. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 19:16">16</verse-number>He who guards commandments guards his life;<note>Or “soul,” or “inner self”</note> </li1>
				<li2>he who is careless of his ways will be killed. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 19:17">17</verse-number>He who lends to Yahweh <supplied>is</supplied> he who is kind to the poor, </li1>
				<li2>and his benefits he will repay to him. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 19:18">18</verse-number>Discipline your child, for there is hope, </li1>
				<li2>but on his destruction do not set your desire.<note>Or “soul,” or “inner self”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 19:19">19</verse-number>A hot-tempered person pays a penalty; </li1>
				<li2>if you rescue <supplied>him</supplied>, you will do <supplied>it</supplied> yet again. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 19:20">20</verse-number>Listen <supplied>to</supplied> advice and accept instruction </li1>
				<li2>so that you will gain wisdom for your <idiom-start/>future<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “after <supplied>things</supplied>”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 19:21">21</verse-number>Many plans <supplied>are</supplied> in the heart<note>Or “mind”</note> of a man, </li1>
				<li2>but the purpose of Yahweh will be established. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 19:22">22</verse-number>The craving of a man <supplied>is</supplied> his steadfast loyalty, </li1>
				<li2>and <supplied>it is</supplied> better <supplied>to be</supplied> poor than a <idiom-start/>liar<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “man of lying”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 19:23">23</verse-number>Fear of Yahweh <supplied>leads</supplied> to life; </li1>
				<li2>he who is filled <supplied>with it</supplied> will rest—he will not suffer harm. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 19:24">24</verse-number>A lazy person buries his hand in the dish, </li1>
				<li2>and even to his mouth he will not bring it back. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 19:25">25</verse-number>The scoffer you shall strike, and the simple, may they learn prudence, </li1>
				<li2>and reprove the intelligent <supplied>and</supplied> he will gain knowledge. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 19:26">26</verse-number>He who does violence to a father, he who chases away a mother, </li1>
				<li2><supplied>is</supplied> a child who causes shame and brings reproach. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 19:27">27</verse-number>Cease to listen to instruction, my child, </li1>
				<li2><idiom-start/>and you will stray<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<supplied>in order</supplied> to stray”</note> from sayings of knowledge. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 19:28">28</verse-number>A worthless witness will mock justice, </li1>
				<li2>and the mouth of the wicked will devour iniquity. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 19:29">29</verse-number>Judgments<note>Or “Punishments,” or “Condemnations”</note> are prepared for the scoffers, </li1>
				<li2>and flogging for the back of fools. </li2>
			</ul>
		</chapter>