<chapter id="Pr 25">
			<pericope>More Proverbs of Solomon</pericope>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 25:1">1</verse-number>These are also proverbs of Solomon which officials of Hezekiah king of Judah copied: </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 25:2">2</verse-number>The glory of God<note>Or “gods”</note> conceals things, </li1>
				<li2>but the glory of kings searches out things. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 25:3">3</verse-number>As heaven is to height and the earth is to depth, </li1>
				<li2>so <supplied>is</supplied> the heart<note>Or “mind”</note> of kings—there is no searching. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 25:4">4</verse-number>Remove the dross from silver, </li1>
				<li2>and it will become a vessel for the smith. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 25:5">5</verse-number>Remove the wicked before a king, </li1>
				<li2>and his throne will be established in righteousness.<note>Hebrew “in the righteousness”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 25:6">6</verse-number>Do not promote yourself before the king, </li1>
				<li2>and in the place of the great ones do not stand. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 25:7">7</verse-number>For <supplied>it is</supplied> better <supplied>that</supplied> he say to you, “Ascend here,” </li1>
				<li2>than he humble you before a noble. </li2>
				<li1>What your eyes have seen, </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 25:8">8</verse-number>do not hastily bring out to court, </li1>
				<li2>for<note>Or “lest”</note> what will you do at its end, </li2>
				<li2>when your neighbor puts you to shame? </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 25:9">9</verse-number>Argue your argument with your neighbor <supplied>himself</supplied>, </li1>
				<li2>the secret of another do not disclose, </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 25:10">10</verse-number>lest he who hears shame you </li1>
				<li2>and your ill repute will not end. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 25:11">11</verse-number>Apples of gold in a setting of silver </li1>
				<li2>is a matter spoken at<note>Hebrew “on”</note> its proper time. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 25:12">12</verse-number>A ring of gold and an ornament of fine gold </li1>
				<li2><supplied>is</supplied> a rebuke of the wise to the ear of a listener. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 25:13">13</verse-number>Like the cold of snow on a day<note>Or “at a season”</note> of harvest </li1>
				<li2><supplied>is</supplied> a faithful messenger to those who send him, </li2>
				<li2>and the soul<note>Or “life,” or “inner self”</note> of his master is refreshed.<note>Or “returned”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 25:14">14</verse-number><supplied>Like</supplied> clouds and wind when there is no rain, </li1>
				<li2><supplied>so too is</supplied> a man who boasts in a gift of deception. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 25:15">15</verse-number><idiom-start/>With patience<idiom-end/><note>Literally “With length of face”</note> a ruler may be persuaded, </li1>
				<li2>and a soft tongue will break a bone.<note>Or “strength”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 25:16">16</verse-number><supplied>If</supplied> you find honey, eat what is sufficient for you, </li1>
				<li2>lest you have your fill of it and vomit it out. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 25:17">17</verse-number>Make your foot scarce in the house of your neighbor, </li1>
				<li2>lest he become weary of you and hate you. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 25:18">18</verse-number><supplied>Like</supplied> a club and sword and a sharp arrow </li1>
				<li2><supplied>is</supplied> a man who bears false witness against his neighbor. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 25:19">19</verse-number>A bad tooth and a lame foot </li1>
				<li2><supplied>is</supplied> the trust of a faithless person <idiom-start/>in a time<idiom-end/><note>Literally “on a day”</note> of trouble. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 25:20">20</verse-number><supplied>Like</supplied> one who removes a garment on a cold day, <supplied>or like</supplied> vinegar on natron,<note>A mineral salt found on dry lake beds often used as a preservative.</note> </li1>
				<li2><supplied>is</supplied> he who sings songs to a heavy heart. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 25:21">21</verse-number>If your enemy <supplied>is</supplied> hungry, feed him bread, </li1>
				<li2>and if thirsty, let him drink water. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 25:22">22</verse-number>For coals of fire you will heap upon his head, </li1>
				<li2>and Yahweh will reward you. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 25:23">23</verse-number>The wind of the north produces rain, </li1>
				<li2>and a backbiting tongue, angry faces. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 25:24">24</verse-number>Better to live upon the corner of a roof </li1>
				<li2>than <supplied>with</supplied> a woman<note>Or “wife”</note> of contention and <supplied>in a</supplied> shared house. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 25:25">25</verse-number><supplied>Like</supplied> cold water<note>Hebrew “waters”</note> upon a weary soul,<note>Or “life,” or “inner self”</note> </li1>
				<li2><supplied>so too is</supplied> good news from a distant place. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 25:26">26</verse-number><supplied>Like</supplied> a muddied spring or a polluted fountain </li1>
				<li2>is the righteous who gives way before the wicked. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 25:27">27</verse-number>To eat much honey is not good, </li1>
				<li2>nor <supplied>is</supplied> seeking one’s honor<note>Hebrew “their honor”</note> honorable. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 25:28">28</verse-number>A breached city <supplied>where</supplied> there is no wall </li1>
				<li2><supplied>is like</supplied> a man who <idiom-start/>has no<idiom-end/><note>Literally “there is no”</note> self-control for his spirit. </li2>
			</ul>
		</chapter>