<chapter id="Pr 29">
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 29">29</verse-number><verse-number id="Pr 29:1">1</verse-number> A man who is reproved, being stubborn of neck— </li1>
				<li2>suddenly he will be broken, and there will not be healing. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 29:2">2</verse-number>When the righteous are numerous, the people will rejoice, </li1>
				<li2>but when the wicked are ruling, people will groan. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 29:3">3</verse-number>A man who loves wisdom will make his parents glad, </li1>
				<li2>but the friend of prostitutes<note>Or “whores”</note> will squander his wealth. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 29:4">4</verse-number>By justice a king gives stability <supplied>to</supplied> a land, </li1>
				<li2>but a man of bribes will ruin it. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 29:5">5</verse-number>A strong man who flatters his neighbor </li1>
				<li2>is spreading a net for his feet. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 29:6">6</verse-number>In transgression, an evil man <supplied>is</supplied> a snare, </li1>
				<li2>but <supplied>the</supplied> righteous will sing and rejoice.<note>Hebrew “he will rejoice”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 29:7">7</verse-number><supplied>The</supplied> righteous knows <supplied>the</supplied> case of the poor, </li1>
				<li2>but <supplied>the</supplied> wicked does not understand knowledge. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 29:8">8</verse-number>Men of scoffing set a city aflame, </li1>
				<li2>but the wise turn away wrath. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 29:9">9</verse-number><supplied>If</supplied> a wise man goes to court with a foolish man, </li1>
				<li2>then there is rankling and ridicule,<note>Hebrew “there is ridicule”</note> but there is no relief. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 29:10">10</verse-number>Men of blood hate <supplied>the</supplied> blameless, </li1>
				<li2>and they seek the life of the upright.<note>Or “soul,” or “inner self”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 29:11">11</verse-number>A fool gives all his breath,<note>Or “spirit”</note> </li1>
				<li2>but <supplied>the</supplied> wise holds back in quiet. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 29:12">12</verse-number>A ruler listening to a word of falsehood, </li1>
				<li2>all his officials are wicked. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 29:13">13</verse-number>The poor and a man of oppression have <supplied>this</supplied> in common: </li1>
				<li2>Yahweh gives <idiom-start/>light to the eyes of them both<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “light of the eyes of the two of them”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 29:14">14</verse-number>A king who judges with truthfulness <supplied>to</supplied> the poor, </li1>
				<li2>his throne will be established forever. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 29:15">15</verse-number>As for a rod and reproof, they<note>Hebrew “it”</note> will give wisdom, </li1>
				<li2>but a neglected child is disgraced <supplied>by</supplied> his mother. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 29:16">16</verse-number>With the increase of the wicked, transgression will increase, </li1>
				<li2>but the righteous will look on his downfall. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 29:17">17</verse-number>Discipline your children, and they will give you rest, </li1>
				<li2>and they will give delight to your soul.<note>Or “life,” or “inner self”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 29:18">18</verse-number>When there is no prophecy, the people cast off restraint, </li1>
				<li2>but as for he who guards instruction, happiness <supplied>is</supplied> his. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 29:19">19</verse-number>By words, a servant is not disciplined, </li1>
				<li2>for he will understand, but there is no giving heed. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 29:20">20</verse-number>You see a man who is hasty in his words: </li1>
				<li2><supplied>there is more</supplied> hope for a fool than him. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 29:21">21</verse-number>He who pampers his servant from childhood, </li1>
				<li2><idiom-start/>arrogance will be his end<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “and its/his end will be arrogance”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 29:22">22</verse-number>A man of anger will stir strife, </li1>
				<li2>and the owner of anger, much transgression. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 29:23">23</verse-number>The pride of a person will bring him humiliation, </li1>
				<li2>and the lowly of spirit will obtain honor. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 29:24">24</verse-number>Being a partner with a thief is hating one’s life;<note>Or “soul,” or “inner self”</note> </li1>
				<li2>a curse he will hear, but not disclose. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 29:25">25</verse-number>The fear of a person will lay a snare, </li1>
				<li2>but he who trusts in Yahweh will be secure. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 29:26">26</verse-number>Many are those who seek the <idiom-start/>favor<idiom-end/><note>Literally “faces”</note> of a ruler, </li1>
				<li2>but from Yahweh <idiom-start/>one obtains justice<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “<supplied>comes</supplied> justice for a man”</note> </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Pr 29:27">27</verse-number>A man of injustice is an abomination to the righteous, </li1>
				<li2>but the <idiom-start/>upright<idiom-end/><note>Literally “upright of way”</note> is an abomination to the wicked. </li2>
			</ul>
		</chapter>