<chapter id="Jon 4">
			<pericope>Jonah Is Angry at Yahweh’s Compassion</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Jon 4:1">1</verse-number>And this<note>Hebrew “it”</note> <idiom-start/>was greatly displeasing<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was displeasing <supplied>with</supplied> great displeasure”</note> to Jonah, and <idiom-start/>he became furious<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “it was hot for him”</note> <verse-number id="Jon 4:2">2</verse-number>And he prayed to Yahweh and said, “O Yahweh, <supplied>was</supplied> this not <idiom-start/>what I said<idiom-end/><note>Literally “my word”</note> while I was in my homeland? Therefore <idiom-start/>I originally fled<idiom-end/><note>Literally “I did the first time to flee”</note> to Tarshish, because I knew that you <supplied>are</supplied> a gracious and compassionate God, slow to anger <idiom-start/>and having great steadfast love<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “and great of steadfast love”</note> and one who relents concerning calamity.<note>That is, calamity sent by God as judgment</note> <verse-number id="Jon 4:3">3</verse-number>And so then, Yahweh, please take my life from me, because <supplied>for</supplied> me death <supplied>is</supplied> better than life!” <verse-number id="Jon 4:4">4</verse-number>And Yahweh said, “<idiom-start/>Is it right for you to be angry<idiom-end/>?”<note>Literally “Rightfully is it hot for you”; some take this to mean “Are you so very angry?” (<i>Targum</i> <cite title="BibleLEB2: Jon 4:4">Jonah 4:4; </cite>see also JPS, NEB, NET)</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jon 4:5">5</verse-number>And Jonah went out from the city and sat <supplied>down</supplied> east of the city, and he made for himself a shelter there. And he sat under it in the shade, <idiom-start/>waiting to see<idiom-end/><note>Literally “until he would see”</note> what would happen with the city. <verse-number id="Jon 4:6">6</verse-number>And Yahweh God appointed a plant,<note>Probably a castor oil plant, though some have suggested some type of gourd plant</note> and he made it grow up over Jonah to be a shade over his head, to save him from his discomfort. And Jonah <idiom-start/>was very glad<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was glad with great joy”</note> about the plant. <verse-number id="Jon 4:7">7</verse-number>So God appointed a worm <idiom-start/>at daybreak<idiom-end/><note>Literally “at the coming up of the dawn”</note> the next day, and it attacked the plant, and it withered. <verse-number id="Jon 4:8">8</verse-number><idiom-start/>And when the sun rose<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “and it happened at the rising of the sun”</note> God appointed a scorching east wind, and the sun beat down on Jonah’s head and he grew faint. <idiom-start/>And he asked that he could die<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and he asked his soul to die”</note> and said, “My death <supplied>is</supplied> better than my life!” <verse-number id="Jon 4:9">9</verse-number>So God said to Jonah, “<idiom-start/>Is it right for you to be angry<idiom-end/><note>Literally “rightfully is it hot for you”; some take this to mean “Are you so very angry?” (<i>Targum</i> <cite title="BibleLEB2: Jon 4:4">Jonah 4:4; </cite>see also JPS, NEB, NET)</note> about the plant?” And he said, “<idiom-start/>It is right for me to be angry enough to die<idiom-end/>!”<note>Literally “Rightfully it is hot for me until death”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Jon 4:10">10</verse-number>But Yahweh said, “You are troubled about the plant, for which you did not labor nor cause it to grow. <idiom-start/>It grew up in a night and it perished in a night<idiom-end/>!<note>Literally “Which was a son of a night and <supplied>as</supplied> a son of a night it perished”</note> <verse-number id="Jon 4:11">11</verse-number>And should I not be concerned about Nineveh, the great city, <idiom-start/>in which there are<idiom-end/><note>Literally “which there are in it”</note> more <idiom-start/>than one hundred and twenty thousand<idiom-end/><note>Literally “than two ten myriad” (12 x 10,000)</note> people who do not know right from left,<note>“<supplied>hand</supplied>” is often supplied, but it is not clear just what deficiency is meant by this expression, which occurs only here in biblical Hebrew</note> plus many animals?” </p>
		</chapter>