<chapter id="Titus 1">
			<pericope>Greeting</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Titus 1:1">1</verse-number> Paul, a slave of God and an apostle of Jesus Christ for the faith of the chosen of God and the knowledge of the truth that <supplied>is</supplied> according to godliness, <verse-number id="Titus 1:2">2</verse-number>in the hope of eternal life which God, who does not lie, promised before eternal ages, <verse-number id="Titus 1:3">3</verse-number>but at the proper time has disclosed his message in the proclamation <supplied>with</supplied> which I was entrusted according to the command of God our Savior, <verse-number id="Titus 1:4">4</verse-number>to Titus, <supplied>my</supplied> true child according to a common faith. Grace and peace from God the Father and Christ Jesus our Savior. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Instructions to Titus in Crete</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Titus 1:5">5</verse-number>On account of this, I left you behind in Crete, in order that what remains may be set in order and you may appoint elders in every town, as I ordered you. <verse-number id="Titus 1:6">6</verse-number>If anyone is blameless, <supplied>the</supplied> husband of one wife, having faithful<note>Or “believing”</note> children, not <idiom-start/>accused of dissipation<idiom-end/><note>Literally “with an accusation of dissipation”</note> or rebellious. <verse-number id="Titus 1:7">7</verse-number>For it is necessary <supplied>for</supplied> the overseer to be blameless as God’s steward, not self-willed, not quick-tempered, not addicted to wine, not violent, not greedy for dishonest gain, <verse-number id="Titus 1:8">8</verse-number>but hospitable, loving what is good, prudent, just, devout, self-controlled, <verse-number id="Titus 1:9">9</verse-number>holding fast to the faithful message according to the teaching, in order that he may be able both to exhort with sound instruction and to reprove those who speak against <supplied>it</supplied>. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Titus 1:10">10</verse-number>For there are many rebellious <supplied>people</supplied>, idle talkers and deceivers, especially those of the circumcision, <verse-number id="Titus 1:11">11</verse-number>whom it is necessary to silence, whoever are ruining whole families <supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“teaching”) which is understood as means</note> teaching <supplied>things</supplied> which must not be <supplied>taught</supplied> for the sake of dishonest gain. <verse-number id="Titus 1:12">12</verse-number>A certain one of them, <supplied>one of</supplied> their own prophets, has said, “Cretans <supplied>are</supplied> always liars, evil beasts, lazy gluttons.” <verse-number id="Titus 1:13">13</verse-number>This testimony is true, for which reason reprove them severely, in order that they may be sound in the faith, <verse-number id="Titus 1:14">14</verse-number>not paying attention to Jewish myths and commandments of people who turn away from the truth. <verse-number id="Titus 1:15">15</verse-number>To the pure all <supplied>things</supplied> <supplied>are</supplied> pure, but to those who are defiled and unbelieving nothing <supplied>is</supplied> pure, but both their mind and conscience are defiled. <verse-number id="Titus 1:16">16</verse-number>They profess to know God, but by their deeds they deny <supplied>him</supplied>, <supplied>because they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“are”) which is understood as causal</note> are detestable and disobedient, and unfit for every good deed. </p>
		</chapter>