<chapter id="Titus 2">
			<pericope>Sound Instruction and Consistent Behavior</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Titus 2:1">1</verse-number> But you, speak <supplied>the things</supplied> which are fitting for sound instruction. <verse-number id="Titus 2:2">2</verse-number>Older men are to be temperate, worthy of respect, self-controlled, sound in faith, in love, <supplied>and</supplied> in endurance. <verse-number id="Titus 2:3">3</verse-number>Older women likewise <supplied>are to be</supplied> reverent in <supplied>their</supplied> behavior, not slanderous, not enslaved to much wine, teaching what is good, <verse-number id="Titus 2:4">4</verse-number>in order that they may encourage the young women to love their husbands <supplied>and to</supplied> love their children, <verse-number id="Titus 2:5">5</verse-number><supplied>to be</supplied> self-controlled, pure, busy at home, good, being subject to their own husbands, in order that the word of God may not be slandered. <verse-number id="Titus 2:6">6</verse-number>Likewise, exhort the young men to be self-controlled, <verse-number id="Titus 2:7">7</verse-number>concerning everything showing yourself <supplied>to be</supplied> an example of good deeds, in your teaching <supplied>demonstrating</supplied> soundness, dignity, <verse-number id="Titus 2:8">8</verse-number><supplied>a</supplied> sound message beyond reproach, in order that <idiom-start/>an opponent<idiom-end/><note>Literally “one from <supplied>the</supplied> opposed”</note> may be put to shame, <supplied>because he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“has”) which is understood as causal</note> has nothing bad to say concerning us. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Titus 2:9">9</verse-number>Slaves must be subject to their own masters in everything, to be well-pleasing, not to talk back, <verse-number id="Titus 2:10">10</verse-number>not stealing, but demonstrating all good faith, in order that they may do credit to the teaching of God our Savior in everything. <verse-number id="Titus 2:11">11</verse-number>For the grace of God has appeared, bringing salvation to all people, <verse-number id="Titus 2:12">12</verse-number>training us in order that, denying impiety and worldly desires, we may live self-controlled and righteously and godly in the present age, <verse-number id="Titus 2:13">13</verse-number>looking forward to the blessed hope and the glorious appearing of our great God and Savior Jesus Christ, <verse-number id="Titus 2:14">14</verse-number>who gave himself for us, in order that he might redeem us from all lawlessness and purify for himself a people for his own possession, zealous for good deeds. <verse-number id="Titus 2:15">15</verse-number>Speak these <supplied>things</supplied> and exhort and reprove with all authority. Let no one disregard you. </p>
		</chapter>