<chapter id="Titus 3">
			<pericope>Conduct Toward All People</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Titus 3:1">1</verse-number> Remind them to be subject to the rulers <supplied>and</supplied> to the authorities, to obey, to be prepared for every good work, <verse-number id="Titus 3:2">2</verse-number>to speak evil of no one, to be peaceable, gentle, showing all courtesy to all people. <verse-number id="Titus 3:3">3</verse-number>For we also were once foolish, disobedient, led astray, enslaved to various desires and pleasures, spending our lives in wickedness and envy, despicable, hating one another. <verse-number id="Titus 3:4">4</verse-number>But when the kindness and love for mankind of God our Savior appeared, <verse-number id="Titus 3:5">5</verse-number>he saved us, not by deeds of righteousness that we have done, but because of his mercy, through the washing of regeneration and renewal by the Holy Spirit, <verse-number id="Titus 3:6">6</verse-number>whom he poured out on us abundantly through Jesus Christ our Savior, <verse-number id="Titus 3:7">7</verse-number>so that, having been justified by his grace, we may become heirs according to the hope of eternal life. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Final Instructions to Titus</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Titus 3:8">8</verse-number>The saying <supplied>is</supplied> trustworthy, and I want you to insist concerning these <supplied>things</supplied>, so that those who have believed in God may be careful to engage in good deeds. These things are good and beneficial for people. <verse-number id="Titus 3:9">9</verse-number>But avoid foolish controversies and genealogies and contentions and quarrels about the law, for they are useless and fruitless. <verse-number id="Titus 3:10">10</verse-number>Reject a divisive person after a first and second admonition, <verse-number id="Titus 3:11">11</verse-number>knowing that such a person is perverted and is sinning, being self-condemned. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Titus 3:12">12</verse-number>When I send Artemas or Tychicus to you, make haste to come to me in Nicopolis, for I have decided to spend the winter there. <verse-number id="Titus 3:13">13</verse-number>Diligently send on their way Zenas the lawyer and Apollos, so that <idiom-start/>they may lack nothing<idiom-end/><note>Literally “nothing may lack to them”</note>. <verse-number id="Titus 3:14">14</verse-number>But also our <supplied>people</supplied> must learn to engage in good deeds for necessary needs, so that they will not be unfruitful. <verse-number id="Titus 3:15">15</verse-number>All those with me greet you. Greet those who love us in the faith. Grace <supplied>be</supplied> with all of you. </p>
		</chapter>