<chapter id="2 Co 1">
			<pericope>Greeting</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Co 1:1">1</verse-number> Paul, an apostle of Christ Jesus through the will of God, and Timothy our brother, to the church of God that is in Corinth, together with all the saints who are in all Achaia. <verse-number id="2 Co 1:2">2</verse-number>Grace to you and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Thanksgiving for God’s Compassion and Comfort</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Co 1:3">3</verse-number>Blessed <supplied>is</supplied> the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, the Father of mercies and God of all comfort, <verse-number id="2 Co 1:4">4</verse-number>who comforts us in all our affliction, so that we may be able to comfort those <supplied>who are</supplied> in all affliction with the comfort with which <supplied>we</supplied> ourselves are comforted by God. <verse-number id="2 Co 1:5">5</verse-number>For just as the sufferings of Christ overflow to us, thus through Christ our comfort overflows also. <verse-number id="2 Co 1:6">6</verse-number>But if we are afflicted, <supplied>it is</supplied> for your comfort and salvation; if we are comforted, <supplied>it is</supplied> for your comfort that is at work in the patient endurance of the same sufferings that we also suffer. <verse-number id="2 Co 1:7">7</verse-number>And our hope for you <supplied>is</supplied> firm, <supplied>because we</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“is”) which is understood as causal</note> know that as you are sharers in the sufferings, so also <supplied>you will be sharers</supplied> in the comfort. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Co 1:8">8</verse-number>For we do not want you to be ignorant, brothers, concerning our affliction that happened in the <supplied>province of</supplied> Asia,<note>A reference to the Roman province of Asia (modern Asia Minor)</note> that we were burdened to an extraordinary degree, beyond <supplied>our</supplied> strength, so that we were in despair even of living. <verse-number id="2 Co 1:9">9</verse-number>But <supplied>we</supplied> ourselves had the sentence of death in ourselves, so that we would not be putting confidence in ourselves, but in God who raises the dead, <verse-number id="2 Co 1:10">10</verse-number>who delivered us from so great <supplied>a risk</supplied> of death, and will deliver <supplied>us</supplied>, in whom we have put our hope that he will also deliver <supplied>us</supplied> again, <verse-number id="2 Co 1:11">11</verse-number><supplied>while</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“join in helping”)</note> you also join in helping <idiom-start/>on our behalf<idiom-end/><note>Literally “on behalf of us”</note> by prayer, so that thanks may be given <idiom-start/>on our behalf<idiom-end/><note>Literally “on behalf of us”</note> by many persons for this gracious gift <supplied>given</supplied> to us through <supplied>the help</supplied> of many. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Paul’s Clear Conscience</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Co 1:12">12</verse-number>For our reason for boasting is this: the testimony of our conscience that we conducted ourselves in the world, and especially toward you, in holiness<note>Some manuscripts have “sincerity”</note> and purity of motive from God, not<note>Some manuscripts have “and not”</note> in merely human wisdom, but by the grace of God. <verse-number id="2 Co 1:13">13</verse-number>For we are not writing <supplied>anything</supplied> else to you except what you can read or also understand. But I hope that you will understand <idiom-start/>completely<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the end”</note>, <verse-number id="2 Co 1:14">14</verse-number>just as you have also understood us in part, that we are your reason for boasting, just as you <supplied>are</supplied> also ours in the day of our Lord Jesus. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Paul Delays His Visit to Corinth</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Co 1:15">15</verse-number>And with this confidence, I was wanting to come to you previously, in order that you may have a second proof of my goodwill, <verse-number id="2 Co 1:16">16</verse-number>and through you to go to Macedonia, and to come to you again from Macedonia, and to be sent on my way by you to Judea. <verse-number id="2 Co 1:17">17</verse-number>Therefore, <supplied>when I</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was wanting”) which is understood as temporal</note> was wanting <supplied>to do</supplied> this, perhaps then was I making use of vacillation? Or was I deciding what I was deciding according to the flesh, in order that with me my “yes” may be “yes” and my “no” <supplied>may be</supplied> “no” <supplied>at the same time</supplied>?<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The words “at the same time” are supplied for clarity</note> <verse-number id="2 Co 1:18">18</verse-number>But God <supplied>is</supplied> faithful, so that our word to you is not “yes” and “no.” <verse-number id="2 Co 1:19">19</verse-number>For the Son of God, Jesus Christ, the one who was proclaimed among you by us, by me and Silvanus and Timothy, did not become “yes” and “no,” but has become “yes” in him. <verse-number id="2 Co 1:20">20</verse-number>For as many as <supplied>are the</supplied> promises of God, in him <supplied>they are</supplied> “yes”; therefore also through him <supplied>is</supplied> the “amen” to the glory of God through us. <verse-number id="2 Co 1:21">21</verse-number>Now the one who establishes us together with you in Christ and who anoints us <supplied>is</supplied> God, <verse-number id="2 Co 1:22">22</verse-number><supplied>who</supplied> also sealed us and gave the down payment of the Spirit in our hearts. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Co 1:23">23</verse-number>But I call upon God <supplied>as</supplied> witness against my life, that <supplied>in order to</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>in order to</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“spare”) which is understood as purpose</note> spare you, I did not come again to Corinth. <verse-number id="2 Co 1:24">24</verse-number>Not that we lord it over your faith, but we are fellow workers for your joy, because by faith you stand firm. </p>
		</chapter>