<chapter id="2 Co 2">
			<p><verse-number id="2 Co 2">2</verse-number><verse-number id="2 Co 2:1">1</verse-number> For I have decided this for myself, not to come to you again in sorrow. <verse-number id="2 Co 2:2">2</verse-number>For if I <supplied>cause</supplied> you sorrow, then who will make me glad except the one who is caused to be sad by me? <verse-number id="2 Co 2:3">3</verse-number>And I wrote this very <supplied>thing</supplied> in order that <supplied>when I</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“came”) which is understood as temporal</note> came, I would not experience sorrow from those who ought to have made me glad, <supplied>because I</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“have confidence”) which is understood as causal</note> have confidence about you all, that my joy <idiom-start/>belongs to all of you<idiom-end/><note>Literally “is of all of you”</note>. <verse-number id="2 Co 2:4">4</verse-number>For out of great distress and anguish of heart I wrote to you through many tears, not so that you may be caused to be sad, but so that you may know the love that I have especially for you. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Forgive and Comfort the Offender</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Co 2:5">5</verse-number>But if anyone has caused sorrow, he has not caused me sorrow, but <idiom-start/>to some degree<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in part”</note>—<idiom-start/>in order not to say too much<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in order not to burden”</note>—<supplied>to</supplied> all <supplied>of</supplied> you. <verse-number id="2 Co 2:6">6</verse-number>This punishment by the majority <supplied>is</supplied> sufficient for such a person. <verse-number id="2 Co 2:7">7</verse-number>So then, you should rather forgive and comfort him, lest somehow this person should be overwhelmed by excessive sorrow. <verse-number id="2 Co 2:8">8</verse-number>Therefore I urge you to confirm <supplied>your</supplied> love for him. <verse-number id="2 Co 2:9">9</verse-number>Because for this <supplied>reason</supplied> also I wrote, in order that I could know your proven character, whether you are obedient in everything. <verse-number id="2 Co 2:10">10</verse-number>Now to whomever you forgive anything, I also <supplied>do</supplied>; for indeed, whatever I have forgiven, if I have forgiven anything, <supplied>it is</supplied> <idiom-start/>for your sake<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for the sake of you”</note> in the presence of Christ, <verse-number id="2 Co 2:11">11</verse-number>in order that we may not be exploited by Satan (for we are not ignorant of his schemes). </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Triumphant Ministry in Christ</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Co 2:12">12</verse-number>Now <supplied>when I</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“arrived”) which is understood as temporal</note> arrived in Troas for the gospel of Christ and a door was opened for me by the Lord, <verse-number id="2 Co 2:13">13</verse-number>I did not experience rest in my spirit, <supplied>because</supplied><note>This infinitive (“find”) is understood as causal</note> I did not find Titus my brother, but saying farewell to them, I departed for Macedonia. <verse-number id="2 Co 2:14">14</verse-number>But thanks <supplied>be</supplied> to God, who always leads us in triumphal procession in Christ, and who reveals the fragrance of the knowledge of him through us in every place. <verse-number id="2 Co 2:15">15</verse-number>For we are the aroma of Christ to God among those who are being saved and among those who are perishing, <verse-number id="2 Co 2:16">16</verse-number>to those on the one hand an odor from death to death, <supplied>and</supplied> to those on the other hand a fragrance from life to life. And who <supplied>is</supplied> qualified for these <supplied>things</supplied>? <verse-number id="2 Co 2:17">17</verse-number>For we are not like the majority who peddle the word of God, but as from pure motives—but as from God—we speak before God in Christ. </p>
		</chapter>