<chapter id="2 Co 5">
			<pericope>Absent from the Body and at Home with the Lord</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Co 5:1">1</verse-number> For we know that if our earthly house, the tent, is destroyed, we have a building from God, a house not made by hands, eternal in the heavens. <verse-number id="2 Co 5:2">2</verse-number>For indeed, in this <supplied>house</supplied> we groan, <supplied>because we</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“desire”) which is understood as causal</note> desire to put on our dwelling from heaven, <verse-number id="2 Co 5:3">3</verse-number>if indeed, even <supplied>after we</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“have taken off”) which is understood as temporal</note> have taken <supplied>it</supplied> off,<note>A number of important early manuscripts read “have put <supplied>it</supplied> on” here</note> we will not be found naked. <verse-number id="2 Co 5:4">4</verse-number>For indeed we who are in this tent groan, being burdened <idiom-start/>for this reason, that<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in that”</note> we do not want to be unclothed, but to be clothed, in order that what is mortal may be swallowed up by life. <verse-number id="2 Co 5:5">5</verse-number>Now the one who has prepared us for this very <supplied>thing</supplied> <supplied>is</supplied> God, who has given us the down payment, the Spirit. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Co 5:6">6</verse-number>Therefore, <supplied>although we are</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>although</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“confident”) which is understood as concessive</note> always confident and know that <supplied>while we</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“are at home”) which is understood as temporal</note> are at home in the body we are absent from the Lord—<verse-number id="2 Co 5:7">7</verse-number>for we live by faith, not by sight—<verse-number id="2 Co 5:8">8</verse-number>so we are confident and prefer rather to be absent from the body and to be at home with the Lord. <verse-number id="2 Co 5:9">9</verse-number>Therefore indeed we have as our ambition, whether at home <supplied>in the body</supplied> or absent <supplied>from the body</supplied>, to be acceptable to him. <verse-number id="2 Co 5:10">10</verse-number>For we must all appear before the judgment seat of Christ, in order that each one may receive back the <supplied>things</supplied> through the body according to what he has done, whether good or bad. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Controlled by the Love of Christ</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Co 5:11">11</verse-number>Therefore, <supplied>because we</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“know”) which is understood as causal</note> know the fear of the Lord, we are attempting to persuade people, but we are revealed to God, and I hope to be revealed in your consciences. <verse-number id="2 Co 5:12">12</verse-number>We are not commending ourselves to you again, but are giving you an opportunity to boast about us, in order that you may have <supplied>an answer</supplied> for those who boast in appearance and not in heart. <verse-number id="2 Co 5:13">13</verse-number>For if we are out of our senses, <supplied>it is</supplied> for God; if we are of sound mind, <supplied>it is</supplied> for you. <verse-number id="2 Co 5:14">14</verse-number>For the love of Christ controls us, <supplied>because we</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“have concluded”) which is understood as causal</note> have concluded this: that one died for all; as a result all died. <verse-number id="2 Co 5:15">15</verse-number>And he died for all, in order that those who live should no longer live for themselves, but for the one who died for them and was raised. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Co 5:16">16</verse-number>So then, from now on we know no one <idiom-start/>from a human point of view<idiom-end/><note>Literally “according to the flesh”</note>, if indeed we have known Christ <idiom-start/>from a human point of view<idiom-end/><note>Literally “according to the flesh”</note>, but now we know <supplied>him this way</supplied> no longer. <verse-number id="2 Co 5:17">17</verse-number>Therefore if anyone <supplied>is</supplied> in Christ, <supplied>he is</supplied> a new creation; the old <supplied>things</supplied> have passed away; behold, new <supplied>things</supplied> have come. <verse-number id="2 Co 5:18">18</verse-number>And all these <supplied>things</supplied> <supplied>are</supplied> from God, who has reconciled us to himself through Christ, and who has given us the ministry of reconciliation, <verse-number id="2 Co 5:19">19</verse-number>namely, that God was in Christ reconciling the world to himself, not counting their trespasses against them, and entrusting to us the message of reconciliation. <verse-number id="2 Co 5:20">20</verse-number>Therefore we are ambassadors on behalf of Christ, as <supplied>if</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>if</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“were imploring”) which is understood as conditional</note> God were imploring <supplied>you</supplied> through us. We beg <supplied>you</supplied> on behalf of Christ, be reconciled to God. <verse-number id="2 Co 5:21">21</verse-number>He made the one who did not know sin <supplied>to be</supplied> sin on our behalf, in order that we could become the righteousness of God in him. </p>
		</chapter>