<chapter id="2 Co 6">
			<pericope>Afflictions of God’s Servants</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Co 6:1">1</verse-number> Now <supplied>because we</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“are fellow workers”) which is understood as causal</note> are fellow workers, we also urge you not to receive the grace of God in vain. <verse-number id="2 Co 6:2">2</verse-number>For he says, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“At the acceptable time I heard you, </li1>
				<li1>and in the day of salvation I helped you.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 49:8">Isa 49:8</cite></note> </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p>Behold, now <supplied>is</supplied> the acceptable time; behold, now <supplied>is</supplied> the day of salvation! <verse-number id="2 Co 6:3">3</verse-number><supplied>We are</supplied> giving no one an occasion for taking offense in anything, in order that our ministry will not have fault found <supplied>with it</supplied>, <verse-number id="2 Co 6:4">4</verse-number>but commending ourselves as servants of God in every <supplied>way</supplied>, in much endurance, in afflictions, in distresses, in difficulties, <verse-number id="2 Co 6:5">5</verse-number>in beatings, in prisons, in disturbances, in troubles, in sleepless nights, in going hungry, <verse-number id="2 Co 6:6">6</verse-number>in purity, in knowledge, in patience, in kindness, in the Holy Spirit, in love without hypocrisy, <verse-number id="2 Co 6:7">7</verse-number>in the word of truth, in the power of God, with the weapons of righteousness for the right hand and left hand, <verse-number id="2 Co 6:8">8</verse-number>through glory and dishonor, through slander and good repute, <supplied>regarded</supplied> as deceivers and <supplied>yet</supplied> truthful, <verse-number id="2 Co 6:9">9</verse-number>as unknown and <supplied>yet</supplied> known completely, as dying, and behold, we go on living, as disciplined, and <supplied>yet</supplied> not put to death, <verse-number id="2 Co 6:10">10</verse-number>as grieving, but always rejoicing, as poor, but making many rich, as having nothing, and possessing everything. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Co 6:11">11</verse-number><idiom-start/>We have spoken freely and openly<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the mouth of us has opened”</note> to you, Corinthians; our heart is open wide. <verse-number id="2 Co 6:12">12</verse-number>You are not restricted by us, but you are restricted in your affections. <verse-number id="2 Co 6:13">13</verse-number>Now the same <supplied>way</supplied> <supplied>in</supplied> exchange (I am speaking as to children), you open wide <supplied>your hearts</supplied> also. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Do Not Become Unevenly Yoked with Unbelievers</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Co 6:14">14</verse-number>Do not become unevenly yoked with unbelievers, for what participation <supplied>is there between</supplied> righteousness and lawlessness? Or what fellowship <supplied>does</supplied> light <supplied>have</supplied> with darkness? <verse-number id="2 Co 6:15">15</verse-number>And what agreement <supplied>does</supplied> Christ <supplied>have</supplied> with Beliar? Or what share <supplied>does</supplied> a believer <supplied>have</supplied> with an unbeliever? <verse-number id="2 Co 6:16">16</verse-number>And what agreement <supplied>does the</supplied> temple of God <supplied>have</supplied> with idols? For we are the temple of the living God, just as God said, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“I will live in<note>Or “with”</note> them and will walk about <supplied>among them</supplied>, </li1>
				<li1>and I will be their God and they will be my people.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Le 26:12">Lev 26:12 </cite>(also similar to <cite title="BibleLEB2: Je 32:38">Jer 32:38</cite>, <cite title="BibleLEB2: Eze 37:27">Ezek 37:27</cite>)</note> </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="2 Co 6:17">17</verse-number>Therefore “come out from their midst </li1>
				<li1>and be separate,” says the Lord, </li1>
				<li1>“and do not touch what is unclean,<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 52:11">Isa 52:11</cite></note> </li1>
				<li1>and I will welcome you,<note>A paraphrased quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Eze 20:41">Ezek 20:41</cite></note> </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="2 Co 6:18">18</verse-number>and I will be a father to you, </li1>
				<li1>and you will be sons and daughters to me,”<note>A paraphrased quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: 2 Sa 7:14">2 Sam 7:14 </cite>and <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 43:6">Isa 43:6</cite></note> </li1>
				<li1>says the all-powerful Lord. </li1>
			</ul>
		</chapter>