<chapter id="2 Co 7">
			<pericope>Paul’s Joy at the Corinthians’ Repentance</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Co 7:1">1</verse-number> Therefore <supplied>since we</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>since</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“have”) which is understood as causal</note> have these promises, dear friends, let us cleanse ourselves from all defilement of body and spirit, accomplishing holiness in the fear of God. <verse-number id="2 Co 7:2">2</verse-number><idiom-start/>Make room for us in your hearts<idiom-end/><note>Literally “make room for us”</note>. We have wronged no one, we have ruined no one, we have defrauded no one. <verse-number id="2 Co 7:3">3</verse-number>I do not say <supplied>this</supplied> <idiom-start/>to condemn you<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for condemnation”</note>, because I have already said that you are in our hearts, so that we die together and we live together. <verse-number id="2 Co 7:4">4</verse-number>Great <supplied>is</supplied> my confidence toward you; great <supplied>is</supplied> my boasting on your behalf; I am filled with encouragement; I am overflowing with joy in all our affliction. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Co 7:5">5</verse-number>For even <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“arrived”)</note> we arrived in Macedonia, our body had no rest, but we were afflicted in every <supplied>way</supplied>—quarrels outside, fears within. <verse-number id="2 Co 7:6">6</verse-number>But God, who comforts the humble, comforted us by the coming of Titus, <verse-number id="2 Co 7:7">7</verse-number>and not only by his coming, but also by the comfort <supplied>with</supplied> which he was comforted among you, <supplied>because he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“reported”) which is understood as causal</note> reported to us your longing, your mourning, your zeal for me, so that I rejoiced even more. <verse-number id="2 Co 7:8">8</verse-number>For if indeed I grieved you by my letter, I do not regret <supplied>it</supplied>. Even if I did regret <supplied>it</supplied> (I see<note>Some manuscripts have “for I see”</note> that that letter grieved you, even though for <idiom-start/>a short time<idiom-end/><note>Literally “an hour”</note>), <verse-number id="2 Co 7:9">9</verse-number>now I rejoice, not that you were grieved, but that you were grieved to repentance. For you were grieved according to <supplied>the will of</supplied> God, so that you suffered loss in no way through us. <verse-number id="2 Co 7:10">10</verse-number>For grief according to <supplied>the will of</supplied> God brings about a repentance <supplied>leading</supplied> to salvation, not to be regretted, but worldly grief brings about death. <verse-number id="2 Co 7:11">11</verse-number>For behold how much diligence this very <supplied>thing</supplied>, being grieved according to <supplied>the will of</supplied> God, has brought about in you: what defense <supplied>of yourselves</supplied>, what indignation, what fear, what longing, what zeal, what punishment! In everything you have demonstrated yourselves to be innocent in this matter. <verse-number id="2 Co 7:12">12</verse-number>Consequently, even if I wrote to you, it was not because of the one who did wrong or because of the one who had been wronged, but in order that your diligence <idiom-start/>on our behalf<idiom-end/><note>Literally “on behalf of us”</note> might be revealed to you before God. <verse-number id="2 Co 7:13">13</verse-number>Because of this we have been encouraged, and in addition to our encouragement, we rejoiced much more over the joy of Titus, because his spirit had been refreshed by all of you. <verse-number id="2 Co 7:14">14</verse-number>For if I have boasted anything to him about you, I have not been put to shame, but as I have spoken everything to you in truth, thus also our boasting to Titus <idiom-start/>has proven to be true<idiom-end/><note>Literally “has become truth”</note>. <verse-number id="2 Co 7:15">15</verse-number>And his affection for you is all the more <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“remembers”) which is understood as temporal</note> remembers the obedience of all of you as you welcomed him with fear and trembling. <verse-number id="2 Co 7:16">16</verse-number>I rejoice, because in everything I am completely confident in you. </p>
		</chapter>