<chapter id="2 Co 8">
			<pericope>Generosity in Giving</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Co 8:1">1</verse-number> Now we make known to you, brothers, the grace of God that has been given among the churches of Macedonia, <verse-number id="2 Co 8:2">2</verse-number>that with a great ordeal of affliction, the abundance of their joy and the extreme depth of their poverty have overflowed to the wealth of their generosity. <verse-number id="2 Co 8:3">3</verse-number>I testify that <supplied>they gave</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The words “<supplied>they gave</supplied>” are not in the Greek text, but are implied</note> according to <supplied>their</supplied> ability, and beyond <supplied>their</supplied> ability, by their own choice, <verse-number id="2 Co 8:4">4</verse-number>requesting of us with much exhortation the favor and the fellowship of the ministry to the saints, <verse-number id="2 Co 8:5">5</verse-number>and not just as we had hoped, but they gave themselves first to the Lord and <supplied>then</supplied> to us, by the will of God. <verse-number id="2 Co 8:6">6</verse-number>So we urged Titus that, just as he had previously begun <supplied>it</supplied>, thus he would also complete for you this <supplied>act of</supplied> grace. <verse-number id="2 Co 8:7">7</verse-number>But just as you excel in everything—in faith and in speaking and in knowledge and with all diligence and in the love from us <supplied>that is</supplied> in you—so may you excel in this grace also. <verse-number id="2 Co 8:8">8</verse-number>I am not saying <supplied>this</supplied> as a command, but proving the genuineness of your love by means of the diligence of others. <verse-number id="2 Co 8:9">9</verse-number>For you know the grace of our Lord Jesus Christ, that <supplied>although he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>although</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was”) which is understood as concessive</note> was rich, for your sake he became poor, in order that you, by his poverty, may become rich. <verse-number id="2 Co 8:10">10</verse-number>And I am giving an opinion in this <supplied>matter</supplied>, because this is profitable for you who not only began previously, a year ago, to do <supplied>something</supplied>, but also to want <supplied>to do it</supplied>. <verse-number id="2 Co 8:11">11</verse-number>So now also complete the doing <supplied>of it</supplied>, in order that just as <supplied>you have</supplied> the eagerness to want <supplied>to do it</supplied>, thus also <supplied>you may</supplied> complete <supplied>it</supplied> from <supplied>what you</supplied> have. <verse-number id="2 Co 8:12">12</verse-number>For if the eagerness is present <idiom-start/>according to what one has<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the degree that if he might have”</note>, <supplied>it is</supplied> acceptable not <idiom-start/>according to what one does not have<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the degree that he might not have”</note>. <verse-number id="2 Co 8:13">13</verse-number>For <supplied>this is</supplied> not that for others <supplied>there may be</supplied> relief, <supplied>and</supplied> for you difficult circumstances, but <supplied>as a matter</supplied> of equality. <verse-number id="2 Co 8:14">14</verse-number>At the present time your abundance <supplied>will be</supplied> for their need, in order that their abundance may also be for your need, so that there may be equality, <verse-number id="2 Co 8:15">15</verse-number>just as it is written, “The <supplied>one</supplied> who <supplied>gathered</supplied> much did not have too much, and the <supplied>one</supplied> who <supplied>gathered</supplied> little did not have too little.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ex 16:18">Exod 16:18</cite></note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Arrangements for Administering the Corinthians’ Gift</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Co 8:16">16</verse-number>But thanks <supplied>be</supplied> to God, who has put in the heart of Titus the same devotion <idiom-start/>on your behalf<idiom-end/><note>Literally “on behalf of you”</note>, <verse-number id="2 Co 8:17">17</verse-number>because he not only welcomed our request, but being very earnest, by his own choice he went out<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Or “he is going out” (if this verb is understood as an epistolary aorist)</note> to you. <verse-number id="2 Co 8:18">18</verse-number>And we have sent at the same time with him the brother whose praise in the gospel <supplied>has become known</supplied> throughout all the churches. <verse-number id="2 Co 8:19">19</verse-number>And not only <supplied>this</supplied>, but he was also chosen by the churches <supplied>as</supplied> our traveling companion together with this gift that is being administered by us to the glory of the Lord himself and <supplied>to show</supplied> our readiness <supplied>to help</supplied>. <verse-number id="2 Co 8:20">20</verse-number><supplied>We are</supplied> trying to avoid this, lest anyone should find fault with us in this abundant gift that is being administered by us. <verse-number id="2 Co 8:21">21</verse-number>For we are taking into consideration what is honorable not only before the Lord, but also before people. <verse-number id="2 Co 8:22">22</verse-number>And we are sending with them our brother whom we have tested many times in many <supplied>things</supplied> that he is diligent, but now much more diligent <supplied>because of his</supplied> great confidence in you. <verse-number id="2 Co 8:23">23</verse-number>If <supplied>there is a question</supplied> concerning Titus, <supplied>he is</supplied> my partner and fellow worker for you. If <supplied>there is a question concerning</supplied> our brothers, <supplied>they are</supplied> messengers of the churches, the glory of Christ. <verse-number id="2 Co 8:24">24</verse-number>Therefore show to them the proof of your love and our boasting about you <idiom-start/>openly before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face of”</note> the churches. </p>
		</chapter>