<chapter id="2 Co 9">
			<pericope>God Loves a Cheerful Giver</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Co 9:1">1</verse-number> For it is unnecessary for me to write to you concerning the ministry to the saints, <verse-number id="2 Co 9:2">2</verse-number>because I know your readiness <supplied>to help</supplied>, <supplied>concerning</supplied> which I keep on boasting to the Macedonians about you, that Achaia has been ready <supplied>to help</supplied> since last year, and your zeal has stirred up the majority <supplied>of them</supplied>. <verse-number id="2 Co 9:3">3</verse-number>But I am sending the brothers in order that our boasting about you would not prove to be empty in this case, so that you may be prepared just as I was saying, <verse-number id="2 Co 9:4">4</verse-number>lest somehow if Macedonians should come with me and find you unprepared, we—<idiom-start/>not to speak of you<idiom-end/><note>Literally “so that we do not speak about you”; some manuscripts have “so that I do not speak about you”</note>—would be humiliated in connection with this project. <verse-number id="2 Co 9:5">5</verse-number>Therefore I considered <supplied>it</supplied> necessary to urge the brothers that they should go on ahead to you and make arrangements in advance for your generous gift that was promised previously, so this would be prepared as a generous gift and not as grudgingly granted. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Co 9:6">6</verse-number>Now <supplied>the point is</supplied> this: the one who sows sparingly will also reap sparingly, and the one who sows bountifully will also reap bountifully. <verse-number id="2 Co 9:7">7</verse-number>Each one <supplied>should give</supplied> as he has decided in his heart, not <idiom-start/>reluctantly<idiom-end/><note>Literally “out of sorrow”</note> or from compulsion, for God loves a cheerful giver. <verse-number id="2 Co 9:8">8</verse-number>And God is able to cause all grace to abound to you, so that in everything at all times, <supplied>because you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“have”) which is understood as causal</note> have enough of everything, you may overflow in every good work. <verse-number id="2 Co 9:9">9</verse-number>Just as it is written, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“He scattered widely, he gave to the poor; </li1>
				<li1>his righteousness remains <idiom-start/>forever<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for the age”</note>.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 112:9">Ps 112:9</cite></note> </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Co 9:10">10</verse-number>Now the one who supplies seed to the sower and bread for food will provide and multiply your seed, and will cause the harvest of your righteousness to grow, <verse-number id="2 Co 9:11">11</verse-number>being made rich in every <supplied>way</supplied> for all generosity, which is producing through us thanksgiving to God, <verse-number id="2 Co 9:12">12</verse-number>because the service of this ministry is not only supplying the needs of the saints, but also is overflowing through many <supplied>expressions of</supplied> thanksgiving to God. <verse-number id="2 Co 9:13">13</verse-number>Through the proven character of this service <supplied>they will</supplied> glorify God because of the submission of your confession to the gospel of Christ and the generosity of <supplied>your</supplied> participation toward them and toward everyone, <verse-number id="2 Co 9:14">14</verse-number>and <supplied>they are</supplied> longing for you in their prayers for you, because of the surpassing grace of God to you. <verse-number id="2 Co 9:15">15</verse-number>Thanks <supplied>be</supplied> to God for his indescribable gift! </p>
		</chapter>