<chapter id="2 Co 10">
			<pericope>Paul’s Ministry Defended</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Co 10:1">1</verse-number> Now I, Paul, appeal to you myself by the humility and gentleness of Christ, who <idiom-start/>when I am present in person<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the face”</note> <supplied>am</supplied> humble among you, but <supplied>when I</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“am absent”) which is understood as temporal</note> am absent am bold toward you—<verse-number id="2 Co 10:2">2</verse-number>now I ask <supplied>when I</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“am present”) which is understood as temporal</note> am present <supplied>that I will</supplied> not <supplied>need</supplied> to be bold with the confidence <supplied>with</supplied> which I propose to show boldness toward some who consider us as behaving according to the flesh. <verse-number id="2 Co 10:3">3</verse-number>For <supplied>although we</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>although</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“are living”) which is understood as concessive</note> are living in the flesh, we do not wage war according to the flesh, <verse-number id="2 Co 10:4">4</verse-number>for the weapons of our warfare <supplied>are</supplied> not merely human, but powerful to God for the tearing down of fortresses, tearing down arguments <verse-number id="2 Co 10:5">5</verse-number>and all pride that is raised up against the knowledge of God, and taking every thought captive to the obedience of Christ. <verse-number id="2 Co 10:6">6</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>we are ready<idiom-end/><note>Literally “having with ready”</note> to punish all disobedience, whenever your obedience is completed. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Co 10:7">7</verse-number>You are looking at things according to appearance. If anyone is convinced he himself is Christ’s, he should consider this concerning himself again: that just as Christ himself <supplied>is</supplied>, so also <supplied>are</supplied> we. <verse-number id="2 Co 10:8">8</verse-number>For even if I boast somewhat more about our authority that the Lord gave <supplied>us</supplied> <idiom-start/>for building you up and not for tearing you down<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for building up and not for tearing down of you”</note>, I will not be put to shame, <verse-number id="2 Co 10:9">9</verse-number>so that I do not want to appear as if I were terrifying you by my letters, <verse-number id="2 Co 10:10">10</verse-number>because it is said, “His letters <supplied>are</supplied> severe and powerful, but his bodily presence <supplied>is</supplied> weak and his speech is of no account.” <verse-number id="2 Co 10:11">11</verse-number>Let such a person consider this: that what we are in word by letters <supplied>when we</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“are absent”) which is understood as temporal</note> are absent, <supplied>we will</supplied> also <supplied>be</supplied> in <idiom-start/>actions<idiom-end/><note>Literally “deed”</note> <supplied>when we</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“are present”) which is understood as temporal</note> are present. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Co 10:12">12</verse-number>For we do not dare to classify or to compare ourselves with some who commend themselves, but <supplied>they</supplied> themselves, <supplied>when they</supplied> measure themselves by themselves and compare themselves with themselves, do not understand. <verse-number id="2 Co 10:13">13</verse-number>But we will not boast <idiom-start/>beyond limits<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the things immeasurable”</note>, but according to the measure of the assignment that God has assigned to us as a measure to reach even as far as you. <verse-number id="2 Co 10:14">14</verse-number>For we are not overextending ourselves, as <supplied>if we</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>if</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“reached”) which is understood as conditional</note> had not reached you, because we have reached even as far as you with the gospel of Christ, <verse-number id="2 Co 10:15">15</verse-number>not boasting <idiom-start/>beyond limits<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the things immeasurable”</note> in the labors of others, but having hope <supplied>that as</supplied> your faith is growing to be enlarged greatly by you according to our assignment, <verse-number id="2 Co 10:16">16</verse-number>so that we may proclaim the gospel in the regions that lie beyond you, <supplied>and</supplied> not boast in the things accomplished in the <supplied>area</supplied> assigned to someone else. <verse-number id="2 Co 10:17">17</verse-number>But “the one who boasts, let him boast in the Lord.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Je 9:24">Jer 9:24</cite></note> <verse-number id="2 Co 10:18">18</verse-number>For it is not the one commending himself who is approved, but <supplied>the one</supplied> whom the Lord commends. </p>
		</chapter>