<chapter id="2 Co 11">
			<pericope>Paul Defends His Apostleship</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Co 11:1">1</verse-number> I wish that you would put up with me <idiom-start/>in something a little foolish<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a little something of foolishness”</note>—but indeed you are putting up with me. <verse-number id="2 Co 11:2">2</verse-number>For I am jealous <supplied>for</supplied> you with a godly jealousy, because I promised you <supplied>in marriage</supplied> to one husband, to present <supplied>you</supplied> <supplied>as</supplied> a pure virgin to Christ. <verse-number id="2 Co 11:3">3</verse-number>But I am afraid lest somehow, as the serpent deceived Eve by his craftiness, your minds may be led astray from the sincerity and the purity of <supplied>devotion</supplied> to Christ. <verse-number id="2 Co 11:4">4</verse-number>For if the one who comes proclaims another Jesus whom we have not proclaimed, or you receive a different spirit which you did not receive, or a different gospel which you did not accept, you put up with <supplied>it</supplied> well <supplied>enough</supplied>! <verse-number id="2 Co 11:5">5</verse-number>For I consider myself in no way to be inferior to the preeminent apostles.<note>Some interpreters take this to refer to the original apostles in Jerusalem; others take Paul to be referring sarcastically to his opponents in Corinth.</note> <verse-number id="2 Co 11:6">6</verse-number>But even if <supplied>I am</supplied> unskilled in speech, yet <supplied>I am</supplied> not in knowledge; certainly in everything <supplied>we</supplied> have made this clear to you in every <supplied>way</supplied>. <verse-number id="2 Co 11:7">7</verse-number>Or did I commit a sin <supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“humbling”) which is understood as means</note> humbling myself in order that you may be exalted, because I proclaimed the gospel of God to you without payment? <verse-number id="2 Co 11:8">8</verse-number>I robbed other churches <supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“accepting”) which is understood as means</note> accepting support <supplied>from them</supplied> for the ministry to you. <verse-number id="2 Co 11:9">9</verse-number>And <supplied>when I</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was present”) which is understood as temporal</note> was present with you and was in need, I did not burden anyone, for the brothers who came from Macedonia supplied my need, and in everything I kept myself from being a burden to you, and will keep <supplied>myself from being a burden</supplied>. <verse-number id="2 Co 11:10">10</verse-number><supplied>As the</supplied> truth of Christ is in me, this boasting <idiom-start/>of mine<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to me”</note> will not be stopped in the regions of Achaia. <verse-number id="2 Co 11:11">11</verse-number><idiom-start/>Why<idiom-end/><note>Literally “because of what”</note>? Because I do not love you? God knows <supplied>I do</supplied>! <verse-number id="2 Co 11:12">12</verse-number>But what I am doing, I will also do, in order that I may remove the opportunity of those who want an opportunity, that they may be found just as also we <supplied>are</supplied> in what they are boasting about. <verse-number id="2 Co 11:13">13</verse-number>For such people <supplied>are</supplied> false apostles, deceitful workers, disguising themselves as apostles of Christ. <verse-number id="2 Co 11:14">14</verse-number>And no wonder, for Satan himself disguises himself as an angel of light. <verse-number id="2 Co 11:15">15</verse-number>Therefore <supplied>it is</supplied> not a great thing if his servants also disguise themselves as servants of righteousness, whose end will be according to their deeds. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Paul Boasts in His Sufferings</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Co 11:16">16</verse-number>Again I say, do not let anyone think I am foolish. But indeed, if <supplied>you do</supplied>, accept me even as foolish, in order that I also may boast a little. <verse-number id="2 Co 11:17">17</verse-number>What I am saying in this project of boasting, I am not saying as the Lord <supplied>would say</supplied>, but as in foolishness. <verse-number id="2 Co 11:18">18</verse-number>Since many are boasting according to human standards, I also will boast. <verse-number id="2 Co 11:19">19</verse-number>For <supplied>because you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“are”) which is understood as causal</note> are wise, you put up with foolish people gladly! <verse-number id="2 Co 11:20">20</verse-number>For you put up with <supplied>it</supplied> if someone enslaves you, if someone devours <supplied>you</supplied>, if someone takes advantage of <supplied>you</supplied>, if someone is presumptious <supplied>toward you</supplied>, if someone strikes you in the face. <verse-number id="2 Co 11:21">21</verse-number>I say <supplied>this</supplied> to <supplied>my</supplied> shame, namely, that we have been weak. </p>
			<p>But in whatever anyone dares to <supplied>boast</supplied>—I am speaking in foolishness—I also dare to <supplied>boast</supplied>. <verse-number id="2 Co 11:22">22</verse-number>Are they Hebrews? I <supplied>am</supplied> also! Are they Israelites? I <supplied>am</supplied> also! Are they descendants of Abraham? I <supplied>am</supplied> also! <verse-number id="2 Co 11:23">23</verse-number>Are they servants of Christ?—I am speaking as though I were beside myself—I <supplied>am</supplied> more so, with far greater labors, with far more imprisonments, with beatings to a much greater degree, in <supplied>danger of</supplied> death many times. <verse-number id="2 Co 11:24">24</verse-number>Five times I received at the hands of the Jews forty <supplied>lashes</supplied> less one. <verse-number id="2 Co 11:25">25</verse-number>Three times I was beaten with rods. Once I received a stoning. Three times I was shipwrecked. A day and a night I have spent in the deep water. <verse-number id="2 Co 11:26">26</verse-number><supplied>I have been</supplied> on journeys many times, in dangers from rivers, in dangers from robbers, in dangers from <supplied>my own</supplied> people, in dangers from the Gentiles, in dangers in the city, in dangers in the wilderness, in dangers at sea, in dangers because of false brothers, <verse-number id="2 Co 11:27">27</verse-number>with toil and hardship, often in sleepless nights, with hunger and thirst, often going hungry, in cold and poorly clothed. <verse-number id="2 Co 11:28">28</verse-number>Apart from these external things, <supplied>there is</supplied> the pressure on me every day of the anxiety about all the churches. <verse-number id="2 Co 11:29">29</verse-number>Who is weak, and <supplied>I am</supplied> not weak? Who is caused to sin, and I do not burn <supplied>with indignation</supplied>? <verse-number id="2 Co 11:30">30</verse-number>If it is necessary to boast, I will boast <supplied>about</supplied> <idiom-start/>the things related to my weakness<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the things of my weakness”</note>. <verse-number id="2 Co 11:31">31</verse-number>The God and Father of the Lord Jesus, who is blessed <idiom-start/>forever<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the ages”</note>, knows that I am not lying. <verse-number id="2 Co 11:32">32</verse-number>In Damascus, the governor under King Aretas was guarding the city of the Damascenes in order to take me into custody, <verse-number id="2 Co 11:33">33</verse-number>and I was lowered through a window through the wall in a rope-basket, and I escaped his hands. </p>
		</chapter>