<chapter id="2 Co 12">
			<pericope>A Vision of Paradise</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Co 12:1">1</verse-number> It is necessary to boast; <supplied>it is</supplied> not profitable, but I will proceed to visions and revelations of the Lord. <verse-number id="2 Co 12:2">2</verse-number>I know a man in Christ fourteen years ago—whether in the body I do not know, or outside the body I do not know, God knows—such a man was caught up to the third heaven, <verse-number id="2 Co 12:3">3</verse-number>and I know this man—whether in the body or apart from the body I do not know, God knows—<verse-number id="2 Co 12:4">4</verse-number>that he was caught up to paradise and heard words not to be spoken, which <supplied>it is</supplied> not permitted for a person to speak. <verse-number id="2 Co 12:5">5</verse-number>On behalf of such a person I will boast, but on behalf of myself I will not boast, except in my weaknesses. <verse-number id="2 Co 12:6">6</verse-number>For if I want to boast, I will not be foolish, because I will be telling the truth, but I am refraining, so that no one can credit to me more than what he sees <supplied>in</supplied> me or hears anything from me, <verse-number id="2 Co 12:7">7</verse-number>even because of the extraordinary degree of the revelations. Therefore, so that I would not exalt myself, a thorn in the flesh was given to me, a messenger of Satan, in order that it would torment me so that I would not exalt myself. <verse-number id="2 Co 12:8">8</verse-number>Three times I appealed to the Lord about this, that it would depart from me. <verse-number id="2 Co 12:9">9</verse-number>And he said to me, “My grace is sufficient for you, because the<note>A majority of later manuscripts read “my”</note> power is perfected in weakness.” Therefore rather I will boast most gladly in my weaknesses, in order that the power of Christ may reside in me. <verse-number id="2 Co 12:10">10</verse-number>Therefore I delight in weaknesses, in insults, in calamities, in persecutions and difficulties for the sake of Christ, for whenever I am weak, then I am strong. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Paul’s Concern for the Christians at Corinth</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Co 12:11">11</verse-number>I have become a fool! You compelled me, for I ought to have been commended by you, for <supplied>I am</supplied> in no way inferior to the preeminent apostles,<note>Some interpreters take this to refer to the original apostles in Jerusalem; others take Paul to be referring sarcastically to his opponents in Corinth.</note> even if I am nothing. <verse-number id="2 Co 12:12">12</verse-number>Indeed, the signs of an apostle have been done among you with all patient endurance, both signs and wonders and deeds of power. <verse-number id="2 Co 12:13">13</verse-number><idiom-start/>For in what respect are you made worse off<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for what is it <supplied>with respect to</supplied> which you are made worse off”</note> more than the rest of the churches, except that I myself was not a burden to you? Forgive me this wrong! <verse-number id="2 Co 12:14">14</verse-number>Behold, this third <supplied>time</supplied> I am ready to come to you, and I will not be a burden <supplied>to you</supplied>. For I am not seeking your possessions, but you. For children are not obligated to save up for their parents, but parents for their children. <verse-number id="2 Co 12:15">15</verse-number>But I will spend and be expended most gladly for your lives. If I love you much more, am I to be loved less? <verse-number id="2 Co 12:16">16</verse-number>But let <supplied>it</supplied> be. I have not been a burden to you, but <supplied>because I</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was”) which is understood as causal</note> was crafty, I took you by cunning. <verse-number id="2 Co 12:17">17</verse-number>I have not taken advantage of you <idiom-start/>through anyone whom I sent to you<idiom-end/><note>Literally “anyone whom I sent to you, through him”</note>, <supplied>have I</supplied>?<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here</note> <verse-number id="2 Co 12:18">18</verse-number>I urged Titus <supplied>to go</supplied>, and I sent the brother <supplied>with him</supplied>. Titus did not take advantage of you, <supplied>did he</supplied>?<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here</note> Did we not conduct ourselves in the same spirit?<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a positive answer here</note> Did we not walk in the same footsteps?<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a positive answer here</note> <verse-number id="2 Co 12:19">19</verse-number>Have you been thinking all this time that we are defending ourselves to you? We are speaking in Christ before God, and all <supplied>these things</supplied>, dear friends, <supplied>are</supplied> for your edification. <verse-number id="2 Co 12:20">20</verse-number>For I am afraid lest somehow <supplied>when I</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“arrive”) which is understood as temporal</note> arrive, I will not find you as I want, and I may be found by you as you do not want. <supplied>I am afraid</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The words “I am afraid” are not in the Greek text, but are an understood repetition from the previous clause</note> lest somehow <supplied>there will be</supplied> strife, jealousy, outbursts of anger, selfish ambition, slander, gossip, pride, disorder. <verse-number id="2 Co 12:21">21</verse-number><supplied>I am afraid</supplied> lest <supplied>when I</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“come”) which is understood as temporal</note> come again my God will humiliate me <idiom-start/>in your presence<idiom-end/><note>Literally “with you”</note>, and I will grieve over many of those who sinned previously and have not repented because of their impurity and sexual immorality and licentiousness that they have practiced. </p>
		</chapter>