<chapter id="2 Co 13">
			<pericope>Final Warnings to the Church at Corinth</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Co 13:1">1</verse-number> This <supplied>is</supplied> the third <supplied>time</supplied> I am coming to you. <idiom-start/>By the testimony<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from the mouth”</note> of two or three witnesses every word<note>Or “matter”</note> will be established. <verse-number id="2 Co 13:2">2</verse-number>I have already said when <supplied>I</supplied> was present the second time, and <supplied>although I</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>although</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“am absent”) which is understood as concessive</note> am absent now <supplied>I</supplied> also say in advance to those who sinned previously and to all the rest, that if I come again I will not spare <supplied>anyone</supplied>, <verse-number id="2 Co 13:3">3</verse-number>since you are demanding proof that Christ, who <supplied>is</supplied> not weak toward you, but is powerful among you, is speaking in me. <verse-number id="2 Co 13:4">4</verse-number>For indeed, he was crucified because of weakness, but he lives because of the power of God. For we also are weak in him, but we will live together with him because of the power of God toward you. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Co 13:5">5</verse-number>Test yourselves <supplied>to see</supplied> if you are in the faith. Examine yourselves! Or do you not recognize regarding yourselves that Jesus Christ <supplied>is</supplied> in you, unless you are unqualified? <verse-number id="2 Co 13:6">6</verse-number>And I hope that you will recognize that we are not unqualified! <verse-number id="2 Co 13:7">7</verse-number>Now we pray to God that you not do wrong in any way, not that we are seen as approved, but that you do what is good, even <supplied>though</supplied> we are <supplied>seen</supplied> as though unqualified. <verse-number id="2 Co 13:8">8</verse-number>For we are not able <supplied>to do</supplied> anything against the truth, but rather <supplied>only</supplied> for the truth. <verse-number id="2 Co 13:9">9</verse-number>For we rejoice whenever we are weak, but you are strong, and we pray for this: your maturity. <verse-number id="2 Co 13:10">10</verse-number>Because of this, I am writing these <supplied>things</supplied> <supplied>although I</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>although</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“am absent”) which is understood as concessive</note> am absent, in order that <supplied>when I</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“am present”) which is understood as temporal</note> am present I may not have to act severely according to the authority that the Lord has given me for building up and not for tearing down. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Final Greetings and Benediction</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="2 Co 13:11">11</verse-number>Finally, brothers, rejoice, be restored, be encouraged, <idiom-start/>be in agreement<idiom-end/><note>Literally “think the same thing”</note>, be at peace, and the God of love and peace will be with you. <verse-number id="2 Co 13:12">12</verse-number>Greet one another with a holy kiss. All the saints greet you. <verse-number id="2 Co 13:13">13</verse-number>The grace of the Lord Jesus Christ and the love of God and the fellowship of the Holy Spirit <supplied>be</supplied> with all of you. </p>
		</chapter>