<chapter id="1 Pe 1">
			<pericope>Greeting</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Pe 1:1">1</verse-number> Peter, an apostle of Jesus Christ, to the chosen<note>Or “elect”</note> who are residing temporarily in the dispersion in Pontus, Galatia, Cappadocia, Asia, and Bithynia, <verse-number id="1 Pe 1:2">2</verse-number>according to the foreknowledge of God the Father, by the sanctification of the Spirit, for obedience and <supplied>for</supplied> sprinkling with the blood of Jesus Christ. May grace and peace be multiplied to you. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A New Birth to a Living Hope</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Pe 1:3">3</verse-number>Blessed <supplied>be</supplied> the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, who according to his great mercy has caused us to be born again to a living hope through the resurrection of Jesus Christ from the dead, <verse-number id="1 Pe 1:4">4</verse-number>into an inheritance imperishable and undefiled and unfading, reserved in heaven for you <verse-number id="1 Pe 1:5">5</verse-number>who are being protected by the power of God through faith for a salvation ready to be revealed in the last time, <verse-number id="1 Pe 1:6">6</verse-number>in which you rejoice greatly, <supplied>although</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>although</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“are distressed”) which is understood as concessive</note> now for a short time, if necessary,<note>Some manuscripts have “if it is necessary”</note> you are distressed by various trials, <verse-number id="1 Pe 1:7">7</verse-number>so that the genuineness of your faith, more valuable than gold that is passing away, but is tested by fire, may be found to <supplied>result in</supplied> praise and glory and honor at the revelation of Jesus Christ, <verse-number id="1 Pe 1:8">8</verse-number>whom, <supplied>although you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>although</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“seen”) which is understood as concessive</note> have not seen, you love; in whom now you believe, <supplied>although you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>although</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“see”) which is understood as concessive</note> do not see <supplied>him</supplied>, and you rejoice greatly with joy inexpressible and full of glory, <verse-number id="1 Pe 1:9">9</verse-number>obtaining the goal of your faith, the salvation of <supplied>your</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*This is an understood repetition of the previous “your”</note> souls. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Pe 1:10">10</verse-number>Concerning this<note>Literally “which”</note> salvation, the prophets who prophesied about the grace meant for you sought and made careful inquiry, <verse-number id="1 Pe 1:11">11</verse-number>investigating for what <supplied>person</supplied> or which time the Spirit of Christ in them was indicating <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“testified beforehand”) which is understood as temporal</note> testified beforehand to the sufferings with reference to Christ and the glories after these <supplied>things</supplied>, <verse-number id="1 Pe 1:12">12</verse-number>to whom it was revealed that they were serving not themselves but you with reference to the same <supplied>things</supplied> which now have been announced to you through those who proclaimed the gospel to you by the Holy Spirit sent from heaven, <idiom-start/>things into which<idiom-end/><note>Literally “into which <supplied>things</supplied>”</note> angels desire to look. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Be Holy in All Your Conduct</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Pe 1:13">13</verse-number>Therefore, <idiom-start/>when you have prepared your minds for action<idiom-end/><note>Literally “having girded up the loins of your mind”</note> <supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“being self-controlled”) which is understood as means</note> being self-controlled, put your hope completely in the grace that will be brought to you at the revelation of Jesus Christ. <verse-number id="1 Pe 1:14">14</verse-number>As obedient children, do not be conformed to the former desires <supplied>you used to conform to</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*This is an understood repetition of the earlier verb “be conformed to”</note> in your ignorance, <verse-number id="1 Pe 1:15">15</verse-number>but as the one who called you <supplied>is</supplied> holy, <supplied>you</supplied> yourselves be holy in all <supplied>your</supplied> conduct, <verse-number id="1 Pe 1:16">16</verse-number>for it is written, “You will be holy, because I <supplied>am</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here the verb is understood in Greek and is supplied in the translation</note> holy.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Le 19:2">Lev 19:2</cite></note><note>Some manuscripts explicitly state “I am holy”</note> <verse-number id="1 Pe 1:17">17</verse-number>And if you call on <supplied>him</supplied> <supplied>as</supplied> Father who judges impartially according to each one’s work, conduct yourselves with fear during the time of your temporary residence, <verse-number id="1 Pe 1:18">18</verse-number><supplied>because you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“know”) which is understood as causal</note> know that you were redeemed from your futile way of life inherited from your ancestors not with perishable things like silver or gold, <verse-number id="1 Pe 1:19">19</verse-number>but with the precious blood of Christ, like <supplied>that of</supplied> an unblemished and spotless lamb <verse-number id="1 Pe 1:20">20</verse-number>who was foreknown before the foundation of the world, but has been revealed in these last times for you <verse-number id="1 Pe 1:21">21</verse-number>who through him <supplied>are</supplied> believing in God, who raised him from the dead and gave him glory, so that your faith and hope are in God. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Pe 1:22">22</verse-number>Having purified your souls by your obedience to the truth for sincere brotherly love, love one another fervently from the heart,<note>Some manuscripts have “from a pure heart”</note> <verse-number id="1 Pe 1:23">23</verse-number><supplied>because you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“have been born again”) which is understood as causal</note> have been born again, not from perishable seed but imperishable, through the living and enduring word of God. <verse-number id="1 Pe 1:24">24</verse-number>For </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“all flesh <supplied>is</supplied> like grass, </li1>
				<li2>and all its glory like the flower of the grass. </li2>
				<li1>The grass withers and the flower falls off, </li1>
				<li2><verse-number id="1 Pe 1:25">25</verse-number>but the word of the Lord endures <idiom-start/>forever<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for the age”</note>.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 40:6">Isa 40:6</cite>, <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 40:8">8</cite></note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p>And this is the word that has been proclaimed to you. </p>
		</chapter>