<chapter id="1 Pe 2">
			<pericope>Chosen as Living Stones</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Pe 2:1">1</verse-number> Therefore, ridding yourselves of all malice and all deceit and hypocrisy and envy and all slander, <verse-number id="1 Pe 2:2">2</verse-number>like newborn infants long for the unadulterated spiritual milk, so that by it you may grow up to salvation, <verse-number id="1 Pe 2:3">3</verse-number>if you have tasted that the Lord <supplied>is</supplied> kind,<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 34:8">Ps 34:8</cite></note> <verse-number id="1 Pe 2:4">4</verse-number>to whom you are drawing near, a living stone rejected by men but chosen <supplied>and</supplied> precious in the sight of God. <verse-number id="1 Pe 2:5">5</verse-number>And <supplied>you</supplied> yourselves, as living stones, are being built up <supplied>as</supplied> a spiritual house for a holy priesthood, to offer up spiritual sacrifices acceptable to God through Jesus Christ. <verse-number id="1 Pe 2:6">6</verse-number>For it stands in scripture, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Behold, I am laying in Zion a stone, a chosen <supplied>and</supplied> precious cornerstone, </li1>
				<li1>and the one who believes in him will never be put to shame.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 28:16">Isa 28:16</cite></note> </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Pe 2:7">7</verse-number>Therefore the honor <supplied>is</supplied> for you who believe, but for those who refuse to believe, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“The stone that the builders rejected, </li1>
				<li1>this one has become <idiom-start/>the cornerstone<idiom-end/><note>Literally “into the head of the corner”</note>,” </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Pe 2:8">8</verse-number>and </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“A stone of stumbling and a rock of offense,”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 8:14">Isa 8:14</cite></note> </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p>who stumble <supplied>because they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“disobey”) which is understood as causal</note> disobey the word to which also they were consigned. <verse-number id="1 Pe 2:9">9</verse-number>But you <supplied>are</supplied> a chosen race,<note>Or “people,” or “generation,” or “nation”</note> a royal priesthood, a holy nation, a people for <supplied>God’s</supplied> possession, so that you may proclaim the virtues of the one who called you out of darkness into his marvelous light, <verse-number id="1 Pe 2:10">10</verse-number>who once <supplied>were</supplied> not a people, but now <supplied>are</supplied> the people of God, the ones <supplied>who were</supplied> not shown mercy, but now are shown mercy.<note>This verse contains quotations from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ho 1:6">Hos 1:6</cite>, <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ho 1:9">9</cite>; <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ho 2:23">2:23</cite></note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Pe 2:11">11</verse-number>Dear friends, I urge <supplied>you</supplied> as foreigners and temporary residents to abstain from fleshly desires which wage war against your<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> soul, <verse-number id="1 Pe 2:12">12</verse-number>maintaining your good conduct among the Gentiles, so that in <supplied>the things</supplied> in which they slander you as evildoers, by seeing your good deeds they may glorify God on the day of visitation. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Submission to Established Authority</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Pe 2:13">13</verse-number>Subject yourselves to every human authority for the sake of the Lord, whether to a king<note>Or “to the emperor”</note> as having supreme authority, <verse-number id="1 Pe 2:14">14</verse-number>or to governors as those sent out by him for the punishment of those who do evil and the praise of those who do good. <verse-number id="1 Pe 2:15">15</verse-number>For the will of God is as follows: <supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“doing good”) which is understood as means</note> doing good to silence the ignorance of foolish people. <verse-number id="1 Pe 2:16">16</verse-number><supplied>Live</supplied> as free <supplied>persons</supplied>, and not using your<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> freedom as a covering for evil, but as slaves of God. <verse-number id="1 Pe 2:17">17</verse-number>Honor all <supplied>people</supplied>, love the community of believers, fear God, honor the king.<note>Or “the emperor”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Pe 2:18">18</verse-number>Domestic slaves, be subject to your<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> masters with all respect, not only to those <supplied>who are</supplied> good and gentle, but also to those <supplied>who are</supplied> unjust. <verse-number id="1 Pe 2:19">19</verse-number>For this <supplied>finds</supplied> favor, if because of consciousness of God someone endures sorrows <supplied>while</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“suffering”) which is understood as temporal</note> suffering unjustly. <verse-number id="1 Pe 2:20">20</verse-number>For what credit <supplied>is it</supplied> if, <supplied>when you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“sin”) which is understood as temporal</note> sin and are beaten <supplied>for it</supplied>, you endure? But if you endure <supplied>when you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“do good”) which is understood as temporal</note> do good and suffer <supplied>for it</supplied>, this <supplied>finds</supplied> favor with God. <verse-number id="1 Pe 2:21">21</verse-number>For to this you were called, because Christ also suffered for you, leaving you an example, so that you should follow in his footsteps, <verse-number id="1 Pe 2:22">22</verse-number>who did not commit sin, nor was deceit found in his mouth,<note>This verse contains quotations from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 53:9">Isa 53:9</cite></note> <verse-number id="1 Pe 2:23">23</verse-number>who <supplied>when he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was reviled”) which is understood as temporal</note> was reviled, did not revile in return; <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“suffering”) which is understood as temporal</note> suffering, he did not threaten, but entrusted <supplied>himself</supplied> to the one who judges justly, <verse-number id="1 Pe 2:24">24</verse-number>who himself bore our sins in his body on the tree, so that <supplied>we</supplied> may die to sins <supplied>and</supplied> live to righteousness, by whose wounds you were healed. <verse-number id="1 Pe 2:25">25</verse-number>For you were going astray like sheep, but you have turned back now to the shepherd and guardian of your souls. </p>
		</chapter>