<chapter id="1 Pe 3">
			<pericope>Wives and Husbands</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Pe 3:1">1</verse-number> In the same way, wives, be subject to your own husbands, so that even if some are disobedient to the word, they may be won over without a word by the conduct of their wives, <verse-number id="1 Pe 3:2">2</verse-number><supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“see”) which is understood as temporal</note> see your respectful, pure conduct. <verse-number id="1 Pe 3:3">3</verse-number>Let your<note>Literally “of whom,” referring to the wives</note> adornment not be the external <supplied>kind</supplied>, braiding hair and putting on gold jewelry or putting on <supplied>fine</supplied> clothing, <verse-number id="1 Pe 3:4">4</verse-number>but the hidden person of the heart, with the imperishable <supplied>quality</supplied> of a gentle and quiet spirit, which is highly valuable in the sight of God. <verse-number id="1 Pe 3:5">5</verse-number>For in the <supplied>same</supplied> way formerly the holy women also, who hoped in God, used to adorn themselves <supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“being subject”) which is understood as means</note> being subject to their own husbands, <verse-number id="1 Pe 3:6">6</verse-number>like Sarah obeyed Abraham, calling him lord, whose children you have become <supplied>when you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“do good”) which is understood as temporal</note> do good and are not frightened with respect to any terror. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Pe 3:7">7</verse-number>Husbands, in the same way live with <supplied>your wives</supplied> <idiom-start/>knowledgeably<idiom-end/><note>Literally “according to knowledge”</note>, as with the weaker female vessel, showing <supplied>them</supplied> honor as fellow heirs also of the grace of life, so that your prayers will not be hindered. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Called to Inherit a Blessing</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Pe 3:8">8</verse-number>And finally, all <supplied>of you be</supplied> harmonious, sympathetic, showing mutual affection, compassionate, humble, <verse-number id="1 Pe 3:9">9</verse-number>not repaying evil for evil or insult for insult, but on the other hand blessing <supplied>others</supplied>, because for this <supplied>reason</supplied> you were called, so that you could inherit a blessing. <verse-number id="1 Pe 3:10">10</verse-number>For </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“The one who wants to love life </li1>
				<li2>and see good days </li2>
				<li1>must keep his<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> tongue from evil </li1>
				<li2>and <supplied>his</supplied> lips must not speak deceit. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="1 Pe 3:11">11</verse-number>And he must turn away from evil and do good; </li1>
				<li2>he must seek peace and pursue it. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="1 Pe 3:12">12</verse-number>For the eyes of the Lord <supplied>are</supplied> on the righteous, </li1>
				<li2>and his ears <supplied>are open to</supplied> their prayer. </li2>
				<li1>But the face of the Lord <supplied>is</supplied> against those who do evil.<note>Verses <cite title="BibleLEB2:1 Pe 3:10–12">10–12</cite> are a quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ps 34:12–16">Ps 34:12–16</cite></note> </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Suffer for Doing What is Good</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Pe 3:13">13</verse-number>And who <supplied>is</supplied> the one who will harm you if you are a zealous adherent for what is good? <verse-number id="1 Pe 3:14">14</verse-number>But even if you might suffer for the sake of righteousness, <supplied>you are</supplied> blessed. And do not be afraid of their intimidation or be disturbed,<note>The second half of this verse contains a quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 8:12">Isa 8:12</cite></note> <verse-number id="1 Pe 3:15">15</verse-number>but set Christ apart <supplied>as</supplied> Lord in your hearts, always ready to <supplied>make</supplied> a defense to anyone who asks you <supplied>for</supplied> an accounting concerning the hope <supplied>that is</supplied> in you. <verse-number id="1 Pe 3:16">16</verse-number>But <supplied>do so</supplied> with courtesy and respect, having a good conscience, so that in <supplied>the things</supplied> in which you are slandered, the ones who malign your good conduct in Christ may be put to shame. <verse-number id="1 Pe 3:17">17</verse-number>For <supplied>it is</supplied> better to suffer for doing good, <idiom-start/>if God wills it<idiom-end/><note>Literally “if the will of God wills”</note>, than for doing evil. </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="1 Pe 3:18">18</verse-number>For Christ also suffered once for sins, </li1>
				<li2>the just for the unjust, </li2>
				<li1>in order that he could bring you to God, </li1>
				<li2>being put to death in the flesh, </li2>
				<li1>but made alive in the spirit, </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="1 Pe 3:19">19</verse-number>in which also he went <supplied>and</supplied> proclaimed to the spirits in prison, </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Pe 3:20">20</verse-number>who were formerly disobedient, when the patience of God waited in the days of Noah, <supplied>while</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>while</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was being constructed”)</note> an ark was being constructed, in which a few—that is, eight souls—were rescued through water. <verse-number id="1 Pe 3:21">21</verse-number>And<note>Literally “which”</note> also, corresponding to <supplied>this</supplied>, baptism now saves you, not the removal of dirt from the flesh, but an appeal to God for a good conscience through the resurrection of Jesus Christ, <verse-number id="1 Pe 3:22">22</verse-number>who is at the right hand of God, having gone into heaven, with angels and authorities and powers having been subjected to him. </p>
		</chapter>