<chapter id="1 Pe 4">
			<pericope>The Time for Behaving Like the Gentiles is Past</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Pe 4:1">1</verse-number> Therefore, <supplied>because</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“suffered”) which is understood as causal</note> Christ suffered in the flesh, you also equip yourselves with the same way of thinking, because the one who has suffered in the flesh has ceased from sin, <verse-number id="1 Pe 4:2">2</verse-number>in order to live the remaining time in the flesh no longer for human desires, but for the will of God. <verse-number id="1 Pe 4:3">3</verse-number>For the time that has passed <supplied>was</supplied> sufficient <idiom-start/>to do what the Gentiles desire to do<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to do the intention of the Gentiles”</note>, having lived in licentiousness, <supplied>evil</supplied> desires, drunkenness, carousing, drinking parties, and wanton idolatries, <verse-number id="1 Pe 4:4">4</verse-number>with respect to which they are surprised <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“run with”) which is understood as temporal</note> you do not run with <supplied>them</supplied> into the same flood of dissipation, <supplied>and so they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>and so</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“revile”) which is understood as result</note> revile <supplied>you</supplied>. <verse-number id="1 Pe 4:5">5</verse-number>They<note>Literally “who”</note> will give an account to the one who is ready to judge the living and the dead. <verse-number id="1 Pe 4:6">6</verse-number>Because for this reason also the gospel was preached to those who are dead, so that they were judged <idiom-start/>by human standards<idiom-end/><note>Literally “according to men”</note> in the flesh, but they may live in the spirit <idiom-start/>by God’s standards<idiom-end/><note>Literally “according to God”</note>. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Serving to the Glory of God</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Pe 4:7">7</verse-number>Now the end of all <supplied>things</supplied> draws near. Therefore be self-controlled and sober-minded for <supplied>your</supplied> prayers. <verse-number id="1 Pe 4:8">8</verse-number>Above all, keep<note>Literally “having”</note> your love for one another constant, because love covers a large number of sins. <verse-number id="1 Pe 4:9">9</verse-number><supplied>Be</supplied> hospitable to one another without complaining. <verse-number id="1 Pe 4:10">10</verse-number>Just as each one has received a gift, <supplied>use</supplied> it for serving one another, as good stewards of the varied grace of God. <verse-number id="1 Pe 4:11">11</verse-number>If anyone speaks, <supplied>let it be</supplied> as the oracles of God; if anyone serves, <supplied>let it be</supplied> as by the strength that God provides, so that in all <supplied>things</supplied> God will be glorified through Jesus Christ, to whom is the glory and the power <idiom-start/>forever and ever<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for the ages of the ages”</note>. Amen. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Sharing the Sufferings of Christ</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Pe 4:12">12</verse-number>Dear friends, do not be surprised at the fiery ordeal among you, <supplied>when it</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“takes place”) which is understood as temporal</note> takes place to test you, as <supplied>if</supplied> <supplied>something</supplied> strange were happening to you. <verse-number id="1 Pe 4:13">13</verse-number>But to the degree that you share in the sufferings of Christ, rejoice, so that also at the revelation of his glory you may rejoice <supplied>and</supplied> be glad. <verse-number id="1 Pe 4:14">14</verse-number>If you are reviled on account of the name of Christ, <supplied>you are</supplied> blessed, because the Spirit of glory and of God rests on you. <verse-number id="1 Pe 4:15">15</verse-number>By all means do not let anyone of you suffer as a murderer or a thief or an evildoer or as a meddler. <verse-number id="1 Pe 4:16">16</verse-number>But if <supplied>someone suffers</supplied> as a Christian, he must not be ashamed, but must glorify God with this name. <verse-number id="1 Pe 4:17">17</verse-number>For <supplied>it is</supplied> the time for the judgment to begin out from the household of God. But if <supplied>it begins</supplied> out from us first, what will be the outcome for those who are disobedient to the gospel of God? <verse-number id="1 Pe 4:18">18</verse-number>And if the righteous are saved with difficulty, <idiom-start/>what will become of the ungodly and the sinner<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the ungodly and sinner where will he appear”</note>?<note>This verse contains a quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Pr 11:31">Prov 11:31</cite></note> <verse-number id="1 Pe 4:19">19</verse-number>So then also those who suffer according to the will of God must entrust their souls to a faithful Creator in doing good. </p>
		</chapter>