<chapter id="1 Pe 5">
			<pericope>Leadership and Humility</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Pe 5:1">1</verse-number> Therefore <supplied>I, your</supplied> fellow elder and a witness of the sufferings of Christ, <supplied>and</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The conjunction “<supplied>and</supplied>” is supplied here to make it clear that the following phrase refers also to the author of the letter and not to Christ</note> also a sharer of the glory that is going to be revealed, exhort the elders among you: <verse-number id="1 Pe 5:2">2</verse-number>shepherd the flock of God among you, exercising oversight not by compulsion but willingly, in accordance with God, and not greedily but eagerly, <verse-number id="1 Pe 5:3">3</verse-number>and not as lording it over <idiom-start/>those under your care<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the portion”</note>, but being examples for the flock. <verse-number id="1 Pe 5:4">4</verse-number>And <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“appears”)</note> the chief Shepherd appears, you will receive the unfading crown of glory. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Pe 5:5">5</verse-number>In the same way, younger men, be subject to the elders, and all <supplied>of you</supplied> clothe yourselves with humility toward one another, because God opposes the proud, but gives grace to the humble. <verse-number id="1 Pe 5:6">6</verse-number>Humble yourselves therefore under the mighty hand of God, so that he may exalt you at the <supplied>right</supplied> time, <verse-number id="1 Pe 5:7">7</verse-number>casting all your cares on him, because <idiom-start/>he cares<idiom-end/><note>Literally “it is a care to him”</note> for you. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Pe 5:8">8</verse-number>Be sober; be on the alert. Your adversary the devil walks around like a roaring lion, looking for someone to devour. <verse-number id="1 Pe 5:9">9</verse-number><idiom-start/>Resist him<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to whom resist”</note>, steadfast in your<note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> faith, <supplied>because you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“know”) which is understood as causal</note> know the same <supplied>kinds</supplied> of sufferings are being accomplished by your community of believers in the world. <verse-number id="1 Pe 5:10">10</verse-number>And the God of all grace, who called you to his eternal glory in Christ,<note>Some manuscripts have “in Christ Jesus”</note> <supplied>after you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“have suffered”) which is understood as temporal</note> have suffered for a short time, will himself restore, confirm, strengthen, <supplied>and</supplied> establish <supplied>you</supplied>. <verse-number id="1 Pe 5:11">11</verse-number>To him <supplied>be</supplied> the power <idiom-start/>forever and ever<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to the ages of the ages”</note>.<note>Some manuscripts have “forever” (literally “to the ages”)</note> Amen. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Conclusion and Final Greetings</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="1 Pe 5:12">12</verse-number>Through Silvanus, the faithful brother (as I consider <supplied>him</supplied>), I have written to you <idiom-start/>briefly<idiom-end/><note>Literally “by a few”</note> to encourage <supplied>you</supplied> and to attest that this is the true grace of God. Stand firm in it. <verse-number id="1 Pe 5:13">13</verse-number>She <supplied>who is</supplied> in Babylon, chosen the same as <supplied>you</supplied>, greets you, and <supplied>so does</supplied> my son Mark. <verse-number id="1 Pe 5:14">14</verse-number>Greet one another with a loving kiss. Peace to all of you who are in Christ. </p>
		</chapter>