<chapter id="Ga 1">
			<pericope>Greeting</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ga 1:1">1</verse-number> Paul, an apostle not from men nor by men but through Jesus Christ and God the Father who raised him from the dead, <verse-number id="Ga 1:2">2</verse-number>and all the brothers with me, to the churches of Galatia. <verse-number id="Ga 1:3">3</verse-number>Grace to you and peace from God the Father and our Lord Jesus Christ,<note>Some manuscripts have “God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ”</note> <verse-number id="Ga 1:4">4</verse-number>who gave himself for our sins in order to rescue us from the present evil age, according to the will of our God and Father, <verse-number id="Ga 1:5">5</verse-number>to whom <supplied>be</supplied> the glory forever and ever. Amen. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A Different Gospel</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ga 1:6">6</verse-number>I am astonished that you are turning away so quickly from the one who called you by the grace of Christ to a different gospel, <verse-number id="Ga 1:7">7</verse-number>not that <supplied>there</supplied> is a different <supplied>gospel</supplied>, except there are some who are disturbing you and wanting to distort the gospel of Christ. <verse-number id="Ga 1:8">8</verse-number>But even if we or an angel from heaven should proclaim a gospel to you contrary to what we proclaimed to you, let him be accursed! <verse-number id="Ga 1:9">9</verse-number>As we said before, and now I say again, if anyone is proclaiming a gospel <supplied>to</supplied> you contrary to what you have received, let him be accursed! <verse-number id="Ga 1:10">10</verse-number>For am I now making an appeal to people or <supplied>to</supplied> God? Or am I seeking to please people? If I were still trying to please people, I would not be a slave of Christ. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Paul’s Defense of His Apostleship</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ga 1:11">11</verse-number>For I make known to you, brothers, the gospel that has been proclaimed by me, that it is not <idiom-start/>of human origin<idiom-end/><note>Literally “according to man”</note>. <verse-number id="Ga 1:12">12</verse-number>For neither did I receive it from man, nor was I taught <supplied>it</supplied>, but <supplied>I received it</supplied> through a revelation of Jesus Christ. <verse-number id="Ga 1:13">13</verse-number>For you have heard about my former way of life in Judaism, that to an extraordinary degree I was persecuting the church of God, and trying to destroy it, <verse-number id="Ga 1:14">14</verse-number>and was progressing in Judaism beyond many contemporaries in my nation, <supplied>because</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was”) which is understood as causal</note> I was a far more zealous adherent of the traditions handed down by my forefathers. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ga 1:15">15</verse-number>But when the one who set me apart<note>Some manuscripts have “when God who set me apart”</note> from my mother’s womb and called <supplied>me</supplied> by his grace was pleased <verse-number id="Ga 1:16">16</verse-number>to reveal his Son in me in order that I would proclaim the gospel <supplied>about</supplied> him among the Gentiles, immediately I did not consult with flesh and blood, <verse-number id="Ga 1:17">17</verse-number>nor did I go up to Jerusalem to those <supplied>who were</supplied> apostles before me, but I went away to Arabia and I returned again to Damascus. <verse-number id="Ga 1:18">18</verse-number>Then after three years I went up to Jerusalem to become acquainted with Cephas, and I stayed with him fifteen days, <verse-number id="Ga 1:19">19</verse-number>but I did not see <supplied>any</supplied> others of the apostles except James, the brother of the Lord. <verse-number id="Ga 1:20">20</verse-number>(Now <supplied>the things</supplied> which I am writing to you, behold, <supplied>I assure you</supplied> before God that I am not lying.) <verse-number id="Ga 1:21">21</verse-number>Then I came to the regions of Syria and of Cilicia, <verse-number id="Ga 1:22">22</verse-number>but I was unknown <idiom-start/>in person<idiom-end/><note>Literally “by face”</note> to the churches of Judea <supplied>that are</supplied> in Christ, <verse-number id="Ga 1:23">23</verse-number>and they were only hearing, “The one formerly persecuting us is now proclaiming the faith that formerly he was attempting to destroy,” <verse-number id="Ga 1:24">24</verse-number>and they were glorifying God because of me. </p>
		</chapter>