<chapter id="Ga 2">
			<pericope>Paul’s Ministry Recognized by the Jerusalem Apostles</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ga 2:1">1</verse-number> Then after fourteen years I went up again to Jerusalem with Barnabas, taking along Titus also. <verse-number id="Ga 2:2">2</verse-number>Now I went up <supplied>there</supplied> because of a revelation and laid out to them the gospel that I preach among the Gentiles, but in private to the influential people, lest somehow I was running, or had run, in vain. <verse-number id="Ga 2:3">3</verse-number>But not even Titus <supplied>who was</supplied> with me, <supplied>although</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>although</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was”) which is understood as concessive</note> he was a Greek, was compelled to be circumcised. <verse-number id="Ga 2:4">4</verse-number>Now <supplied>this was</supplied> because of the false brothers secretly brought in, who slipped in to spy out our freedom that we have in Christ Jesus, in order that they might enslave us, <verse-number id="Ga 2:5">5</verse-number>to whom not even for an hour did we yield in subjection, in order that the truth of the gospel might remain continually with you. <verse-number id="Ga 2:6">6</verse-number>But from those <idiom-start/>who were influential<idiom-end/><note>Literally “who were thought to be something”</note> (whatever they were, <supplied>it makes</supplied> no difference to me, <idiom-start/>God does not show partiality<idiom-end/><note>Literally “God does not receive the face of man”</note>)—for those who were influential added nothing to me. <verse-number id="Ga 2:7">7</verse-number>But these, <supplied>when they</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> saw that I had been entrusted <supplied>with</supplied> the gospel to the uncircumcision, just as Peter to the circumcision <verse-number id="Ga 2:8">8</verse-number>(for the one who was at work through Peter for <supplied>his</supplied> apostleship to the circumcision was at work also through me for the Gentiles), <verse-number id="Ga 2:9">9</verse-number>and <supplied>when</supplied> James and Cephas and John—those thought to be pillars—acknowledged the grace given to me, they gave to me and Barnabas the right <supplied>hand</supplied> of fellowship, in order that we <supplied>should go</supplied> to the Gentiles and they to the circumcision. <verse-number id="Ga 2:10">10</verse-number><supplied>They asked</supplied> only that we should remember the poor, the very thing I was also eager to do. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Paul Confronts Peter at Antioch</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ga 2:11">11</verse-number>But when Cephas came to Antioch, I opposed <supplied>him</supplied> to his face, because he was condemned. <verse-number id="Ga 2:12">12</verse-number>For before certain people came from James, he used to eat with the Gentiles, but when they came, he withdrew and separated himself, <supplied>because he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>because</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was afraid of”) which is understood as causal</note> was afraid of those <supplied>who were</supplied> of the circumcision, <verse-number id="Ga 2:13">13</verse-number>and the rest of the Jews also joined in <supplied>this</supplied> hypocrisy with him, so that even Barnabas was carried away with them in <supplied>their</supplied> hypocrisy. <verse-number id="Ga 2:14">14</verse-number>But when I saw that they were not being straightforward with the truth of the gospel, I said to Cephas in the presence of <supplied>them</supplied> all, “If you, <supplied>although you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>although</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“are”) which is understood as concessive</note> are a Jew, live like a Gentile and not like a Jew, how can you try to compel the Gentiles to live like Jews?” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Justified by Faith in Christ</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ga 2:15">15</verse-number>We <supplied>are</supplied> Jews by nature and not sinners from among the Gentiles, <verse-number id="Ga 2:16">16</verse-number>but knowing that a person is not justified by the works of the law, if not by faith in Jesus Christ,<note>Or “by the faithfulness of Jesus Christ”</note> and we have believed in Christ Jesus so that we may be justified by faith in Christ<note>Or “by the faithfulness of Christ”</note> and not by the works of the law, because by the works of the law <idiom-start/>no human being will be justified<idiom-end/><note>Literally “all flesh will not be justified”</note>. <verse-number id="Ga 2:17">17</verse-number>But if <supplied>while</supplied> seeking to be justified by Christ, <supplied>we</supplied> ourselves also have been found <supplied>to be</supplied> sinners, then <supplied>is</supplied> Christ an agent of sin? May it never be! <verse-number id="Ga 2:18">18</verse-number>For if I build up again these <supplied>things</supplied> which I destroyed, I show myself <supplied>to be</supplied> a transgressor. <verse-number id="Ga 2:19">19</verse-number>For through the law I died to the law, in order that I might live to God. I have been crucified with Christ, <verse-number id="Ga 2:20">20</verse-number>and I no longer live, but Christ lives in me, and that <supplied>life</supplied> I now live in the flesh, I live by faith in the Son of God, who loved me and gave himself for me. <verse-number id="Ga 2:21">21</verse-number>I do not declare invalid the grace of God, for if righteousness <supplied>is</supplied> through the law, then Christ died to no purpose. </p>
		</chapter>