<chapter id="Ga 3">
			<pericope>Justified by the Law, or Justified by Faith?</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ga 3:1">1</verse-number> O foolish Galatians, who has bewitched you, before whose eyes Jesus Christ was publicly portrayed <supplied>as</supplied> having been crucified? <verse-number id="Ga 3:2">2</verse-number>I want only to learn this from you: Did you receive the Spirit by the works of the law, or by the hearing of faith? <verse-number id="Ga 3:3">3</verse-number>Are you so foolish? Having begun by the Spirit, are you now trying to be made complete by the flesh? <verse-number id="Ga 3:4">4</verse-number>Have you suffered so many <supplied>things</supplied> for nothing—if indeed also <supplied>it was</supplied> for nothing? <verse-number id="Ga 3:5">5</verse-number>Therefore does the one who gives you the Spirit and who works miracles among you <supplied>do so</supplied> by the works of the law, or by the hearing of faith? </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ga 3:6">6</verse-number>Just as Abraham believed God, and it was credited to him for righteousness, <verse-number id="Ga 3:7">7</verse-number>then understand that the ones <idiom-start/>who have faith<idiom-end/><note>Literally “of faith”</note>, these are sons of Abraham. <verse-number id="Ga 3:8">8</verse-number>And the scripture, foreseeing that God would justify the Gentiles by faith, proclaimed the good news in advance to Abraham: “In you all the nations<note>Or “Gentiles”; the same Greek word can be translated “nations” or “Gentiles” depending on the context</note> will be blessed.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ge 12:3">Gen 12:3</cite>; <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ge 18:18">18:18</cite></note> <verse-number id="Ga 3:9">9</verse-number>So then, the ones <supplied>who have</supplied> faith are blessed together with Abraham who believed. <verse-number id="Ga 3:10">10</verse-number>For as many as are of the works of the law are under a curse, for it is written, “Cursed <supplied>is</supplied> everyone who does not abide by all <supplied>the things</supplied> that are written in the book of the law to do them.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Dt 27:26">Deut 27:26</cite></note> <verse-number id="Ga 3:11">11</verse-number>Now <supplied>it is</supplied> clear that no one is justified in the sight of God by the law, because “the one who is righteous will live by faith.”<note>Or “the one who is righteous by faith will live,” a quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Hab 2:4">Hab 2:4</cite></note> <verse-number id="Ga 3:12">12</verse-number>But the law is not from faith, but “the one who does these <supplied>things</supplied> will live by them.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Le 18:5">Lev 18:5</cite></note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ga 3:13">13</verse-number>Christ redeemed us from the curse of the law <supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“becoming”) which is understood as means</note> becoming a curse for us, because it is written, “Cursed <supplied>is</supplied> everyone who hangs on a tree,”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Dt 21:23">Deut 21:23</cite></note> <verse-number id="Ga 3:14">14</verse-number>in order that the blessing of Abraham might come to the Gentiles in Christ Jesus, so that we might receive the promise of the Spirit through faith. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Promise to Abraham and His Descendant</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ga 3:15">15</verse-number>Brothers, I am speaking according to a human perspective. Nevertheless, <supplied>when</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“has been ratified”) which is understood as temporal</note> the covenant of a man has been ratified, no one declares <supplied>it</supplied> invalid or adds additional provisions <supplied>to it</supplied>. <verse-number id="Ga 3:16">16</verse-number>Now to Abraham and to his descendant the promises were spoken. It does not say, “and to descendants,” as concerning many, but as concerning one, “and to your descendant,”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ge 12:7">Gen 12:7</cite>; <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ge 13:15">13:15</cite>; <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ge 17:7">17:7</cite>; <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ge 24:7">24:7</cite></note> who is Christ. <verse-number id="Ga 3:17">17</verse-number>Now I am saying this: the law, that came after four hundred and thirty years, does not revoke a covenant previously ratified by God, in order to nullify the promise. <verse-number id="Ga 3:18">18</verse-number>For if the inheritance <supplied>is</supplied> from the law, <supplied>it is</supplied> no longer from the promise, but God graciously gave <supplied>it</supplied> to Abraham through the promise. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Addition of the Law</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ga 3:19">19</verse-number>Why then the law? It was added on account of transgressions, until the descendant should come to whom it had been promised, having been ordered through angels by the hand of a mediator. <verse-number id="Ga 3:20">20</verse-number>Now the mediator is not for one, but God is one. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ga 3:21">21</verse-number>Therefore <supplied>is</supplied> the law opposed to the promises of God? May it never be! For if a law had been given that was able to give life, certainly righteousness would have been from the law. <verse-number id="Ga 3:22">22</verse-number>But the scripture imprisoned all under sin, in order that the promise could be given by faith<note>Or “through the faithfulness of Jesus Christ”</note> in Jesus Christ to those who believe. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ga 3:23">23</verse-number>But before faith came, we were detained under the law, imprisoned until the coming faith was revealed. <verse-number id="Ga 3:24">24</verse-number>So then, the law became our guardian until Christ, in order that we could be justified by faith. <verse-number id="Ga 3:25">25</verse-number>But <supplied>after</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>after</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“has come”) which is understood as temporal</note> faith has come, we are no longer under a guardian. <verse-number id="Ga 3:26">26</verse-number>For you are all sons of God through faith in Christ Jesus,<note>Or “For in Christ Jesus you are all sons of God through faith”</note> <verse-number id="Ga 3:27">27</verse-number>for as many <supplied>of you</supplied> as were baptized into Christ have put on Christ. <verse-number id="Ga 3:28">28</verse-number>There is neither Jew nor Greek, there is neither slave nor free, there is neither male and female, for you are all one in Christ Jesus. <verse-number id="Ga 3:29">29</verse-number>And if you <supplied>are</supplied> Christ’s, then you are descendants of Abraham, heirs according to the promise. </p>
		</chapter>