<chapter id="Ga 4">
			<pericope>No Longer Slaves But Sons and Heirs</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ga 4:1">1</verse-number> Now I say, for as long a time <supplied>as</supplied> the heir is a child, <supplied>he is</supplied> no different from a slave, <supplied>although he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>although</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“is”) which is understood as concessive</note> is master of everything, <verse-number id="Ga 4:2">2</verse-number>but he is under guardians and managers until the time set by <supplied>his</supplied> father. <verse-number id="Ga 4:3">3</verse-number>So also we, when we were children, we were enslaved under the elemental spirits of the world. <verse-number id="Ga 4:4">4</verse-number>But when the fullness of time came, God sent out his Son, born of a woman, born under the law, <verse-number id="Ga 4:5">5</verse-number>in order that he might redeem those under the law, in order that we might receive the adoption. <verse-number id="Ga 4:6">6</verse-number>And because you are sons, God sent out the Spirit of his Son into our hearts, crying out, “Abba!<note>“Abba” is Aramaic for “father”</note> (Father!),” <verse-number id="Ga 4:7">7</verse-number>so that you are no longer a slave but a son, and if a son, also an heir through God. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Do Not Be Enslaved Again</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ga 4:8">8</verse-number>But at that time <supplied>when you</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>when</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“know”) which is understood as temporal</note> did not know God, you were enslaved to the things which by nature are not gods. <verse-number id="Ga 4:9">9</verse-number>But now, <supplied>because you</supplied> have come to know God, or rather have come to be known by God, how can you turn back again to the weak and miserable elemental spirits? Do you want to be enslaved to them<note>Literally “to whom”</note> all over again? <verse-number id="Ga 4:10">10</verse-number>You carefully observe days and months and seasons and years. <verse-number id="Ga 4:11">11</verse-number>I am afraid <supplied>for</supplied> you, lest perhaps I have labored for you in vain! <verse-number id="Ga 4:12">12</verse-number>I ask you, brothers, become like me, because I also <supplied>have become</supplied> like you. You have done me no <supplied>wrong</supplied>! </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Paul’s Personal Appeal</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ga 4:13">13</verse-number>But you know that because of an illness of the flesh I proclaimed the gospel to you the first time. <verse-number id="Ga 4:14">14</verse-number>And you did not despise or disdain <supplied>what was</supplied> a trial for you in my flesh, but you welcomed me like an angel of God, like Christ Jesus. <verse-number id="Ga 4:15">15</verse-number>So where <supplied>is</supplied> your blessing? For I testify to you that, if possible, you would have torn out your eyes <supplied>and</supplied> given <supplied>them</supplied> to me! <verse-number id="Ga 4:16">16</verse-number>So then, have I become your enemy <supplied>by</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>by</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“being truthful”) which is understood as means</note> being truthful to you? <verse-number id="Ga 4:17">17</verse-number>They zealously seek you, not commendably, but they want to exclude you, in order that you may seek them <supplied>zealously</supplied>. <verse-number id="Ga 4:18">18</verse-number>But <supplied>it is</supplied> good to be sought zealously in good at all times, and not only when I am present with you. <verse-number id="Ga 4:19">19</verse-number>My children, for whom I am having birth pains again, until Christ is formed in you! <verse-number id="Ga 4:20">20</verse-number>But I could wish to be present with you now, and to change my tone because I am perplexed about you. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Hagar and Sarah Represent Two Covenants</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ga 4:21">21</verse-number>Tell me, <supplied>you</supplied> who are wanting to be under the law, do you not understand<note>Literally “hear”</note> the law? <verse-number id="Ga 4:22">22</verse-number>For it is written that Abraham had two sons, one by the female slave and one by the free woman. <verse-number id="Ga 4:23">23</verse-number>But the one by the female slave was born according to human descent, and the one by the free woman through the promise, <verse-number id="Ga 4:24">24</verse-number>which <supplied>things</supplied> are spoken allegorically, for these <supplied>women</supplied> are two covenants, one from Mount Sinai, bearing <supplied>children</supplied> for slavery, who is Hagar. <verse-number id="Ga 4:25">25</verse-number>Now Hagar is Mount Sinai in Arabia, and corresponds to the present Jerusalem, for she is a slave with her children. <verse-number id="Ga 4:26">26</verse-number>But the Jerusalem above is free, which is our mother. <verse-number id="Ga 4:27">27</verse-number>For it is written, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Rejoice, O barren woman, who does not give birth to <supplied>children</supplied>; </li1>
				<li2>burst out and shout, <supplied>you</supplied> who do not have birth pains, </li2>
				<li1>because many <supplied>are</supplied> the children of the desolate <supplied>woman</supplied>, </li1>
				<li2>even more than <supplied>those of</supplied> the one who has a husband.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Is 54:1">Isa 54:1</cite></note> </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Ga 4:28">28</verse-number>But you, brothers, are children of the promise, just as Isaac. <verse-number id="Ga 4:29">29</verse-number>But just as at that time the <supplied>child</supplied> born according to human descent persecuted the <supplied>child born</supplied> according to the Spirit, so also now. <verse-number id="Ga 4:30">30</verse-number>But what does the scripture say? “Drive out the female slave and her son, for the son of the female slave will never inherit with the son”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Ge 21:10">Gen 21:10, </cite>which does not include the words “of the free woman”</note> of the free woman. <verse-number id="Ga 4:31">31</verse-number>Therefore, brothers, we are not children of the female slave but of the free woman. </p>
		</chapter>