<chapter id="Ga 5">
			<pericope>Live in Freedom and Love One Another</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ga 5:1">1</verse-number> For freedom Christ has set us free. Stand firm, therefore, and do not be subject again to a yoke of slavery. <verse-number id="Ga 5:2">2</verse-number>Look! I, Paul, tell you that if you become circumcised, Christ will profit you nothing! <verse-number id="Ga 5:3">3</verse-number>And again I testify to every man who becomes circumcised, that he is under obligation to keep the whole law. <verse-number id="Ga 5:4">4</verse-number>You are estranged from Christ, <supplied>you</supplied> who are attempting to be justified<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The present tense has been translated as conative here (“are attempting”)</note> by the law; you have fallen from grace. <verse-number id="Ga 5:5">5</verse-number>For through the Spirit by faith we eagerly await the hope of righteousness. <verse-number id="Ga 5:6">6</verse-number>For in Christ Jesus neither circumcision counts for anything nor uncircumcision, but faith working through love. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ga 5:7">7</verse-number>You were running well. Who hindered you from obeying the truth? <verse-number id="Ga 5:8">8</verse-number>This persuasion <supplied>is</supplied> not from the one who calls you! <verse-number id="Ga 5:9">9</verse-number>A little leaven leavens the whole batch of dough. <verse-number id="Ga 5:10">10</verse-number>I have confidence in you in the Lord that you will think nothing different, but the one who is confusing you <idiom-start/>will pay the penalty<idiom-end/><note>Literally “will bear the <supplied>= his</supplied> condemnation”</note>, whoever he may be. <verse-number id="Ga 5:11">11</verse-number>Now, brothers, if I am still preaching circumcision, why am I still being persecuted? In that case the stumbling block of the cross has been abolished. <verse-number id="Ga 5:12">12</verse-number>I wish that the ones who are disturbing you would also <idiom-start/>castrate themselves<idiom-end/><note>Literally “cut themselves off”</note>! </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ga 5:13">13</verse-number>For you were called to freedom, brothers. Only do not let your freedom <supplied>become</supplied> an opportunity for the flesh, but through love serve one another. <verse-number id="Ga 5:14">14</verse-number>For the whole law is fulfilled in one statement, namely, “You shall love your neighbor as yourself.”<note>A quotation from <cite title="BibleLEB2: Le 19:18">Lev 19:18</cite></note> <verse-number id="Ga 5:15">15</verse-number>But if you bite and devour one another, watch out <supplied>that</supplied> you are not consumed by one another. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Live by the Spirit and Reject the Deeds of the Flesh</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ga 5:16">16</verse-number>But I say, live by the Spirit, and you will never carry out the desire of the flesh. <verse-number id="Ga 5:17">17</verse-number>For the flesh desires against the Spirit, and the Spirit against the flesh, for these are in opposition to one another, so that whatever you want, you may not do these <supplied>things</supplied>. <verse-number id="Ga 5:18">18</verse-number>But if you are led by the Spirit, you are not under the law. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ga 5:19">19</verse-number>Now the deeds of the flesh are evident, which are sexual immorality, impurity, licentiousness, <verse-number id="Ga 5:20">20</verse-number>idolatry, sorcery, enmity, strife, jealousy, outbursts of anger, selfish ambition, dissension, factions, <verse-number id="Ga 5:21">21</verse-number>envy, drunkenness, carousing, and things like these, <supplied>things</supplied> which I am telling you <supplied>in advance</supplied>, just as I said before, that the ones who practice such things will not inherit the kingdom of God. <verse-number id="Ga 5:22">22</verse-number>But the fruit of the Spirit is love, joy, peace, patience, kindness, goodness, faithfulness, <verse-number id="Ga 5:23">23</verse-number>gentleness, self control. Against such things <supplied>there</supplied> is no law. <verse-number id="Ga 5:24">24</verse-number>Now those <idiom-start/>who belong to Christ<idiom-end/><note>Literally “of Christ”</note><note>Some manuscripts have “Christ Jesus”</note> have crucified the flesh together with its feelings and its desires. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Ga 5:25">25</verse-number>If we live by the Spirit, we must also follow the Spirit. <verse-number id="Ga 5:26">26</verse-number>We must not become conceited, provoking one another, envying one another. </p>
		</chapter>