<chapter id="Ga 6">
			<pericope>Carry One Another’s Burdens</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ga 6:1">1</verse-number> Brothers, even if a person is caught in some trespass, you <supplied>who are</supplied> spiritual restore such a person in a spirit of humility, looking out for yourself, lest you also be tempted. <verse-number id="Ga 6:2">2</verse-number>Carry the burdens of one another, and so fulfill the law of Christ. <verse-number id="Ga 6:3">3</verse-number>For if anyone thinks he is something <supplied>although he</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>although</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“is”) which is understood as concessive</note> is nothing, he is deceiving himself. <verse-number id="Ga 6:4">4</verse-number>But let each one examine his own work, and then he will have a reason for boasting in himself alone, and not in someone else. <verse-number id="Ga 6:5">5</verse-number>For each one will carry his own burden. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Do Good to All People</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ga 6:6">6</verse-number>Now the one who is taught the word must share in all good <supplied>things</supplied> with the one who teaches. <verse-number id="Ga 6:7">7</verse-number>Do not be deceived: God is not to be mocked, for whatever a person sows, this he will also reap, <verse-number id="Ga 6:8">8</verse-number>because the one who sows to his own flesh will reap corruption from the flesh, but the one who sows to the Spirit will reap eternal life from the Spirit. <verse-number id="Ga 6:9">9</verse-number>And let us not grow weary in doing good, for at the proper time we will reap, <supplied>if we</supplied><note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*Here “<supplied>if</supplied>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“give up”) which is understood as conditional</note> do not give up. <verse-number id="Ga 6:10">10</verse-number>So then, as we have opportunity, let us do good to all <supplied>people</supplied>, and especially to those who belong to the household of faith. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>A Final Warning</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ga 6:11">11</verse-number>See with what large letters I am writing to you with my <supplied>own</supplied> hand. <verse-number id="Ga 6:12">12</verse-number>As many as are wanting to make a good showing in the flesh, these are attempting to compel<note tag="NOT_FOR_PRINT">﻿*The present tense has been translated as conative here (“are attempting”)</note> you to be circumcised, only so that they will not be persecuted for the cross of Christ. <verse-number id="Ga 6:13">13</verse-number>For not even those who are circumcised observe the law themselves, but they want you to be circumcised in order that they may boast in your flesh. <verse-number id="Ga 6:14">14</verse-number>But <supplied>as</supplied> for me, may it never be <supplied>that I</supplied> boast, except in the cross of our Lord Jesus Christ, through whom the world has been crucified to me, and I to the world. <verse-number id="Ga 6:15">15</verse-number>For neither is circumcision anything nor uncircumcision, but a new creation. <verse-number id="Ga 6:16">16</verse-number>And all those who follow this rule, peace and mercy <supplied>be</supplied> on them and on the Israel of God. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Conclusion and Benediction</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Ga 6:17">17</verse-number>Finally, let no one cause me trouble, for I carry on my body the marks of Jesus. <verse-number id="Ga 6:18">18</verse-number>The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ <supplied>be</supplied> with your spirit, brothers. Amen. </p>
		</chapter>