<chapter id="Nu 1">
			<pericope>God Commands Moses to Take a Census</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 1:1">1</verse-number>Yahweh spoke to Moses in the desert of Sinai, in the tent of assembly, on <supplied>the</supplied> first of the month, in the second year <idiom-start/>after they came out<idiom-end/><note>Literally “of their coming out”</note> of the land of Egypt, saying, <verse-number id="Nu 1:2">2</verse-number>“<idiom-start/>Take a census of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Lift up the head of”</note> the entire community of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> according to their clans and <idiom-start/>their families<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the house of their fathers”</note> according to <supplied>the</supplied> number of names, every male individually <verse-number id="Nu 1:3">3</verse-number>from <idiom-start/>twenty years old<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a son of twenty years”</note> and above, everyone in Israel who <supplied>is able</supplied> to go to war. You and Aaron must muster them<note>Or “count them,” or “summon them,” or “enroll them”</note> for their wars. <verse-number id="Nu 1:4">4</verse-number>A man from each tribe will be with you, each man the head of <idiom-start/>his family<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the house of his father”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 1:5">5</verse-number>And these <supplied>are</supplied> the names of the men who will <idiom-start/>assist you<idiom-end/>:<note>Literally “stand with you”</note> from Reuben, Elizur son of Shedeur; <verse-number id="Nu 1:6">6</verse-number>from Simeon, Shelumiel son of Zurishaddai; <verse-number id="Nu 1:7">7</verse-number>from Judah, Nahshon son of Amminadab; <verse-number id="Nu 1:8">8</verse-number>from Issachar, Nethanel son of Zuar; <verse-number id="Nu 1:9">9</verse-number>from Zebulun, Eliab son of Helon. <verse-number id="Nu 1:10">10</verse-number>From the descendants of Joseph: from Ephraim, Elishama son of Ammihud; from Manasseh, Gamaliel son of Pedahzur. <verse-number id="Nu 1:11">11</verse-number>From Benjamin, Abidan son of Gideoni; <verse-number id="Nu 1:12">12</verse-number>from Dan, Ahiezer son of Ammishaddai; <verse-number id="Nu 1:13">13</verse-number>from Asher, Pagiel son of Ocran; <verse-number id="Nu 1:14">14</verse-number>from Gad, Eliasaph son of Deuel; <verse-number id="Nu 1:15">15</verse-number><supplied>and</supplied> from Naphtali, Ahira son of Enan.” <verse-number id="Nu 1:16">16</verse-number>These <supplied>are</supplied> the ones summoned from the community, the leaders of their ancestors’<note>Or “fathers’ ”</note> tribes; they <supplied>are</supplied> the heads of Israel’s clans. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 1:17">17</verse-number>So Moses and Aaron took these men who had been designated by name, <verse-number id="Nu 1:18">18</verse-number>and they summoned the entire community on <supplied>the</supplied> first day of the second month. And they registered themselves among their clans according to <idiom-start/>their families<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the house of their fathers”</note> according to <supplied>the</supplied> number of names from <idiom-start/>those twenty years old<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a son of twenty years”</note> and above individually, <verse-number id="Nu 1:19">19</verse-number>just as Yahweh commanded Moses. And he counted them in the desert of Sinai. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 1:20">20</verse-number>The descendants of Reuben, the firstborn of Israel, their genealogies according to their clans, according to <idiom-start/>their families<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the house of their fathers”</note> according to <supplied>the</supplied> number of names, every male individually from <idiom-start/>twenty years old<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a son of twenty years”</note> and above, everyone who <supplied>is able</supplied> to go to war: <verse-number id="Nu 1:21">21</verse-number>those who were counted from the tribe of Reuben were forty-six thousand five hundred. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 1:22">22</verse-number>From the descendants of Simeon, their genealogies according to their clans, according to <idiom-start/>their families<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the house of their fathers”</note> those who were counted according to <supplied>the</supplied> number of their names, every individual male from <idiom-start/>twenty years old<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a son of twenty years”</note> and above, everyone who <supplied>is able</supplied> to go to war: <verse-number id="Nu 1:23">23</verse-number>those who were counted from the tribe of Simeon were fifty-nine thousand three hundred. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 1:24">24</verse-number>From the descendants of Gad, their genealogies according to their clans, according to <idiom-start/>their families<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the house of their fathers”</note> according to <supplied>the</supplied> number of names, from <idiom-start/>those twenty years old<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a son of twenty years”</note> and above, everyone who <supplied>is able</supplied> to go to war: <verse-number id="Nu 1:25">25</verse-number>those who were counted from the tribe of Gad were forty-five thousand six hundred and fifty. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 1:26">26</verse-number>From the descendants of Judah, their genealogies according to their clans, according to <idiom-start/>their families<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the house of their fathers”</note> according to <supplied>the</supplied> number of names, from <idiom-start/>those twenty years old<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a son of twenty years”</note> and above, everyone who <supplied>is able</supplied> to go to war: <verse-number id="Nu 1:27">27</verse-number>those who were counted from the tribe of Judah were seventy-four thousand six hundred. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 1:28">28</verse-number>From the descendants of Issachar, their genealogies according to their clans, according to <idiom-start/>their families<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the house of their fathers”</note> according to <supplied>the</supplied> number of names, from <idiom-start/>those twenty years old<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a son of twenty years”</note> and above, everyone who <supplied>is able</supplied> to go to war: <verse-number id="Nu 1:29">29</verse-number>those who were counted from the tribe of Issachar were fifty-four thousand four hundred. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 1:30">30</verse-number>From the descendants of Zebulun, their genealogies according to their clans, according to <idiom-start/>their families<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the house of their fathers”</note> according to <supplied>the</supplied> number of names, from <idiom-start/>those twenty years old<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a son of twenty years”</note> and above, everyone who <supplied>is able</supplied> to go to war: <verse-number id="Nu 1:31">31</verse-number>those who were counted from the tribe of Zebulun were fifty-seven thousand four hundred. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 1:32">32</verse-number>From the descendants of Joseph: from the descendants of Ephraim, their genealogies according to their clans, according to <idiom-start/>their families<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the house of their fathers”</note> according to <supplied>the</supplied> number of names, from <idiom-start/>those twenty years old<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a son of twenty years”</note> and above, everyone who <supplied>is able</supplied> to go to war: <verse-number id="Nu 1:33">33</verse-number>those who were counted from the tribe of Ephraim were forty thousand five hundred. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 1:34">34</verse-number>From the descendants of Manasseh, their genealogies according to their clans, according to <idiom-start/>their families<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the house of their fathers”</note> according to <supplied>the</supplied> number of names, from <idiom-start/>those twenty years old<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a son of twenty years”</note> and above, everyone who <supplied>is able</supplied> to go to war: <verse-number id="Nu 1:35">35</verse-number>those who were counted from the tribe of Manasseh were thirty-two thousand two hundred. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 1:36">36</verse-number>From the descendants of Benjamin, their genealogies according to their clans, according to <idiom-start/>their families<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the house of their fathers”</note> according to <supplied>the</supplied> number of names, from <idiom-start/>those twenty years old<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a son of twenty years”</note> and above, everyone who <supplied>is able</supplied> to go to war: <verse-number id="Nu 1:37">37</verse-number>those who were counted from the tribe of Benjamin were thirty-five thousand four hundred. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 1:38">38</verse-number>From the descendants of Dan, their genealogies according to their clans, according to <idiom-start/>their families<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the house of their fathers”</note> according to <supplied>the</supplied> number of names, from <idiom-start/>those twenty years old<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a son of twenty years”</note> and above, everyone who <supplied>is able</supplied> to go to war: <verse-number id="Nu 1:39">39</verse-number>those who were counted from the tribe of Dan were sixty-two thousand seven hundred. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 1:40">40</verse-number>From the descendants of Asher, their genealogies according to their clans, according to <idiom-start/>their families<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the house of their fathers”</note> according to <supplied>the</supplied> number of names, from <idiom-start/>those twenty years old<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a son of twenty years”</note> and above, everyone who <supplied>is able</supplied> to go to war: <verse-number id="Nu 1:41">41</verse-number>those who were counted from the tribe of Asher were forty-one thousand five hundred. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 1:42">42</verse-number>From the descendants of Naphtali, their genealogies according to their clans, according to <idiom-start/>their families<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “their fathers”</note> according to <supplied>the</supplied> number of names, from <idiom-start/>those twenty years old<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a son of twenty years”</note> and above, everyone who <supplied>is able</supplied> to go to war: <verse-number id="Nu 1:43">43</verse-number>those who were counted from the tribe of Naphtali were fifty-three thousand four hundred. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 1:44">44</verse-number>These <supplied>are</supplied> the ones counted whom Moses and Aaron mustered,<note>Or “counted,” or “summoned,” or “enrolled”</note> with the twelve leaders of Israel, each one from <idiom-start/>his family<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the house of his fathers”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 1:45">45</verse-number>So all those who were counted from the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> according to <idiom-start/>their families<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the house of their fathers”</note> from <idiom-start/>those twenty years old<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a son of twenty years”</note> and above, everyone in Israel who <supplied>is able</supplied> to go to war. <verse-number id="Nu 1:46">46</verse-number>All of the ones counted were six hundred and three thousand, five hundred and fifty. <verse-number id="Nu 1:47">47</verse-number>The Levites from their ancestors’<note>Or “fathers’ ”</note> tribe were not mustered<note>Or “counted,” or “summoned,” or “enrolled”</note> in their midst. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 1:48">48</verse-number>And Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Nu 1:49">49</verse-number>“You will not muster<note>Or “count,” or “summon,” or “enroll”</note> the tribe of Levi, and you will not <idiom-start/>take a census of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Lift up the head of”</note> them in the midst of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 1:50">50</verse-number>You will <idiom-start/>appoint<idiom-end/><note>Or “count,” or “summon,” or “enroll”</note> them over the tabernacle of the testimony,<note>Other modern translations read “tabernacle of the covenant”</note> over all its vessels, and over all that belongs to it. They will carry the tabernacle and all its vessels, and they will care for it; and they will camp around the tabernacle. <verse-number id="Nu 1:51">51</verse-number>And when the tabernacle is set out, the Levites will <idiom-start/>take it down<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “lower it”</note> and when encamping the tabernacle the Levites will set it up; the stranger<note>Or “outsider”</note> that approaches <supplied>it</supplied> will be put to death. <verse-number id="Nu 1:52">52</verse-number>The <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> will encamp, each in their own camp, and each by their<note>Hebrew “his” or “its”</note> own banner according to their divisions. <verse-number id="Nu 1:53">53</verse-number>But the Levites will encamp around the tabernacle of the testimony,<note>Other modern translations read “tabernacle of the covenant”</note> and there will not be wrath on the community of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and the Levites will keep the requirements of the tabernacle of the testimony.”<note>Other modern translations read “tabernacle of the covenant”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 1:54">54</verse-number>And the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> did thus; they did everything that Yahweh commanded Moses. </p>
		</chapter>