<chapter id="Nu 2">
			<pericope>The Arrangement of the Camps</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 2:1">1</verse-number>Yahweh spoke to Moses and Aaron, saying, <verse-number id="Nu 2:2">2</verse-number>“The <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> will encamp each with his standard, with a banner according to <idiom-start/>their families<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “the house of their fathers”</note> they will encamp around the tent of assembly. <verse-number id="Nu 2:3">3</verse-number>The ones who encamp on the eastern side, toward the sunrise, <supplied>will be</supplied> of the standard of the camp of Judah according to their divisions; and the leader of the descendants of Judah <supplied>will be</supplied> Nahshon son of Amminadab, <verse-number id="Nu 2:4">4</verse-number>and his division and <idiom-start/>the ones counted<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the ones counted of them,” or “the ones mustered of them”</note> <supplied>are</supplied> seventy-four thousand six hundred. <verse-number id="Nu 2:5">5</verse-number>And the ones who encamp next to him <supplied>will be</supplied> the tribe of Issachar. And the leader of the descendants of Issachar <supplied>will be</supplied> Nethanel son of Zuar, <verse-number id="Nu 2:6">6</verse-number>and his division <supplied>are</supplied> fifty-four thousand four hundred. <verse-number id="Nu 2:7">7</verse-number>For the tribe of Zebulun: the leader of the descendants of Zebulun <supplied>will be</supplied> Eliab son of Helon, <verse-number id="Nu 2:8">8</verse-number>and his division and the <idiom-start/>ones counted<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the ones counted of him,” or “the ones mustered of him”</note> <supplied>are</supplied> fifty-seven thousand four hundred. <verse-number id="Nu 2:9">9</verse-number>All those counted from the camp of Judah <supplied>are</supplied> one hundred and eighty-six thousand four hundred. They will set out first according to their divisions. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 2:10">10</verse-number>“The standard of the camp of Reuben <supplied>will be</supplied> to the south according to their divisions. The leader of the descendants <supplied>will be</supplied> Elizur son of Shedeur. <verse-number id="Nu 2:11">11</verse-number>And his division and the <idiom-start/>ones counted<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the ones counted of him,” or “the ones mustered of him”</note> <supplied>are</supplied> forty-six thousand five hundred. <verse-number id="Nu 2:12">12</verse-number>Those encamped next to him <supplied>will be</supplied> the tribe of Simeon. The leader of the descendants of Simeon <supplied>will be</supplied> Shelumiel son of Zurishaddai. <verse-number id="Nu 2:13">13</verse-number>And his division and the <idiom-start/>ones counted<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the ones counted of them,” or “the ones mustered of them”</note> <supplied>are</supplied> fifty-nine thousand three hundred. <verse-number id="Nu 2:14">14</verse-number>For the tribe of Gad: the leader of the descendants of Gad <supplied>will be</supplied> Eliasaph son of Reuel. <verse-number id="Nu 2:15">15</verse-number>And his division and the <idiom-start/>ones counted<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the ones counted of them,” or “the ones mustered of them”</note> <supplied>are</supplied> forty-five thousand six hundred and fifty. <verse-number id="Nu 2:16">16</verse-number>All <idiom-start/>those counted<idiom-end/><note>Or “those mustered”</note> from the camp of Reuben <supplied>are</supplied> one hundred and fifty-one thousand four hundred and fifty. They will set out second according to their divisions. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 2:17">17</verse-number>“The tent of assembly the camp of the Levites will set out in the midst of the camps; they will set out just as they encamped, <idiom-start/>each according to their standards<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “each man on his hand according to their standards”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 2:18">18</verse-number>“The standard of the camp of Ephraim according to their divisions <supplied>will be</supplied> to the west. The leader of the descendants of Ephraim <supplied>will be</supplied> Elishama son of Ammihud. <verse-number id="Nu 2:19">19</verse-number>And his division and the <idiom-start/>ones counted<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the ones counted of them,” or “the ones mustered of them”</note> <supplied>are</supplied> forty thousand five hundred. <verse-number id="Nu 2:20">20</verse-number>The tribe of Manasseh <supplied>will be</supplied> next to him. The leader of the descendants of the tribe of Manasseh <supplied>will be</supplied> Camaliel son of Pedahzur. <verse-number id="Nu 2:21">21</verse-number>And his division and the <idiom-start/>ones counted<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the ones counted of them,” or “the ones mustered of them”</note> <supplied>are</supplied> thirty-two thousand two hundred. <verse-number id="Nu 2:22">22</verse-number>For the tribe of Benjamin: the leader of the descendants of Benjamin <supplied>will be</supplied> Abidan son of Gideoni. <verse-number id="Nu 2:23">23</verse-number>And his division and the <idiom-start/>ones counted<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the ones counted of them,” or “the ones mustered of them”</note> <supplied>are</supplied> thirty-five thousand four hundred. <verse-number id="Nu 2:24">24</verse-number>All <idiom-start/>those counted<idiom-end/><note>Or “those mustered”</note> from the camp of Ephraim <supplied>are</supplied> one hundred and eighty thousand one hundred. They will set out third according to their divisions. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 2:25">25</verse-number>“The standard of the camp of Dan according to their divisions <supplied>will be</supplied> to the west. The leader of the descendants of Dan <supplied>will be</supplied> Ahiezer son of Ammishaddai. <verse-number id="Nu 2:26">26</verse-number>And his division and the <idiom-start/>ones counted<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the ones counted of them,” or “the ones mustered of them”</note> <supplied>are</supplied> sixty-two thousand seven hundred. <verse-number id="Nu 2:27">27</verse-number>Those encamped next to him <supplied>will be</supplied> the tribe of Asher. The leader of the descendants of Asher <supplied>will be</supplied> Pagiel son of Ocran. <verse-number id="Nu 2:28">28</verse-number>And his division and the <idiom-start/>ones counted<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the ones counted of them,” or “the ones mustered of them”</note> <supplied>are</supplied> forty-one thousand five hundred. <verse-number id="Nu 2:29">29</verse-number>For the tribe of Naphtali: the leader of the descendants of Naphtali <supplied>will be</supplied> Ahira son of Enan. <verse-number id="Nu 2:30">30</verse-number>And his division and the <idiom-start/>ones counted<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the ones counted of them,” or “the ones mustered of them”</note> <supplied>are</supplied> fifty-three thousand four hundred. <verse-number id="Nu 2:31">31</verse-number>All the <idiom-start/>ones counted<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the ones counted of them,” or “the ones mustered of them”</note> from the camp of Dan <supplied>are</supplied> one hundred and fifty-seven thousand six hundred. They will set out <idiom-start/>last<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from behind”</note> according to their divisions.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 2:32">32</verse-number>These <supplied>were</supplied> the ones counted of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> according to <idiom-start/>their families<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “the house of their fathers”</note> all those counted from the camps according to their divisions <supplied>were</supplied> six hundred and three thousand five hundred. <verse-number id="Nu 2:33">33</verse-number>The Levites were not counted in the midst of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> just as Yahweh commanded Moses. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 2:34">34</verse-number>And the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> did everything that Yahweh commanded Moses. They encamped according to their standards, and they<note>Hebrew “each one,” or “each man”</note> set out each one according to their clans<note>Hebrew “his clans”</note> among <idiom-start/>their families<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the house of his fathers”</note> </p>
		</chapter>