<chapter id="Nu 3">
			<pericope>Aaron’s Sons</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 3:1">1</verse-number>These <supplied>are</supplied> the genealogies of Aaron and Moses <idiom-start/>at the time<idiom-end/><note>Literally “on a day”</note> when Yahweh spoke to Moses on Mount Sinai. <verse-number id="Nu 3:2">2</verse-number>These <supplied>are</supplied> the names of the descendants of Aaron: Nadab the firstborn, Abihu, Eleazar, and Ithamar. <verse-number id="Nu 3:3">3</verse-number>These <supplied>are</supplied> the names of the descendants of Aaron, the priests, the anointed ones whom <idiom-start/>he consecrated as priests<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “he filled their hands to serve as a priest”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 3:4">4</verse-number>Nadab and Abihu died <idiom-start/>before Yahweh<idiom-end/><note>Literally “before the face of Yahweh”</note> when they presented a strange fire <idiom-start/>before Yahweh<idiom-end/><note>Literally “before the face of Yahweh”</note> in the desert of Sinai, and <idiom-start/>they had no children<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sons were not for them”</note> Eleazar and Ithamar served as priest during the presence of Aaron their father. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 3:5">5</verse-number>Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Nu 3:6">6</verse-number>“Bring near the tribe of Levi, and <idiom-start/>set the tribe<idiom-end/><note>Literally “cause it to stand”</note> <idiom-start/>before Aaron<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the presence of Aaron”</note> the priest, and they will minister to him. <verse-number id="Nu 3:7">7</verse-number>They shall observe his duties and the duties of the entire community before the tent of assembly, to do the work of the tabernacle. <verse-number id="Nu 3:8">8</verse-number>And they will keep all the vessels of the tent of assembly and the responsibilities of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> to do the work<note>Or “service”</note> of the tabernacle. <verse-number id="Nu 3:9">9</verse-number>You will give the Levites to Aaron and to his descendants; they <supplied>are</supplied> surely assigned to him from among the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 3:10">10</verse-number>But you will count Aaron and his descendants; they will keep their priesthood, and the stranger<note>Or “outsider”</note> who approaches will be put to death.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 3:11">11</verse-number>Yahweh spoke to Moses saying, <verse-number id="Nu 3:12">12</verse-number>“I <supplied>myself</supplied> receive the Levites from the midst of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> in the place of all <supplied>the</supplied> firstborn of <supplied>the</supplied> offspring of the womb from the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> The Levites will be mine <verse-number id="Nu 3:13">13</verse-number>because all <supplied>the</supplied> firstborn <supplied>are</supplied> mine; on the day of my killing all <supplied>the</supplied> firstborn in the land of Egypt, I consecrated for myself all <supplied>the</supplied> firstborn in Israel, <idiom-start/>both humankind and animal<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “from humankind to animal”</note> they will be mine. I am Yahweh.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 3:14">14</verse-number>Yahweh spoke to Moses in the desert of Sinai, saying, <verse-number id="Nu 3:15">15</verse-number>“Muster<note>Or “count,” or “summon,” or “enroll”</note> the descendants of Levi according to <idiom-start/>their families<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the house of their fathers”</note> according to their clans. You will count every male from <idiom-start/>one month<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the son of a month”</note> and above.” <verse-number id="Nu 3:16">16</verse-number>So Moses mustered<note>Or “counted,” or “summoned,” or “enrolled”</note> them according to the <idiom-start/>command of Yahweh<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “mouth of Yahweh”</note> just as he commanded. <verse-number id="Nu 3:17">17</verse-number>These were the sons of Levi according to their names: Gershon, Kohath, and Merari. <verse-number id="Nu 3:18">18</verse-number>And these <supplied>are</supplied> the names of the sons of Gershon according to their clans: Libni and Shimei. <verse-number id="Nu 3:19">19</verse-number>And the sons of Kohath according to their clans: Amram, Izhar, Hebron, and Uzziel. <verse-number id="Nu 3:20">20</verse-number>The sons of Merari according to their tribes: Mahli and Mushi. These <supplied>are</supplied> the clans of the Levites according to <idiom-start/>their families<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the house of their fathers”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 3:21">21</verse-number><idiom-start/>To Gershon belonged<idiom-end/><note>Literally “To Gershon was”</note> the clan of the Libnites and the clan of the Shimeites; these <supplied>are</supplied> the clans of the Gershonites. <verse-number id="Nu 3:22">22</verse-number>The <idiom-start/>ones counted<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the ones counted of them,” or “the ones mustered of them”</note> according to the number of every male from <idiom-start/>one month<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the son of a month and above”</note> and above <supplied>were</supplied> seven thousand five hundred. <verse-number id="Nu 3:23">23</verse-number>The clans of the Gershonites will camp behind the tabernacle to the west, <verse-number id="Nu 3:24">24</verse-number>and the leader of <idiom-start/>the family<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<supplied>the</supplied> house of <supplied>his</supplied> father”</note> of the Gershonites is Eliasaph son of Lael. <verse-number id="Nu 3:25">25</verse-number>And the responsibility of the descendants of Gershon in the tent of assembly <supplied>is</supplied> the tabernacle, and the tent covering it and the curtain of the doorway of the tent of the assembly, <verse-number id="Nu 3:26">26</verse-number>and the hangings of the courtyard and the curtain of the doorway of the courtyard that <supplied>is</supplied> around the tabernacle and the altar, and its ten cords, all of its use. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 3:27">27</verse-number><idiom-start/>To Kohath belonged<idiom-end/><note>Literally “For Kohath <supplied>was</supplied>”</note> the clan of Amramites,<note>Hebrew “Amramite”</note> the clan of the Izharites,<note>Hebrew “Izharite”</note> the clan of the Hebronites,<note>Hebrew “Hebronite”</note> and the clan <supplied>of</supplied> the Uzzielites;<note>Hebrew “Uzzielite”</note> these <supplied>were</supplied> the clans of the Kohathites.<note>Hebrew “Kohathite”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 3:28">28</verse-number>According to <supplied>the</supplied> number of every male from <idiom-start/>one month<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the son of a month”</note> and above <supplied>there were</supplied> eight thousand six hundred keeping the responsibility of the sanctuary. <verse-number id="Nu 3:29">29</verse-number>The clan of the descendants of Kohath will encamp on the side of the tabernacle to the south. <verse-number id="Nu 3:30">30</verse-number>The leader of <idiom-start/>his family<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the house of <supplied>his</supplied> father”</note> according to the clans of the Kohathites<note>Hebrew “Kohathite”</note> <supplied>is</supplied> Elizaphan the son of Uzziel. <verse-number id="Nu 3:31">31</verse-number>Their responsibility <supplied>was</supplied> the ark, the table, the lampstand, the altar, and the vessels of the sanctuary, with which they ministered, and the curtain, and all of its use. <verse-number id="Nu 3:32">32</verse-number>The <idiom-start/>chief of the leaders<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the leader of leaders”</note> of the Levites<note>Hebrew “Levite”</note> was Eleazar son of Aaron the priest <supplied>who had</supplied> oversight of those keeping the responsibility of the sanctuary. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 3:33">33</verse-number><idiom-start/>To Merari belonged<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for Merari <supplied>was</supplied>”</note> the clan of Mahlites<note>Hebrew “Mahlite”</note> and the clan of the Mushites:<note>Hebrew “Mushite”</note> these <supplied>are</supplied> the clans of Merari. <verse-number id="Nu 3:34">34</verse-number>The <idiom-start/>ones counted<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the ones counted of them,” or “the ones mustered of them”</note> according to the number of every male from <idiom-start/>one month<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the son of a month”</note> and above <supplied>were</supplied> six thousand two hundred. <verse-number id="Nu 3:35">35</verse-number><supplied>The</supplied> leader of <idiom-start/>the family<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<supplied>the</supplied> house of <supplied>his</supplied> father”</note> according to the clans of Merari <supplied>is</supplied> Zuriel son of Abihail; they will encamp of the side of the tabernacle to the north. <verse-number id="Nu 3:36">36</verse-number>The responsibility of the sons of Merari <supplied>was</supplied> the supervision of the frames of the tabernacle, its bars, pillars, bases, and all its vessels and all its service, <verse-number id="Nu 3:37">37</verse-number>and the pillars around the courtyard, and their bases, pegs, and cords. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 3:38">38</verse-number>Those encamped before the tabernacle to the east—before the tent of assembly to the east—<supplied>were</supplied> Moses and Aaron and his sons; they will keep the responsibility of the sanctuary <idiom-start/>for the Israelites<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “for the responsibility of the children of Israel”</note> and the stranger<note>Or “outsider”</note> who approaches will be put to death. <verse-number id="Nu 3:39">39</verse-number>All those counted from the Levites whom Moses and Aaron mustered<note>Or “counted,” or “summoned,” or “enrolled”</note> according to <idiom-start/>the word of Yahweh<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the mouth of Yahweh”</note> according to their clans, every male from <idiom-start/>one month<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the son of a month”</note> and above <supplied>were</supplied> twenty-two thousand. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 3:40">40</verse-number>And Yahweh said to Moses, “Muster every firstborn male from the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> from <idiom-start/>one month<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the son of a month”</note> and above and <idiom-start/>count<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and lift up the number of”</note> their names. <verse-number id="Nu 3:41">41</verse-number>And you will receive the Levites for me—I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh—in the place of all <supplied>the</supplied> firstborn among the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and the animals<note>Hebrew “animal”</note> of the Levites in the place of all <supplied>the</supplied> firstborn among the animals<note>Hebrew “animal”</note> among the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 3:42">42</verse-number>So Moses mustered<note>Or “counted” or “summoned” or “enrolled”</note> all the firstborn among the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> just as Yahweh commanded him. <verse-number id="Nu 3:43">43</verse-number>And all <supplied>the</supplied> firstborn males<note>Hebrew “male”</note> among the number of names from <idiom-start/>one month<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the son of a month”</note> and above, the <idiom-start/>ones counted<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the ones counted of them,” or “the ones mustered of them”</note> <supplied>were</supplied> twenty-two thousand two hundred and seventy-three. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 3:44">44</verse-number>Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Nu 3:45">45</verse-number>“Receive the Levites in the place of all <supplied>the</supplied> firstborn among the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and the animals of the Levites in the place of their animals; the Levites will be mine. I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh. <verse-number id="Nu 3:46">46</verse-number>And the ransom of the two hundred and seventy-three of the firstborn of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> who are excessive over the Levites, <verse-number id="Nu 3:47">47</verse-number>you will receive five shekels a person, in the sanctuary shekel; you will collect twenty gerahs<note>Hebrew “gerah”</note> <supplied>per</supplied> shekel. <verse-number id="Nu 3:48">48</verse-number>You will give the money to Aaron, and to his sons the ransom of the ones who are excessive among them.” <verse-number id="Nu 3:49">49</verse-number>And Moses received the money of the redemption from the ones who were excessive from those redeemed of the Levites. <verse-number id="Nu 3:50">50</verse-number>From the firstborn of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> he took the money, one thousand three hundred and sixty-five shekels, in the sanctuary shekel. <verse-number id="Nu 3:51">51</verse-number>And Moses gave the money of the ransom to Aaron and to his sons according to the <idiom-start/>word<idiom-end/><note>Literally “mouth”</note> of Yahweh just as Yahweh commanded Moses. </p>
		</chapter>