<chapter id="Nu 4">
			<pericope>The Census of the Kohathites</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 4:1">1</verse-number>Yahweh spoke to Moses and Aaron, saying, <verse-number id="Nu 4:2">2</verse-number>“<idiom-start/>Take a census<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and lift up the number of”</note> of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Kohath from the midst of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Levi, according to their clans and <idiom-start/>their families<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the house of their fathers”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 4:3">3</verse-number>from <idiom-start/>thirty years old<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a son of thirty years”</note> and above, up to <idiom-start/>fifty years old<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “a son of fifty years”</note> everyone who comes to the service to do the work in the tent of assembly. <verse-number id="Nu 4:4">4</verse-number>This <supplied>is</supplied> the work of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Kohath in the tent of assembly, concerning the holiness of the sanctuary: <verse-number id="Nu 4:5">5</verse-number>When setting out the camp, Aaron and his sons will go and lower the curtain of the covering and cover with it the ark of the testimony.<note>Or “the ark of the covenant”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 4:6">6</verse-number>They will put on it a covering of <idiom-start/>fine leather<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the hide of a sea cow”</note> and they will spread a cloth of perfect blue over it, and they will place its poles. <verse-number id="Nu 4:7">7</verse-number>And over the table of the presence they will spread <supplied>out</supplied> a blue cloth and put on it the plates, dishes, and libation bowls, and the pitchers of the libation; and the bread of continuity will be on it. <verse-number id="Nu 4:8">8</verse-number>They will spread over it a scarlet cloth, and they will cover it with a covering of <idiom-start/>fine leather<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the hide of a sea cow”</note> and they will place its poles. <verse-number id="Nu 4:9">9</verse-number>They will take a blue cloth and cover the lampstand for the light source, its lamps, a pair of its tongs, its small pans, and all the vessels of its oil with which they attend to it. <verse-number id="Nu 4:10">10</verse-number>They will put it and all its vessels inside a covering of <idiom-start/>fine leather<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the hide of a sea cow”</note> and put it on the carrying frame. <verse-number id="Nu 4:11">11</verse-number>Over the altar of gold they will spread a blue cloth, and they will cover it with a covering of <idiom-start/>fine leather<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the hide of a sea cow”</note> and place its poles. <verse-number id="Nu 4:12">12</verse-number>They will take all the vessels of the cultic service with which they serve in the sanctuary and put <supplied>them</supplied> on a blue cloth, and they will cover them with a covering of <idiom-start/>fine leather<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “the hide of a sea cow”</note> and they will put <supplied>them</supplied> on the carrying frame. <verse-number id="Nu 4:13">13</verse-number>They will remove the fat-soaked ashes from the altar and spread a purple cloth over it; <verse-number id="Nu 4:14">14</verse-number>they will put on it all the vessels with which they serve, the fire pans, forks, shovels, and bowls—all the vessels of the altar. They will spread on it a covering of <idiom-start/>fine leather<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “the hide of a sea cow”</note> and they will place its poles. <verse-number id="Nu 4:15">15</verse-number>And when Aaron and his sons have finished covering the sanctuary and all the vessels of the sanctuary when the camp sets out, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Kohath will come after to carry <supplied>these</supplied>, but they must not touch the sanctuary, or they will die. These <supplied>are</supplied> the load of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Kohath in the tent of assembly. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 4:16">16</verse-number>“Eleazar son of Aaron the priest is to supervise the oil of the light source, the incense, <idiom-start/>the regular grain offering<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the grain offering of continuity”</note> the oil of anointment, the supervision of all the tabernacle and all that <supplied>is</supplied> in it, in the sanctuary and in its vessels.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 4:17">17</verse-number>Yahweh spoke to Moses and Aaron, saying, <verse-number id="Nu 4:18">18</verse-number>“You must not cut off the tribe of the clan of the Kohathites<note>Hebrew “Kohathite”</note> from the midst of the Levites. <verse-number id="Nu 4:19">19</verse-number>Do this to them and they will live and not die when they come near the most holy things. Aaron and his sons will go and appoint them, each one to his task and burden. <verse-number id="Nu 4:20">20</verse-number>But they must not go and look <idiom-start/>for a moment<idiom-end/><note>Literally “as devouring”</note> at the holy objects.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 4:21">21</verse-number>Yahweh spoke to Moses and Aaron, saying, <verse-number id="Nu 4:22">22</verse-number>“<idiom-start/>Take a census<idiom-end/><note>Literally “And lift up the number of”</note> of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Gershon also, according to <idiom-start/>their families<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the house of their fathers”</note> and clans, <verse-number id="Nu 4:23">23</verse-number>from <idiom-start/>those twenty years old<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a son of twenty years”</note> and above until <idiom-start/>fifty years old<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “a son of fifty years”</note> you will muster<note>Or “count,” or “summon,” or “enroll”</note> them, all who come to help to do the work of the tent of assembly. <verse-number id="Nu 4:24">24</verse-number>This <supplied>is</supplied> the work of the clans of the Gershonites:<note>Hebrew “Gershonite”</note> to serve and to carry. <verse-number id="Nu 4:25">25</verse-number>They will carry the curtains of the tabernacle and the tent of assembly <supplied>and</supplied> its covering and the covering of <idiom-start/>fine leather<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the hide of a sea cow”</note> which <idiom-start/>is on top of it<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “is above upon it”</note> and the curtain of the doorway of the tent of assembly, <verse-number id="Nu 4:26">26</verse-number>and the curtains of the courtyard, and the covering for the doorway of the gate of the courtyard, which <supplied>is</supplied> all around on the tabernacle and altar, and their cords and all the vessels of their work; and all that is done to them they will do. <verse-number id="Nu 4:27">27</verse-number>And all the work of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of the Gershonites<note>Hebrew “Gershonite”</note> will be at <idiom-start/>the command<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the mouth”</note> of Aaron and his sons, for all they <supplied>are to</supplied> carry and for all their work, and you will appoint to them responsibility for all they <supplied>are to</supplied> carry. <verse-number id="Nu 4:28">28</verse-number>This <supplied>is</supplied> the work of the clan of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of the Gershonites<note>Hebrew “Gershonite”</note> in the tent of assembly, and their responsibility <supplied>lies</supplied> <idiom-start/>under the direction<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the hand”</note> of Ithamar son of Aaron the priest. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 4:29">29</verse-number>“<supplied>For</supplied> the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Merari according to their clans, according to <idiom-start/>their families<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the house of their fathers”</note> you will muster<note>Or “count,” or “summon,” or “enroll”</note> them; <verse-number id="Nu 4:30">30</verse-number>from <idiom-start/>those thirty years old<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a son of thirty years”</note> and above until <idiom-start/>fifty years old<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “a son of fifty years”</note> you will muster<note>Or “count,” or “summon,” or “enroll”</note> them, all who come to do the work of the tent of assembly. <verse-number id="Nu 4:31">31</verse-number>And this <supplied>is</supplied> the responsibility of <idiom-start/>those who are to carry<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “them carrying”</note> all their work in the tent of assembly: the frames of the tabernacle and its bars, pillars, and bases, <verse-number id="Nu 4:32">32</verse-number>and the pillars of the courtyard all around, and their bases, pegs, and cords, with all their vessels and for all their work. You will appoint by name the vessels that they <supplied>are</supplied> responsible to carry. <verse-number id="Nu 4:33">33</verse-number>This <supplied>is</supplied> the work of the clan of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Merari, for all their work in the tent of assembly <idiom-start/>under the direction<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the hand”</note> of Ithamar son of Aaron the priest.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 4:34">34</verse-number>And Moses and Aaron mustered the leaders of the community according to the house of <idiom-start/>their families<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the house of their fathers”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 4:35">35</verse-number>from <idiom-start/>those thirty years old<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a son of thirty years”</note> and above until <idiom-start/>fifty years old<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “a son of fifty years”</note> everyone who comes to the service to work in the tent of assembly, <verse-number id="Nu 4:36">36</verse-number>the <idiom-start/>ones counted<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the ones counted of them,” or “the ones mustered of them”</note> were two thousand seven hundred and fifty. <verse-number id="Nu 4:37">37</verse-number>These <supplied>were</supplied> those counted of the clans of the Kohathites,<note>Hebrew “Kohathite”</note> everyone who served in the tent of assembly whom Moses and Aaron mustered<note>Or “counted,” or “summoned,” or “enrolled”</note> according to <idiom-start/>the command<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the mouth”</note> of Yahweh by the hand of Moses.<note>Or “through Moses”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 4:38">38</verse-number>And the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Gershon counted according to their clans and according to <idiom-start/>their families<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the house of their fathers”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 4:39">39</verse-number>from <idiom-start/>those thirty years old<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a son of thirty years”</note> and above until <idiom-start/>fifty years old<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “a son of fifty years”</note> everyone who comes to the service to work in the tent of assembly; <verse-number id="Nu 4:40">40</verse-number>the <idiom-start/>ones counted<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the ones counted of them,” or “the ones mustered of them”</note> according to their clans, according to <idiom-start/>their families<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the house of their fathers”</note> were two thousand six hundred and thirty. <verse-number id="Nu 4:41">41</verse-number>These <supplied>were</supplied> those counted of the clans of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Gershon, everyone who serves in the tent of assembly whom Moses and Aaron mustered<note>Or “counted,” or “summoned,” or “enrolled”</note> according to <idiom-start/>the command<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the mouth”</note> of Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 4:42">42</verse-number>Those counted of the clans of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Merari according to their clans, according to <idiom-start/>their families<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the house of their fathers”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 4:43">43</verse-number>from <idiom-start/>those thirty years old<idiom-end/><note>Literally “thirty years and above”</note> and above until <idiom-start/>fifty years old<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “a son of fifty years”</note> everyone who comes to the service to work in the tent of assembly, <verse-number id="Nu 4:44">44</verse-number>the <idiom-start/>ones counted<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the ones counted of them,” or “the ones mustered of them”</note> according to their clans, were three thousand two hundred. <verse-number id="Nu 4:45">45</verse-number>These <supplied>were</supplied> those counted of the clans of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Merari, whom Moses and Aaron mustered<note>Or “counted,” or “summoned,” or “enrolled”</note> according to <idiom-start/>the command<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the mouth”</note> of Yahweh by the hand of Moses.<note>Or “through Moses”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 4:46">46</verse-number>All those counted of the Levites whom Moses and Aaron and all the leaders of Israel mustered<note>Or “counted,” or “summoned,” or “enrolled”</note> according to their clans, according to <idiom-start/>their families<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the house of their fathers”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 4:47">47</verse-number>from <idiom-start/>those thirty years old<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a son of thirty years”</note> and above until <idiom-start/>fifty years old<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “a son of fifty years”</note> everyone who comes to the service to do <supplied>the</supplied> work of the service carrying in the tent of assembly, <verse-number id="Nu 4:48">48</verse-number>the <idiom-start/>ones counted<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the ones counted of them,” or “the ones mustered of them”</note> were eighty thousand five hundred and eighty. <verse-number id="Nu 4:49">49</verse-number>According to <idiom-start/>the command<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the mouth”</note> of Yahweh by the hand of Moses<note>Or “through Moses”</note> <idiom-start/>they were mustered<idiom-end/>,<note>Hebrew “he mustered”</note> each man according to his service and according to their<note>Hebrew “his”</note> service and according to their<note>Hebrew “his”</note> burden; and so they were counted by him just as Yahweh commanded Moses. </p>
		</chapter>