<chapter id="Nu 5">
			<pericope>Rules Concerning Those Unclean</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 5:1">1</verse-number>Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Nu 5:2">2</verse-number>“Command the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>:<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> they must send everyone from the camp who is afflicted with a rash,<note>The precise meaning is uncertain; many modern translations suggest “leprosy”</note> everyone with a fluid discharge, and everyone unclean through <supplied>contact with</supplied> a corpse. <verse-number id="Nu 5:3">3</verse-number>You will send away <idiom-start/>both male and female<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “from male until female”</note> you will send them <idiom-start/>outside the camp<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to an outside place of the camp”</note> They must not make unclean their camps where I <supplied>am</supplied> dwelling in their midst.” <verse-number id="Nu 5:4">4</verse-number>So the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> did so. They sent them away <idiom-start/>outside the camp<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “to an outside place of the camp”</note> just as Yahweh spoke to Moses, so did the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Rules of Restitution</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 5:5">5</verse-number>Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Nu 5:6">6</verse-number>“Speak to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>:<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> ‘When a man or woman <idiom-start/>commits<idiom-end/><note>Literally “does”</note> any of the sins of humankind by acting unfaithfully, <supplied>it is</supplied> a sin against Yahweh, and that person will be guilty; <verse-number id="Nu 5:7">7</verse-number>they will confess their sin that they did and will make restitution <supplied>for</supplied> their<note>Hebrew “his”</note> guilt by adding a fifth <idiom-start/>to it<idiom-end/><note>Literally “on top of it”</note> and giving <supplied>it</supplied> <idiom-start/>to whomever was wronged<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “to whomever he was guilty”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 5:8">8</verse-number>But if the man does not have a redeemer to make restitution to him for the reparation, the reparation is to be given to Yahweh for the priest, in addition to the ram of atonement by which atonement is made for him. <verse-number id="Nu 5:9">9</verse-number>And every contribution of all the holy objects of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> that they bring to the priest for him will be his. <verse-number id="Nu 5:10">10</verse-number>The holy objects of a man will be for him;<note>That is, the priest</note> whatever he gives to the priest will be for him.’ ” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Rules Concerning an Unfaithful Wife</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 5:11">11</verse-number>Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Nu 5:12">12</verse-number>“Speak to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and say to them, ‘If any man’s wife goes astray and acts unfaithfully to him, <verse-number id="Nu 5:13">13</verse-number>and a man sleeps with her and ejaculates and it is hidden from the eyes of her husband and she is concealed, although she is defiled, and there is no witness against her and she was not caught, <verse-number id="Nu 5:14">14</verse-number>if a spirit of jealousy comes over him, and he is jealous <supplied>of</supplied> his wife and she is defiled; or if a spirit of jealousy comes over him and he is jealous <supplied>of</supplied> his wife but she is not defiled, <verse-number id="Nu 5:15">15</verse-number>he will bring his wife to the priest. And he will bring her offering for her, one-tenth of an ephah of flour. He will not pour oil on it, and he will not put frankincense on it because <supplied>it is</supplied> a grain offering of jealousy, a grain offering of remembering,<note>Or “memorial”</note> a reminding of guilt. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 5:16">16</verse-number>“ ‘Then the priest will bring her near and present her <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “before the face of”</note> Yahweh; <verse-number id="Nu 5:17">17</verse-number>the priest will take holy waters in a clay vessel, and from the dust that is on the floor of the tabernacle, and the priest will put <supplied>it</supplied> into the waters. <verse-number id="Nu 5:18">18</verse-number>And the priest will present the woman <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “before the face of”</note> Yahweh, and he will uncover the head of the woman; he will then put in her hands the grain offering of the remembering—<supplied>which is</supplied> the grain offering of jealousy—and in the hand of the priest will be the waters of bitterness that brings a curse. <verse-number id="Nu 5:19">19</verse-number>Then the priest will make her swear an oath, and he will say to the woman, “If a man has not slept with you, and if you have not had an impurity affair under your husband, go unpunished from the waters of bitterness that brings this curse. <verse-number id="Nu 5:20">20</verse-number>But if you have had an affair under your husband, and if you are defiled and a man other than your husband had intercourse with you,” <verse-number id="Nu 5:21">21</verse-number>the priest will make the woman swear an oath of the sworn oath of the curse, the priest will say to the woman, “May Yahweh give you a curse and a sworn oath in the midst of your people with Yahweh making<note>Hebrew “giving”</note> your hip fall away<note>Or “waste away”</note> and your stomach swollen; <verse-number id="Nu 5:22">22</verse-number>and these waters that bring a curse will go into your intestines to cause <supplied>your</supplied> womb to swell and to make <supplied>your</supplied> hip fall away.”<note>Or “waste away”</note> And the women will say, “Amen. Amen.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 5:23">23</verse-number>“ ‘And the priests will write these curses on the scroll, and he will wipe <supplied>them</supplied> off into the waters of the bitterness. <verse-number id="Nu 5:24">24</verse-number>He will make the woman drink the waters of the bitterness that brings<note>Hebrew “bring”</note> a curse, and the waters of bitterness that bring a curse will go into her. <verse-number id="Nu 5:25">25</verse-number>The priest will take the grain offering of jealousy from the hand of the woman, and he will wave the grain offering <idiom-start/>before Yahweh<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “before the face of Yahweh”</note> and he will present it to the altar; <verse-number id="Nu 5:26">26</verse-number>the priest will grasp her memorial offering from the grain offering, and he will turn <supplied>it</supplied> into smoke <supplied>on</supplied> the altar, and afterward he will make the woman drink the waters. <verse-number id="Nu 5:27">27</verse-number>When he has made her drink the waters, it will come about, if she has defiled herself and acted unfaithfully to her husband and the waters of bitterness that bring a curse go into her and her stomach swells and her hip falls away,<note>Or “wastes away”</note> the woman will be as a curse in the midst of her people. <verse-number id="Nu 5:28">28</verse-number>And if the woman is not defiled, and she <supplied>is</supplied> pure, she will go unpunished and be able to conceive children. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 5:29">29</verse-number>“ ‘This <supplied>is</supplied> the regulation of jealousy, when a woman has an affair under her husband and she is defiled, <verse-number id="Nu 5:30">30</verse-number>or when a spirit of jealousy comes over a man and he is jealous <supplied>of</supplied> his wife, he will present the woman <idiom-start/>before Yahweh<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “before the face of”</note>and the priest will do to her all of this law. <verse-number id="Nu 5:31">31</verse-number>The man will go unpunished from guilt, and the woman, she will bear her guilt.’ ” </p>
		</chapter>