<chapter id="Nu 6">
			<pericope>Rules Concerning Nazirites</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 6:1">1</verse-number>Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Nu 6:2">2</verse-number>“Speak to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and say to them, ‘When a man or a woman takes a special vow, a vow of a <idiom-start/>Nazirite<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “one separated”</note> to keep separate for Yahweh, <verse-number id="Nu 6:3">3</verse-number>he will abstain from wine and fermented drink; he will not drink wine vinegar or vinegar of fermented drink; he will not drink the fruit juice of grapes or eat fresh or dry grapes. <verse-number id="Nu 6:4">4</verse-number>All the days of his separation<note>That is, “the Nazirite”</note> you will not eat from anything that is made from the grapevine, from sour grapes to the skin <supplied>of grapes</supplied>. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 6:5">5</verse-number>“ ‘All the days of the vow of his separation a razor will not pass over his head. Until fulfilling the days that he separated himself to Yahweh he will be holy and grow long the locks of the hair of his head. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 6:6">6</verse-number>“ ‘All the days of keeping himself separated for Yahweh he will not go to a person who is dead; <verse-number id="Nu 6:7">7</verse-number>for even his father, mother, brother, or sister he will not make himself unclean <idiom-start/>by their death<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “with their dying”</note> because the separation to his God <supplied>is</supplied> on his head. <verse-number id="Nu 6:8">8</verse-number>He will be holy for Yahweh all the days of his separation.<note>That is, “the Nazirite”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 6:9">9</verse-number>“ ‘If someone dies suddenly and makes the head of his separation<note>That is, “the Nazirite”</note> unclean, he will shave off <supplied>the hair of</supplied> his head on the day of his cleansing; on the seventh day he will shave it off. <verse-number id="Nu 6:10">10</verse-number>On the eighth day he will bring two turtledoves or two <idiom-start/>young pigeons<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the sons of doves”</note> to the priest by the doorway of the tent of assembly, <verse-number id="Nu 6:11">11</verse-number>and the priest will offer one for a sin offering and one for a burnt offering, and he will make atonement for him because he sinned concerning the corpse. He will consecrate his head on that day. <verse-number id="Nu 6:12">12</verse-number>He will rededicate to Yahweh the days of his separation<note>That is, “the Nazirite”</note> and bring a ram-lamb <idiom-start/>in its first year<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a son of his year”</note> as a guilt offering. The former days <supplied>of his vow</supplied> will fall away because his separation was defiled. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 6:13">13</verse-number>“ ‘This <supplied>is</supplied> the regulation of the Nazirite for the day of the fulfilling of the days of his separation: one will bring him to the doorway of the tent of the assembly. <verse-number id="Nu 6:14">14</verse-number>He will present his offering to Yahweh, one ram-lamb <idiom-start/>in its first year<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a son of his year”</note> without defect as a burnt offering, and one ewe-lamb <idiom-start/>in its first year<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a daughter of his year”</note> without defect as a sin offering, and one ram without defect as a fellowship offering; <verse-number id="Nu 6:15">15</verse-number>and a basket of unleavened bread, finely milled flour of ring-shaped bread cakes mixed with oil, and wafers of unleavened bread smeared with oil, and their grain offering and their libations. <verse-number id="Nu 6:16">16</verse-number>The priest will present <idiom-start/>before Yahweh<idiom-end/><note>Or “before the face of Yahweh”</note> and offer his sin offering, his burnt offering; <verse-number id="Nu 6:17">17</verse-number>he will offer a ram as a sacrifice of a fellowship offering to Yahweh, in addition to the basket of the unleavened bread; the priest will offer his grain offering and his libation. <verse-number id="Nu 6:18">18</verse-number>The Nazirite will shave off <supplied>the hair of</supplied> <idiom-start/>his consecrated head<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the head of his separation”</note> <supplied>at</supplied> the doorway of the tent of assembly, and he will take the hair of <idiom-start/>his consecrated head<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the head of his separation”</note> and he will put <supplied>it</supplied> on the fire that <supplied>is</supplied> beneath the sacrifice of the fellowship offering. <verse-number id="Nu 6:19">19</verse-number>The priest will take the shoulder from the ram that is boiled, and one ring-shaped bread cake of unleavened bread from the basket, and one wafer of unleavened bread, and he will put <supplied>them</supplied> on the hands of the Nazirite after he has shaved <idiom-start/>his consecrated head<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “his separation”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 6:20">20</verse-number>The priest will wave them <supplied>as</supplied> a wave offering <idiom-start/>before the presence of<idiom-end/><note>Literally “before the face of”</note> Yahweh; they<note>Hebrew “it”</note> are a holy object to the priest, in addition to the breast section of the wave offering, and in addition to the upper thigh of the contribution; and afterward the Nazirite may drink wine. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 6:21">21</verse-number>“ ‘This is the regulation of the Nazirite who has made a vow of his offering to Yahweh according to his separation, <idiom-start/>in addition to what he can afford<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “except from that which overtakes his hand”</note> In accordance to the word of his vow that he vowed, he will do, concerning the instruction of his separation.’ ” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Priestly Blessing</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 6:22">22</verse-number>Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Nu 6:23">23</verse-number>“Speak to Aaron and his sons, saying, ‘You will bless the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>:<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> You will say to them: </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1><verse-number id="Nu 6:24">24</verse-number>Yahweh will bless you </li1>
				<li2>and keep you; </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Nu 6:25">25</verse-number>Yahweh will make shine his face on you </li1>
				<li2>and be gracious to you; </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Nu 6:26">26</verse-number>Yahweh will lift up his face upon you, </li1>
				<li2>and he will give you peace.’ </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 6:27">27</verse-number>And they will put my name on the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and I will bless them.” </p>
		</chapter>