<chapter id="Nu 8">
			<pericope>The Seven Lamps</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 8:1">1</verse-number>Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Nu 8:2">2</verse-number>“Speak to Aaron, and say to him: ‘When you are setting up the lamps, the seven lamps will give light in front of the face of the lampstand.’ ” <verse-number id="Nu 8:3">3</verse-number>And Aaron did so; he set up the lampstand in front of the face of its lamps, just as Yahweh commanded Moses. <verse-number id="Nu 8:4">4</verse-number>And this <supplied>is</supplied> <idiom-start/>how the lampstand was made<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the work of the lampstand”</note> a hammered-work of gold; from its base up to its blossom,<note>Or “flower”</note> it <supplied>was</supplied> hammered-work according to the pattern that Yahweh showed Moses; so he made the lampstand. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Moses Consecrates the Levites</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 8:5">5</verse-number>Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Nu 8:6">6</verse-number>“Take the Levites from the midst of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and purify them. <verse-number id="Nu 8:7">7</verse-number>So you will do to them, to purify them: sprinkle on them waters of purification, and <idiom-start/>they will shave their whole body<idiom-end/><note>Literally “they will send a razor on all their body”</note> and wash their garments. <verse-number id="Nu 8:8">8</verse-number>And they will take a <idiom-start/>young bull<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a bull, a son of cattle”</note> and its grain offering of finely milled flour mixed with oil, and you will take a second <idiom-start/>young bull<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a bull, a son of cattle”</note> as a sin offering. <verse-number id="Nu 8:9">9</verse-number>You will bring the Levites <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the presence of”</note> the tent of assembly, and you will summon the entire community of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 8:10">10</verse-number>And you will bring the Levites <idiom-start/>before Yahweh<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “in the presence of Yahweh”</note> and the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> will lay their hands on the Levites, <verse-number id="Nu 8:11">11</verse-number>and <idiom-start/>Aaron will offer<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Aaron will wave”</note> the Levites <supplied>as</supplied> a wave offering <idiom-start/>before Yahweh<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the presence of Yahweh”</note> from the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and they will do the work of Yahweh. <verse-number id="Nu 8:12">12</verse-number>And the Levites will lay their hands on the head of the one bull and offer <supplied>it</supplied> as a sin offering and the other one as a burnt offering to Yahweh, to make atonement for the Levites. <verse-number id="Nu 8:13">13</verse-number>And you will present the Levites <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the presence of”</note> Aaron and <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the presence of”</note> his sons, and he <idiom-start/>will offer<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Aaron will wave”</note> them <supplied>as</supplied> a wave offering to Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 8:14">14</verse-number>“And you will separate the Levites from the midst of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and the Levites will be for me. <verse-number id="Nu 8:15">15</verse-number>And after this the Levites will come to serve <supplied>at</supplied> the tent of assembly, and you will purify them, and you <idiom-start/>will offer<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Aaron will wave”</note> them <supplied>as</supplied> a wave offering. <verse-number id="Nu 8:16">16</verse-number>For they <supplied>are</supplied> given to me exclusively from the midst of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> I have taken them for myself in place of <supplied>the</supplied> firstborn of every womb, every firstborn from the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 8:17">17</verse-number>For every firstborn among the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> <supplied>is</supplied> mine, both humankind and animal. On the day I destroyed every firstborn in the land of Egypt I consecrated them to me, <verse-number id="Nu 8:18">18</verse-number>and I have taken the Levites in the place of every firstborn among the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 8:19">19</verse-number>And I have given the Levites; they are given to Aaron and his sons from the midst of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> to do the work of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> in the tent of the assembly and to make atonement for the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> so a plague will not be among the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> when the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> come near the sanctuary.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 8:20">20</verse-number>And Moses and Aaron and the entire community of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> did to the Levites; everything that Yahweh commanded Moses concerning the Levites, the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> did to them. <verse-number id="Nu 8:21">21</verse-number>And the Levites purified themselves, and they washed their garments, and <idiom-start/>Aaron offered them<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Aaron waved them”</note> <supplied>as</supplied> a wave offering <idiom-start/>before Yahweh<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “in the presence of Yahweh”</note> and Aaron made atonement for them to purify them. <verse-number id="Nu 8:22">22</verse-number>After this the Levites came to do their work in the tent of assembly before Aaron and his sons. Just as Yahweh commanded Moses concerning the Levities, so they did to them. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 8:23">23</verse-number>Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Nu 8:24">24</verse-number>“This <supplied>is</supplied> what is for the Levites: <idiom-start/>those twenty-five years old<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from a son of twenty-five years”</note> and above will<note>Hebrew “and he will”</note> come to help <supplied>with the</supplied> service in the work of the tent of assembly; <verse-number id="Nu 8:25">25</verse-number>and <idiom-start/>those fifty years old<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from a son of fifty years”</note> will<note>Hebrew “he will”</note> return from the service of the work and will serve no longer. <verse-number id="Nu 8:26">26</verse-number>They<note>Hebrew “he”</note> can attend<note>Or “assist”</note> their brothers in the tent of assembly to keep <supplied>their</supplied> responsibilities, but they<note>Hebrew “he”</note> will not do work. This is what you will do concerning the Levities and their responsibilities.” </p>
		</chapter>