<chapter id="Nu 9">
			<pericope>The Passover</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 9:1">1</verse-number>Yahweh spoke to Moses in the desert of Sinai, in the second year after they came out from the land of Egypt, in the first month, saying, <verse-number id="Nu 9:2">2</verse-number>“Let the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> observe the Passover at its appointed time. <verse-number id="Nu 9:3">3</verse-number>On the fourteenth day of this month <idiom-start/>at twilight<idiom-end/><note>Literally “between the two evenings”</note> you will perform it at its appointed time according to all its decrees; and according to all its stipulations you will observe it.” <verse-number id="Nu 9:4">4</verse-number>So Moses spoke to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> to observe the Passover. <verse-number id="Nu 9:5">5</verse-number>And they observed the Passover on the fourteenth day of the month <idiom-start/>at twilight<idiom-end/><note>Literally “between the two evenings”</note> in the desert of Sinai. According to all that Yahweh commanded Moses, thus the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> did. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 9:6">6</verse-number>And it happened, men who were unclean <idiom-start/>by a dead person<idiom-end/><note>Literally “by a life of a person”</note> were not able to perform the Passover on that day. And they came <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the presence of”</note> Moses and Aaron on that day. <verse-number id="Nu 9:7">7</verse-number>And those men said to him, “<supplied>Although</supplied> we <supplied>are</supplied> unclean <idiom-start/>by a dead person<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “by a life of a person”</note> why are we hindered from presenting the offering of Yahweh at its appointed time in the midst of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>?”<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 9:8">8</verse-number>Moses said to them, “Stay. I will hear what Yahweh commands to you.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 9:9">9</verse-number>And Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Nu 9:10">10</verse-number>“Speak to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> saying, ‘Each man that is unclean <idiom-start/>by a dead person<idiom-end/><note>Literally “by a life of a person”</note> or <supplied>is</supplied> on a far journey, you or your <idiom-start/>descendants<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “generations”</note> he will observe the Passover of Yahweh. <verse-number id="Nu 9:11">11</verse-number>On the second month on the fourteenth day <idiom-start/>at twilight<idiom-end/><note>Literally “between the two evenings”</note> they will observe it; they will eat it with unleavened bread and bitter plants. <verse-number id="Nu 9:12">12</verse-number>They will leave none of it until morning, and they will not break a bone in it; they will observe it according to every decree of the Passover. <verse-number id="Nu 9:13">13</verse-number>But the man who <supplied>is</supplied> clean and not on a journey, and he fails to observe the Passover, that person will be cut off from the people because he did not present the offering of Yahweh on its appointed time. That man will bear his guilt. <verse-number id="Nu 9:14">14</verse-number>If an alien dwells with you he will observe the Passover of Yahweh according <supplied>to</supplied> the decree of the Passover and according <supplied>to</supplied> its stipulation; thus you will have one decree for you, for the alien and for the native of the land.’ ” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Cloud and the Fire</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 9:15">15</verse-number>And on a day setting up the tabernacle, the cloud covered the tent of the tabernacle, the tent of the testimony; in the evening it was on the tabernacle as an appearance of fire until morning. <verse-number id="Nu 9:16">16</verse-number>So it was<note>Hebrew “it will be”</note> continually; the cloud would cover it and the appearance of fire <supplied>by</supplied> night. <verse-number id="Nu 9:17">17</verse-number><supplied>Whenever</supplied> the cloud lifted up from on the tent, after that the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> would set out, and in the place where the cloud dwelled, there the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> camped. <verse-number id="Nu 9:18">18</verse-number>On the <idiom-start/>command of Yahweh<idiom-end/><note>Literally “mouth of Yahweh”</note> the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> would set out, and on the <idiom-start/>command of Yahweh<idiom-end/><note>Literally “mouth of Yahweh”</note> they encamped; all the days that the cloud dwelled on the tabernacle they encamped. <verse-number id="Nu 9:19">19</verse-number>And when the cloud prolonged on the tabernacle many days the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> kept the kept requirement of Yahweh and did not set out. <verse-number id="Nu 9:20">20</verse-number>When the cloud <idiom-start/>remained<idiom-end/><note>Literally “it was there”</note> a number of days on the tabernacle, on the <idiom-start/>command of Yahweh<idiom-end/><note>Literally “mouth of Yahweh”</note> they encamped; and on the <idiom-start/>command of Yahweh<idiom-end/><note>Literally “mouth of Yahweh”</note> they set out. <verse-number id="Nu 9:21">21</verse-number>When the cloud <idiom-start/>remained<idiom-end/><note>Literally “it was there”</note> from evening until morning, and the cloud lifted up in the morning, they would set out, or <supplied>if it remained</supplied> in the daytime and <supplied>at</supplied> night, <supplied>when</supplied> the cloud lifted up they set out. <verse-number id="Nu 9:22">22</verse-number>When <supplied>it was</supplied> two days, a month, <idiom-start/>or a year<idiom-end/><note>Literally “or days”</note> that the cloud prolonged to dwell on the tabernacle, the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> encamped, and they did not set out; when it lifted up they set out. <verse-number id="Nu 9:23">23</verse-number>On the <idiom-start/>command of Yahweh<idiom-end/><note>Literally “mouth of Yahweh”</note> they encamped, and on the <idiom-start/>command of Yahweh<idiom-end/><note>Literally “mouth of Yahweh”</note> they set out. They kept the requirement of Yahweh, on the <idiom-start/>command of Yahweh<idiom-end/><note>Literally “mouth of Yahweh”</note> in the hand of Moses.<note>Or “through Moses”</note> </p>
		</chapter>