<chapter id="Nu 10">
			<pericope>The Silver Trumpets</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 10:1">1</verse-number>Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Nu 10:2">2</verse-number>“Make yourself two silver trumpets; make them <supplied>of</supplied> hammered-work. <idiom-start/>You will use them<idiom-end/><note>Literally “They will be for you”</note> for calling the community and for breaking the camp. <verse-number id="Nu 10:3">3</verse-number>You will blow them, and all the community will assemble to the doorway of the tent of assembly. <verse-number id="Nu 10:4">4</verse-number>But if they blow only one, the leaders, the heads of the thousands of Israel, will assemble to you. <verse-number id="Nu 10:5">5</verse-number><supplied>When</supplied> you will blow a blast, the camps that are camping on the east will set out; <verse-number id="Nu 10:6">6</verse-number><supplied>when</supplied> you blow a second blast, the camps that are camping on the south will set out; they will blow a blast for their journeys. <verse-number id="Nu 10:7">7</verse-number>But when summoning the assembly, you will blow, but you will not signal with a loud noise. <verse-number id="Nu 10:8">8</verse-number>The sons of Aaron, the priests, will blow on the trumpets; this will be an eternal decree for your generations. <verse-number id="Nu 10:9">9</verse-number>If you go <supplied>to</supplied> war in your land against the enemy who attacks you, you will signal with a loud noise on the trumpets. You will be remembered <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the presence of”</note> Yahweh your God, and you will be rescued from your enemies. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 10:10">10</verse-number>“And on the day of your joy and in your appointed times, at the beginning of your months, you will blow on the trumpets in addition to your burnt offerings and in addition to the sacrifices of your fellowship offerings. And they will be as a memorial for you <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the presence of”</note> your God; I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh your God.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Israelites Depart from Sinai</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 10:11">11</verse-number>And it happened, in the second year, in the second month, on <supplied>the</supplied> twentieth of the month the cloud was lifted from upon the tabernacle of the testimony.<note>Some modern translations (e.g., the NRSV) have “tabernacle of the covenant”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 10:12">12</verse-number>And the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> set out for their journey<note>Hebrew “journeys”</note> from the desert of Sinai, and the cloud dwelled in the desert of Paran. <verse-number id="Nu 10:13">13</verse-number>They set out <idiom-start/>for the first time<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the beginning”</note> on the command of Yahweh in the hand of Moses.<note>Or “through Moses”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 10:14">14</verse-number>The standard of the camp of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Judah set out for the first time according to their divisions, with Nahshon son of Amminadab over its division. <verse-number id="Nu 10:15">15</verse-number>And Nathanel son of Zuar <supplied>was</supplied> over the division of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Issachar; <verse-number id="Nu 10:16">16</verse-number>Eliab son of Helon <supplied>was</supplied> over the division of the tribe of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Zebulun. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 10:17">17</verse-number>The tabernacle was taken down, and the sons of Gershon and the sons of Merari, the bearers of the tabernacle, set out. <verse-number id="Nu 10:18">18</verse-number>And the standard of the camp of Reuben according to their divisions; Elizur son of Shedeur <supplied>was</supplied> over their division. <verse-number id="Nu 10:19">19</verse-number>Shelumiel son of Zurishaddai <supplied>was</supplied> over the division of the sons of the tribe of Simeon. <verse-number id="Nu 10:20">20</verse-number>Eliasaph son of Deuel <supplied>was</supplied> over the division of the tribe of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Gad. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 10:21">21</verse-number>The Kohathites, the bearers of the sanctuary, set out, and they set up the tabernacle before they arrived. <verse-number id="Nu 10:22">22</verse-number>And the stand of the camp of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Ephraim set out according to their divisions; Elishama son of Ammihud <supplied>was</supplied> over its division. <verse-number id="Nu 10:23">23</verse-number>Gamaliel son of Pedahzur <supplied>was</supplied> over the division of the tribe of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Manasseh. <verse-number id="Nu 10:24">24</verse-number>Abidan son of Gideoni <supplied>was</supplied> over the division of the tribe of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Benjamin. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 10:25">25</verse-number>Then the standard of the camp of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Dan, who formed a rear guard for all the camps, set out according to their divisions; Ahiezer son of Ammishaddai <supplied>was</supplied> over its division. <verse-number id="Nu 10:26">26</verse-number>Pagiel son of Ocran <supplied>was</supplied> over the division of the tribe of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Asher. <verse-number id="Nu 10:27">27</verse-number>Ahira son of Enan <supplied>was</supplied> over the division of the tribe of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Naphtali. <verse-number id="Nu 10:28">28</verse-number>These <supplied>were</supplied> the departures of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> according to their divisions; and so they set out. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 10:29">29</verse-number>Moses said to Hobab son of Reuel the Midianite, the father-in-law of Moses, “We <supplied>are</supplied> setting out to the place that Yahweh said, ‘I will give it to you’; go with us, and we will <idiom-start/>treat you well<idiom-end/><note>Literally “do good to you”</note> because <idiom-start/>Yahweh promised<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Yahweh spoke”</note> good concerning Israel.” <verse-number id="Nu 10:30">30</verse-number>But he said to him, “I will not go. I will only go to my land and to my family.” <verse-number id="Nu 10:31">31</verse-number>He<note>That is, Moses</note> said, “Please, do not abandon us because you know our encampment in the desert, and <idiom-start/>you should be our guide<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “you should be our eyes”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 10:32">32</verse-number>Moreover, if you go with us, the good that Yahweh will do to us we will do to you.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 10:33">33</verse-number>And so they set out from the mountain of Yahweh a journey of three days, with the ark of the covenant of Yahweh setting out ahead of them<note>Or “before them”</note> three days’ journey to search out a resting place for them; <verse-number id="Nu 10:34">34</verse-number>and the cloud of Yahweh <supplied>was</supplied> over them by day when they set out from the camp. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 10:35">35</verse-number>And whenever the ark was setting out Moses would say, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Rise up, Yahweh! </li1>
				<li1>May your enemies be scattered; </li1>
				<li1>may the ones that hate you flee from your presence.” </li1>
				<li1><verse-number id="Nu 10:36">36</verse-number>And when it rested he would say, </li1>
				<li1>“Return, Yahweh, </li1>
				<li1>to the countless thousands of Israel.” </li1>
			</ul>
		</chapter>