<chapter id="Nu 11">
			<pericope>The Israelites Complain</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 11:1">1</verse-number>And it happened, the people were like those who <idiom-start/>complain of hardship<idiom-end/><note>Literally “complain of bad”</note> <idiom-start/>in the hearing<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the ears”</note> of Yahweh, and Yahweh <idiom-start/>became angry<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “his nose became hot”</note> and the fire of Yahweh burned among them, and it consumed the edge of the camp. <verse-number id="Nu 11:2">2</verse-number>Then the people cried out to Moses, and Moses prayed to Yahweh, and the fire died down. <verse-number id="Nu 11:3">3</verse-number>And he called the name of that place Taberah<note>This word is difficult, but some modern translations suggest the word in Hebrew means “burning” (see NRSV, NASB)</note> because the fire of Yahweh burned among them. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 11:4">4</verse-number>The riff-raff that <supplied>were</supplied> in their midst <idiom-start/>had a strong desire<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “desired a desire”</note> and the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> turned back and also wept, and they said, “Who will feed us meat? <verse-number id="Nu 11:5">5</verse-number>We remember the fish that we ate in Egypt for nothing, the cucumber, melon, leek, the onions, and the garlic. <verse-number id="Nu 11:6">6</verse-number>But now <idiom-start/>our strength is dried up<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “our life <supplied>is</supplied> dry”</note> there is nothing whatsoever except <idiom-start/>for the manna before us<idiom-end/>.”<note>Literally “for the manna of our eyes”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 11:7">7</verse-number>Now the manna <supplied>was</supplied> like coriander seed, and its outward appearance was like that of bdellium-gum. <verse-number id="Nu 11:8">8</verse-number>The people went about and gathered <supplied>it</supplied>, and they ground <supplied>it</supplied> with mills or crushed <supplied>it</supplied> with mortar. Then they boiled <supplied>it</supplied> in a pot and made it <supplied>into</supplied> bread-cakes; and it tasted like olive oil cakes. <verse-number id="Nu 11:9">9</verse-number>When the dew came down on the camp <supplied>at</supplied> night, the manna came down <supplied>with</supplied> it. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 11:10">10</verse-number>Moses heard the people weeping according to their<note>Hebrew “its”</note> clans, each at the doorway of their tents. Then <idiom-start/>Yahweh became very angry<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the nose of Yahweh became very hot”</note> and in the eyes of Moses it was bad. <verse-number id="Nu 11:11">11</verse-number>And Moses said to Yahweh, “Why have you brought trouble to your servant? Why have I not found favor in your eyes, that the burdens of all these people have been placed on me? <verse-number id="Nu 11:12">12</verse-number>Did I conceive all these people? If I have fathered them,<note>Hebrew “him/it”</note> that you could say to me, ‘Carry them<note>Hebrew “him/it”</note> in your lap, just as a foster-father carries the suckling on the land that you swore an oath to their ancestors?’<note>Or “fathers”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 11:13">13</verse-number>From where do I have meat to give all these people? They weep before me, saying, ‘Give us meat and let us eat!’ <verse-number id="Nu 11:14">14</verse-number>I am not able to carry all these people along alone; they are too heavy for me. <verse-number id="Nu 11:15">15</verse-number>If this is how you <supplied>are</supplied> going to treat me, please kill me immediately if I find favor in your eyes, and do not let me see my misery.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 11:16">16</verse-number>And Yahweh said to Moses, “Gather for me seventy men from the elders of Israel whom you know <supplied>are</supplied> elders of the people and their<note>Hebrew “his/its”</note> officials; take them to the tent of assembly, and they will stand there with you. <verse-number id="Nu 11:17">17</verse-number>I will come down and speak with you there; I will take away from the spirit that <supplied>is</supplied> on you, and I will place <supplied>it</supplied> on them; and they will bear the burdens of the people with you; you will not bear it alone. <verse-number id="Nu 11:18">18</verse-number>And you will say to the people, ‘Sanctify yourselves tomorrow, for you will eat meat because you have wept in the ears of Yahweh, saying, “Who will feed us good meat? <supplied>It was</supplied> good for us in Egypt.” Yahweh will give to you meat, and you will eat. <verse-number id="Nu 11:19">19</verse-number>You will eat, not one day, or two days, or five days, or ten days, or twenty days, <verse-number id="Nu 11:20">20</verse-number><idiom-start/>but for a whole month<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “until a period of one month”</note> until it comes out from your nose and becomes as nausea to you; because you have rejected Yahweh, who <supplied>is</supplied> in your midst, and you wept before <idiom-start/>his presence<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “before his face”</note> saying, “Why did we ever leave Egypt?” ’ ” <verse-number id="Nu 11:21">21</verse-number>But Moses said, “<supplied>There are</supplied> six hundred thousand on foot, among whom I <supplied>am</supplied> in the midst, and you yourself said, ‘I will give meat to them, and they will eat for a whole month.’ <verse-number id="Nu 11:22">22</verse-number>Should flocks and cattle be slaughtered for them? Should all the fish of the sea be gathered together for them, to be enough for them?” <verse-number id="Nu 11:23">23</verse-number>And Yahweh said to Moses, “<idiom-start/>Is Yahweh’s power limited<idiom-end/>?<note>Literally “Is Yahweh’s hand short?”</note> Now you will see if my word will happen or not.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 11:24">24</verse-number>So Moses went out, and he spoke the words of Yahweh to the people, and he gathered <supplied>together</supplied> seventy men from the elders of the people, and he <idiom-start/>made them stand<idiom-end/><note>Literally “caused them to stand”</note> all around the tent. <verse-number id="Nu 11:25">25</verse-number>Then Yahweh went down in the cloud and spoke to him, and he took away the spirit that <supplied>was</supplied> on him, and he <idiom-start/>put it<idiom-end/><note>Or “gave it”</note> on the seventy elders. And as soon as the spirit was resting on them they prophesied, but they did not do it again. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 11:26">26</verse-number>But two men were left in the camp; the name of one <supplied>was</supplied> Eldad, and the name of the second <supplied>was</supplied> Medad, and the spirit rested on them; they were among those who were written <supplied>down</supplied>, but they did not go out to the tent, so they prophesied in the camp. <verse-number id="Nu 11:27">27</verse-number>So a boy<note>Hebrew “the boy”</note> ran and told Moses and said, “Eldad and Medad <supplied>are</supplied> prophesying in the camp.” <verse-number id="Nu 11:28">28</verse-number>And Joshua son of Nun, the assistant of Moses from time of his youth, answered, “Moses, my lord, stop them.” <verse-number id="Nu 11:29">29</verse-number>But Moses said to him, “Are you jealous for my sake? Would that he<note>That is, Yahweh</note> give all Yahweh’s people prophets, that Yahweh put his spirit on them!” <verse-number id="Nu 11:30">30</verse-number>Then Moses and the elders of Israel were gathered to the camp. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Quail</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 11:31">31</verse-number>Then a wind set out from Yahweh, and it drove quails from the west, and he spread <supplied>them</supplied> out on the camp about a day’s journey on one side and about a day’s journey on the other, all around the camp, about two cubits on the surface of the land. <verse-number id="Nu 11:32">32</verse-number>And so the people <idiom-start/>worked<idiom-end/><note>Literally “arose”</note> all day and all night and all the next day, and they gathered the quail (the least of the ones collecting gathered ten homers).<note>HALOT 330, “a dry measure”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 11:33">33</verse-number>While the meat <supplied>was</supplied> still between their teeth, before it was consumed, Yahweh was angry with the people, and Yahweh struck a very great plague among the people. <verse-number id="Nu 11:34">34</verse-number>And he called the name of that place Kibroth Hattaavah<note>Hebrew “the graves of greediness”</note> because they buried the people that <idiom-start/>were greedy<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “craved”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 11:35">35</verse-number>From Kibroth Hattaavah<note>Hebrew “the graves of greediness”</note> the people set out <supplied>to</supplied> Hazeroth; and they stayed<note>Hebrew “they were”</note> in Hazeroth. </p>
		</chapter>