<chapter id="Nu 13">
			<pericope>Spies Sent to Spy Out the Land of Canaan</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 13:1">1</verse-number>And Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Nu 13:2">2</verse-number>“Send for yourself men, and let them explore the land of Canaan, which I <supplied>am about</supplied> to give to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> <idiom-start/>from each tribe of his father send one man<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “one man one man from the tribe of his father”</note> everyone a leader among them.” <verse-number id="Nu 13:3">3</verse-number>So Moses sent them from the desert of Paran on the command of Yahweh; all of the men <supplied>were</supplied> <idiom-start/>leaders<idiom-end/><note>Literally “heads”</note> of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 13:4">4</verse-number>And these <supplied>are</supplied> their names: from the tribe of Reuben, Shammua son of Zaccur; <verse-number id="Nu 13:5">5</verse-number>from the tribe of Simeon, Shaphat son of Hori; <verse-number id="Nu 13:6">6</verse-number>from the tribe of Judah, Caleb son of Jephunneh; <verse-number id="Nu 13:7">7</verse-number>from the tribe of Issachar, Igal son of Joseph; <verse-number id="Nu 13:8">8</verse-number>from the tribe of Ephraim, Hoshea son of Nun; <verse-number id="Nu 13:9">9</verse-number>from the tribe of Benjamin, Palti son of Raphu; <verse-number id="Nu 13:10">10</verse-number>from the tribe of Zebulun, Gaddiel son of Sodi; <verse-number id="Nu 13:11">11</verse-number>from the tribe of Joseph, from the tribe of Manasseh, Gaddi son of Susi; <verse-number id="Nu 13:12">12</verse-number>from the tribe of Dan, Ammiel son of Gemalli; <verse-number id="Nu 13:13">13</verse-number>from the tribe of Asher, Sethur son of Michael; <verse-number id="Nu 13:14">14</verse-number>from the tribe of Naphtali, Nahbi son of Vophsi; <verse-number id="Nu 13:15">15</verse-number>from the tribe of Gad, Geuel son of Maki. <verse-number id="Nu 13:16">16</verse-number>These <supplied>are</supplied> the names of the men whom Moses sent to explore the land. And Moses called Hoshea son of Nun Joshua. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 13:17">17</verse-number>Moses sent them to explore the land of Canaan, and he said to them, “Go up <supplied>like</supplied> this to the Negev,<note>An arid region south of the Judean hills</note> and go up into the hill country, <verse-number id="Nu 13:18">18</verse-number>and you will see what the land is <supplied>like</supplied> and if the people who inhabit it <supplied>are</supplied> strong or weak, or whether they are few or many, <verse-number id="Nu 13:19">19</verse-number>and whether the land that they <supplied>are</supplied> inhabiting <supplied>is</supplied> good or bad, and whether the cities they <supplied>are</supplied> inhabiting are camps or fortifications, <verse-number id="Nu 13:20">20</verse-number>and whether the land <supplied>is</supplied> fertile or lean, and whether there are trees on it or not. You will show yourself courageous, and you will take some of the fruit of the land.” It <supplied>was</supplied> the time of first ripe grapes. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 13:21">21</verse-number>So they went up and explored the land from the desert of Zin until Rehob, at Lebo Hamath.<note>Or “near Hamath”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 13:22">22</verse-number>They went up through the Negev<note>An arid region south of the Judean hills</note> and came to Hebron, where<note>Hebrew “and there”</note> Ahiman, Sheshai, and Talmai the descendants of the Anakites <supplied>were</supplied>. (Hebron was built seven years before Zoan <supplied>in</supplied> Egypt.) <verse-number id="Nu 13:23">23</verse-number>And they came up to the valley<note>Or “wadi”</note> of Eshcol, and they cut off a vine branch and one cluster of grapes from there; they carried it on <supplied>a</supplied> pole between two <supplied>men</supplied>, <supplied>with</supplied> pomegranates and figs. <verse-number id="Nu 13:24">24</verse-number>That place he called the valley<note>Or “wadi”</note> of Eshcol on account of the cluster of grapes that the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> cut off from there. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Spies Return</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 13:25">25</verse-number>They returned from exploring the land at the end of forty days.<note>Hebrew “day”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 13:26">26</verse-number>And they came<note>Hebrew “they went and came”</note> to Moses and Aaron and to the entire community of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> in the desert of Paran at Kadesh; they brought back word to them and <supplied>to</supplied> all the community, and they showed them the fruit of the land. <verse-number id="Nu 13:27">27</verse-number>And they told him,<note>Hebrew “they told him and said”</note> “We came to the land that you sent us, and it <supplied>is</supplied> flowing of milk and honey; this <supplied>is</supplied> its fruit. <verse-number id="Nu 13:28">28</verse-number>Yet the people who are inhabiting <supplied>it are</supplied> strong and the cities <supplied>are</supplied> fortified and very large; moreover, we saw the descendants of the Anakites there. <verse-number id="Nu 13:29">29</verse-number><supplied>The</supplied> Amalekites <supplied>are</supplied> living in the land of the Negev;<note>An arid region south of the Judean hills</note> the Hittites, Jebusites, and the Amorites <supplied>are</supplied> living in the hill country; and the Canaanites <supplied>are</supplied> living at the sea and on the banks of the Jordan.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 13:30">30</verse-number>And Caleb silenced the people before Moses and said, “Surely, let us go up and let us take possession of it because surely we will be able to prevail over it.” <verse-number id="Nu 13:31">31</verse-number>And the men who went up with him said, “We are not able to go up to the people because they <supplied>are</supplied> stronger than us.” <verse-number id="Nu 13:32">32</verse-number>And they presented the report of the land that they explored to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> saying, “The land that we went through to explore <supplied>is</supplied> a land that eats its inhabitants, and all the people whom we saw in its midst <supplied>are</supplied> <idiom-start/>men of great size<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “men of measurements”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 13:33">33</verse-number>There we saw the Nephilim (the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Anak <supplied>came</supplied> from the Nephilim), and we were like grasshoppers in our own sight, and so we were in their eyes.” </p>
		</chapter>