<chapter id="Nu 15">
			<pericope>Various Sacrifices and Offerings</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 15:1">1</verse-number>Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Nu 15:2">2</verse-number>“Speak to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and say to them, ‘When you come into the land of your dwellings that I <supplied>am about</supplied> to give to you, <verse-number id="Nu 15:3">3</verse-number>you will make an offering by fire for Yahweh from the cattle or from the flock, a burnt offering or a sacrifice to fulfill a vow, or as a freewill offering or at your feasts, to make a fragrance of appeasement for Yahweh. <verse-number id="Nu 15:4">4</verse-number>And the one who presents an offering<note>Hebrew “his offering”</note> for Yahweh, he will present a grain offering <supplied>of</supplied> finely milled flour; a tenth will be mixed with a fourth of the liquid measure <supplied>of</supplied> oil; <verse-number id="Nu 15:5">5</verse-number>and you will add a fourth of wine for the libation upon the burnt offering, or to the sacrifice for each ram-lamb. <verse-number id="Nu 15:6">6</verse-number>Or for the ram you will make a grain offering <supplied>of</supplied> two-tenths of finely milled flour mixed into a third of a liquid measure of oil. <verse-number id="Nu 15:7">7</verse-number>You will present a third of the liquid measure of wine for the libation, a fragrance of appeasement for Yahweh. <verse-number id="Nu 15:8">8</verse-number>When you prepare <idiom-start/>a bull<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a son of cattle”</note> as a burnt offering or a sacrifice to fulfill a vow or <supplied>a</supplied> fellowship offering for Yahweh, <verse-number id="Nu 15:9">9</verse-number>you will present with <idiom-start/>the bull<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the son of the cattle”</note> a grain offering of three-tenths <supplied>of</supplied> finely milled flour mixed with half a liquid measure of oil, <verse-number id="Nu 15:10">10</verse-number>and you will present half a liquid measure of wine as a libation, as an offering made by fire, a fragrance of appeasement for Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 15:11">11</verse-number>“ ‘This is how it should be done for each bull, or for the each ram, or for the small four-footed mammal, or ram-lambs, or goats. <verse-number id="Nu 15:12">12</verse-number>According to the number that you prepare, so should you do to each according to their number. <verse-number id="Nu 15:13">13</verse-number>Every native must do these <supplied>things</supplied> to present an offering made by fire, a fragrance of appeasement for Yahweh. <verse-number id="Nu 15:14">14</verse-number>If an alien dwells among you, or whoever <supplied>is</supplied> in your midst throughout your generations,<note>Hebrew “for your generations”</note> and prepares an offering made by fire, a fragrance of appeasement for Yahweh, he should do as you do. <verse-number id="Nu 15:15">15</verse-number><supplied>For</supplied> the assembly, there will be one decree for you and for the alien who dwells <supplied>among you</supplied>; <supplied>it is</supplied> an eternal decree for <supplied>all</supplied> your generations. <idiom-start/>You as well as the alien<idiom-end/><note>Literally “like you like the alien”</note> will be <idiom-start/>before Yahweh<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “in the presence of Yahweh”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 15:16">16</verse-number>There will be one law and one stipulation for you and for the alien dwelling among you.’ ” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 15:17">17</verse-number>Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Nu 15:18">18</verse-number>“Speak to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and say to them, ‘When you come into the land to which I <supplied>am about</supplied> to bring you, <verse-number id="Nu 15:19">19</verse-number>whenever you eat from the food of the land, you will lift up a contribution to Yahweh. <verse-number id="Nu 15:20">20</verse-number>You must lift up a contribution of the first <supplied>batch</supplied> of your ring-shaped dough bread; you must lift it up as a contribution of the threshing floor. <verse-number id="Nu 15:21">21</verse-number>You will give to Yahweh a contribution from the first of your dough throughout your generations.<note>Hebrew “for your generations”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 15:22">22</verse-number>“ ‘But if you go astray and you do not follow<note>Or “do”</note> all these commandments that Yahweh commanded to Moses, <verse-number id="Nu 15:23">23</verse-number>all that Yahweh commanded you by the hand of Moses<note>Or “through Moses”</note> from the day that Yahweh commanded and beyond, throughout your generations,<note>Hebrew “for your generations”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 15:24">24</verse-number>and if it was done unintentionally <idiom-start/>without the knowledge<idiom-end/><note>Literally “from the eyes”</note> of the community, then the entire community must prepare one <idiom-start/>young bull<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a bull a son of cattle”</note> as a burnt offering, as a fragrance of appeasement for Yahweh, and its grain offering and its libation, according to the stipulation, and one male goat as a sin offering. <verse-number id="Nu 15:25">25</verse-number>The priest will make atonement for all of the community of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and <idiom-start/>they will be forgiven<idiom-end/><note>Literally “it will be forgiven to them”</note> because it <supplied>was</supplied> unintentional; they will bring their offering, an offering made by fire for Yahweh, their sin offering <idiom-start/>before Yahweh<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the presence of Yahweh”</note> for their unintentional sin. <verse-number id="Nu 15:26">26</verse-number>All of the community of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> will be forgiven, as well as the alien that dwells in their midst, because the whole community <supplied>was involved</supplied> in the unintentional wrong. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 15:27">27</verse-number>“ ‘If one person sins unintentionally, that person will present a female goat <idiom-start/>in its first year<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a daughter of a year”</note> as a sin offering. <verse-number id="Nu 15:28">28</verse-number>And the priest will make atonement for the person who <idiom-start/>sinned unintentionally<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sinned unintentionally when sinning an unintentional wrong”</note> <idiom-start/>before Yahweh<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “in the presence of Yahweh”</note> to make atonement for him, and he will be forgiven. <verse-number id="Nu 15:29">29</verse-number><supplied>For</supplied> the native among the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and the alien that dwells in their midst, there will be one law for anyone who commits an unintentional wrong. <verse-number id="Nu 15:30">30</verse-number>But the one <idiom-start/>who acts presumptuously<idiom-end/><note>Literally “who acts with a high hand”</note> from among the native or alien blasphemes against Yahweh, and that person must be cut off from the midst of the people. <verse-number id="Nu 15:31">31</verse-number>Because he despised the word of Yahweh and broke his command, that person will be surely cut off and bear the guilt.’ ” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Violation of the Sabbath</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 15:32">32</verse-number>When the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> were in the desert, they found a man who was gathering wood on the day of the Sabbath. <verse-number id="Nu 15:33">33</verse-number>The ones who found him gathering wood brought him to Moses, Aaron, and to all the community. <verse-number id="Nu 15:34">34</verse-number>And they put him under watch because it was not made clear what should be done to him. <verse-number id="Nu 15:35">35</verse-number>And Yahweh said to Moses, “Surely the man must be put to death by stoning him; all the community <supplied>must stone him</supplied> with stones from outside the camp.” <verse-number id="Nu 15:36">36</verse-number>So the entire community brought him out to a place outside the camp, and <idiom-start/>they stoned him to death<idiom-end/><note>Literally “they stoned him with stones and he died”</note> just as Yahweh commanded Moses. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Garment Fringes</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 15:37">37</verse-number>Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Nu 15:38">38</verse-number>“Speak to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and tell them to make for themselves tassels<note>Hebrew “tassel”</note> on the hems of their garments throughout their generations<note>Hebrew “for their generations”</note> and to put a blue cord on the tassel of the hem. <verse-number id="Nu 15:39">39</verse-number>You will have a tassel <idiom-start/>for you to look at<idiom-end/><note>Literally “and you will look at it”</note> and remember all the commands of Yahweh and do them, and not follow <idiom-start/>after the unfaithfulness of your own heart and eyes<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “after your heart and after your eyes, which you <supplied>are</supplied> unfaithful after them”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 15:40">40</verse-number>so that you will remember and do all my commandments, and you will be holy for your God. <verse-number id="Nu 15:41">41</verse-number>I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh your God, who brought you out of the land of Egypt, to be your God; I <supplied>am</supplied> Yahweh your God.” </p>
		</chapter>