<chapter id="Nu 16">
			<pericope>Korah, Dathan, and Abiram Rebel</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 16:1">1</verse-number>Now Korah son of Izhar, son of Kohath, son of Levi, and Dathan and Abiram sons of Eliab, and On son of Peleth, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Reuben, <verse-number id="Nu 16:2">2</verse-number>took two hundred and fifty men from the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> leaders of the community summoned from the assembly, <idiom-start/>renowned men<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “men of name”</note> and <idiom-start/>they confronted<idiom-end/><note>Literally “they rose up before”</note> Moses. <verse-number id="Nu 16:3">3</verse-number>They were assembled in front of Moses and Aaron, and they said to them, “<idiom-start/>You take too much upon yourselves<idiom-end/>!<note>Literally “It is much for you”</note> All of the community is holy, every one of them, and Yahweh <supplied>is</supplied> in their midst, so why do you raise yourselves over the assembly of Yahweh?” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 16:4">4</verse-number>When Moses heard <supplied>this</supplied>, he fell on his face. <verse-number id="Nu 16:5">5</verse-number>And he said to Korah and to his entire company, saying, “<supplied>Tomorrow</supplied> morning Yahweh will make known who <supplied>is</supplied> his and <supplied>who</supplied> is holy, and he will bring him near to him, whomever he chooses he will bring near to him. <verse-number id="Nu 16:6">6</verse-number>Do this: take for yourselves censers, Korah and all of your company;<note>Hebrew “his company”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 16:7">7</verse-number>tomorrow put fire in them and place incense on them <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the presence of”</note> Yahweh; the man whom Yahweh chooses <supplied>will be</supplied> the holy <supplied>one</supplied>. You take too much upon yourselves, sons of Levi!” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 16:8">8</verse-number>And Moses said to Korah, “Please listen, sons of Levi! <verse-number id="Nu 16:9">9</verse-number><supplied>Is it</supplied> too little for you that the God of Israel set you apart from the community of Israel <idiom-start/>to allow you to approach him<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to bring you near to him”</note> to do the work of the tabernacle of Yahweh, to stand <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the presence of”</note> the community to serve them? <verse-number id="Nu 16:10">10</verse-number><idiom-start/>He has allowed you to approach him<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “He has brought you near”</note> you with all your brothers, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Levi, but yet you also seek the priesthood. <verse-number id="Nu 16:11">11</verse-number>Therefore you and your company that has banded together against Yahweh. What is Aaron that you grumble against him?” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 16:12">12</verse-number>Moses sent to call <supplied>for</supplied> Dathan and Abiram son of Eliab, but they said, “We will not come!<note>Hebrew “We will not come up!”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 16:13">13</verse-number>Is it too little that you have brought us from a land that flows with milk and honey to kill us in the desert, and that you also appoint yourself as a ruler over us? <verse-number id="Nu 16:14">14</verse-number>Surely, you have not brought us to a land that flows with milk and honey, and you have not given us the inheritance of fields and a vineyard. Will you gouge out the eyes of these men? We will not come!”<note>Hebrew “We will not come up!”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 16:15">15</verse-number>Then Moses became angry, and he said to Yahweh, “Do not notice their grain offering. I have not offered one donkey from them, and I have not mistreated one of them.” <verse-number id="Nu 16:16">16</verse-number>And Moses said to Korah, “You and your entire company will be <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the presence of”</note> Yahweh tomorrow, you and they and Aaron. <verse-number id="Nu 16:17">17</verse-number>Each one take his censer, and put incense on it<note>Hebrew “on them”</note> and you will present it <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the presence of”</note> Yahweh, and each of you bring his censer, two hundred and fifty censers, you and Aaron, each his censer.” <verse-number id="Nu 16:18">18</verse-number>So each of them took his censer, and they put fire on them, and they placed incense on them; they stood <supplied>at the</supplied> doorway of the tent of the assembly of Moses and Aaron. <verse-number id="Nu 16:19">19</verse-number>And Korah summoned them, the entire community, by the doorway of the tent of assembly, and the glory of Yahweh appeared to all the community. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 16:20">20</verse-number>And Yahweh spoke to Moses and Aaron, saying, <verse-number id="Nu 16:21">21</verse-number>“Separate yourselves from the midst of this community, that I can destroy them in a moment.” <verse-number id="Nu 16:22">22</verse-number>And they fell on their faces, and they said, “God, God of the spirits of all flesh, will one man sin and you become angry toward the entire community?” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 16:23">23</verse-number>Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Nu 16:24">24</verse-number>“Speak to the community, saying, ‘Move away from the dwelling of Korah, Dathan, and Abiram.’ ” <verse-number id="Nu 16:25">25</verse-number>So Moses stood up and went to Dathan and Abiram; the elders of Israel followed after him. <verse-number id="Nu 16:26">26</verse-number>He said to the community, saying, “Please turn away from the tents of these wicked men, and do not touch anything <idiom-start/>that belongs to them<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “that <supplied>is</supplied> to them”</note> or you will be destroyed with all their sins.” <verse-number id="Nu 16:27">27</verse-number>And so they moved away from around the dwellings<note>Hebrew “dwelling”</note> of Korah, Dathan, and Abiram; and Dathan and Abiram came out standing <supplied>at</supplied> the doorway of their tents, with their wives, sons, and little children. <verse-number id="Nu 16:28">28</verse-number>And Moses said, “In this you will know that Yahweh has sent me to do all these works; <supplied>it is</supplied> not from my heart. <verse-number id="Nu 16:29">29</verse-number><idiom-start/>If they die a natural death<idiom-end/><note>Literally “If they die like the death of every human”</note> or <idiom-start/>if a natural fate is visited upon them<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “If the fate of every human is visited upon them”</note> Yahweh has not sent me. <verse-number id="Nu 16:30">30</verse-number>But if Yahweh creates something new, and the ground opens its mouth and swallows them up and <idiom-start/>all that belongs to them<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “All that <supplied>is</supplied> for them”</note> and they go down alive <supplied>to</supplied> Sheol, and you will know that these men have despised Yahweh.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 16:31">31</verse-number>And it happened, as soon as he finished <idiom-start/>speaking<idiom-end/><note>Literally “to speak”</note> all these words, the ground that <supplied>was</supplied> under them split open. <verse-number id="Nu 16:32">32</verse-number>The land opened its mouth and swallowed them up with their houses and every person <idiom-start/>that belonged to Korah<idiom-end/><note>Literally “that was to Korah”</note> and all the property. <verse-number id="Nu 16:33">33</verse-number>They went down alive <supplied>to</supplied> Sheol, they and all that belonged to them, and the land covered over them, and they perished from the midst of the assembly. <verse-number id="Nu 16:34">34</verse-number>All Israel who <supplied>were</supplied> around them fled at their cry, because they said, “Lest the land swallow us up!” <verse-number id="Nu 16:35">35</verse-number>And fire went out from Yahweh, and it consumed the two hundred and fifty men presenting the incense. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 16:36">36</verse-number><note><cite title="BibleLEB2: Nu 16:36–17:13">Numbers 16:36–17:13 </cite>in the English Bible is 17:1–28 in the Hebrew Bible</note> And Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Nu 16:37">37</verse-number>“Say to Eleazar son of Aaron the priest, ‘<idiom-start/>Take out<idiom-end/><note>Literally “raise up”</note> the censers from among the place of burning because they are sacred, and scatter the fire outside. <verse-number id="Nu 16:38">38</verse-number>The censers of these <idiom-start/>who have sinned<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sinners”</note> at the cost of their lives, let them be made into gilded leafing plating for the altar; because they presented them <idiom-start/>before Yahweh<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “in the presence of Yahweh”</note> they are holy; and they will be a sign for the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>.’ ”<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 16:39">39</verse-number>Eleazar the priest took the bronze censers that the ones who were burned presented, and they hammered them out thinly <supplied>as</supplied> plating for the altar; <verse-number id="Nu 16:40">40</verse-number><supplied>it was</supplied> a memorial for the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> so that <idiom-start/>no strange man<idiom-end/><note>NASB translates “no layman”</note> who is not from <idiom-start/>the offspring<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the seed”</note> of Aaron should approach the presence <supplied>of</supplied> Yahweh to burn a smoke offering;<note>That is, an incense offering</note> he will not be like Korah and his company, just as Yahweh had spoken to him by the hand of Moses.<note>Or “through Moses”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Israelites Grumble</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 16:41">41</verse-number>The next day all the community of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> grumbled against Moses and Aaron, saying, “You have killed the people of Yahweh!” <verse-number id="Nu 16:42">42</verse-number>Then, when the community had gathered against Moses and Aaron, they turned to the tent of assembly, and behold, the cloud covered it, and the glory of Yahweh appeared. <verse-number id="Nu 16:43">43</verse-number>And Moses and Aaron came to the front of the tent of assembly, <verse-number id="Nu 16:44">44</verse-number>and Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Nu 16:45">45</verse-number>“Get away from the midst of this community, and I will finish them in an instant,”<note>Or “in a moment”</note> but they fell on their faces. <verse-number id="Nu 16:46">46</verse-number>And Moses and Aaron said, “Take the censer, and put fire on it from the altar. Place incense <supplied>on it</supplied>, and bring it quickly to the community, and make atonement for them, because wrath went out from the presence of Yahweh, and a plague has begun.” <verse-number id="Nu 16:47">47</verse-number>And so Aaron took <supplied>it</supplied> just as Moses had spoken, and he ran into the midst of the assembly, for behold, the plague had begun among the people; so he gave the incense and made atonement for the people. <verse-number id="Nu 16:48">48</verse-number>He stood between the dead and between the living, and the plague was stopped. <verse-number id="Nu 16:49">49</verse-number>Those who died by the plague were fourteen thousand seven hundred, besides those who died on account of Korah. <verse-number id="Nu 16:50">50</verse-number>Then Aaron returned to Moses at the doorway of the tent of assembly, and the plague was stopped. </p>
		</chapter>