<chapter id="Nu 17">
			<pericope>Aaron’s Staff Is Chosen</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 17:1">1</verse-number>Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Nu 17:2">2</verse-number>“Speak to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and take from among them twelve staffs, <idiom-start/>a staff from each family<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a staff from a house of a father”</note> from among all their leaders according to their families’ households. Write the name of each man on his staff, <verse-number id="Nu 17:3">3</verse-number>and the name of Aaron on the staff of Levi, because one staff <supplied>is</supplied> for the head of <supplied>each of</supplied> <idiom-start/>their families<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “the house of their fathers”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 17:4">4</verse-number>You must then put them in the tent of assembly <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the presence of”</note> the testimony<note>Or “the statute”</note> where I meet with you. <verse-number id="Nu 17:5">5</verse-number>And it will happen, the man whom I will choose, his staff will blossom, and so I will rid from upon myself the grumblings of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> who <supplied>are</supplied> grumbling against you.” <verse-number id="Nu 17:6">6</verse-number>Moses spoke to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and all their leaders gave him a staff for each leader, one from <idiom-start/>each of their families<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “each from the house of their fathers”</note> twelve staffs, and the staff of Aaron <supplied>was</supplied> in the midst of their tribes. <verse-number id="Nu 17:7">7</verse-number>And Moses put the staffs before Yahweh in the tent of testimony. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 17:8">8</verse-number>Then the next day, Moses went into the tent of the testimony, and behold the staff of Aaron for the house of Levi blossomed and put forth a flower and produced blossoms, and it produced almonds. <verse-number id="Nu 17:9">9</verse-number>Then Moses brought out to all the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> all the staffs before the presence of Yahweh, and they saw, and each man took his staff. <verse-number id="Nu 17:10">10</verse-number>And Yahweh said to Moses, “Bring back the staff of Aaron before the testimony<note>Or “the statute”</note> as a guard and sign for the children of rebellion, and let them finish their grumblings before me and not die.” <verse-number id="Nu 17:11">11</verse-number>So Moses did; just as Yahweh commanded him, so he did. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 17:12">12</verse-number>And the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> said to Moses, saying, “Look! We will die! We will be destroyed! All of us will perish! <verse-number id="Nu 17:13">13</verse-number>Anyone who approaches the tabernacle of Yahweh will die. <idiom-start/>Will we all die<idiom-end/>?”<note>Literally “Will we all die to perish?”</note> </p>
		</chapter>