<chapter id="Nu 20">
			<pericope>Miriam Dies</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 20:1">1</verse-number>Then the entire community of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> came <supplied>to</supplied> the desert of Zin on the first month, and the people stayed in Kadesh; Miriam died and was buried there. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 20:2">2</verse-number>There was no water for the community, and they were gathered before Moses and Aaron. <verse-number id="Nu 20:3">3</verse-number>And the people quarreled with Moses and spoke, saying, “If only we died when our brothers were dying <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the presence of”</note> Yahweh! <verse-number id="Nu 20:4">4</verse-number>Why have you brought the assembly of Yahweh, us and our livestock, into this desert to die here? <verse-number id="Nu 20:5">5</verse-number>Why have you brought us from Egypt to bring us to this bad place? It is not a place of seed or figs<note>Hebrew “fig”</note> or vines<note>Hebrew “vine”</note> or pomegranate trees,<note>Hebrew “tree”</note> and there is not water to drink.” <verse-number id="Nu 20:6">6</verse-number>And Moses and Aaron went from the presence of the assembly to the doorway of the tent of assembly. They fell on their faces, and the glory of Yahweh appeared to them. <verse-number id="Nu 20:7">7</verse-number>Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Nu 20:8">8</verse-number>“Take the staff and summon the community, you and Aaron your brother, and speak to the rock before their eyes, and it will give water. Bring out for them water from the rock, and let the community and their livestock drink.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 20:9">9</verse-number>So Moses took the staff from <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the presence of”</note> Yahweh just as he command him, <verse-number id="Nu 20:10">10</verse-number>and Moses and Aaron summoned the assembly to the presence of the rock, and he said to them, “Please listen, you rebels; can we bring out water for you from this rock?” <verse-number id="Nu 20:11">11</verse-number>Then Moses lifted up his hand and struck the rock with his staff twice. And abundant water went out, and the community and their livestock drank. <verse-number id="Nu 20:12">12</verse-number>But Yahweh said to Moses and Aaron, “Because you have not trusted in me, to regard me as holy <idiom-start/>in the sight of<idiom-end/><note>Or “before the eyes of”</note> the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> you will not bring this assembly into the land that I have given to them.” <verse-number id="Nu 20:13">13</verse-number>Those <supplied>were</supplied> the waters of Meribah, where the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> quarreled with Yahweh, and he showed himself holy among them. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 20:14">14</verse-number>From Kadesh Moses sent messengers to the king of Edom: “Thus your brother Israel has said, ‘You know all the hardship that has found us; <verse-number id="Nu 20:15">15</verse-number>our ancestors<note>Or “fathers”</note> went down to Egypt, and we lived in Egypt <idiom-start/>a long time<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “many days”</note> and the Egyptians mistreated us and our ancestors.<note>Or “fathers”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 20:16">16</verse-number>Then we cried to Yahweh, and he heard our voice; he sent an angel and brought us out from Egypt. And look, we <supplied>are</supplied> in Kadesh, a city on the edge of your territory. <verse-number id="Nu 20:17">17</verse-number>Please let us go through your land. We will not go through a field or vineyard, and we will not drink water from a well. We will go along the road of the king; we will not turn aside right or left until we have gone through your territory.’ ” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 20:18">18</verse-number>Then Edom said to him, “You will not pass through us<note>Hebrew “me”</note> lest <idiom-start/>we will go out<idiom-end/><note>Hebrew “I will go out”</note> to meet you with the sword.” <verse-number id="Nu 20:19">19</verse-number>The <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> said to him, “We will go up on the main road, and if we<note>Hebrew “I”</note> and our livestock<note>Hebrew “my livestock”</note> drink your water, we will pay <supplied>for it</supplied>.<note>Hebrew “I will give their worth”</note> It is only a small matter; let us pass through on our feet.”<note>Hebrew “I will go through on my feet”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 20:20">20</verse-number>But he said, “You will not go through.” And Edom went out to meet <idiom-start/>them<idiom-end/><note>Hebrew “him”</note> with a large army and a strong hand. <verse-number id="Nu 20:21">21</verse-number>So Edom refused to give Israel passage through his territory, and Israel turned aside from him. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Aaron Dies</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 20:22">22</verse-number>And they set out from Kadesh. The <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> the whole community, came <supplied>to</supplied> Mount Hor. <verse-number id="Nu 20:23">23</verse-number>Yahweh said to Moses and to Aaron on Mount Hor, on the boundary of the land of Edom, saying, <verse-number id="Nu 20:24">24</verse-number>“Let Aaron be gathered to his people; he will not come into the land that I have given to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> because you rebelled against <idiom-start/>my word<idiom-end/><note>Literally “my mouth”</note> at the waters of Meribah. <verse-number id="Nu 20:25">25</verse-number>Take Aaron and Eleazar his son, and take them up Mount Hor. <verse-number id="Nu 20:26">26</verse-number>Strip off Aaron’s garments, and put them on Eleazar his son; Aaron will be gathered <supplied>to his people</supplied>, and he will die there.” <verse-number id="Nu 20:27">27</verse-number>So Moses did just as Yahweh commanded, and they went up to Mount Hor before the eyes of all the community. <verse-number id="Nu 20:28">28</verse-number>And Moses stripped off Aaron’s garments and put them on Eleazar his son. Aaron died there on the top of the mountain; and Moses and Eleazar went down from the mountain. <verse-number id="Nu 20:29">29</verse-number>All the community saw that Aaron died; so all the house of Israel wept for Aaron thirty days.<note>Hebrew “day”</note> </p>
		</chapter>