<chapter id="Nu 21">
			<pericope>Arad Captured</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 21:1">1</verse-number>The Canaanite king of Arad, who was dwelling <supplied>in</supplied> the Negev,<note>An arid region south of the Judean hills</note> heard that Israel came <supplied>along</supplied> the way of Atharim; he fought against Israel and took some of them captive. <verse-number id="Nu 21:2">2</verse-number>Israel made a vow to Yahweh, and they said, “If you will surely give this people into our<note>Hebrew “my”</note> hand, then we<note>Hebrew “I”</note> <idiom-start/>will destroy<idiom-end/><note>Literally “devote to God”</note> their cities.” <verse-number id="Nu 21:3">3</verse-number>Yahweh heard the voice of Israel; he gave <supplied>to them</supplied> the Canaanites, and <idiom-start/>they destroyed them<idiom-end/><note>Literally “they devoted to God”</note> and their cities. They called the name of the place Hormah. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 21:4">4</verse-number>They set out from Mount Hor <supplied>by</supplied> the way of the <idiom-start/>Red Sea<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sea of reed”</note> to go around the land of Edom; but <idiom-start/>the people became impatient<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the life of the people became short”</note> along the way. <verse-number id="Nu 21:5">5</verse-number>The people spoke against God and against Moses, “Why have you brought us from Egypt to die in the desert? There is no food and no water, and our hearts detest <supplied>this</supplied> miserable food.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>The Bronze Serpent</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 21:6">6</verse-number>And Yahweh sent among the people poisonous snakes; they bit the people, and many people from Israel died. <verse-number id="Nu 21:7">7</verse-number>The people came to Moses and said, “We have sinned because we have spoken against Yahweh and against you. Pray to Yahweh and let him remove the snakes<note>Hebrew “snake”</note> from among us.” So Moses prayed for the people. <verse-number id="Nu 21:8">8</verse-number>And Yahweh said to Moses, “Make for yourself a snake and place it on a pole. When<note>Hebrew “And it will happen”</note> anyone is bitten and looks at it, that person will live.” <verse-number id="Nu 21:9">9</verse-number>So Moses made a snake of bronze, and he placed it on the pole; whenever<note>Hebrew “And it will happen”</note> a snake bit someone, and that person looked at the snake of bronze, he lived. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 21:10">10</verse-number>The <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> set out and encamped at Oboth. <verse-number id="Nu 21:11">11</verse-number>They set out from Oboth and encamped at Iye Abarim in the desert, which <supplied>was</supplied> in front of Moab <idiom-start/>toward the sunrise<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “from the east of the sun”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 21:12">12</verse-number>From there they set out and encamped at the valley of Zered. <verse-number id="Nu 21:13">13</verse-number>From there they set out and encamped beyond Arnon, which <supplied>is</supplied> in the desert that goes out from the boundary of the Amorites,<note>Hebrew “Amorite”</note> because Arnon <supplied>is</supplied> the boundary of Moab, between Moab and the Amorites.<note>Hebrew “Amorite”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 21:14">14</verse-number>Therefore thus it is said in the scroll of the Wars of Yahweh, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Waheb in Suphah, </li1>
				<li2>and the wadis of Arnon, </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Nu 21:15">15</verse-number>and the slope of the wadis </li1>
				<li2>that spreads out to the dwelling of Ar </li2>
				<li1>and lies at the boundary of Moab.” </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 21:16">16</verse-number>From there <supplied>they went</supplied> to Beer, which is the water well where Yahweh spoke to Moses, “Gather the people, that I may give them water.” <verse-number id="Nu 21:17">17</verse-number>Then Israel sang this song, “Arise, well water! Sing to it! <verse-number id="Nu 21:18">18</verse-number>Well water that the princes dug, that the leaders of the people dug, with a staff <supplied>and</supplied> with their rods.” And from <supplied>the</supplied> desert <supplied>they continued to</supplied> Mattanah, <verse-number id="Nu 21:19">19</verse-number>and from Mattanah <supplied>to</supplied> Nahaliel, and from Nahaliel <supplied>to</supplied> Bamoth; <verse-number id="Nu 21:20">20</verse-number>and from Bamoth to the valley that <supplied>is</supplied> in the territory of Moab, <supplied>by</supplied> the top of Pisgah, which overlooks the surface of the wasteland. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Sihon and Og Defeated</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 21:21">21</verse-number>Israel sent messengers to Sihon, the king of the Amorites,<note>Hebrew “Amorite”</note> saying, <verse-number id="Nu 21:22">22</verse-number>“Let us go through your land; we will not turn aside into a field or vineyard; we will not drink well water along the way of the king until we have gone through your territory.” <verse-number id="Nu 21:23">23</verse-number>But Sihon did not allow Israel to go through his territory. Sihon gathered all his people and went out to meet Israel; he came <supplied>to</supplied> the desert, to Jahaz, and he fought against Israel. <verse-number id="Nu 21:24">24</verse-number>But Israel struck him with <supplied>the</supplied> edge of <supplied>the</supplied> sword, and they took possession of his land from Arnon to Jabbok, until the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons of Ammon”</note> because the boundary of the <idiom-start/>Ammonites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons of Ammon”</note> <supplied>was</supplied> strong. <verse-number id="Nu 21:25">25</verse-number>Israel took all these cities, and Israel inhabited all the cities of the Amorites,<note>Hebrew “Amorite”</note> in Heshbon, and in all its environs.<note>Hebrew “her daughters;” other modern versions translate “its villages”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 21:26">26</verse-number>Because Heshbon <supplied>was</supplied> the city of Sihon king of the Amorites,<note>Hebrew “Amorite”</note> who had fought against the former king of Moab and taken all his land from his hand until Arnon. <verse-number id="Nu 21:27">27</verse-number>Thus the ones who quote proverbs say, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Come <supplied>to</supplied> Heshbon! Let it be built! </li1>
				<li2>And let the city of Sihon be established. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Nu 21:28">28</verse-number>Because fire went out from Heshbon, </li1>
				<li2>a flame from the city of Sihon; </li2>
				<li1>it consumed Ar of Moab, </li1>
				<li2>the lords of the<note>Or “the dominant”</note> high places of Arnon. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Nu 21:29">29</verse-number>Woe to you, Moab! </li1>
				<li2>You have perished, people of Chemosh. </li2>
				<li1>He has given his sons as fugitives, </li1>
				<li2>and his daughters into captivity, </li2>
				<li1>to the king of the Amorites,<note>Hebrew “Amorite”</note> Sihon. </li1>
				<li2><verse-number id="Nu 21:30">30</verse-number>We destroyed them; </li2>
				<li1>Heshbon has perished up to Dibon; </li1>
				<li2>we laid waste up to Nophah, </li2>
				<li1>which <idiom-start/>reaches<idiom-end/><note>Literally “<supplied>is</supplied> up to”</note> Medeba.” </li1>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 21:31">31</verse-number>Thus Israel lived in the land of the Amorites.<note>Hebrew “Amorite”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 21:32">32</verse-number>Moses sent to explore Jaazer; they captured <idiom-start/>its environs<idiom-end/><note>Hebrew “her daughters;” other modern versions translate “its villages”</note> and dispossessed the Amorites<note>Hebrew “Amorite”</note> who <supplied>were</supplied> there. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 21:33">33</verse-number>Then they turned and went up <supplied>by</supplied> the way of the Bashan, and Og king of the Bashan and all his people went out to meet them for battle <supplied>at</supplied> Edrei. <verse-number id="Nu 21:34">34</verse-number>And Yahweh said to Moses, “Do not fear him because I will give him and all his people and all his land into your hand. You will do to him just as you did to Sihon king of the Amorites,<note>Hebrew “Amorite”</note> who was living in Heshbon.” <verse-number id="Nu 21:35">35</verse-number>And so they destroyed him and his sons, and all his people until they had not spared a survivor; and they took possession of his land. </p>
		</chapter>