<chapter id="Nu 23">
			<pericope>Balaam’s Oracles</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 23:1">1</verse-number>Balaam said to Balak, “Build for me this: seven altars. And prepare for me this: seven bulls and seven rams.” <verse-number id="Nu 23:2">2</verse-number>And Balak did just as Balaam spoke, and Balak offered Balaam a bull and a ram on the altar. <verse-number id="Nu 23:3">3</verse-number>And Balaam said to Balak, “Station yourself at your burnt offering, and I will go; perhaps Yahweh will come to meet me, and whatever he shows me I will tell to you.” So he went <supplied>to</supplied> a barren height. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 23:4">4</verse-number>And God met with Balaam, and he said to him, “I have arranged seven altars, and I have offered a bull and a ram on the altar.” <verse-number id="Nu 23:5">5</verse-number>Yahweh put a word in the mouth of Balaam and said, “Return to Balak, and you must speak thus.” <verse-number id="Nu 23:6">6</verse-number>So he returned to him, and behold, he was standing beside his burnt offering, he and all the leaders of Moab. <verse-number id="Nu 23:7">7</verse-number>And he lifted up his oracle and said, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“From Aram Balak lead me, </li1>
				<li2>from the mountains of the east the king of Moab, </li2>
				<li1>‘Go for me, curse Jacob, </li1>
				<li2>and go, denounce Israel.’ </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Nu 23:8">8</verse-number>How can I curse <supplied>whom</supplied> God has not cursed, </li1>
				<li2>and how can I denounce <supplied>whom</supplied> Yahweh has not denounced? </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Nu 23:9">9</verse-number>Because from the top of <supplied>the</supplied> rocks I see him, </li1>
				<li2>from hilltops I watch him. </li2>
				<li1>Behold, a people <supplied>who</supplied> dwell alone, </li1>
				<li2>they do not consider themselves among the nations. </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Nu 23:10">10</verse-number>Who can count the dust of Jacob, </li1>
				<li2>or <supplied>as</supplied> a number the fourth part of Israel? </li2>
				<li1>Let my life die the death of an upright person, </li1>
				<li2>and let my end be like his!” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 23:11">11</verse-number>And Balak said to Balaam, “What have you done to me? I took you to curse my enemies, and look, you have surely blessed them!” <verse-number id="Nu 23:12">12</verse-number>He answered and said, “<idiom-start/>Should I not speak<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Should I not observe to speak”</note> what Yahweh puts in my mouth?” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 23:13">13</verse-number>Then Balak said, “Please walk with me to another place where you will see them, <supplied>but</supplied> you will only see part of them and will not see all of them; and curse them for me from there.” <verse-number id="Nu 23:14">14</verse-number>So he took him to the field of Zophim to the top of Pisgah, and he built seven altars, and he offered a bull and a ram on <supplied>each</supplied> altar. <verse-number id="Nu 23:15">15</verse-number>Balaam<note>Hebrew “He”</note> said to Balak, “Station yourself here at the burnt offering while I myself meet with <supplied>Yahweh</supplied> there.” <verse-number id="Nu 23:16">16</verse-number>Then Yahweh met with Balaam, and he put a word in his mouth, and he said, “Return to Balak, and you must speak thus.” <verse-number id="Nu 23:17">17</verse-number>He came to him, and behold, he <supplied>was</supplied> standing at his burnt offering, and the princes of Moab with him. And Balak said to him, “What has Yahweh spoken?” <verse-number id="Nu 23:18">18</verse-number>Then <idiom-start/>he uttered<idiom-end/><note>Literally “he lifted up”</note> his oracle, and said, </p>
			<p/>
			<ul>
				<li1>“Stand up, Balak, and hear; </li1>
				<li2>listen to me, son of Zippor! </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Nu 23:19">19</verse-number>God <supplied>is</supplied> not a man, that he should lie, </li1>
				<li2>nor a son of humankind, </li2>
				<li1>that he should change his mind. </li1>
				<li2>Has he said, and will he not do <supplied>it</supplied>? </li2>
				<li1>And has he spoken, and will he not fulfill it? </li1>
				<li2><verse-number id="Nu 23:20">20</verse-number>Behold, I have received <supplied>a command</supplied> to bless; </li2>
				<li1>when he has blessed, I cannot cause it to return. </li1>
				<li2><verse-number id="Nu 23:21">21</verse-number>He has no regard <supplied>for</supplied> evil in Jacob, </li2>
				<li1>and he does not see trouble in Israel; </li1>
				<li2>Yahweh his God <supplied>is</supplied> with him, </li2>
				<li1>and a shout<note>Or “a blast”</note> of a king <supplied>is</supplied> among them.<note>Hebrew “him”</note> </li1>
				<li2><verse-number id="Nu 23:22">22</verse-number>God, who brings them out from Egypt, </li2>
				<li1><supplied>is</supplied> like the strength<note>Or “like the horns”</note> of a wild ox for them.<note>Hebrew “him”</note> </li1>
				<li2><verse-number id="Nu 23:23">23</verse-number>Because <supplied>there is</supplied> no sorcery against Jacob, </li2>
				<li1>and <supplied>there is</supplied> no divination against Israel. </li1>
				<li2>Now<note>Or “At the right time”</note> it will be said to Jacob and Israel, </li2>
				<li2>what God has done! </li2>
				<li1><verse-number id="Nu 23:24">24</verse-number>Look! <supplied>the</supplied> people will rise like the lion; </li1>
				<li2>he raises himself and will not lie down </li2>
				<li1>until he eats <supplied>the</supplied> prey </li1>
				<li2>and drinks the blood of the slain.” </li2>
			</ul>
			<p/>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 23:25">25</verse-number>Then Balak said to Balaam, “Do not curse them<note>Hebrew “him”</note> at all, nor bless them<note>Hebrew “him”</note> at all!” <verse-number id="Nu 23:26">26</verse-number>But Balaam answered and said to Balak, “Did I not speak to you, saying, ‘Whatever Yahweh speaks I will do’?” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 23:27">27</verse-number>Then Balak said to Balaam, “Please, come, I will take you to another place; perhaps <idiom-start/>it will be acceptable to<idiom-end/><note>Literally “it will be right in the eyes of”</note> God, and you will curse for me from there.” <verse-number id="Nu 23:28">28</verse-number>So Balak took Balaam <supplied>to</supplied> the top of Peor, which looks down on the face of the Jeshimon.<note>Or “the wasteland”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 23:29">29</verse-number>And Balaam said to Balak, “Build for me these seven altars, and prepare for me these seven bulls and seven rams.” <verse-number id="Nu 23:30">30</verse-number>Balak did just as Balaam said, and he offered a bull and a ram on <supplied>each</supplied> altar. </p>
		</chapter>