<chapter id="Nu 25">
			<pericope>The Plague of Israel</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 25:1">1</verse-number>When Israel dwelled in Shittim, the people began to prostitute<note>Or “have sexual relations”</note> <supplied>themselves</supplied> with the daughters of Moab. <verse-number id="Nu 25:2">2</verse-number>And they invited the people to the sacrifices of their gods, and the people ate and worshiped their gods. <verse-number id="Nu 25:3">3</verse-number>So Israel was joined together to Baal Peor, and <idiom-start/>Yahweh became angry<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the nose of Yahweh became hot”</note> with Israel. <verse-number id="Nu 25:4">4</verse-number>Yahweh said to Moses, “Take all <idiom-start/>the leaders<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the heads”</note> of the people and kill them before the sun, so the fierce anger of Yahweh will turn from Israel.” <verse-number id="Nu 25:5">5</verse-number>So Moses said to the judges of Israel, “Each <supplied>of you</supplied> kill his men who are joined together with Baal Peor.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 25:6">6</verse-number>And behold, a man from the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> came and brought to his brothers <supplied>a</supplied> Midianite woman before the eyes of Moses and before the eyes of all of the community of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and they <supplied>were</supplied> weeping <supplied>at</supplied> the doorway of the tent of assembly. <verse-number id="Nu 25:7">7</verse-number>When Phinehas son of Eleazar son of Aaron the priest saw, he got up from the midst of the community and took a spear in his hand. <verse-number id="Nu 25:8">8</verse-number>He went after the man of Israel into the woman’s section of the tent, and he drove the two of them, the man of Israel and the woman, into her belly. And the plague among the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> stopped. <verse-number id="Nu 25:9">9</verse-number>The ones who died in the plague were twenty-four thousand. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 25:10">10</verse-number>Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Nu 25:11">11</verse-number>“Phinehas son of Eleazar, son of Aaron the priest, turned away my anger from among the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> when he was jealous with my jealousy in their midst, and I did not destroy the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> with my jealousy. <verse-number id="Nu 25:12">12</verse-number>Therefore say, ‘Behold, I <supplied>am</supplied> giving to him my covenant of peace, <verse-number id="Nu 25:13">13</verse-number>and it will be for him and his <idiom-start/>offspring<idiom-end/><note>Literally “seed”</note> after him a covenant of an eternal priesthood because he was jealous for his God and made atonement for the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>.’ ”<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 25:14">14</verse-number>The name of the man of Israel who was struck with the Midianite woman <supplied>was</supplied> Zimri son of Salu, a leader of <idiom-start/>the family<idiom-end/><note>Or “the father’s house” or “the ancestor’s house”</note> of the Simeonites.<note>Hebrew “Simeonite”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 25:15">15</verse-number>The name of the Midianite woman who was struck <supplied>was</supplied> Cozbi daughter of Zur, <idiom-start/>a leader<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a head”</note> of <supplied>a</supplied> tribe of <idiom-start/>the family<idiom-end/><note>Or “the father’s house” or “the ancestor’s house”</note> in Midian. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 25:16">16</verse-number>Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Nu 25:17">17</verse-number>“Attack the Midianites and strike them <verse-number id="Nu 25:18">18</verse-number>because they <supplied>were</supplied> attacking you with their deception, <supplied>with</supplied> which they have deceived you on the matter of Peor and on the matter of Cozbi the daughter of the leader of Midian, their sister who was struck on the day of the plague because of the matter of Peor.” </p>
		</chapter>