<chapter id="Nu 26">
			<pericope>A New Census</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 26:1">1</verse-number><note><cite title="BibleLEB2: Nu 26:1a">Numbers 26:1a </cite>in the English Bible is 25:19b in the Hebrew Bible</note> And it happened after the plague, <note>In the Hebrew Bible, <cite title="BibleLEB2: Nu 26:1">Numbers 26:1 </cite>begins here</note>Yahweh said to Moses and to Eleazar son of Aaron the priest, saying, <verse-number id="Nu 26:2">2</verse-number>“<idiom-start/>Take a census<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Lift up the head<supplied>s</supplied>”</note> of the community of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> from <idiom-start/>those twenty years old<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a son of twenty years”</note> and above, according to <idiom-start/>their families<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “the house of their fathers”</note> all who are able to go out to war in Israel.” <verse-number id="Nu 26:3">3</verse-number>So Moses and Eleazar the priest spoke with them on the desert-plateau of Moab by <supplied>the</supplied> Jordan <supplied>across from</supplied> Jericho, saying, <verse-number id="Nu 26:4">4</verse-number>“<supplied>Take a census of the community</supplied> from <idiom-start/>those twenty years old<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a son of twenty years”</note> and above, just as Yahweh commanded Moses.” </p>
			<p>The Israelites who went out from the land of Egypt <supplied>were</supplied>: </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 26:5">5</verse-number>Reuben, the firstborn of Israel, the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Reuben: <supplied>of</supplied> Hanoch, the clan of the Hanochites; of Pallu, the clan of the Palluites;<note>Hebrew “Palluite”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 26:6">6</verse-number>of Hezron, the clan of the Hezronites;<note>Hebrew “Hezronite”</note> of Carmi, the clan of the Carmites.<note>Hebrew “Carmite”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 26:7">7</verse-number>These <supplied>are</supplied> the clans of the Reubenites,<note>Hebrew “Reubenite”</note> and the ones counted of them were forty-three thousand seven hundred and thirty. <verse-number id="Nu 26:8">8</verse-number>The children of Pallu: Eliab. <verse-number id="Nu 26:9">9</verse-number>The children of Eliab: Nemuel, Dathan, and Abiram. These <supplied>are the same</supplied> Dathan and Abiram who <supplied>were</supplied> appointed of the community, who rebelled against Moses and Aaron in the company of Korah, when they rebelled against Yahweh, <verse-number id="Nu 26:10">10</verse-number>and the land opened its mouth and swallowed them with Korah, when that company died, when the fire consumed two hundred and fifty men, and they were a sign.<note>That is, a warning sign</note> <verse-number id="Nu 26:11">11</verse-number>The children<note>Or “sons”</note> of Korah, however, did not die. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 26:12">12</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Simeon, according to their clans: of Nemuel, the clan of the Nemuelites;<note>Hebrew “Nemuelite”</note> of Jamin, the clan of the Jaminites;<note>Hebrew “Jaminite”</note> of Jakin, the clan of the Jakinites;<note>Hebrew “Jakinite”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 26:13">13</verse-number>of Zerah, the clan of the Zerahites;<note>Hebrew “Zerahite”</note> of Shaul, the clan of the Shaulites.<note>Hebrew “Shaulite”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 26:14">14</verse-number>These <supplied>were</supplied> the clans of the Simeonites,<note>Hebrew “Simeonite”</note> twenty-two thousand two hundred. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 26:15">15</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Gad according to their clans: of Zephon, the clan of the Zephonites;<note>Hebrew “Zephonite”</note> of Haggi, the clan of the Haggites;<note>Hebrew “Haggite”</note> of Shuni, the clan of the Shunites;<note>Hebrew “Shunite”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 26:16">16</verse-number>of Ozni, the clan of the Oznites;<note>Hebrew “Oznite”</note> of Eri, the clan of the Erites;<note>Hebrew “Erite”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 26:17">17</verse-number>of Arod, the clan of the Arodites;<note>Hebrew “Arodite”</note> of Areli, the clan of the Arelites;<note>Hebrew “Arelite”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 26:18">18</verse-number>These <supplied>were</supplied> the clans of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Gad according to the ones counted of them, forty thousand five hundred. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 26:19">19</verse-number>The sons of Judah: Er and Onan; but Er and Onan died in the land of Canaan. <verse-number id="Nu 26:20">20</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Judah according to their clans <supplied>were</supplied>: of Shelah, the clan of the Shelanites;<note>Hebrew “Shelanite”</note> of Perez, the clan of the Perezites;<note>Hebrew “Perezite”</note> of Zerah, the clan of the Zerahites.<note>Hebrew “Zerahite”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 26:21">21</verse-number>The children of Perez were: of Hezron, the clan of the Hezronites;<note>Hebrew “Hezronite”</note> of Hamul, the clan of the Hamulites.<note>Hebrew “Hamulite”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 26:22">22</verse-number>These <supplied>were</supplied> the clans of Judah according to the ones counted of them, seventy-six thousand five hundred. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 26:23">23</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Issachar according to their clans: <supplied>of</supplied> Tola, the clan of the Tolaites;<note>Hebrew “Tolaite”</note> of Puvah, the clan of the Punites;<note>Hebrew “Punite”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 26:24">24</verse-number>of Jashub, the clans of the Jashubites;<note>Hebrew “Jashubite”</note> of Shimron, the clan of the Shimronites.<note>Hebrew “Shimronite”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 26:25">25</verse-number>These <supplied>were</supplied> the clans of Issachar according to the ones counted of them, sixty-four thousand three hundred. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 26:26">26</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Zebulun according to their clans: of Sered, the clan of the Seredites;<note>Hebrew “Seredite”</note> of Elon, the clan of the Elonites;<note>Hebrew “Elonite”</note> of Jahleel, the clan of the Jahleelites.<note>Hebrew “Jahleelite”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 26:27">27</verse-number>These <supplied>were</supplied> the clans of the Zebulunites<note>Hebrew “Zebulunite”</note> according to the ones counted of them, sixty thousand five hundred. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 26:28">28</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Joseph according to their clans: Manasseh and Ephraim. <verse-number id="Nu 26:29">29</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Manasseh: of Makir, the clan of the Makirites.<note>Hebrew “Makirite”</note> And Makir fathered Gilead; of Gilead, the clan of the Gileadites.<note>Hebrew “Gileadite”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 26:30">30</verse-number>These <supplied>were</supplied> the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Gilead: <supplied>of</supplied> Iezer, the clan of the Iezerites;<note>Hebrew “Iezerite”</note> of Helek, the clan of the Helekites;<note>Hebrew “Helekite”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 26:31">31</verse-number>and <supplied>of</supplied> Asriel, the clan of the Asrielites;<note>Hebrew “Asrielite”</note> and <supplied>of</supplied> Shechem, the clan of the Shechemites;<note>Hebrew “Shechemite”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 26:32">32</verse-number>and <supplied>of</supplied> Shemida, the clan of the Shemidaites;<note>Hebrew “Shemidaite”</note> and <supplied>of</supplied> Hepher, the clan of the Hepherites.<note>Hebrew “Hepherite”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 26:33">33</verse-number>Zelophehad son of Hepher did not have sons, but only daughters; and the names<note>Hebrew “name”</note> of the daughters of Zelophehad <supplied>were</supplied> Mahlah, Noah, Hoglah, Milcah, and Tirzah. <verse-number id="Nu 26:34">34</verse-number>These <supplied>were</supplied> the clans of Manasseh, and the ones counted of them <supplied>were</supplied> fifty-two thousand seven hundred. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 26:35">35</verse-number>These <supplied>were</supplied> the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Ephraim according to their clans: of Shuthelah, the clan of the Shuthelahites;<note>Hebrew “Shuthelahite”</note> of Beker, the clan of the Bekerites;<note>Hebrew “Bekerite”</note> of Tahan, the clan of the Tahanites.<note>Hebrew “Tahanite”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 26:36">36</verse-number>And these <supplied>were</supplied> the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Shuthelah: of Eran, the family of the Eranites.<note>Hebrew “Eranite”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 26:37">37</verse-number>These <supplied>were</supplied> the clans of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Ephraim according to the ones counted of them, thirty-two thousand five hundred. These <supplied>were</supplied> the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Joseph according to their clans. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 26:38">38</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Benjamin according to their clans: of Bela, the clan of the Belaites;<note>Hebrew “Belaite”</note> of Ashbel, the clan of the Ashbelites;<note>Hebrew “Ashbelite”</note> of Ahiram, the clan of the Ahiramites;<note>Hebrew “Ahiramite”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 26:39">39</verse-number>of Shephupham, the clan of the Shuphamites;<note>Hebrew “Shuphamite”</note> of Hupham, the clan of the Huphamites.<note>Hebrew “Huphamite”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 26:40">40</verse-number>The sons of Bela were Ard and Naaman: <supplied>of Ard</supplied>, the clan of the Ardites;<note>Hebrew “Ardite”</note> of Naaman, the clan of the Naamites.<note>Hebrew “Naamite”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 26:41">41</verse-number>These <supplied>were</supplied> the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Benjamin according to their clans. And the ones counted of them <supplied>were</supplied> forty-five thousand six hundred. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 26:42">42</verse-number>These <supplied>were</supplied> the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Dan according to their clans: of Shuham, the clan of the Shuhamites.<note>Hebrew “Shuhamite”</note> These <supplied>were</supplied> the clans of Dan according to their clans. <verse-number id="Nu 26:43">43</verse-number>All the clans of the Shuhamites,<note>Hebrew “Shumhamite”</note> according to the ones counted of them, <supplied>were</supplied> sixty-four thousand four hundred. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 26:44">44</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Asher according to their clans: of Imnah, the clan of the Imnahites;<note>Hebrew “Imnahite”</note> of Ishvi, the clan of the Ishvites;<note>Hebrew “Ishvite”</note> of Beriah, the clan of the Beriahites.<note>Hebrew “Beriahite”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 26:45">45</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Beriah: of Heber, the clan of the Heberites;<note>Hebrew “Heberite”</note> of Malkiel, the clan of the Malkielites.<note>Hebrew “Malkielite”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 26:46">46</verse-number>The name of the daughter of Asher <supplied>was</supplied> Serah. <verse-number id="Nu 26:47">47</verse-number>These <supplied>were</supplied> the clans of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Asher according to the ones counted of them, fifty-three thousand four hundred. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 26:48">48</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Naphtali according to their clans: of Jahzeel, the clan of the Jahzeelites;<note>Hebrew “Jahzeelite”</note> of Guni, the clan of the Gunites;<note>Hebrew “Gunite”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 26:49">49</verse-number>of Jezer, the clan of the Jezerites;<note>Hebrew “Jezerite”</note> of Shillem, the clan of the Shillemites.<note>Hebrew “Shillemite”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 26:50">50</verse-number>These <supplied>were</supplied> the clans of Naphtali according to their clans, the ones counted of them, forty-five thousand four hundred. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 26:51">51</verse-number>These <supplied>were</supplied> the ones counted of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> six hundred and one thousand seven hundred and thirty. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 26:52">52</verse-number>Then Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Nu 26:53">53</verse-number>“For these the land must be divided as an inheritance according to the number of names. <verse-number id="Nu 26:54">54</verse-number>For the larger group you must increase their inheritance, and for the smaller group you must make smaller their inheritance; each must be given <idiom-start/>their<idiom-end/><note>Hebrew “his”</note> inheritance according to the number of the ones counted of them. <verse-number id="Nu 26:55">55</verse-number>Surely the land will be divided by lot. They will inherit according to the names of the tribes of their ancestors.<note>Or “fathers”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 26:56">56</verse-number><idiom-start/>Their<idiom-end/><note>Hebrew “His”</note> inheritance must be divided according to the lot between the larger and smaller <supplied>groups</supplied>.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 26:57">57</verse-number>These <supplied>are</supplied> the ones counted of the Levites according to their clans: of Gershon, the clan of the Gershonites;<note>Hebrew “Gershonite”</note> of Kohath, the clan of the Kohathites;<note>Hebrew “Kohathite”</note> of Merari, the clan of the Merarites.<note>Hebrew “Merarite”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 26:58">58</verse-number>These <supplied>are</supplied> the clans of Levi: the clan of the Libnites,<note>Hebrew “Libnite”</note> the clan of the Hebronites,<note>Hebrew “Hebronite”</note> the clan of the Mahlites,<note>Hebrew “Mahlite”</note> the clan of the Mushites,<note>Hebrew “Mushite”</note> the clan of the Korahites.<note>Hebrew “Korahite”</note> Kohath fathered Amram. <verse-number id="Nu 26:59">59</verse-number>The name of the wife of Amram <supplied>was</supplied> Jochebed, the daughter of Levi, whose <supplied>mother</supplied> bore her for Levi in Egypt; she bore to Amram: Aaron and Moses and their sister Miriam. <verse-number id="Nu 26:60">60</verse-number>To Aaron were born Nadab and Abihu, Eleazar and Ithamar. <verse-number id="Nu 26:61">61</verse-number>But Nadab and Abihu died when they presented strange fire <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the presence of”</note> Yahweh. <verse-number id="Nu 26:62">62</verse-number>The ones counted were twenty-three thousand, every male from <idiom-start/>a month old<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a son of one month”</note> and above, because they were not counted in the midst of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> since no inheritance was given to them in the midst of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 26:63">63</verse-number>These <supplied>were</supplied> the ones counted by Moses and Eleazar the priest, who counted the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> on the desert-plateau of Moab on <supplied>the</supplied> Jordan <supplied>across</supplied> Jericho. <verse-number id="Nu 26:64">64</verse-number>And among these there was not a man of those counted by Moses and Aaron the priest, who counted the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> in the desert of Sinai. <verse-number id="Nu 26:65">65</verse-number>For Yahweh said to them, “They will surely die in the desert.” And not a man was left over from them, except Caleb son of Jephunneh and Joshua son of Nun. </p>
		</chapter>