<chapter id="Nu 27">
			<pericope>Laws of Inheritance</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 27:1">1</verse-number>Then the daughters of Zelophehad, the son of Hepher, the son of Gilead, the son of Makir, the son of Manasseh, of the clan of Manasseh the son of Joseph, came near; and these <supplied>were</supplied> the names of his daughters: Mahlah, Noah, Hoglah, and Tirzah. <verse-number id="Nu 27:2">2</verse-number>They stood before Moses and before Eleazar the priest and before the leaders of the entire community <supplied>at</supplied> the doorway of the tent of assembly,<note>Or “meeting”</note> saying, <verse-number id="Nu 27:3">3</verse-number>“Our father died in the desert; he was not in the midst of the company of those who banded together against Yahweh in the company of Korah, but he died in his own sin, and he had no sons. <verse-number id="Nu 27:4">4</verse-number>Why should the name of our father disappear from the midst of his clan because he does not have a son? Give us property in the midst of the brothers of our father.” <verse-number id="Nu 27:5">5</verse-number>So Moses brought their case before Yahweh. <verse-number id="Nu 27:6">6</verse-number>And Yahweh said to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Nu 27:7">7</verse-number>“<idiom-start/>The statements of the daughters of Zelophehad are right<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “Such as the daughters of Zelophehad <supplied>are</supplied> speaking”</note> You must surely give them <supplied>the</supplied> property of an inheritance in the midst of their father’s brothers, and you must transfer the inheritance of their father to them. <verse-number id="Nu 27:8">8</verse-number>And you must speak to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> saying, ‘If a man dies and has no son, you must transfer his inheritance to his daughter. <verse-number id="Nu 27:9">9</verse-number>And if he has no daughter, you must give his inheritance to his brothers. <verse-number id="Nu 27:10">10</verse-number>If he has no brothers, then you must give his inheritance to his father’s brothers. <verse-number id="Nu 27:11">11</verse-number>If his father has no brothers, then you must give his inheritance to his nearest relative from his own clan, and he will take possession of it. It will be as a decree of stipulation for the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> just as Yahweh commanded Moses.’ ” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 27:12">12</verse-number>Yahweh said to Moses, “Go up to this mountain of Abarim, and see the land that I have given to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 27:13">13</verse-number>When you see it, you will be gathered to your people, just as Aaron your brother was gathered, <verse-number id="Nu 27:14">14</verse-number>because you rebelled against my word in the desert of Zin when the community quarreled regarding my holiness at the waters.” (These <supplied>are</supplied> the waters of Meribah-Kadesh <supplied>in</supplied> the desert of Zin.) </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Joshua Succeeds Moses</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 27:15">15</verse-number>Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Nu 27:16">16</verse-number>“Let Yahweh, the God of the spirits of all flesh, appoint a man over the community <verse-number id="Nu 27:17">17</verse-number>who will go out before them and will come in before them, and who will lead them out and bring them in, so the community of Yahweh will not be like a flock that does not have a shepherd.” <verse-number id="Nu 27:18">18</verse-number>Then Yahweh said to Moses, “Take Joshua son of Nun, a man in whom is <supplied>the</supplied> spirit, and place your hand on him. <verse-number id="Nu 27:19">19</verse-number>Have him stand before Eleazar the priest and before the entire community, and <idiom-start/>commission him<idiom-end/><note>Literally “command him”</note> <idiom-start/>in their sight<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “before their eyes”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 27:20">20</verse-number>You will give to him from your authority so that the entire community of Israel will <idiom-start/>obey him<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “hear <supplied>him</supplied>”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 27:21">21</verse-number>He will stand before Eleazar the priest, who will ask for him by the decision<note>Or “judgment”</note> of the Urim before Yahweh. On <idiom-start/>his command<idiom-end/><note>Literally “his word”</note> they will go out, and at <idiom-start/>his command<idiom-end/><note>Literally “his word”</note> they will come in, <supplied>both</supplied> he and all of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> with him, the entire community.” <verse-number id="Nu 27:22">22</verse-number>Moses did just as Yahweh commanded him, and he took Joshua and set him before Eleazar the priest and before the entire community. <verse-number id="Nu 27:23">23</verse-number>And he placed his hands on him and <idiom-start/>commissioned him<idiom-end/><note>Literally “commanded him”</note> just as Yahweh spoke by the hand of Moses.<note>Or “through Moses”</note> </p>
		</chapter>