<chapter id="Nu 28">
			<pericope>Daily Sacrifice</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 28:1">1</verse-number>Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Nu 28:2">2</verse-number>“Command the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and say to them, ‘<idiom-start/>You will be careful to present<idiom-end/><note>Literally “you will observe to present”</note> my offering, my food of my offerings made by fire, of a fragrance of appeasement to me, at its appointed time.’ <verse-number id="Nu 28:3">3</verse-number>You will say to them, ‘This <supplied>is</supplied> the offering made by fire that you will offer to Yahweh: two male lambs without defect <idiom-start/>in their first year<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons of a year”</note> as a continual burnt offering each day. <verse-number id="Nu 28:4">4</verse-number>You will offer one male lamb in the morning, and the second male lamb you will offer <idiom-start/>at twilight<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “between the two evenings”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 28:5">5</verse-number>and a tenth of an ephah of finely milled flour as a grain offering, mixed with a fourth of a measure of beaten oil. <verse-number id="Nu 28:6">6</verse-number>It is a continual burnt offering that was <idiom-start/>ordained<idiom-end/><note>Literally “done”</note> on Mount Sinai as a fragrance of appeasement, an offering made by fire for Yahweh. <verse-number id="Nu 28:7">7</verse-number>The libation with it <supplied>will be</supplied> a fourth of a liquid measure for each male lamb; in the sanctuary you will pour out the libation of fermented drink for Yahweh. <verse-number id="Nu 28:8">8</verse-number>And the second male lamb you will offer <idiom-start/>at twilight<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “between the two evenings”</note> as the grain offering of the morning and as its libation you will offer it, an offering made by fire, a fragrance of appeasement for Yahweh. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 28:9">9</verse-number>“ ‘On the day of the Sabbath, two male lambs without defect <idiom-start/>in their first year<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons of a year”</note> and two-tenths of finely milled flour mixed with oil <supplied>for</supplied> a grain offering and its libation. <verse-number id="Nu 28:10">10</verse-number><supplied>This is</supplied> the burnt offering every Sabbath <supplied>in addition to</supplied> the continual burnt offering and its libation. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 28:11">11</verse-number>“ ‘And at the beginning of each of your months, you will present a burnt offering for Yahweh: two bulls and one ram, seven male lambs without defect <idiom-start/>in their first year<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “sons of a year”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 28:12">12</verse-number>and three-tenths of finely milled flour mixed with oil <supplied>for</supplied> a grain offering, for each bull; and two-tenths of finely milled flour mixed with oil <supplied>for</supplied> a grain offering for the one ram; <verse-number id="Nu 28:13">13</verse-number>and a tenth of finely milled flour mixed with oil <supplied>as</supplied> a grain offering for each male lamb, for a burnt offering of a fragrance of appeasement, an offering of fire for Yahweh. <verse-number id="Nu 28:14">14</verse-number>Their libations will be half a liquid measure of wine for the bull and a third of a liquid measure of wine for the ram and a fourth of a liquid measure of wine for the male lamb; this <supplied>is</supplied> the burnt offering for every month for the months of the year. <verse-number id="Nu 28:15">15</verse-number>And one male goat as a sin offering for Yahweh; it will be offered in addition to the continual burnt offering and its libation. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 28:16">16</verse-number>“ ‘On the fourteenth day of the first month <supplied>is</supplied> the Passover for Yahweh. <verse-number id="Nu 28:17">17</verse-number>On the fifteenth day of this month <supplied>is</supplied> a religious feast, unleavened bread must be eaten for seven days. <verse-number id="Nu 28:18">18</verse-number>On the first day <supplied>there will be</supplied> a holy convocation; <idiom-start/>you will not do any regular work<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “you will not do work of labor”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 28:19">19</verse-number>You will present an offering by fire, a burnt offering for Yahweh: two bulls and one ram and seven male lambs <idiom-start/>in their first year<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “sons of a year”</note> they will be for you without defect. <verse-number id="Nu 28:20">20</verse-number>For their grain offering, you will offer finely milled flour mixed with oil: three-tenths for the bull and two-tenths for the ram. <verse-number id="Nu 28:21">21</verse-number>You will offer a tenth for each of the seven male lambs; <verse-number id="Nu 28:22">22</verse-number>and a goat for one sin offering to make atonement for you. <verse-number id="Nu 28:23">23</verse-number>You will offer these besides the burnt offering of the morning, which <supplied>is</supplied> for the continual burnt offering. <verse-number id="Nu 28:24">24</verse-number>Like this you will offer daily, for seven days, <supplied>the</supplied> food of the offering made by fire, a fragrance of appeasement for Yahweh; it will be offered in addition to the continual burnt offering and its libation. <verse-number id="Nu 28:25">25</verse-number>On the seventh day you will have a holy convocation; <idiom-start/>you will not do any regular work<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “you will not do work of labor”</note> </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Offerings for the Festival of Weeks</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 28:26">26</verse-number>“ ‘And on the day of firstfruits, when you are presenting a new offering for Yahweh during your Festival of Weeks, you will have a holy convocation; <idiom-start/>you will not do any regular work<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “you will not do work of labor”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 28:27">27</verse-number>You will present a burnt offering for a fragrance of appeasement for Yahweh: two bulls, one ram, seven male lambs <idiom-start/>in their first year<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “sons of a year”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 28:28">28</verse-number>and their grain offering will be finely milled flour mixed with oil: three-tenths for each bull, two-tenths for one ram, <verse-number id="Nu 28:29">29</verse-number>a tenth for each of the male lambs; <verse-number id="Nu 28:30">30</verse-number>and one male goat to make atonement for you. <verse-number id="Nu 28:31">31</verse-number>In addition to the continual burnt offering and its grain offering, you will offer <supplied>them</supplied> without defect with their libation. </p>
		</chapter>