<chapter id="Nu 29">
			<pericope>Offers for the Seventh Month</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 29:1">1</verse-number>“ ‘On the seventh month, on the first day of the month, you will have a holy convocation; <idiom-start/>you will not do any regular work<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “you will not do work of labor”</note> It will be a day for you of blowing trumpets. <verse-number id="Nu 29:2">2</verse-number>You will offer a burnt offering as a fragrance of appeasement for Yahweh: one bull, one ram, <supplied>and</supplied> seven male lambs <idiom-start/>in their first year<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “sons of a year”</note> they will be without defect. <verse-number id="Nu 29:3">3</verse-number>Their grain offering will be finely milled flour mixed with oil: three-tenths for the bull, two-tenths for the ram; <verse-number id="Nu 29:4">4</verse-number>and one-tenth for each of the seven male lambs; <verse-number id="Nu 29:5">5</verse-number>with one male goat for a sin offering, to make atonement for you, <verse-number id="Nu 29:6">6</verse-number>in addition to the burnt offering of the new moon and its grain offering, the continual burnt offering and its grain offering, and their libations, according to their stipulations, as a fragrance of appeasement by fire for Yahweh. </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Offerings for the Day of Atonement</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 29:7">7</verse-number>“ ‘And on the tenth of this seventh month you will have a holy convocation, and <idiom-start/>you will afflict yourselves<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “you will afflict your lives” or “you will afflict your souls”</note> you will not do any work. <verse-number id="Nu 29:8">8</verse-number>You will present a burnt offering for Yahweh, a fragrance of appeasement: one bull, one ram, seven male lambs <idiom-start/>in their first year<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “sons of a year”</note> they will be without defect. <verse-number id="Nu 29:9">9</verse-number>And their grain offering <supplied>will be of</supplied> finely milled flour mixed with oil: three-tenths for the bull, two-tenths for the one ram, <verse-number id="Nu 29:10">10</verse-number>one-tenth for each of the seven male lambs; <verse-number id="Nu 29:11">11</verse-number>one male goat for a sin offering, in addition to the sin offering of atonement and the continual burnt offering and its grain offering, and their libations. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 29:12">12</verse-number>“ ‘Then on the fifteenth day of the seventh month you will have a holy convocation; <idiom-start/>you will not do any regular work<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “you will not do work of labor”</note> and you will hold a religious feast for Yahweh for seven days. <verse-number id="Nu 29:13">13</verse-number>You will present a burnt offering, an offering made by fire as a fragrance of appeasement for Yahweh: thirteen bulls, two rams, fourteen male lambs <idiom-start/>in their first year<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “sons of a year”</note> they will be without defect. <verse-number id="Nu 29:14">14</verse-number>And their grain offering <supplied>will be of</supplied> finely milled flour mixed with oil: three-tenths for the bull, two-tenths for the one ram, <verse-number id="Nu 29:15">15</verse-number>one-tenth for each of the seven male lambs; <verse-number id="Nu 29:16">16</verse-number>and one male goat for a sin offering, in addition to the continual burnt offering, its grain offering, and its libation. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 29:17">17</verse-number>“ ‘On the second day: twelve bulls, two rams, fourteen male lambs <idiom-start/>in their first year<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “sons of a year”</note> they will be without defect; <verse-number id="Nu 29:18">18</verse-number>and their grain offering and their libations for the bulls, for the rams, and for the male lambs, by their number according to the stipulation; <verse-number id="Nu 29:19">19</verse-number>and one male goat for a sin offering, in addition to the continual burnt offering and its grain offering, and their libations. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 29:20">20</verse-number>“ ‘On the third day: eleven bulls, two rams, fourteen male lambs without defect <idiom-start/>in their first year<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “sons of a year”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 29:21">21</verse-number>and their grain offering and their libations for the bulls, for the rams, and for the male lambs, by their number according to the stipulation; <verse-number id="Nu 29:22">22</verse-number>and one male goat for a sin offering, in addition to the continual burnt offering, its grain offering, and its libation. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 29:23">23</verse-number>“ ‘On the fourth day: ten bulls, two rams, fourteen male lambs without defect <idiom-start/>in their first year<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “sons of a year”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 29:24">24</verse-number>and their grain offering and their libations for the bulls, for the rams, and for the male lambs by their number according to the stipulation; <verse-number id="Nu 29:25">25</verse-number>and one male goat for a sin offering, in addition to the continual burnt offering, its grain offering, and its libation. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 29:26">26</verse-number>“ ‘On the fifth day: nine bulls, two rams, fourteen male lambs without defect <idiom-start/>in their first year<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “sons of a year”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 29:27">27</verse-number>and their grain offering and their libations for the bulls, for the rams, and for the male lambs by their number according to the stipulation; <verse-number id="Nu 29:28">28</verse-number>and one male goat for a sin offering, in addition to the continual burnt offering, its grain offering, and its libation. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 29:29">29</verse-number>“ ‘On the sixth day: eight bulls, two rams, fourteen male lambs without defect <idiom-start/>in their first year<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “sons of a year”</note> and their grain offering and their libations for the bulls, for the rams, and for the male lambs by their number according to the stipulation; <verse-number id="Nu 29:30">30</verse-number>and their grain offering and their libations for the bulls, for the rams, and for the male lambs by their number according to the stipulation; <verse-number id="Nu 29:31">31</verse-number>and one male goat for a sin offering, in addition to the continual burnt offering, its grain offering, and its libation. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 29:32">32</verse-number>“ ‘On the seventh day: seven bulls, two rams, fourteen male lambs without defect <idiom-start/>in their first year<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “sons of a year”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 29:33">33</verse-number>and their grain offering and their libations for the bulls, for the rams, and for the male lambs by their number according to the stipulation; <verse-number id="Nu 29:34">34</verse-number>and one male goat for a sin offering, in addition to the continual burnt offering, its grain offering, and its libation. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 29:35">35</verse-number>“ ‘On the eighth day you will have an assembly; <idiom-start/>you will not do any regular work<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “you will not do work of labor”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 29:36">36</verse-number>You will present a burnt offering, an offering made by fire as a fragrance of appeasement for Yahweh: one bull, one ram, seven male lambs without defect <idiom-start/>in their first year<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “sons of a year”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 29:37">37</verse-number>and their grain offering and their libations for the bulls, for the rams, and for the male lambs by their number according to the stipulation; <verse-number id="Nu 29:38">38</verse-number>and one male goat for a sin offering, in addition to the continual burnt offering, its grain offering, and its libation. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 29:39">39</verse-number>“ ‘You will present these to Yahweh at your appointed time, in addition to your vows and your freewill offerings, for your burnt offerings and for you grain offerings and for your libations and for your fellowship offerings.’ ” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 29:40">40</verse-number><note><cite title="BibleLEB2: Nu 29:40–30:16">Numbers 29:40–30:16 </cite>in the English Bible is 30:1–17 in the English Bible</note> So Moses said to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> in accordance with all that Yahweh commanded Moses. </p>
		</chapter>