<chapter id="Nu 30">
			<pericope>Laws for Vows</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 30:1">1</verse-number>Then Moses spoke to <idiom-start/>the leaders<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the heads”</note> of the tribes concerning the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> saying, “This <supplied>is</supplied> the word that Yahweh commanded: <verse-number id="Nu 30:2">2</verse-number>if a man makes a vow for Yahweh or swears an oath with a binding pledge on himself, he must not render his word invalid; he must do all that went out from his mouth. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 30:3">3</verse-number>“If a woman makes a vow to Yahweh, and she binds a pledge <supplied>on herself</supplied> in her father’s house in your childhood, <verse-number id="Nu 30:4">4</verse-number>but if her father hears her vow or her pledge that she bound on herself and says nothing to her, then all her vows will stand, and every pledge that she binds on her life will stand. <verse-number id="Nu 30:5">5</verse-number>If her father forbids her on the day he hears <supplied>of it</supplied>, all her vows or her pledges that she bound on herself will not stand, and Yahweh will forgive her because her father has forgiven her. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 30:6">6</verse-number>“If <idiom-start/>she has a husband<idiom-end/><note>Literally “she is to a man”</note> while bound by her vows or a rash promise of her lips, <verse-number id="Nu 30:7">7</verse-number>and her husband hears <supplied>of it</supplied> and is silent on the day he hears <supplied>it</supplied>, her vows will stand, and her pledge that she bound upon herself will stand. <verse-number id="Nu 30:8">8</verse-number>But if on the day her husband hears <supplied>of it</supplied>, he forbids her, then he will nullify her vow that she is under, and the rash promise of her lips that she bound on herself; and Yahweh will forgive her. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 30:9">9</verse-number>“But the vow of a widow or a woman who is divorced, all that she binds on herself will stand on her. <verse-number id="Nu 30:10">10</verse-number>But if she made a vow <supplied>in</supplied> her husband’s house, or bound herself on a pledge with a sworn oath, <verse-number id="Nu 30:11">11</verse-number>and her husband heard <supplied>it</supplied> but was silent to her, and he did not forbid her, all her vows will stand and every pledge that she bound on herself will stand. <verse-number id="Nu 30:12">12</verse-number>But if her husband nullified them on the day he hears <supplied>them</supplied>, all her vows going out of her lips concerning her vows or the pledge on herself will not stand; her husband has nullified them, and Yahweh will forgive her. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 30:13">13</verse-number>“Any vow and any sworn oath of a pledge to inflict on herself, her husband can confirm it or her husband can nullify it. <verse-number id="Nu 30:14">14</verse-number>But if her husband is completely silent from day to day, then he confirms all her vows or all her pledges that <supplied>are</supplied> on her; he confirms them because he was silent to her on the day he heard <supplied>them</supplied>. <verse-number id="Nu 30:15">15</verse-number>But if he indeed nullifies them after he hears them, then he will bear her guilt.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 30:16">16</verse-number>These <supplied>are</supplied> the decrees that Yahweh commanded Moses, as between a husband and his wife, and between a father and his daughter, <supplied>while</supplied> her childhood <supplied>is in</supplied> her father’s house. </p>
		</chapter>