<chapter id="Nu 32">
			<pericope>Gad and Reuben Inherit Gilead</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 32:1">1</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Reuben and the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Gad had a very large number of livestock. And they saw the land of Jazer and the land of Gilead, and behold it <supplied>was</supplied> a place for livestock. <verse-number id="Nu 32:2">2</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Gad and the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Reuben came, and they said to Moses and to Eleazar the priest and to the leaders of the community, saying, <verse-number id="Nu 32:3">3</verse-number>“Ataroth, Dibon, Jazer, Nimrah, Heshbon, Elealeh, Sebam, Nebo, and Beon, <verse-number id="Nu 32:4">4</verse-number>the land that Yahweh struck before the community of Israel, <supplied>is</supplied> a land of livestock, and your servants have livestock.” <verse-number id="Nu 32:5">5</verse-number>They said, “If we have found favor in <idiom-start/>your sight<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “your eyes”</note> let this land be given to your servants as property; do not lead us <supplied>across</supplied> the Jordan.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 32:6">6</verse-number>But Moses said to the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Gad and to the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Reuben, “Will your brothers go to war while you yourselves live here? <verse-number id="Nu 32:7">7</verse-number>Why are you discouraging the hearts of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> from crossing into the land that Yahweh gave to them? <verse-number id="Nu 32:8">8</verse-number>This is what your fathers did when I sent them from Kadesh Barnea to see the land. <verse-number id="Nu 32:9">9</verse-number>When they went up to the valley<note>Or “the wadi”</note> of Eshcol and saw the land, they discouraged the heart of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> so that they did not come to the land that Yahweh gave to them. <verse-number id="Nu 32:10">10</verse-number>So <idiom-start/>Yahweh’s anger burned<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Yahweh’s nose became hot”</note> on that day, and he swore an oath, saying, <verse-number id="Nu 32:11">11</verse-number>‘The men who went up from Egypt, from <idiom-start/>those twenty years old<idiom-end/><note>Literally “a son of twenty years”</note> and above, will not see the land that I swore with an oath to Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob because they have not wholly followed me, <verse-number id="Nu 32:12">12</verse-number>except Caleb son of Jephunneh the Kenizzite and Joshua son of Nun, because they followed Yahweh wholly.’ <verse-number id="Nu 32:13">13</verse-number>And <idiom-start/>Yahweh became angry<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “Yahweh’s nose became hot”</note> and he made them wander in the desert forty years until the entire generation who did evil in the <idiom-start/>sight of Yahweh<idiom-end/><note>Literally “eyes of Yahweh”</note> <idiom-start/>had died<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “had completed”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 32:14">14</verse-number>Behold, you stand in the place of your fathers, a brood of sinful men, to increase still more <idiom-start/>Yahweh’s fierce anger<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the fierce anger of Yahweh’s nose”</note> against Israel. <verse-number id="Nu 32:15">15</verse-number>If you turn from following him, he will again abandon them<note>Hebrew “him”</note> in the wilderness, and you would have destroyed all these people.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 32:16">16</verse-number>They came near to him and said, “We will build sheep pens here for <supplied>the</supplied> flock of our livestock and cities for our little children; <verse-number id="Nu 32:17">17</verse-number>but we ourselves will become armed <supplied>and</supplied> ready before the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> until we have brought them to their place, and our little children will live in the fortified cities because of the inhabitants of the land. <verse-number id="Nu 32:18">18</verse-number>We will not return to our houses until the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> each obtain their<note>Hebrew “his”</note> inheritance for themselves. <verse-number id="Nu 32:19">19</verse-number>For we will not take possession with them from across the Jordan and beyond because our inheritance has come to us from across the Jordan to the east.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 32:20">20</verse-number>So Moses said to them, “If you do this thing, if you arm yourselves <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the presence of”</note> Yahweh for the war, <verse-number id="Nu 32:21">21</verse-number>and everyone of you armed cross the Jordan <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the presence of”</note> Yahweh until he has driven out his enemies from before him, <verse-number id="Nu 32:22">22</verse-number>and the land is subdued <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the presence of”</note> Yahweh, then afterward you will return and be free of obligation from Yahweh and from Israel, and this land will be your property <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the presence of”</note> Yahweh. <verse-number id="Nu 32:23">23</verse-number>But if you do not do so, behold, you have sinned against Yahweh, and know that your sin will find you. <verse-number id="Nu 32:24">24</verse-number>Build for yourselves cities for your little children and sheep pens for your flocks; what has gone out from your mouth you will do.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 32:25">25</verse-number>So the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Gad and the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Reuben said to Moses, saying, “Your servants will do just as my lord commands. <verse-number id="Nu 32:26">26</verse-number>Our little children, our wives, our livestock, and all of our animals<note>Hebrew “animal”</note> <idiom-start/>will remain<idiom-end/><note>Literally “will be there”</note> in the cities of Gilead, <verse-number id="Nu 32:27">27</verse-number>but your servants, everyone who is armed for battle, will cross over <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the presence of”</note> Yahweh to the war, just as my lord says.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 32:28">28</verse-number>So Moses commanded them, Eleazar the priest, Joshua son of Nun, and the heads of the <idiom-start/>families<idiom-end/><note>Literally “fathers”</note> of the tribes of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 32:29">29</verse-number>Moses said to them, “If the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Gad and the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Reuben, everyone who is armed for the war, cross over the Jordan <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the presence of”</note> Yahweh, and the land is subdued before you, you will give them the land of Gilead as property. <verse-number id="Nu 32:30">30</verse-number>But if they will not cross over with you armed, they will acquire land in your midst in Canaan.” <verse-number id="Nu 32:31">31</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Gad and the descendants of Reuben answered and said, “What Yahweh has commanded your servants, we will do. <verse-number id="Nu 32:32">32</verse-number>We ourselves will cross over armed <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “in the presence of”</note> Yahweh to the land of Canaan, and the property of our inheritance <supplied>will remain</supplied> with us beyond the Jordan.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 32:33">33</verse-number>So Moses gave to them, to the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Gad and the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Reuben, and to half of the tribe of Joseph’s son Manasseh, the kingdom of Sihon the king of Amorites and the kingdom of Og the king of the Bashan, the land with its cities <supplied>and their</supplied> territories, the cities of the surrounding land. <verse-number id="Nu 32:34">34</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Gad rebuilt Dibon, Ataroth, and Aroer, <verse-number id="Nu 32:35">35</verse-number>and Atroth Shophan, Jazer, and Jogbehah, <verse-number id="Nu 32:36">36</verse-number>and Beth Nimrah and Beth Haran, the cities of Mibzar, and the sheep pens for flocks. <verse-number id="Nu 32:37">37</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Reuben rebuilt Heshbon, Elealeh, and Kiriathaim, <verse-number id="Nu 32:38">38</verse-number>and Nebo, Baal Meon (their names<note>Hebrew “name”</note> <supplied>were</supplied> changed), and Sibmah, and <idiom-start/>they renamed<idiom-end/><note>Literally “they called to names the names”</note> the cities that they rebuilt. <verse-number id="Nu 32:39">39</verse-number>The descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Makir son of Manasseh went to Gilead, and they captured it and drove out the Amorites<note>Hebrew “Amorite”</note> who <supplied>were</supplied> in it. <verse-number id="Nu 32:40">40</verse-number>So Moses gave Gilead to Makir son of Manasseh, and he lived in it. <verse-number id="Nu 32:41">41</verse-number>And Jair son of Manasseh went and captured their unwalled villages, and he called them Havvoth Jair. <verse-number id="Nu 32:42">42</verse-number>Nobah went and captured Kenath and its villages, and he called it Nobah after his <supplied>own</supplied> name. </p>
		</chapter>