<chapter id="Nu 33">
			<pericope>The Travels Are Recounted</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 33:1">1</verse-number>These <supplied>were</supplied> the journeys of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> who went out from the land of Egypt according to their divisions, by the hand of Moses and Aaron. <verse-number id="Nu 33:2">2</verse-number>Moses wrote down their movements according to their journeys on the command of Yahweh, and these <supplied>are</supplied> their journeys according to their movements. <verse-number id="Nu 33:3">3</verse-number>They set out from Rameses on the first month, on the fifteenth day of the first month; on the next day after the Passover the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> went out <idiom-start/>boldly<idiom-end/><note>Literally “with a hand that was raised”</note> <idiom-start/>in the sight<idiom-end/><note>Literally “for the eyes”</note> of all the Egyptians <verse-number id="Nu 33:4">4</verse-number>while the Egyptians <supplied>were</supplied> burying all the firstborn among them whom Yahweh struck. Yahweh <supplied>also</supplied> executed punishments among their gods. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 33:5">5</verse-number>Then the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> set out from Rameses, and they camped in Succoth. <verse-number id="Nu 33:6">6</verse-number>They journeyed from Succoth and camped in Etham, which <supplied>is</supplied> on the edge of the desert. <verse-number id="Nu 33:7">7</verse-number>Then they set out from Etham and returned to Pi-Hahiroth, which faces Baal Zephon, and they camped before Migdol. <verse-number id="Nu 33:8">8</verse-number>They set out from Pi-Hahiroth and went through the midst of the sea into the desert; and they went a journey of three days into the desert of Etham and camped at Marah. <verse-number id="Nu 33:9">9</verse-number>They set out from Marah and came to Elim, and in Elim <supplied>there were</supplied> twelve springs of water and seventy palm trees, and they camped there. <verse-number id="Nu 33:10">10</verse-number>They set out from Elim, and they camped at the <idiom-start/>Red Sea<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sea of reed”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 33:11">11</verse-number>They set out from the <idiom-start/>Red Sea<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sea of reed”</note> and camped at the desert of Sin. <verse-number id="Nu 33:12">12</verse-number>They set out from the desert of Sin and camped at Dophkah. <verse-number id="Nu 33:13">13</verse-number>They set out from Dophkah and camped at Alush. <verse-number id="Nu 33:14">14</verse-number>They set out from Alush and encamped at Rephidim; and it was there <supplied>that</supplied> the people had no water to drink. <verse-number id="Nu 33:15">15</verse-number>They set out from Rephidim and camped in the desert of Sinai. <verse-number id="Nu 33:16">16</verse-number>The set out from the desert of Sinai and camped at Kibroth Hattaavah. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 33:17">17</verse-number>They set out from Kibroth Hattaavah and camped at Hazeroth. <verse-number id="Nu 33:18">18</verse-number>They set out from Hazeroth and camped at Rithmah. <verse-number id="Nu 33:19">19</verse-number>They set out from Rithmah and camped at Rimmon Perez. <verse-number id="Nu 33:20">20</verse-number>They set out from Rimmon Perez and camped at Libnah. <verse-number id="Nu 33:21">21</verse-number>They set out from Libnah and camped at Rissah. <verse-number id="Nu 33:22">22</verse-number>They set out from Rissah and camped at Kehelathah. <verse-number id="Nu 33:23">23</verse-number>They set out from Kehelathah and camped at Mount Shapher. <verse-number id="Nu 33:24">24</verse-number>They set out from Mount Shapher and camped at Haradah. <verse-number id="Nu 33:25">25</verse-number>They set out from Haradah and camped at Makheloth. <verse-number id="Nu 33:26">26</verse-number>They set out from Makheloth and camped at Tahath. <verse-number id="Nu 33:27">27</verse-number>They set out from Tahath and camped at Terah. <verse-number id="Nu 33:28">28</verse-number>They set out from Terah and camped at Mithcah. <verse-number id="Nu 33:29">29</verse-number>They set out from Mithcah and camped at Hashmonah. <verse-number id="Nu 33:30">30</verse-number>They set out from Hashmonah and camped at Moserah. <verse-number id="Nu 33:31">31</verse-number>They set out from Moserah and camped at Bene-Jaakan. <verse-number id="Nu 33:32">32</verse-number>They set out from Bene-Jaakan and camped at Hor Haggidgad. <verse-number id="Nu 33:33">33</verse-number>They set out from Hor Haggidgad and camped at Jotbathah. <verse-number id="Nu 33:34">34</verse-number>They set out from Jotbathah and camped at Abronah. <verse-number id="Nu 33:35">35</verse-number>They set out from Abronah and camped at Ezion Geber. <verse-number id="Nu 33:36">36</verse-number>They set out from Ezion Geber and camped in the desert of Zin, that <supplied>is</supplied>, Kadesh. <verse-number id="Nu 33:37">37</verse-number>They set out from Kadesh and camped at Mount Hor, at the edge of the land of Edom. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 33:38">38</verse-number>Aaron the priest went up to Mount Hor at the <idiom-start/>command<idiom-end/><note>Literally “mouth”</note> of Yahweh, and he died there in the fortieth year after the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> had gone out from the land of Egypt, in the fifth month on the first <supplied>day</supplied> of the month. <verse-number id="Nu 33:39">39</verse-number>Aaron was one hundred and twenty-three years old when he died on Mount Hor. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 33:40">40</verse-number>Now the Canaanite, the king of Arad, who <supplied>was</supplied> living in the Negev<note>An arid region south of the Judean hills</note> in the land of Canaan, heard of the coming of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 33:41">41</verse-number>Then they set out from Mount Hor and camped at Zalmonah. <verse-number id="Nu 33:42">42</verse-number>They set out from Zalmonah and camped at Punon. <verse-number id="Nu 33:43">43</verse-number>They set out from Punon and camped at Oboth. <verse-number id="Nu 33:44">44</verse-number>They set out from Oboth and camped at Iye Abarim, the boundary of Moab. <verse-number id="Nu 33:45">45</verse-number>They set out from Iyim and camped at Dibon Gad. <verse-number id="Nu 33:46">46</verse-number>They set out from Dibon Gad and camped at Almon-Diblatayim. <verse-number id="Nu 33:47">47</verse-number>They set out from Almon-Diblatayim and camped in the mountains of Abarim, before Nebo. <verse-number id="Nu 33:48">48</verse-number>They set out from the mountains of Abarim and camped on the desert-plateau of Moab by the Jordan <supplied>across</supplied> Jericho. <verse-number id="Nu 33:49">49</verse-number>They camped by the Jordan, from Beth-Jeshimoth up to Abel Shittim, on the desert-plateau of Moab. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 33:50">50</verse-number>Then Yahweh spoke to Moses on the desert-plateau of Moab by <supplied>the</supplied> Jordan <supplied>across</supplied> Jericho, saying, <verse-number id="Nu 33:51">51</verse-number>“Speak to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and say to them, ‘When you cross the Jordan into the land of Canaan, <verse-number id="Nu 33:52">52</verse-number>you will drive out the inhabitants of the land from your presence, and you will destroy all their idols and all the images of their molten idols, and you will demolish all their high places; <verse-number id="Nu 33:53">53</verse-number>you will dispossess the land and live in it because I have given the land to you to possess it. <verse-number id="Nu 33:54">54</verse-number>You will distribute the land by lot according to your clans; to the larger group you will give a larger inheritance, and to the smaller group you will give less inheritance. However the lot falls for him, there the lot will be. You will distribute it according to the tribes of your ancestors.<note>Or “fathers”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 33:55">55</verse-number>But if you do not drive out the inhabitants of the land from your presence, then it will happen that whomever you let remain of them will be like irritants in your eyes and like thorns in your sides; they will be your enemies in the land in which you live. <verse-number id="Nu 33:56">56</verse-number>And just as I planned to do <supplied>to</supplied> them, I will do to you.’ ” </p>
		</chapter>