<chapter id="Nu 34">
			<pericope>The Land of Canaan Is Divided</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 34:1">1</verse-number>Then Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Nu 34:2">2</verse-number>“Command the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and say to them, ‘When you come into the land of Canaan, this <supplied>is</supplied> the land that was allotted to you as an inheritance, the land of Canaan according to its boundaries. <verse-number id="Nu 34:3">3</verse-number>Your southern edge will be from the desert of Zin toward the side of Edom, and your southern border will be from the end of the Salt Sea<note>That is, the Dead Sea</note> to the east; <verse-number id="Nu 34:4">4</verse-number>your boundary will turn from the south to the ascent of Akrabbim<note>Or “Scorpions”</note> and will pass over to Zin, and its limits will be from the south of Kadesh Barnea; it will continue to Hazar Addar and pass over to Azmon. <verse-number id="Nu 34:5">5</verse-number>The boundary will turn from Azmon to the valley of Egypt, and its limits will be to the sea. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 34:6">6</verse-number>“ ‘Your western boundary will be the Great Sea;<note>That is, the Mediterranean</note> this will be your western boundary. <verse-number id="Nu 34:7">7</verse-number>Your northern border will be from the Great Sea;<note>That is, the Mediterranean</note> you will make a boundary from the Great Sea<note>That is, the Mediterranean</note> to Mount Hor. <verse-number id="Nu 34:8">8</verse-number>From Mount Hor you will make a boundary to reach Hamath; the limits of the territory will be at Zedad. <verse-number id="Nu 34:9">9</verse-number>The boundary will go out to Ziphron, and its limits will be at Hazar Enan. This will be your boundary to the north. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 34:10">10</verse-number>“ ‘You will mark out your eastern boundary from Hazar Enan to Shepham; <verse-number id="Nu 34:11">11</verse-number>the boundary will go down from Shepham to Riblah from the east side of Ain, and the boundary will go down and border on the eastern side of the Sea of Kinnereth. <verse-number id="Nu 34:12">12</verse-number>The boundary will go down to the Jordan, and its limits will be at the Salt Sea.<note>That is, the Dead Sea</note> This will be your land according to its boundaries all around.’ ” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 34:13">13</verse-number>So Moses commanded the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> saying, “This <supplied>is</supplied> the land that you will obtain as an inheritance for yourself by lot, which Yahweh commanded to give to the nine and a half tribes. <verse-number id="Nu 34:14">14</verse-number>For the tribe of the children of the Reubenites,<note>Hebrew “Reubenite”</note> the children of the Gadites,<note>Hebrew “Gadite”</note> and the half-tribe of Manasseh took their inheritance according to the house of their families.<note>Or “their fathers”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 34:15">15</verse-number>The two and a half tribes have taken their inheritance from beyond the Jordan <supplied>across</supplied> Jericho, east toward the sunrise.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 34:16">16</verse-number>Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Nu 34:17">17</verse-number>“These <supplied>are</supplied> the names of the men who divide up the land for your inheritance: Eleazar the priest and Joshua son of Nun. <verse-number id="Nu 34:18">18</verse-number>You will take one leader from every tribe to divide up the land for inheritance. <verse-number id="Nu 34:19">19</verse-number>These <supplied>are</supplied> the names of the men: of the tribe of Judah, Caleb son of Jephunneh; <verse-number id="Nu 34:20">20</verse-number>of the tribe of the descendants of Simeon, Samuel son of Ammihud; <verse-number id="Nu 34:21">21</verse-number>of the tribe of Benjamin, Elidad son of Chislon; <verse-number id="Nu 34:22">22</verse-number>of the tribe of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Dan, the leader Bukki son of Jogli; <verse-number id="Nu 34:23">23</verse-number>of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Joseph, the tribe of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Manasseh, the leader Hanniel son of Ephod. <verse-number id="Nu 34:24">24</verse-number>Of the tribe of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Ephraim, the leader Kemuel son of Shiphtan; <verse-number id="Nu 34:25">25</verse-number>of the tribe of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Zebulum, the leader Elizaphan son of Parnach; <verse-number id="Nu 34:26">26</verse-number>of the tribe of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Issachar, the leader Paltiel son of Azzan; <verse-number id="Nu 34:27">27</verse-number>of the tribe of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Asher, the leader Ahihud son of Shelomi; <verse-number id="Nu 34:28">28</verse-number>of the tribe of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Naphtali, the leader Pedahel son of Ammihud.” <verse-number id="Nu 34:29">29</verse-number>These are those whom Yahweh commanded to allot to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> the land of Canaan. </p>
		</chapter>