<chapter id="Nu 35">
			<pericope>Cities for the Levites</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 35:1">1</verse-number>Yahweh spoke to Moses on the desert plains of Moab beyond the Jordan <supplied>across</supplied> Jericho, saying, <verse-number id="Nu 35:2">2</verse-number>“Command the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> that they give to the Levites from the inheritance of their property cities to live in; and you will give to the Levites pastureland all around the cities.<note>Hebrew “them”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 35:3">3</verse-number>The cities will be theirs to live in, and their pasturelands will be for their domestic animals, for their possessions, and their animals.<note>Hebrew “animal”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 35:4">4</verse-number>“The pasturelands of the cities that you will give to the Levites <supplied>will extend</supplied> from the wall of the city to <supplied>a distance of</supplied> a thousand cubits all around. <verse-number id="Nu 35:5">5</verse-number>You will measure outside the city the eastern edge two thousand cubits, for the southern edge two thousand cubits, for the western edge two thousand cubits, and for the northern edge two thousand cubits, with the city in the middle; this will be for them the pasturelands of the cities. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 35:6">6</verse-number>“All the cities that you will give the Levites will be six cities of refuge, to which the killer can flee; in addition to them you will give forty-two cities. <verse-number id="Nu 35:7">7</verse-number>All the cities that you will give to the Levites will be forty-eight cities, them with their pasturelands. <verse-number id="Nu 35:8">8</verse-number>And the cities that you will give from the property of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> you will take more from the larger group and less from the smaller group; each of them will give according to the portion of their inheritance according to the portion that he inherits.” </p>
			<p/>
			<pericope>Cities of Refuge</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 35:9">9</verse-number>Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, <verse-number id="Nu 35:10">10</verse-number>“Speak to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and say to them, ‘When you cross the Jordan <supplied>into</supplied> the land of Canaan, <verse-number id="Nu 35:11">11</verse-number>you will select for yourselves cities for your cities of refuge, that a killer who has killed a person unintentionally can flee there. <verse-number id="Nu 35:12">12</verse-number>The cities will be to you a refuge from a redeemer, so that the killer will not die until he stands before the community for judgment. <verse-number id="Nu 35:13">13</verse-number>The cities that you are to give will be your six cities of refuge. <verse-number id="Nu 35:14">14</verse-number>You will give three cities across the Jordan and three cities in the land of Canaan; they will be cities of refuge. <verse-number id="Nu 35:15">15</verse-number>To the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> to the alien, and to the temporary resident in their midst there will be these six cities as a refuge to which anyone who unintentionally kills a person may flee. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 35:16">16</verse-number>“ ‘But if he hit him with an object of iron, so that he dies, the killer must surely be put to death. <verse-number id="Nu 35:17">17</verse-number>And if he hit him with a stone in the hand, by which he will die, and he does die, he <supplied>is</supplied> a killer; the killer must surely be put to death. <verse-number id="Nu 35:18">18</verse-number>Or if he hit him with a wooden object, by which he will die, and he does die, he <supplied>is</supplied> a killer; the killer must surely be put to death. <verse-number id="Nu 35:19">19</verse-number>The blood avenger himself will put the killer to death; he must put him to death when meeting him. <verse-number id="Nu 35:20">20</verse-number>If he shoves him in hatred, or he throws something at him with intention, and he dies, <verse-number id="Nu 35:21">21</verse-number>or if he hits him in hostility with his hand, and he dies, the one that struck him will put to death the killer when meeting him. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 35:22">22</verse-number>“ ‘Or if in an instant he shoved him, not in hostility, or threw something at him without intention, <verse-number id="Nu 35:23">23</verse-number>or with any stone, without seeing it dropped on him so that he dies, while <supplied>he was</supplied> not seeking his injury, <verse-number id="Nu 35:24">24</verse-number>then the community will judge between the striker and between the blood avenger according to these ordinances. <verse-number id="Nu 35:25">25</verse-number>The community will deliver the killer from the hand of the blood avenger, and the community will restore him to the city of his refuge to which he fled; and he will live there in it until the death of the high priest who was anointed with holy oil. <verse-number id="Nu 35:26">26</verse-number>But if the killer surely goes out of the territory of the city of his refuge to which he fled, <verse-number id="Nu 35:27">27</verse-number>and the blood avenger finds him outside the territory of the city of his refuge, and the blood avenger kills the killer, <idiom-start/>he will not be guilty of blood<idiom-end/><note>Literally “there will not be blood for him”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 35:28">28</verse-number>because he must live in the city of his refuge until the death of the high priest. But after the death of the high priest the killer will return to the land of his property. <verse-number id="Nu 35:29">29</verse-number>These things will be as a decree of justice for you for your generations in all your dwellings. </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 35:30">30</verse-number>“ ‘If anyone kills a person, the killer will be put to death <idiom-start/>according to the testimony<idiom-end/><note>Literally “according to the mouth”</note> of witnesses, but someone cannot die on testimony of one person. <verse-number id="Nu 35:31">31</verse-number>Also, you will not take a ransom payment for the life of a killer who <supplied>is</supplied> guilty of death; indeed, he must surely be put to death. <verse-number id="Nu 35:32">32</verse-number>You will not take a ransom payment for the one that flees to the city of his refuge, so that he may return to live in the land before the death of the priest. <verse-number id="Nu 35:33">33</verse-number>So you will not pollute the land in which you are; because blood pollutes the land, and no atonement can be made for the land for the blood that is poured out on it except with the blood of the one who poured it out. <verse-number id="Nu 35:34">34</verse-number>You will not defile the land on which you <supplied>are</supplied> living because I <supplied>am</supplied> living in the midst of it; I am Yahweh; I <supplied>am</supplied> living in the midst of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>.’ ”<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> </p>
		</chapter>