<chapter id="Nu 36">
			<pericope>Inheritance Through Marriage</pericope>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 36:1">1</verse-number><idiom-start/>The leaders<idiom-end/><note>Literally “The heads”</note> of the families<note>Or “fathers”</note> of the clans of descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Gilead the son of Makir, the son of Manasseh, of the clans of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Joseph came near and spoke <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “before the face of”</note> Moses and <idiom-start/>before<idiom-end/><note>Literally “before the face of”</note> <idiom-start/>the leaders<idiom-end/><note>Literally “the heads”</note> of the families<note>Hebrew “of the fathers”</note> of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 36:2">2</verse-number>And they said, “Yahweh commanded my lord to give the land by lot as an inheritance to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> and my lord was commanded by Yahweh to give the inheritance of Zelophehad our brother to his daughters. <verse-number id="Nu 36:3">3</verse-number>But if they become wives to one of the sons from <supplied>another</supplied> tribe of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> their inheritance will disappear from the inheritance of our ancestors,<note>Or “fathers”</note> and it will be added to the inheritance of the tribe to which they belong; the lot of our inheritance would disappear. <verse-number id="Nu 36:4">4</verse-number>When the Jubilee of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> <idiom-start/>comes<idiom-end/>,<note>Literally “will be”</note> it will be added to the inheritance of the tribe to which they belong; and their inheritance will disappear from the tribe of our father.” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 36:5">5</verse-number>Then Moses commanded the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> by the command of Yahweh, saying, “The tribe of the descendants<note>Or “sons”</note> of Joseph <supplied>is</supplied> right <supplied>regarding what they are</supplied> speaking. <verse-number id="Nu 36:6">6</verse-number>This <supplied>is</supplied> the word that Yahweh commanded the daughters of Zelophehad, saying, ‘<idiom-start/>Let them marry<idiom-end/><note>Literally “Let them be as wives”</note> <idiom-start/>whomever they like<idiom-end/>;<note>Literally “they will be as the good in their eyes”</note> only <idiom-start/>they must marry<idiom-end/><note>Literally “they must be as wives”</note> from within the clan of the tribe of their father. <verse-number id="Nu 36:7">7</verse-number>Thus an inheritance of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> will not go around from tribe to tribe. Rather, the inheritance of each tribe of his father will remain with the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/>.<note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 36:8">8</verse-number>Every daughter who possesses an inheritance from the tribes of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> will <idiom-start/>marry<idiom-end/><note>Literally “be a wife to”</note> one of the clan of the tribe of her father, so that the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> will possess the inheritance of his ancestors.<note>Or “fathers”</note> <verse-number id="Nu 36:9">9</verse-number>Therefore an inheritance will not go around from <supplied>one</supplied> tribe to another tribe because the tribes of the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> will each hold to their <supplied>own</supplied> inheritance.’ ” </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 36:10">10</verse-number>Just as Yahweh commanded to Moses, so the daughters of Zelophehad did: <verse-number id="Nu 36:11">11</verse-number>Mahlah, Tirzah, Hoglah, Milcah, and Noah, the daughters of Zelophehad, <idiom-start/>married<idiom-end/><note>Literally “were as wives to”</note> the sons of their uncles. <verse-number id="Nu 36:12">12</verse-number><idiom-start/>They married<idiom-end/><note>Literally “They were as wives to”</note> those from the sons of Manasseh son of Joseph, and their inheritance <idiom-start/>remained<idiom-end/><note>Literally “was”</note> among the tribe of the clan of their ancestors.<note>Or “fathers”</note> </p>
			<p><verse-number id="Nu 36:13">13</verse-number>These <supplied>were</supplied> the commands and the stipulations that Yahweh commanded by the hand of Moses<note>Or “through Moses”</note> to the <idiom-start/>Israelites<idiom-end/><note>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</note> on the desert-plateaus of Moab by the Jordan <supplied>across</supplied> Jericho. </p>
		</chapter>